<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73930" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: PRESS DIGEST - Finland - Sept 24.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Finland - Sept 24.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are some of the leading stories in Finnish papers this morning.</p>
<p>HELSINGIN SANOMAT</p>
<p>- The next few years will witness worldwide concentration in the forestry industry as firms come under pressure to merge, says consultancy firm Jaakko Poyry.</p>
<p>- Finnish pianist Ralf Gothoni takes small-scale chamber music festival to Beijing with Finnish corporate sponsorship.</p>
<p>- Lesser white-fronted goose under threat of extinction in the Nordic region due to hunting, experts say. @</p>
<p>- Women's entrance into journalism has not reduced their negative portrayal in the media -- condescending attitude towards them has become subtle, says media consultant.</p>
<p>- Finnish high school students' performance in the International Baccaleauriat programme among best in world.</p>
<p>- Disney to begin operating its own recording company, Biena Vista, in Finland -- reducing Finnkino's share of corporation's wholesale distribution to a third of current level. @</p>
<p>KAUPPALEHTI</p>
<p>- Power producers assess potential environmental impact of several coal- and gas-fired power plants projected to be built along Finland's coast.</p>
<p>- German media giant Bertelsmann's withdrawal from German digital television market boosts Nokia's position in German market for TV set-top multimedia decoders, which Nokia has already sold to competing Kirch group.</p>
<p>Finland's 12 weakest department stores have combined losses of 150 million markka. @</p>
<p>- Consulting firm Propax Ltd founded to secure orders for Finnish companies from U.N. peacekeeping operations.</p>
<p>DEMARI</p>
<p>- Labour Minister Liisa Jaakonsaari says unemployment will not be halved by creating jobs with weaker social security.</p>
<p>- Unfinished project to cover the sunken ferry Estonia with a layer of gravel has so far cost 150 million markka, Swedish navigation authorities say. @</p>
<p>AAMULEHTI</p>
<p>- Tampere city orchestra gives concerts this week under the baton of 93-year-old St Petersburg conductor Ilya Musin.</p>
<p>- Sweden has sent back to Finland 10 Tamil refugees who were smuggled through Finnish territory three weeks ago.</p>
<p>TURUN SANOMAT</p>
<p>- Televised election panel discussion shows political parties, with sole exception of the Conservatives, ready to delay Finnish entry into EMU.</p>
<p>- Finland has offered to coordinate international military support to Estonia, Defence Minister Anneli Taina said. @</p>
<p>--Helsinki Newsroom +358-0-680 50 235</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
