<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13233" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli president agrees to meet Arafat.</title>
<headline>Israeli president agrees to meet Arafat.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Heller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli President Ezer Weizman, answering a &quot;distress&quot; call from Yasser Arafat, said on Sunday he would invite the Palestinian leader to his home but set no date.</p>
<p>Weizman made the announcement at a hurriedly called news conference with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu only hours after a newspaper said the outspoken president had threatened to meet Arafat over the right-wing leader's objections.</p>
<p>&quot;After an exchange of opinions, we agreed that the meeting would be held -- no date was set -- in my house, which is the most appropriate place,&quot; Weizman said after consulting with Netanyahu at the president's Jerusalem office.</p>
<p>Israel Radio reported the talks in the central Israeli village of Caesarea would take place within two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;I see it as an important meeting,&quot; said Nabil Shaath, Palestinian planning and international cooperation minister.</p>
<p>Weizman said Arafat had sent him a letter &quot;in which he spelled out his troubles and problems and said 'I hope we will meet soon'&quot;.</p>
<p>Palestinian Local Government Minister Saeb Erekat said Arafat had also sent the message to U.S. President Bill Clinton and the European Union to underline the &quot;grave&quot; state of Israel-PLO peace efforts.</p>
<p>&quot;The peace process before the (May 29) Israeli elections was like the movement of a turtle and Mr Netanyahu came and turned this turtle on its back,&quot; Erekat told reporters in Gaza.</p>
<p>Weizman said he met Netanyahu last Tuesday and showed him Arafat's letter.</p>
<p>&quot;He read it carefully. Afterwards I told him, 'Look, I want to agree to his request and meet him and I propose I do so in (my private residence) in Caesarea,&quot; Weizman said.</p>
<p>The Yedioth Ahronoth daily said the president had given Netanyahu until Sunday morning to agree either to meet Arafat himself or give Weizman the green light to issue an invitation.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, who opposes exchanging occupied land for peace -- the bedrock of the former Labour government's peace deals with the Palestinians -- has said he is in no hurry to see Arafat.</p>
<p>But Weizman, again putting Netanyahu on the spot, said he believed the prime minister would eventually talk to Arafat.</p>
<p>&quot;I suppose that as times go by and things develop, the prime minister will meet him...at the appropriate date,&quot; said Weizman, who as defence minister in the late Menachem Begin's right-wing government helped forge peace with Egypt.</p>
<p>On Thursday Netanyahu telephoned Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to tell him that peace talks with the PLO last held before the Israeli poll would resume &quot;in the very near future&quot;.</p>
<p>Netanyahu was apparently shaken by Mubarak's suggestion he might cancel a Middle East economic summit in November over Israel's stalling peace moves.</p>
<p>Palestinians are still waiting for Israel to announce a date for a long-delayed troop redeployment in the West Bank town of Hebron. The PLO regards the partial pullout as a test of Netanyahu's peace intentions.</p>
<p>Asked why he had agreed to meet Arafat, Weizman said: &quot;Firstly because of (his) distress. But that is not the main thing: Arafat, whether we want it or not, is the first Palestinian leader in 100 years of confrontation to have attained a great political achievement.&quot;</p>
<p>Weizman has met Arafat once, at the 1994 inauguration of South African President Nelson Mandela.</p>
<p>&quot;Today he has control over more than two million Palestinians. When a leader like that, who is my neighbour...asks to see me, I think I have to agree,&quot; Weizman said.</p>
<p>Only months ago, Weizman -- who has never let his ceremonial post stop him venting his opinions -- publicly demanded the former Labour government suspend peace efforts with Arafat following suicide bombings in Israel by Moslem militants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
