<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="21408" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Dominican Republic opposition proposes reforms.</title>
<headline>Dominican Republic opposition proposes reforms.</headline>
<dateline>SANTO DOMINGO 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dominican Republic opposition parties on Thursday proposed a series of constitutional reforms to reduce the power of the presidency and change the presidential elections process.</p>
<p>The plan was presented to Congress by the Dominican Revolutionary Party, whose candidate lost narrowly to Dominican President Leonel Fernandez in June, and the Social Christian Reform Party, which lost the presidency this year for the first time in four elections.</p>
<p>Among other things, the proposed reforms would reduce to 40 percent the portion of the vote a candidate needs to obtain in the first round presidential election to win. In this year's contest, an outright majority was required to avoid a runoff.</p>
<p>Other reforms include giving Congress independent authority to establish budgets, changing the way judges are appointed, altering the president's ability to rule by decree, giving ex-presidents the position of &quot;senator for life,&quot; and giving congressional representation to Dominicans living outside the country.</p>
<p>An estimated 1 million Dominicans are believed to live in the United States.</p>
<p>A spokesman said President Leonel Fernandez, of the Dominican Liberation Party (PLD), had no immediate response.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTO DOMINGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DOMINICAN REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
