<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="21644" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Deep freeze death for mutiny boat victims.</title>
<headline>Deep freeze death for mutiny boat victims.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four of the 11 seamen who died in an apparent mutiny in the South Pacific on board a fishing boat perished in the ship's deep freeze, a South Korean police officer said on Thursday.</p>
<p>He said surving crewmembers on board the Pescarmar No. 15, now being towed to South Korean, told Seoul investigators three Indonesians and one Chinese mainlander had frozen to death.</p>
<p>It was not clear whether the bodies were still in the refrigerator or had been dumped overboard, he said.</p>
<p>The bodies of the other victims -- all South Koreans, including the skipper -- had definitely been tossed into the sea, the maritime police officer said by telephone from the southern port of Pusan.</p>
<p>Thirteen seamen survived the high seas drama, among them six Chinese mainlanders who are ethnic Koreans and who South Korean authorities allege rose up in mutiny against harsh working conditions.</p>
<p>The police officer said a crude raft fashioned from wooden planks was found on board the Pescarmar.</p>
<p>But he could not confirm local news reports that the raft was part of an escape plan by the alleged mutineers.</p>
<p>He also declined to comment on reports that murder weapons had been found on the fishing boat and there were bloodstains on the walls of the wheelhouse.</p>
<p>On Wednesday a South Korean coastguard ship took over the Honduras-registered 250-gross ton vessel from Japanese maritime authorities in international waters about 550 km (340 miles) south of Tokyo.</p>
<p>The boat is expected to arrive in Pusan early on Saturday, the officer said. It was originally scheduled to dock on Friday but has been delayed by heavy seas.</p>
<p>Korean police have said a mutiny apparently occurred on August 2 when radio contact was lost with the fishing boat as it headed towards the island of Samoa.</p>
<p>It was found drifting last Sunday with empty fuel tanks.</p>
<p>The alleged mutineers are being held in cabins aboard the South Korean coastguard vessel and will be arrested when they arrive in Pusan.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the first such mutiny in which South Korean sailors were killed, although there were some murder cases during fights among fishermen,&quot; an Inchon maritime police spokesman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
