<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33539" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Playmates sees parent's wind up to fail.</title>
<headline>Playmates sees parent's wind up to fail.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Playmates Toys Holdings Ltd and Prestige Properties Holdings Ltd said they believed the petition to wind-up their parent company brought by a major shareholder would be unsuccessful.</p>
<p>In a joint-statement, Playmates and Prestige, formerly Playmates Properties, said &quot;the legal advice which they have received is to effect that there is a strong case for opposing the petition...and that the petition should not be successful.&quot;</p>
<p>The companies said their directors considered the &quot;winding-up proccedings do not have any adverse impact on the operations&quot; of both the companies.</p>
<p>A shareholder of the companies' controlling shareholder Chansam Investments Ltd, formerly Playmates Investments Ltd, has petitioned the High Court to wind up Chansam on allegation of his being prevented from participating in the management of the Playmates group.</p>
<p>Privately-held Chansam owns 66.5 percent of Playmates Toys, which introduced the internationally successful Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles dolls, and of Prestige Properties.</p>
<p>Prestige shares were up one cent at HK$1.10 in morning trade, while Playmates Toys shares were up six cents at HK$1.76.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (8952) 2843 6370</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I49410">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
