<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39136" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>MADAGASCAR: Mysterious disease kills 43 in Madagascar.</title>
<headline>Mysterious disease kills 43 in Madagascar.</headline>
<byline>Honore Razafinsalala</byline>
<dateline>ANTANANARIVO 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A mysterious disease sweeping villages in northeastern Madagascar has killed 43 people and left at least 1,000 ill in hospitals, Radio Madagascar reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>It said the government had sent medical teams to the villages affected, 200 km (120 miles) from the Indian Ocean island state's capital Antananarivo, to pinpoint the disease which causes fever and respiratory problems.</p>
<p>There was no independent government statement on the disease or the level of disaster the health ministry anticipated it may cause. But villagers appealed for urgent help, expressing fears ranging from traditional beliefs to toxic waste.</p>
<p>Some villagers believed the mysterious disease had struck non-believers of the Indian Ocean island's traditional beliefs.</p>
<p>But islanders in the southest appealed to the government to find out whether the deaths in the north were related to similar deaths in the south last year, blamed on toxic waste.</p>
<p>The radio said the disease sweep had captured the same attention as the impeachment of President Albert Zafy, confirmed by the island's constitutional court on Thursday.</p>
<p>In an address to the nation on Thursday, Zafy said he would step down on October 10 but he hit out at the head of the national assembly, Richard Andriamanjato, and the 99 deputies who voted for impeachment. He said he was a victim of a political clique opposed to his policies.</p>
<p>The radio did not say in what period the victims had died.</p>
<p>&quot;People from the southeast pose question; is this the same disease that affected them last year,&quot; the radio reported.</p>
<p>Several people died last year in an epidemic later blamed on toxic waste from cargo ships that ply the coastline. The toxic waste had been taken in by sharks and turtles and the islanders ate the poisoned turtles.</p>
<p>Zafy has accused Andriamanjato of backing a plan to dump toxic waste in Madagascar in return for up to $300 million and for supporting &quot;parallel financing&quot; opposed by the International Monetary Fund (IMF).</p>
<p>Because of the poverty, infrastructure is poor and medical facilities are bare. It takes experts from the capital Antananarivo to deal with any major disease outbreaks, islanders and diplomats said.</p>
<p>Madagascar, the world's fourth largest island, lies 400 km (250 miles) off the coast of Mozambique. With a per capital income of a little over $200, its 11 million people rank as some of the world's poorest.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANTANANARIVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MADAGASCAR"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
