<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50142" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ireland to curb salmon fishing as stocks decline.</title>
<headline>Ireland to curb salmon fishing as stocks decline.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN, Ireland</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Irish government unveiled plans Thursday to save one of its rarest treasures -- salmon.</p>
<p>Minister of State for the Marine, Eamon Gilmore, announced severe restrictions on the netting of salmon off the Irish coast and in estuaries where the fish gather before heading upstream each year to spawn.</p>
<p>&quot;Wild salmon is a priceless resource and Ireland is one of the last strongholds of wild Atlantic salmon stocks,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A government-backed task force comprising commercial and amateur fishermen was formed following widespread concern about the lack of controls over salmon fishing. Sports fishermen come from all over the world to catch salmon in Irish rivers, and many complain that their numbers have dwindled over the years.</p>
<p>Anglers are seen by the government as an important source of revenue. Many come from far away places and spend thousands of pounds on hotels and travel just to catch one fish.</p>
<p>&quot;Action needs to be taken now to conserve stocks and to rebalance the salmon catch between the commercial and angling sectors,&quot; Gilmore said.</p>
<p>&quot;In recent decades, stocks have been declining and an increasing proportion of salmon have been caught by drift nets at sea,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Commercial netting of salmon, using drift nets, will be more than halved to a six-mile limit from the shore beginning from next spring, he said.</p>
<p>Drift-net operators will be limited to fishing four days a week instead of the present five. Daytime fishing will be allowed only between four a.m. and nine p.m.</p>
<p>The fishing season will end on June 1 instead of July. Curbs on the use of drift nets used in river estuaries and on areas where they will be allowed are also being implemented.</p>
<p>In a move aimed at salmon poachers, the government will also ban the sale of salmon caught by fishing rod, ending an age-old practice where poachers presented themselves at hotel doors to sell their illegally acquired gains.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN, Ireland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
