<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="51789" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: CRICKET-RAIN COMES TO ZIMBABWE'S RESCUE AGAINST SRI LANKA.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-RAIN COMES TO ZIMBABWE'S RESCUE AGAINST SRI LANKA.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rain hindered Sri Lanka's push</p>
<p>for victory after they forced Zimbabwe to follow on on the third</p>
<p>day of the first test on Friday.</p>
<p>Play was possible only in the afternoon session during which</p>
<p>Zimbabwe, resuming at 105 for six in reply to Sri Lanka's first</p>
<p>innings 349, were dismissed for 145.</p>
<p>They were 20 without loss in their second innings when rain</p>
<p>return to wash out play for the day.</p>
<p>Only Craig Wishart defied Sri Lanka's pace and spin attack</p>
<p>for any length of time to score a resolute 51, hitting a six and</p>
<p>two fours in his 157-ball innings.</p>
<p>The rest of the Zimbabwe late order succumbed to the spin of</p>
<p>Muthiah Muralitharan and Jayantha Silva after left-arm paceman</p>
<p>Chaminda Vaas provided the initial breakthrough by having Craig</p>
<p>Evans caught behind for nine.</p>
<p>Muralitharan accounted for the wicket of Paul Strang for six</p>
<p>and Silva was left on a hat-trick after picking up the last two</p>
<p>Zimbabwe wickets off successive deliveries.</p>
<p>Left-arm spinner Silva whose only previous test appearance</p>
<p>was against Australia last year, first had Wishart caught off a</p>
<p>drive to mid-off and off the next delivery, bowled after a</p>
<p>10-minute break for rain, had Andrew Whittall caught by Kumara</p>
<p>Dharmasena at square leg.</p>
<p>Silva finished with a test best of three for 10 off 14.5</p>
<p>overs, which included nine maidens, while Muralitharan's two</p>
<p>wickets cost him 28 runs off 24 overs. Vaas was Sri Lanka's</p>
<p>leading wicket-taker with four for 73, which also included his</p>
<p>50th in test cricket.</p>
<p>Zimbabwe openers Grant Flower and Mark Dekker survived 30</p>
<p>minutes batting in the second innings but the visitors face an</p>
<p>uphill task of trying to bat out the next two days with rain as</p>
<p>their best hope of salvation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
