<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54780" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>EU: OFFICIAL JOURNAL CONTENTS - OJ C 269 OF SEPTEMBER 14, 1996.</title>
<headline>OFFICIAL JOURNAL CONTENTS - OJ C 269 OF SEPTEMBER 14, 1996.</headline>
<text>
<p>*</p>
<p>(Note - contents are displayed in reverse order to that in the printed Journal)</p>
<p>*</p>
<p>Action brought on 29 July 1996 by X against the European Parliament (Case T-119/96) (96/C 269/63)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 July 1996 by Biscuiterie-Confiserie LOR and Confiserie du TECH against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-114/96) (96/C 269/62)</p>
<p>Action brought on 22 July 1996 by Jean-Claude Seche against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-112/96) (96/C 269/61)</p>
<p>Action brought on 22 July 1996 by ITT Promedia NV against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-111/96) (96/C 269/60)</p>
<p>Action brought on 12 July 1996 by Pantochim SA against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-107/96) (96/C 269/59)</p>
<p>Action brought on 10 July 1996 by Wirtschaftsvereinigung Stahl against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-106/96) (96/C 269/58)</p>
<p>Action brought on 8 July 1996 by Pharos SA against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-105/96) (96/C 269/57)</p>
<p>Action brought on 27 June 1996 by Franz Eppe against the Commission of the European Communities (Case T-99/96) (96/C 269/56)</p>
<p>ORDER OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE COURT OF FIRST INSTANCE of 13 July 1996 in Case T-76/96 R: The National Farmers' Union and Others v. Commission of the European Communities (1) (96/C 269/55)</p>
<p>ORDER OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE COURT OF FIRST INSTANCE of 12 July 1996 in Case T-52/96 R: Sogecable SA v. Commission of the European Communities (96/C 269/54)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-413/93 (1) (96/C 269/50)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-394/95 (1) (96/C 269/48)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-393/95 (1) (96/C 269/53)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-387/95 (1) (96/C 269/47)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-385/95 (1) (96/C 269/52)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-121/94 (1) (96/C 269/51)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-40/96 (1) (96/C 269/49)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-5/96 (1) (96/C 269/46)</p>
<p>Removal from the register of Case C-327/95 (1) (96/C 269/45)</p>
<p>Action brought on 5 August 1996 by the French Republic against the European Parliament (Case C-267/96) (96/C 269/44)</p>
<p>Action brought on 31 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-265/96) (96/C 269/43)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the House of Lords, by order of that court of 24 July 1996, in the case of Imperial Chemical Industries plc against Colmer (Her Majesty's Inspector of Taxes) (Case C-264/96) (96/C 269/42)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-263/96) (96/C 269/41)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling from the Sozialgericht Aachen - 13th Chamber - by order of that court of 24 July 1996 in the case of Sema Surul v. Bundesanstalt fur Arbeit, Nurnberg (Case C-262/96) (96/C 269/40)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Corte d'Appello (Sezione Prima Civile), Venice, by order of that court of 9 May 1996, in the case of Conserchimica SRL v. Amministrazione delle Finanze dello Stato (Case C-261/96) (96/C 269/39)</p>
<p>Appeal brought on 23 July 1996 by the Council of the European Union against the judgment delivered on 26 June 1996 by the Second Chamber of the Court of First Instance of the European Communities in Case T-91/95 between L. de Nil and C. Impens and the Council of the European Union (Case C-259/96 P) (96/C 269/38)</p>
<p>Appeal brought on 22 July 1996 by the European Parliament against the judgment delivered on 22 May 1996 by the Second Chamber of the Court of First Instance of the European Communities in Case T-140/94 between Enrique Gutierrez de Quijano y Llorens and the European Parliament (Case C-252/96 P) (96/C 269/37)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Industrial Tribunals, Southampton, by order of that court of 19 July 1996, in the case of Lisa Jacqueline Grant against South-West Trains Ltd (Case C-249/96) (96/C 269/36)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling from the Arrondissementsrechtbank, Amsterdam, by judgment of that court of 16 July 1996 in the case of 1. R. O. J. Grahame and 2. L. M. Hollanders v. Bestuur van de Nieuwe Algemene Bedrijfsvereniging (Case C-248/96) (96/C 269/35)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Office of the Industrial Tribunals and the Fair Employment Tribunal, by reference of that court of 9 July 1996, in the Case of Mrs Mary Teresa Maggorian and Mrs Irene Patricia Cunningham against the Eastern Health and Social Services Board and the Department of Health and Social Services (Case C-246/96) (96/C 269/34)</p>
<p>Action brought on 12 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Italian Republic (Case C-245/96) (96/C 269/33)</p>
<p>Action brought on 12 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-244/96) (96/C 269/32)</p>
<p>Action brought on 12 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-243/96) (96/C 269/31)</p>
<p>Action brought on 11 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Hellenic Republic (Case C-241/96) (96/C 269/30)</p>
<p>Action brought on 10 July 1996 by the United Kingdom against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-240/96) (96/C 269/29)</p>
<p>Action brought on 10 July 1996 by the United Kingdom against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-239/96) (96/C 269/28)</p>
<p>Action brought on 10 July 1996 by Ireland against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-238/96) (96/C 269/27)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling from the Cour d'Appel, Mons, by judgment of that court of 28 June 1996 in the case of Ministre des Finances du Royaume de Belgique v. E. Amelynck and Others (Case C-237/96) (96/C 269/26)</p>
<p>Action brought on 9 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Federal Republic of Germany (Case C-236/96) (96/C 269/25)</p>
<p>*</p>
<p>References for a preliminary ruling from the Landesarbeitsgericht Hamburg by orders of that court of 6 February 1996 in the cases of Agnes Vick v. Deutsche Telekom AG and Ute Conze v. Deutsche Telekom AG (Cases C-234/96 and C-235/96) (96/C 269/24)</p>
<p>Action brought on 9 July 1996 by the Government of the Kingdom of Denmark against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-233/96) (96/C 269/23)</p>
<p>Action brought on 8 July 1996 by the French Republic against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-232/96) (96/C 269/22)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling from the Cour d'Appel, Douai, by judgment of that court of 20 June 1996 in the case of SA Cabour and SA Nord Distribution Automobile v. SARL Arnor 'Soco' (interveners: SA Automobile Peugeot and SA Automobiles Citroen) (Case C-230/96) (96/C 269/21)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Arbeitsgericht Frankfurt am Main by order of that court of 11 June 1996 in the case of Friedrich Santner against Hoechst Aktiengesellschaft (Case C-229/96) (96/C 269/20)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Ufficio del Giudice Conciliatore di Milano by order of that court of 25 June 1996 in the case of Aprile SRL against Amministrazione delle Finanze (Case C-228/96) (96/C 269/19)</p>
<p>Action brought on 1 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Hellenic Republic (Case C-227/96) (96/C 269/18)</p>
<p>Action brought on 1 July 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Hellenic Republic (Case C-226/96) (96/C 269/17)</p>
<p>Action brought on 27 June 1996 by SA Promotion Leopold against the European Parliament (Case C-224/96) (96/C 269/16)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the French Republic (Case C-223/96) (96/C 269/15)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-222/96) (96/C 269/14)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-221/96) (96/C 269/13)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-220/96) (96/C 269/12)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-219/96) (96/C 269/11)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Kingdom of Belgium (Case C-218/96) (96/C 269/10)</p>
<p>Action brought on 26 June 1996 by the Kingdom of Belgium against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-217/96) (96/C 269/09)</p>
<p>Reference for a preliminary ruling by the Tribunal Administratif, Saint-Denis de la Reunion, by judgment of that court of 5 June 1996 in the case of Paul Chevassus-Marche v. Conseil Regional de la Reunion (Case C-212/96) (96/C 269/08)</p>
<p>Action brought on 21 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Hellenic Republic (Case C-211/96) (96/C 269/07)</p>
<p>Action brought on 19 June 1996 by the United Kingdom against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-209/96) (96/C 269/06)</p>
<p>Application made on 15 July 1996 by SA Must Interim for authorization to serve a garnishee order on the Commission (Case C-1/96 SA) (96/C 269/03)</p>
<p>Action brought on 18 June 1996 by the Commission of the European Communities against the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg (Case C-206/96) (96/C 269/05)</p>
<p>Action brought on 13 June 1996 by the Kingdom of Spain against the Commission of the European Communities (Case C-199/96) (96/C 269/04)</p>
<p>JUDGMENT OF THE COURT of 18 June 1996 in Case C-303/94: European Parliament v. Council of the European Union (1) (Directive concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market - Prerogatives of the Parliament) (96/C 269/01)</p>
<p>ORDER OF THE COURT of 25 June 1996 in Case C-101/96: criminal proceedings against Italia Testa (1) (Interpretation of the provisions of the Treaty on the free movement of goods and the freedom to provide services with regard to national legislation on the management of copyright by a company governed by public law) (96/C 269/02) END OF DOCUMENT.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
