<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61252" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: FEATURE - Brazil turtle paradise frets over money problems.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Brazil turtle paradise frets over money problems.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>PRAIA DO FORTE, Brazil 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Antonio Mendes, once a fisherman who lived off turtle eggs dug out of the beach at night, is now a &quot;Turtleman,&quot; helping to save endangered marine species from extinction.</p>
<p>Mendes, 33, is one of about 400 fishermen &quot;Projeto TAMAR,&quot; the Brazilian Marine Turtle Project, has turned from killers into guardians of the two million sea turtles it has guided safely into the Atlantic over 15 years. Now, despite its success at persuading former predators that turtles are more valuable alive than dead, Projeto TAMAR's future is being threatened by money problems.</p>
<p>&quot;There are hardly any human predators left,&quot; said Neca Marcovaldi, president of the foundation that runs TAMAR jointly with the government's IBAMA environmental agency. &quot;Now the big battle is to secure continuity of the project. We must increase our financial self-subsistence. We can no longer depend on short-term government or irregular private sector finance.&quot;</p>
<p>The turtle project began in 1979 with government-sponsored surveys after an international outcry over the slaughter of nesting females and the stealing of their eggs, which placed the reptiles on the endangered animals list. Of the eight sea turtle species in the world, five feed and lay their eggs on Brazilian shores, including the Loggerhead, the Hawksbill, the Green Turtle, the Olive Ridley and the giant Leatherback, which can weigh 1,540 pounds (700 kg).</p>
<p>In 1987, Marcovaldi and her husband Guy set up the private Projeto-TAMAR Foundation to work with IBAMA in monitoring part of Brazil's coast. Projeto TAMAR has since set up 22 field stations.</p>
<p>But the project's greatest success is probably psychological. It has convinced fishermen like Mendes and their families that marine turtles should not be killed, and it has provided them with an alternative livelihood by paying them to locate and protect eggs and also through a merchandizing business selling T-shirts, turtle dolls and other items to tourists.</p>
<p>&quot;We realised early on that if we didn't offer the local people an alternative income we wouldn't be able to protect anything,&quot; Marcovaldi said.</p>
<p>TAMAR recently sent its two millionth baby turtle off to a hopefully long life criss-crossing the oceans. But Marcovaldi stresses that the survival of a species is not just a numbers game. Only one in every 450 hatchlings reaches adulthood, and that can take 30 years.</p>
<p>&quot;The 15 years we've been working is a short time in the life of a turtle. Saving them is a long-term project and that's why we need long-term financial stability,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Forty percent of TAMAR's resources come from the government and 60 percent from the foundation, mainly sponsored by state-oil firm Petrobras. The Inter-American Development Bank (IADB) is financing monitoring projects in feeding grounds and the European Union has approved about $400,000 in three-year funding to boost and &quot;professionalize&quot; TAMAR's T-shirt production.</p>
<p>But all the funds are short-term. Every year, Marcovaldi travels to Brasilia to lobby for continued support, a difficult task when government budgets are being slashed. Every year, she has to plead with the private sponsors.</p>
<p>For all its achievements, TAMAR is not an expensive undertaking. Each field station costs some $50,000 a year, bringing total annual operating costs to just over $1 million.</p>
<p>Should the project falter, sea turtles could once again fall prey to human and animal predators.</p>
<p>&quot;I have never liked turtle meat,&quot; Mendes said, glancing sheepishly down at the golden sands of Praia do Forte in Brazil's northeast, where TAMAR has its headquarters. &quot;But there are people in the village who are against TAMAR because they would like to eat turtle soup again.&quot;</p>
<p>Praia do Forte in the northeastern state of Bahia is itself a perfect example of how environmental preservation can pay off. A pristine &quot;Eco-Tourism&quot; reserve, replete with beach bars and artisan shops, it has become the darling of German, Argentine, Italian and even Japanese tourists seeking a bit more than just sea and sun. In the peak season, 2,000 people a day trudge through TAMAR's visitors centre.</p>
<p>Marcovaldi is encouraging the government to use TAMAR's ecological credentials to improve Brazil's image overseas, where its commitment to the environment is often questioned.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAIA DO FORTE, Brazil"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
