<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78455" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: HK activist dies protesting Japan's claim to isles.</title>
<headline>HK activist dies protesting Japan's claim to isles.</headline>
<byline>Simon Kwong</byline>
<dateline>ABOARD THE HANGHAI 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Hong Kong activist drowned in the roiling East China Sea on Thursday after Japanese patrol boats thwarted his protest ship's bid to land on a disputed archipelago to claim it back for China.</p>
<p>David Chan, 45, and four other protesters had leapt into the storm-whipped sea, vowing to defy even Japan's claim to the island's waters, when the Japanese blocked their attempt to make landfall on the archipelago.</p>
<p>Chan's death was the first in a wave of protests to sweep Hong Kong, Taiwan, Macau and China since July, when Japanese ultranationalists built a lighthouse and raised Japan's flag on the islands northeast of Taiwan to assert Tokyo's sovereignty.</p>
<p>The tragedy aboard the rusty tanker Kien Hwa 2, witnessed by reporters aboard the nearby fishing boat Hanghai, brought expressions of regret in Hong Kong, Tokyo, Beijing and Taipei -- and calls for cooler heads.</p>
<p>The death also heightened tension between Japan, which has claimed the islands since 1895 as the Senkakus, and China, which calls them the Diaoyus and has claimed them for centuries.</p>
<p>China, keen to marshal patriotism stirred by the sovereignty dispute without offending Japanese investors, reiterated its call for Tokyo to restrain right-wing activists whose actions have whipped up Chinese nationalism against Japan.</p>
<p>Foreign Ministry spokesman Shen Guofang said China had an &quot;unshakeable&quot; will to safeguard its territory and sovereignty.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope the Japanese side will take action so the situation...will not continue to deteriorate,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Japan, which has sought to cool Chinese anger, issued a statement citing the &quot;utmost efforts&quot; of Japanese medics to save Chan and regretting his death &quot;from the heart&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We strongly hope this type of incident is never repeated,&quot; Japanese Foreign Ministry spokesman Hiroshi Hashimoto said.</p>
<p>Fearing a backlash, Japan's Hong Kong diplomatic mission sought police protection for all Japanese organisations in the British territory, including private companies.</p>
<p>The Kien Hwa was expected to call at Taiwan's Keelung port early on Friday to put Chan's body ashore.</p>
<p>Taipei, which also claims the islands, said the ship was welcome in Keelung if it did not fly the red flag of communist China, Taiwan's rival since a civil war split them in 1949.</p>
<p>The ship had set out from Hong Kong on Sunday, with protest leader Chan vowing to plant China's flag on the islands and pull down Japan's flag and the offending lighthouse.</p>
<p>Some 17 Japanese coastguard patrol boats and several aircraft circled the tanker as it neared the islands, allowing it no closer than two nautical miles offshore early on Thursday.</p>
<p>The tanker's pilot, interviewed by Hong Kong radio, said he had baulked at moving nearer, citing the heavy Japanese presence and rough seas, and had opposed a proposed landing by the protesters using a rubber raft.</p>
<p>It was then that Chan and four others donned life vests, tied themselves to ropes and dived into the sea.</p>
<p>Chan, reportedly a non-swimmer, lost consciousness as he was dragged beside the slow-moving ship for some 15 minutes.</p>
<p>Protesters initially seemed not to sense the seriousness of Chan's plight and although alive when pulled aboard, he could not be revived by crew or Japanese medics put aboard by helicopter. A Japanese doctor later declared Chan dead.</p>
<p>Another protester was seriously injured and flown to Okinawa in southern Japan. Three were plucked from the sea unhurt.</p>
<p>Grief swept those aboard the Kien Hwa 2. &quot;Everybody is extremely sad, thinking about the whole issue. Some are crying and holding onto each other,&quot; a reporter said by radio.</p>
<p>It was not known how Chan's death would affect other Hong Kong and Taiwan groups' plans for further protests.</p>
<p>Japanese patrols on Monday repulsed a flotilla of Taiwan protest boats seeking to challenge Japanese sovereignty by landing on the islands.</p>
<p>Hong Kong, a British colony for more than 150 years, reverts to Chinese rule in mid-1997 and many Hong Kong people see the dispute as a test of China's strength and integrity.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ABOARD THE HANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
