<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78483" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Captain says partly to blame for activist's death.</title>
<headline>Captain says partly to blame for activist's death.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The captain of a protest ship said on Thursday he felt partly to blame for the drowning of one of his passengers, who dived into the East China Sea to protest Japan's claim to disputed chain of islands</p>
<p>Protestor David Chan, leader of 18 activists aboard the protest ship Kien Hwa 2, died on Thursday after leaping into the sea to defy a blockade of the islands by Japanese patrol boats.</p>
<p>&quot;I did not have the time to think for a moment that I should let him (Chan) do this or not, but I agreed to him,&quot; Ngai Lup-chee, captain of the tanker, said on government radio.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Chan) was not a good swimmer and the rope and lifejacket were not tied in a quite correct and traditional way. Under the circumstances, many things had gone wrong. And as the commander of the ship I feel some responsibility,&quot; Ngai said.</p>
<p>Chan and four other protesters who jumped with him, tied themselves to the ship and were dragged along side the vessel for several minutes.</p>
<p>One of the other four was seriously hurt and later flown to a hospital in the Japanese prefecture of Okinawa.</p>
<p>The other three were plucked from the sea unharmed.</p>
<p>Ngai, who twice refused to let the group land on the islands due to rough seas, said he regretted his decision.</p>
<p>&quot;I felt I should have agreed to their second request as I had turned down their first request to land on the island,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chan's drowning was the first death in almost two months of protests that have swept through Hong Kong, China, Taiwan and Macau since Japanese activists built a lighthouse and raised Japanese flags on the islands.</p>
<p>Japan has claimed sovereign rights to the islands and refused to acknowledge that the dispute is still open for discussion with China.</p>
<p>Tokyo's claim to what it calls the Senkaku Islands dates to 1895, when Japan defeated China and seized Taiwan and other territories. China has claimed sovereignty over the islands for centuries, referring to them as the Diaoyus.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
