<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80107" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China tells Japan to match island words with deeds.</title>
<headline>China tells Japan to match island words with deeds.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>China on Thursday urged Japan to match words with deeds in a row over a group of disputed islands in the East China Sea and restrain its right-wingers.</p>
<p>&quot;We the Chinese side ask the Japanese side to match its deeds with its words,&quot; Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Shen Guofang told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope the Japanese side will take action so that the situation in the area will not continue to deteriorate.&quot;</p>
<p>Shen said Japan's Foreign Minister Yukihiko Ikeda told his Chinese counterpart Qian Qichen at the United Nations in New York on Wednesday that Tokyo would not let Japanese rightwingers take further action on the islands, known in Chinese as the Diaoyus and in Japan as the Senkakus.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign Minister Ikeda expressed...(Japan) cannot allow Japanese rightwing groups to take action on the Diaoyu islands issue,&quot; Shen said.</p>
<p>China was still awaiting confirmation of the death of a Hong Kong activist in the seas around the islands, Shen said.</p>
<p>Japanese maritime officials said activist David Chan died on Tuesday after jumping into the sea from a Hong Kong vessel in protest at Japan's claim to the disputed islands. Shen said that if the reports were accurate then Chan's death was regrettable.</p>
<p>A long-running dispute over ownership of the uninhabited but potentially resource-rich islands has flared in recent months after Japanese rightwingers moved to buttress Tokyo's claims by building a lighthouse on one of them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
