<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81444" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK protest ship skipper apologises for death.</title>
<headline>HK protest ship skipper apologises for death.</headline>
<byline>Dominic Lau</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Weeping family members on Friday greeted the coffin of a Hong Kong activist leader who drowned in the East China Sea in an anti-Japan demonstration as the skipper of the protest vessel apologised for the tragedy.</p>
<p>The body of David Chan was flown from Taiwan to Hong Kong, where his weeping wife and sister and other mourners bowed before the coffin on the airport tarmac.</p>
<p>Chan drowned on Thursday after plunging into the sea to press home China's sovereignty over a group of islands claimed by Japan.</p>
<p>Relatives and friends had draped a red communist Chinese flag with five golden stars over the yellow wooden coffin and gave three traditional bows in a simple airport mourning ceremony.</p>
<p>British-ruled Hong Kong reverts to Chinese rule next year.</p>
<p>Mourners also draped cloth banners over the coffin with the words &quot;Eternal Glory to Chan&quot; and &quot;Noble Patriot.&quot;</p>
<p>Ngai Lup-chee, captain of the rusty Kien Hwa 2, which set sail for the islands on Sunday carrying the protesters and journalists, apologised to Chan's family.</p>
<p>&quot;I had promised before setting sail for the Diaoyu Islands that I would bring them back safely,&quot; a weeping Ngai said in the airport building. &quot;I failed. I brought one less person back.</p>
<p>&quot;Although there were so many Japanese vessels and planes, we still succeeded in getting within one mile of the Diaoyu islands,&quot; the skipper said. &quot;But I still feel I failed.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't firmly oppose the request (by protesters to leap off the ship into the sea), and I'm sorry to David Chan and his family.&quot;</p>
<p>Chan led 18 Hong Kong Chinese activists to the islands northeast of Taiwan that the Chinese call the Diaoyus and Japan calls the Senkakus.</p>
<p>Japanese coastguard boats thwarted the tanker's attempts to land on the isles, where the 18 had hoped to remove symbols of Japanese sovereignty, including a lighthouse. So they resorted to a protest dive.</p>
<p>On the airport tarmac were groups of Hong Kong legislators, activists and well-wishers as well as a senior representative of China's de facto embassy in the territory.</p>
<p>Activists on the tarmac held up banners with the slogans &quot;Perished for your country&quot; and &quot;Your name will be remembered for a thousand years.&quot;</p>
<p>Groups of protesters gathered in the morning outside Japan's consulate, shouting &quot;down with Japanese militarism&quot;.</p>
<p>One group of 50 demonstrators blamed Japan for Chan's death. &quot;Maybe more and more people will die if they (Japan) don't stop their occupation of our territory,&quot; said regional councillor Willie Cheng. &quot;We look for peace...they started this not us.&quot;</p>
<p>Fellow activists stood in the airport holding flowers.</p>
<p>&quot;We will never give up the fight for the Diaoyu islands,&quot; activist Lew Mon-hung shouted. Those who had made the ill-fated voyage stood silently behind Lew, too upset to join the chant.</p>
<p>&quot;If Chan dies in Chinese waters then it was worthwhile, but if he died in Japanese waters it is sad, and shame on the Chinese government,&quot; said activist Wong Wai-ming.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
