<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15690" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>PANAMA: FEATURE - Panama mining faces uncertain future.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Panama mining faces uncertain future.</headline>
<byline>Laurens Grant</byline>
<dateline>PANAMA CITY 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hopes that Panama's mining sector will become the country's major export earner in the next century are fading fast amid government bureaucracy and conflicts over Indian land claims.</p>
<p>Mining officials boasted in March that the sector could bring in $500 million a year in copper export revenues in the next century.</p>
<p>Based on important proven copper reserves, Richard Fifer, president of Panama's mining chamber, predicted the industry would surpass bananas -- which account for $180 million a year -- as the nation's main export earner.</p>
<p>But international mining companies, some of which have been in Panama for years waiting to get the go-ahead, are running out of patience. They complain that the administration of President Ernesto Perez Balladares is slow in approving projects and solving conflicts with local Indian-activist groups.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Panama is afraid of mining,&quot; summed up one international mining executive, who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>Panama is known for its rich copper-gold deposits, which stretch from the western provinces of Veraguas to Chiriqui.</p>
<p>DEMAND EXPEXCTED TO INCREASE</p>
<p>Industry analysts say prospects for a mining industry are good and copper demand is expected to increase in the long term as more African and Latin countries develop.</p>
<p>Although changes to Panama's mining law in the early 1990s eased regulations, they remain cumbersome and confusing, foreign mining executives say. The law does not regulate how companies should make federal and municipal tax payments nor does it clarify the scope of environmental impact studies. Final ratification rests with the comptroller general.</p>
<p>Mining chamber executive director Antonio Velazquez fears Panama will lose business to countries with a more developed mining history like Peru and above all Chile, which mines 40 percent of the world's copper output.</p>
<p>&quot;In Peru, a company can have a contract in 45 days. In Panama, it could take years,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Panama's assistant comptroller general Gustavo Perez disagreed, saying he was due to ratify eight projects soon.</p>
<p>&quot;Panama wants mining and all kinds of foreign investment,&quot; he said. &quot;The comptroller doesn't stymie projects. We will only approve projects that conform to the law.&quot;</p>
<p>PROBLEMS WITH LAND CLAIMED BY INDIAN COMMUNITIES</p>
<p>Since 1992, the Panamanian government has given the go-ahead to only three mining projects, two gold and one manganese.</p>
<p>Panama is sitting on 240 mining exploration applications, 85 in Indian communities. Government officials admit privately the applications in Indian communities may never win approval.</p>
<p>One company that did get approval to mine on land claimed by Indians has found itself in the middle of the controversy.</p>
<p>Canadian mining firm Tiomin Resources Inc got authorisation five months ago for a project to mine the world's 12th largest copper deposit in Cerro Colorado, some 220 miles (350 km) from Panama City.</p>
<p>The first set of feasibility studies should be ready next March, said Edward Kurys, Tiomin's Cerro Colorado project director. If they proved successful, the project would continue as an open-pit mine using a type of processing which extracts the copper without emitting acid gases.</p>
<p>The company planned to spend some $13 million by March in feasibility studies and another $1.5 million in social and economic programmes in the area, Kurys said. Only half of the company's 120-person workforce is Indian.</p>
<p>But Indian rights groups in the area say the government signed the Cerro Colorado contract without their knowledge and cheated them out of their lands.</p>
<p>The Ngobe-Bugle Indians, the largest of Panama's six Indian groups at a population of 125,000, have been waiting for an Indian territory for 25 years, said Ferma Baker, a Ngobe-Bugle Indian who is an advisor to Panama's National Coordination of Indigenous Peoples group.</p>
<p>&quot;Negotiations with the government were renewed last year but talks broke down when they signed the mining contract without telling us,&quot; Baker said. &quot;The company says they have a right to be there, but we want the government to give us our territory first. Then let's sit down and talk about mining,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Kurys believes the mining project and the Indian territory can coexist. &quot;We're working with the community...I don't see why the Indians can't have their territory to preserve their culture and have the project continue, too.&quot;</p>
<p>Canada's Western Keltic Mines Inc recently closed a preliminary mining exploration camp after receiving death threats from local Kuna Indians, the most powerful of Panama's Indians.</p>
<p>Vancouver-based Western Keltic pulled out of an area in the Comarca de San Blas region, along the Caribbean coast some 100 miles (160 km) from Panama City.</p>
<p>Stressing his company had been &quot;patient for two years&quot;, Western Keltic president Donald McInnes said: &quot;If the government and the Kunas don't show interest, we'll walk. We have four applications in the Dominican Republic.&quot;</p>
<p>But he added in a telephone interview: &quot;I'm confident we'll return. Not everyone was opposed to the project...We're trying to do this in a cooperative manner. I'm not a rape-and-pillage kind of guy.&quot;</p>
<p>The company is also awaiting approval on 14 exploration contracts, of which five are in Comarca de San Blas.</p>
<p>Also beginning to lose patience is Canada's Inmet Mining Corp. &quot;We came to Panama and Bolivia in 1991. Since then we've drilled five projects in Bolivia and only one here,&quot; said Inmet Latin America manager Marc Boisvert.</p>
<p>&quot;Each year I transfer my budget to projects elsewhere,&quot; he said. &quot;The government is good at wooing companies. They do have the right instruments in place. But we get here and we wait.&quot;</p>
<p>Inmet has begun feasibility studies on a $400-$800 million porphyry copper and gold mine in Colon province, some 125 miles (200 km) from Panama City, and is waiting for the comptroller general to ratify the agreement.</p>
<p>For this project, called Minera Petaquilla SA, Inmet is in a consortium with Canada's Teck Corp and Adrian Resources Ltd.</p>
<p>Inmet has applied for nine other exploration contracts which have not been approved, Boisvert said. &quot;Indians have a right to their lands. They only represent 30 percent of Panama. The government should act on the rest,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The bottom line, according to a mining executive who requested anonymity, is, &quot;Panama has to decide whether it wants mining.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They could say &quot;No, we're a small country and we can't handle it ...' But in that case Panama only has the canal, and nothing else.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PANAMA CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PANAMA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
