<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15861" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: PROBE LIKELY INTO S.AFRICA'S 'APARTHEID' MINES.</title>
<headline>PROBE LIKELY INTO S.AFRICA'S 'APARTHEID' MINES.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Labour Minister Tito Mboweni backed a wide-ranging inquiry into South Africa's violence- plagued mining industry on Tuesday, saying some mines were still run as they were during apartheid.</p>
<p>At least 24 miners have been killed and scores more injured in recent weeks in fights on four mines run by Gold Fields of South Africa Ltd. The violence, which has hit output, has been blamed on differences between ethnic groups and rival unions.</p>
<p>&quot;We are extremely concerned,'' Mboweni told a news conference after talks with National Union of Mineworkers (NUM) President James Motlatsi and Deputy Mineral Affairs Minister Susan Shabangu. The meeting was requested by Motlatsi.</p>
<p>Mboweni said he had also discussed the violence with Gold Fields head of gold mining Alan Munro, who had been &quot;very cooperative&quot;. The violence has affected three gold mines and one platinum operation run by Gold Fields.</p>
<p>The labour minister said he would also have talks with police minister Sydney Mufamadi on Wednesday.</p>
<p>South Africa's mining industry was built on a labour system whereby men left their wives and families for months at a time to work on the mines.</p>
<p>Mine hostels were largely segregated on ethnic lines, with Zulus, Xhosas or Basotho each in separate quarters.</p>
<p>Motlatsi told reporters he had proposed to Mboweni that a comprehensive commission of inquiry be instituted to deal with the migrant labour system and &quot;the command structure&quot; on mines.</p>
<p>&quot;The mining industry is the founder of apartheid, was a pillar of apartheid, so we need to look at that pillar to see how we make it possible to move towards the direction of democracy,&quot; the union leader said.</p>
<p>Mboweni said he favoured the proposal and would discuss it with cabinet colleagues.</p>
<p>&quot;This idea of a comprehensive commission to look into the totality of living and working conditions on the mines, I think it's important. Why is it that segregation along ethnic lines still exists? What is it that causes these fights to take an ethnic dimension?</p>
<p>&quot;I think this proposal has a lot of sense and if the government agrees to it I think it would be good to proceed with it as soon as possible,&quot; Mboweni said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is quite clear that some of the root causes of this violence are historical and in a sense some of the chickens are coming home to roost at the wrong time when now there is a democratic government,&quot; Mboweni said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
