<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24062" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Ukraine in mourning after Arctic miners' crash.</title>
<headline>Ukraine in mourning after Arctic miners' crash.</headline>
<byline>Rostislav Khotin</byline>
<dateline>KIEV 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ukrainian President Leonid Kuchma declared Friday a national day of mourning for 76 Ukrainian miners and their families killed in a Russian plane crash on the Norwegian Arctic island of Spitzbergen.</p>
<p>But trade unionists and coal industry officials said the crash would not deter more Ukrainians from braving harsh conditions to escape the low pay in the country's declining Donbass coalfields, once the power house of Soviet industry.</p>
<p>The Moscow-based Tupolev Tu-154 chartered by Russia's Arktikugol mining company crashed as it came in to land on Thursday. All 141 on board were killed.</p>
<p>Kuchma's press office said the president declared a day of mourning with a minute's silence at 4 p.m. (1200 GMT). The government promised to help the families of those killed.</p>
<p>&quot;We have set up a special commission to bury the dead,&quot; the deputy head of the regional administration in the Donbass city of Donetsk said. &quot;But it appears there is nothing left to bury -- after the crash the plane caught fire and everything burned.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There is nothing left but wreckage,&quot; Viktor Yanukovich told Reuters by telephone from the coal capital of Ukraine.</p>
<p>Asked why so many Ukrainians were working for the Russian firm in Spitzbergen, trade unionists had no doubt.</p>
<p>&quot;The answer is obvious -- money, money, money. That is what has been forcing our miners to go there,&quot; said Yuri Berdnyk, leader of the Independent Miners' union.</p>
<p>&quot;Crashes or accidents will not stop them until they are able to earn enough to keep their families in Ukraine.&quot;</p>
<p>Ukrainian miners generally live in squalid conditions and earn about $100 a month -- almost three times less than in Russia. Miners in the Arctic earn more.</p>
<p>Most of the dead miners and their families, including several children, were from the Donbass, in eastern Ukraine.</p>
<p>&quot;It's shocking. People here are very worried. We are getting dozens and dozens of telephone calls,&quot; Yanukovich said.</p>
<p>&quot;Donbass has been linked to the Spitzbergen for a long time. Many Ukrainians have worked there since the Soviet days.&quot;</p>
<p>Last year's official statistics showed that about 100,000 Ukrainians signed contracts to work in Russia after the break-up of the former Soviet Union in 1991. But Coal Ministry official Viktor Pazenko said the actual number of migrant workers was much higher, since many went seeking work unofficially.</p>
<p>About 200,000 Ukrainian miners went on strike this summer in protest at months of delay in wage payments. The government has promised to settle $600 million in wage arrears by next month.</p>
<p>It has also pledged to modernise pits, close 30 of Ukraine's 236 ageing mines and build new ones. As many as 218 miners were killed in accidents in Ukraine last year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
