<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="34178" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Anglo to probe world's deepest gold mines.</title>
<headline>Anglo to probe world's deepest gold mines.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African mining giant Anglo American Corp said on Thursday it will launch a 33 million rand seismic survey into developing two new ultra-deep gold mines that will bore up to five km (three miles) below surface.  </p>
<p>The survey, using a seismic technique similiar to sonar scanning, will cover some 60 square km south of Western Deep Levels mine southwest of Johannesburg.</p>
<p>&quot;The survey will begin soon and will take between six and 12 months to complete,&quot; said Bobby Godsell, chairman of Anglo's Gold and Uranium Division.</p>
<p>&quot;It should provide us with a better understanding -- down to 5,000 metres -- of major geological structures,&quot; Godsell said in a statement.</p>
<p>Godsell said in June this year that new technology and improved workers' skills now made it possible to reach ore deposits that were previously inaccessible.</p>
<p>Anglo believed there was an amount of gold of the order of 1,750 tonnes with an in situ grade of 12 grammes/tonne.</p>
<p>The new finds in the West Rand region would cost around five billion rand each to develop and have a lifetime of around 25 years, the company said in June.  </p>
<p>Anglo's Western Deep Levels Ltd is currently the deepest mine in the world -- nearly four kilometres into the crust.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Anglo triggered the first blast marking the start of the 1.1 billion rand South Shaft deepening project at the mine.</p>
<p>The project will deepen the shaft by about 670 metres, to a world record 3,841 metres below surface.</p>
<p>Anglo said it expected to gain an extra 475 tonnes of gold through the project.</p>
<p>&quot;This will extend Western Deep Levels' life by 14 years to 2025 and earn the company and additional 4.5 billion rand (profit after tax in real terms),&quot; Anglo said in a statement.</p>
<p>It said full production should be reached by 2005.</p>
<p>The cost of extracting gold have soared in recent years, partly because of the depth of South African mines.</p>
<p>South Africa mined 522.4 tonnes of gold last year, about 23 percent of world production.</p>
<p>-- Marius Bosch, Johannesburg newsroom, +27-11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
