<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36959" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: ZCCM invites preliminary privatisation bids.</title>
<headline>ZCCM invites preliminary privatisation bids.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Zambia Privatisation Agency (ZPA) on Friday invited pre-qualification bids for Zambia Consolidated Copper Mines Ltd's (ZCCM) assets.</p>
<p>Bids for most of the packages on offer are due by February 28, 1997, but potential bidders need to express interest by September 27, ZPA adviser NM Rothschild said in an advertisement carried in the South African press.  </p>
<p>The advertisement listed nine packages subject to tender:</p>
<p>- Nchanga and Nkana division (excluding the Kansanshi and Chambishi mines, the Chingola refractory ore dumps and the Chambishi cobalt plant). Nchanga/Nkana produced some 11.1 million tonnes of ore, 175,000 tonnes of copper cathode and 1,939 tonnes of cobalt in 1995/96;</p>
<p>- Luanshya division (excluding the Ndola precious metals plant). Ore ouput 2.9 million tonnes, copper 47,000 tones, cobalt 1,015 tonnes;</p>
<p>- Mufulira underground mine, output 52,000 tonnes copper in concentrate;</p>
<p>- Chambishi copper mine (currently non-operational), proven reserves 33.5 million tonnes at 2.55 percent copper;</p>
<p>- Kansanshi copper mine (currently small-scale operation only), indicated reserves 24.4 million tonnes at 2.90 percent copper;</p>
<p>- Nampundwe pyrite mine, output 240,000 tonnes ore;</p>
<p>- Chambishi cobalt plant, nominal capacity 2,400 tonnes, output last year 1,638 tonnes;</p>
<p>- Ndola precious metals plant;</p>
<p>- electricity transmission, distribution and generation division.  </p>
<p>The Zambian government is already negotiating with a consortium led by Anglo American Corp of South Africa Ltd on the development of the Konkola Deep mine project.</p>
<p>Developing the 350 million tonnes Konkola Deep ore body is seen as crucial to the future of Zambia's copper mining industry.</p>
<p>Anglo is a minority shareholder in state-run ZCCM.</p>
<p>Zambia produced around 380,000 tonnes of copper last year, making it the world's seventh largest producer. The government said in June it expected copper output to treble following privatisation.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
