<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45819" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.African gold and coal mines clinch wage deal.</title>
<headline>S.African gold and coal mines clinch wage deal.</headline>
<byline>Charles Phahlane</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's Chamber of Mines and the National Union of Mineworkers averted the prospect of a damaging strike on Wednesday by reaching a key wages deal for gold and coal miners.</p>
<p>Most miners are in line for wage increases of eight to 10 percent, although rates vary from a low of five to a high of 13 percent depending on conditions at individual mines.</p>
<p>The union said the agreement would also help kill off outdated mining practices from the apartheid era.</p>
<p>The powerful 350,000-strong NUM declared a dispute with the employer body, the Chamber of Mines, on August 1 and union officials had talked of a strike that would have crippled the huge gold and coal industries.</p>
<p>The union had been pushing for an average 25 percent wage increase. But chief negotiator Ikaneng Matlala said the NUM had accepted less in view of the concessions offered in restructuring miners' provident funds and on training.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite all the difficulties that we had during negotiations, we are glad that we we have arrived at a this particular agreement,&quot; Matlala said at the signing of the annual wage agreement.</p>
<p>At du Plessis, president of the Chamber of Mines, said the successful conclusion of the negotations showed dialogue between management and labour was working well.</p>
<p>&quot;This year's agreement once again underscores the impressive levels of sophistication and maturity that characterise the industrial relations climate within the South African mining industry,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>NUM official Thomas Ketsise said the restructuring of provident funds and the creation of a joint committee to review and set up training programmes would help break down old apartheid barriers.</p>
<p>&quot;Employers have been contributing more in developing white workers than black workers, but with this agreement we will gradually establish parity between white and black workers on training, retirement and death benefits,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Companies signing up to the wage deal represent the core of South Africa's mining establishment, including Anglo American Corp of South Africa Ltd, Gencor Ltd, Gold Fields of South Africa Ltd, JCI Ltd, Randgold and Exploration Co Ltd and Anglovaal Ltd.</p>
<p>Last year the NUM won an average 10.5 percent increase in basic wages in gold mines and 11.5 percent in coal mines.</p>
<p>News of this year's wage agreement help bolster gold shares on the Johannesburg Stock Exchange, already perking up as worries over falling bullion prices faded.</p>
<p>By 1305 GMT the gold share index had gained 1.44 percent to stand at 1,746.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
