<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47759" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-MIM awards A$225 mln mining contracts.</title>
<headline>RTRS-MIM awards A$225 mln mining contracts.</headline>
<dateline>BRISBANE 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Base metals miner MIM Holdings Ltd said on Wednesday it had awarded three mining contracts worth about A$225 million to Thiess Contractors Pty Ltd, a unit of Leighton Holdings Ltd.  </p>
<p>MIM said at its Oaky Creek coking coal mine in central Queensland's Bowen Basin, Thiess, in joint venture with Namoi Coal Pty Ltd, would develop a longwall punch mine from the highwall of the open cut to recover high quality coking coal not economically recoverable by open cut methods.</p>
<p>The mine plan provided for the recovery of about 57 million product tonnes of coal over six years. Development would start later this year and the longwall was scheduled to begin operating early in 1997, MIM said.</p>
<p>Coal from the longwall punch mine would be additional to Oaky Creeks production from other sources, it said.  </p>
<p>At the Collinsville coal mine in the north of the Bowen Basin, part of the Newlands-Collinsville-Abbot Point coal project, Thiess is contracted to produce coking and steaming coal from open cut operations, MIM said.</p>
<p>MIM is the manager and owns 75 percent of Collinsville, while Itochu Corp of Japan owns 25 percent.</p>
<p>This will represent the total output of Collinsville when an underground mine ceases production in the next 12 to 18 months. Collinsville annual output is about 2.2 million, MIM said.</p>
<p>Thiess has also been awarded the mining contract for the Ernest Henry copper-gold open cut mine in north-west Queensland.  </p>
<p>MIM is the manager and owns 51 percent of the Ernest Henry mine, while Savage Resources Ltd holds 49 percent.</p>
<p>MIM chief executive Nick Stump said in a statement that the contracts would result in considerable cost benefits.</p>
<p>&quot;Capital costs for mining at these operations have been eliminated for MIM and its joint venturers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Ernest Henry contract is valued at about $50 million for two and a half years, the Collinsville life of mine contract about A$50 million for the first 12 months, and the Oaky Greek contract in which Thiess is a 50 percent joint venturer, about A$125 million over six years. -- Sydney newsroom 61-2 373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRISBANE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
