<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49144" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru says to auction mining unit Yauliyacu Nov 15.</title>
<headline>Peru says to auction mining unit Yauliyacu Nov 15.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Peru's state mining company Centromin on Thursday set a November 15 date for the auction of polymetallic unit Empresa Minera Yauliyacu S.A.</p>
<p>Centromin added in a statement that the bidding details were now ready for interested parties and offers would be received on November 11 prior to the auction.</p>
<p>Yauliyaca, based in the province of Huarochiri, 75 miles (120 km) east of Lima, includes an underground mine and a concentrating plant with capacity to treat 980,000 tonnes of mineral per year. Centromin said the unit has proven and probable reserves of silver, zinc, lead and copper totalling 7.3 million tonnes.</p>
<p>&quot;Furthermore, there are potential reserves of 14.7 million tonnes. All this assures a prolonged useful life, despite the fact that it began operation in 1889,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>In 1995, 746,000 tonnes of mineral were extracted from the site. In July, Centromin launched its piecemeal sell-off with the successful auction of two of the company's major assets - the copper-rich Antamina prospect and the Quicay gold prospect.</p>
<p>But on Monday, the government declared void its intended auction of state-run polymetallic mine Yauricocha.</p>
<p>-- Andrew Cawthorne, Lima newsroom, 511 221-2134</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C182">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
