<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71759" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: FEATURE - Precious metal refiners tap China market.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Precious metal refiners tap China market.</headline>
<byline>Mishi Saran</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Deep inside a vault near Hong Kong's border with China, a young woman in a white coat examines a freshly-made five-kg (11-lb) platinum bar.</p>
<p>&quot;This is worth about half a million Hong Kong dollars,&quot; or US$64,000, she says casually, replacing the rough, palm-sized slab on a shelf.</p>
<p>The woman, a local employee of the privately-owned German precious metals refiner Heraeus Ltd, Hong Kong (HLH), then indicates with a wave of her hand stacks of one-kg (2.2. lb) gold bars produced at the firm's Hong Kong factory.</p>
<p>Like other international and local precious metal refiners based in the British colony, Heraeus is cashing in on China's dependence on Hong Kong for a steady supply of precious metals.</p>
<p>&quot;Heraeus has increased its Hong Kong refining capacity by four times, just over the last two years,&quot; said company president Juergen Schroeter.</p>
<p>It has invested HK$100 million in a new Hong Kong factory which spreads over 8,000 square metres, he said.</p>
<p>Heraeus processes several hundred tonnes a year of electronic scrap containing precious metals, and under 50 tonnes a year of jewellery scrap, including shavings, cuttings and dust, Schroeter said.</p>
<p>Heraeus-made products and services boast a large share of the Hong Kong market and are also sold to customers in the Philippines, Singapore, Malaysia, Taiwan, South Korea, Indonesia and Australia, he said.</p>
<p>Its chief rival, Britain's Johnson Matthey (JM), says the amount of gold it refines each year depends on prices.</p>
<p>&quot;Every year we refine 20 to 30 tonnes, depending on the price of gold,&quot; said JM's Hong Kong-based sales manager Anthony Tsang. &quot;This year I think we'll have 20 to 25 tonnes, because the price has not been very good.&quot;</p>
<p>Precious metal chiefs are bullish about platinum because China is a market growing at their doorsteps. &quot;We are not aware of any platinum sources within China,&quot; said Schroeter.</p>
<p>China's platinum imports in 1996 are expected to jump more than 50 percent to about 180,000 ounces, compared to 130,000 ounces in 1995, an earlier Johnson Matthey forecast said.</p>
<p>&quot;Richer Chinese people, particularly in Shanghai, now want to buy Japanese-style platinum jewellery instead of gold,&quot; said Tsang. He said JM's platinum jewellery sales to China had jumped from about two tonnes in 1995 to around 2.5 tonnes this year.</p>
<p>Its total platinum sales to China were 4.5 tonnes in 1995 and will hit 5.6 tonnes this year, Tsang said.</p>
<p>The flow of precious metals goes both ways. Hong Kong's refineries have long processed gold for the mainland, industry sources say.</p>
<p>&quot;All (Hong Kong-based) refineries get at least some of their gold from China, especially the local refiners,&quot; one source said.</p>
<p>China's state-determined gold prices lie behind this trade.</p>
<p>Gold prices in China are periodically decided by the People's Bank of China and are often lower than international market prices, prompting the flow of metal over China's borders, bullion traders say.</p>
<p>&quot;The People's Bank of China currently buys 90.0-99.0 percent purity gold at about 90 yuan (US$10.8) per gram (US$335.90 per ounce) and sells the gold to domestic manufacturers at about 105 yuan per gram ($391 an ounce) according to the World Gold Council's Shanghai representative, Helen Mao.</p>
<p>The World Gold Council is a promotional body funded by gold mining companies worldwide.</p>
<p>With world gold prices fluctuating between US$380 and $389 an ounce, the incentive to refine gold in Hong Kong, as opposed to selling it to China's central bank, is powerful, sources say.</p>
<p>Gold trickling into Hong Kong from China is normally of 97-98 percent purity and gets refined to 99.99 percent purity before being sold on behalf of Chinese customers, they added.</p>
<p>&quot;The mainland cannot crack down on this trade as no one knows what channels are used,&quot; one senior gold trader said.</p>
<p>Gold nuggets mined in China's northeast and southwest regions flow to Hong Kong's neighbouring Guangdong Province, where gold is in hot demand.</p>
<p>Some of that gold -- no one knows exactly how much -- finds its way into Hong Kong refineries.</p>
<p>These refineries could be handling more and more Chinese gold as Beijing boosts state output targets but shows little sign of price reform.</p>
<p>Annual gold production in China is set to reach 150 tonnes by the year 2000 at an average growth rate of 6.8 percent, according to an official China Daily report earlier this year.</p>
<p>But the global gold industry has always questioned China's true output of gold.</p>
<p>An analyst from consultants Gold Field's Mineral Services Ltd said earlier this year that China's official gold production figures for 1995, pegged at 108 tonnes, ignored &quot;informal production&quot; of the metal and did not take into account gold sold outside China's central bank.</p>
<p>Offical Chinese media acknowledged last month that illegal mining using primitive extraction techniques accounted for about 16 tonnes of gold produced in 1995 above official figures.</p>
<p>China is trying to eradicate unauthorised gold mining, closing 430 illegal gold pits between January and June this year and rounding up armed gangs involved in the business, the official Xinhua News Agency said.</p>
<p>But China's gold market is showing more conventional signs of opening up, boosting Hong Kong refiners' and traders' confidence in a golden future.</p>
<p>&quot;The People's Bank of China has authority to decide, according to demand, the necessity to import gold to China,&quot; said Raymond Chan Fat-chu, head of Tem Fat Hing Fung Refinery.</p>
<p>&quot;The PBOC has also issued 300 licences to bring in raw materials, process and re-export,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong remains a nerve centre for China's gold imports. The value of Hong Kong's official re-exports of gold to China in 1995 was HK$77.9 million (US$10 million), up from HK$68.0 million in 1994.</p>
<p>Anticipating further growth in the precious metals sector, Heraeus is quietly strengthening its toe hold within China.</p>
<p>In addition to being the first foreign joint-venture to obtain a government gold licence late last year, Heraeus is lobbying the Chinese government for a silver licence.</p>
<p>With the licence to process gold, joint venture Heraeus Zhaoyuan Precious Metal Materials produces gold bond wires in the northeastern Chinese province of Shandong for the computer chip industry.</p>
<p>In late 1995, the company opened Heraeus Materials Technology (HMT), a 100 percent-owned subsidiary to produce tungsten carbide balls in Shanghai for ballpoint pens.</p>
<p>Heraeus has also expanded into the sale of precious metal products such as platinum plating of anodes and cathodes for protection against corrosion.</p>
<p>US$ 1.00 = HK$ 7.79</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
