<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75338" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodia bids to open land link to rebel base.</title>
<headline>Cambodia bids to open land link to rebel base.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodian government troops are trying to open a direct land route to a dissident Khmer Rouge base as top officials try to forge a deal to merge their forces and put more pressure on the guerilla group's hardliners.</p>
<p>Troops are trying to clear mines from a key highway to allow supplies and personnel to reach dissident rebel-controlled zones, the information ministry said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Rebel areas can now only be reached only by helicopter or through Thailand.</p>
<p>The highway, Route 10, is an 85 km (52 mile) link between Cambodia's second largest city, Battambang, and the gem-mining and logging centre of Pailin, which is held by a Khmer Rouge division loyal to dissident guerrilla leader Ieng Sary.</p>
<p>&quot;They are trying to remove mines along Route 10...there is a big problem,&quot; ministry spokesman Sieng Lapresse told a weekly press briefing.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no map of the mines. Some of the mine layers died and that is why there is no real figure for mines.&quot;</p>
<p>Ieng Sary, foreign minister and deputy premier during the brutal 1975-79 Khmer Rouge rule of Pol Pot, broke last month with hardline Khmer Rouge guerrillas loyal to Pol Pot.</p>
<p>He has forged a ceasefire with the government and military commanders of the two sides gathered in Pailin on September 17 for the first meeting of a joint working group set up to discuss merging the two forces and opening up the guerrilla zones.</p>
<p>Sieng Lapresse said the talks were continuing, but did not elaborate other than to say the government was still considering what ranks they should be given in the army and police.</p>
<p>The Khmer Rouge signed a U.N.-brokered peace accord with rivals in 1991, but reneged on the pact and is fighting the coalition that emerged from general elections in 1993.</p>
<p>Khmer Rouge radio, controlled by hardliners in the north, on Wednesday claimed that rival groups in the coalition forces had clashed earlier this week in the northwest town of Sisophon.</p>
<p>The clandestine radio, monitored here, said royalists and nationalists had attacked former communists loyal to Hun Sen with tanks and scores of infantrymen on Sunday and Monday in a row over control of the Sisophon area.</p>
<p>General Nuon Vanna, deputy commander of a division said by the radio to be involved in the fighting, told Reuters: &quot;We didn't send any soldiers to Sisophon and I heard nothing about fighting in Sisophon. We are in our base.&quot;</p>
<p>The Khmer Rouge are blamed for the deaths of more than one million people during their 1970s rule of terror.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
