<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81047" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.African 1996 gold output en route to 40-year low.</title>
<headline>S.African 1996 gold output en route to 40-year low.</headline>
<byline>Melanie Cheary</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African gold production is set to slide to a 40-year low of just 500 tonnes in 1996 before beginning a slow ascent as new and enlarged mines start contributing from 1997, analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I am anticipating a slowdown in production again this year. We're probably going to hit close to the 500 tonnes total production for the year,&quot; Dave Giese, analyst at Davis, Borkum, Hare and Co Inc told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;But then we've got some major mines starting to contribute and do I believe we are going to see a turnaround in production.&quot;</p>
<p>Anglo American Corp of South Africa Ltd's 1.1 billion rand ($243 million) project to deepen the South Shaft at its Western Deep Levels Ltd will alone gain the country an extra 475 tonnes of gold over the next 14 years.</p>
<p>First blasting on the project started earlier this month.</p>
<p>Last year the industry produced 522.4 tonnes of gold -- 61.5 tonnes less than in 1994. Dismal output was blamed on ageing and costly mines, declining ore grade and low productivity due to labour unrest and additional public holidays.</p>
<p>Nick Goodwin, analyst at Fedsure Asset Management, said this year's production could even dip below 500 tonnes, cut further by violence and intimidation at some key mines.</p>
<p>&quot;Productivity on the mines leaves much to be desired. At certain mines tension has broken out into fullscale violence. Generally, the whole atmosphere is not conducive to high productivity and gold mines are very labour intensive,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>More than 50 miners have been killed and scores injured over the last three months in ethnic clashes at gold mines around Johannesburg.</p>
<p>The mines racked by violence include Driefontein Consolidated Ltd, Kloof Gold Mining Co Ltd and Buffelsfontein Gold Mining Company Ltd.</p>
<p>Analysts say production will inevitably have been hit by the violence, although other factors are major contributors to the decline.</p>
<p>&quot;Declining production is a function of the mines' downsizing in the short term. I don't attribute it that much to violence. I don't see it spreading but violence is having an impact on a few of the major producers,&quot; Giese said.</p>
<p>Rising gold theft was starting to eat into the industry's total output as well, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Every mine has got problems with gold theft. About five percent of total official production is stolen. Gold has always been stolen but is now increasing. This year we could expect about 25 tonnes of gold to be stolen,&quot; Goodwin said.</p>
<p>But local analysts disagreed with Germany's WestLB bank which said on Thursday that the current weak bullion price could strengthen soon because of falling South African production.</p>
<p>Gold fixed on Friday in London at $380.30 an ounce -- its lowest since September 6, 1995 -- hit by the International Monetary Fund's plan to sell off five million ounces, or just under five percent, of its gold reserves.</p>
<p>&quot;Saying that South Africa's declining production is likely to boost the gold price is clutching at straws,&quot; said Giese.</p>
<p>($=4.53 rand)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
