<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="22679" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Archaeologists seek proof of first Va. settlement.</title>
<headline>Archaeologists seek proof of first Va. settlement.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Plaisance</byline>
<dateline>WILLIAMSBURG, Va. 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Archaeologists may be closing in on the final piece of proof needed to authenticate the first fort built as a permanent English settlement at Jamestown, the group that owns the property said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>For two years, archaeologists have been digging at a patch of ground along the James River trying to follow what appears to be the remains of a wooden palisade, according to the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (APVA).</p>
<p>Centimetre after centimetre of soil has been sifted, yielding 90,000 artifacts, many of them dating to 1601 and indicating researchers were on the right trail, APVA spokesman Tim Kolly said.</p>
<p>Jamestown was the first permanent English settlement in North America and slavery was also instituted there.</p>
<p>The discovery of a bastion, or corner, that would enable archaeologists to trace the outline of the entire fort would clinch the discovery, Kolly said.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope we'll find something in the next few weeks to prove that the fort has been located,&quot; added William Kelso, project director. &quot;We've just accumulated little bits of the puzzle.&quot;</p>
<p>Still, the organisation was confident enough of the find to plan a September 12 announcement by Virginia Governor George Allen.</p>
<p>Dennis Blanton, co-director of the Centre for Archaeological Research at the College of William and Mary, said a finding that the remains of a wooden palisade wall along the riverbank was the remnant of the 1607 fort first built by Captain John Smith and the earliest New World settlers from Europe would mark a milestone in American archaeology.</p>
<p>&quot;If they have it, it's a world-class discovery,&quot; he said. &quot;It deserves any attention it gets. But 'if' is the key word.&quot;</p>
<p>Since the dig started archaeologists have eagerly shared their progress, exhibiting crucial pieces such as copper coins stamped &quot;1601&quot; and other artifacts.</p>
<p>For years, most archaeologists thought the last traces of the fort had been swept away by erosion along the James River.</p>
<p>Bly Straube, curator of the Jamestown Rediscovery project, said the dig site continues to yield items of interest, but no definitive artifact has been unearthed.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd like to say we've found something to say 'John Smith was here,' but we don't have it,&quot; Straube said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WILLIAMSBURG, Va."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
