<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24911" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Casket may hold Scotland's true &quot;Braveheart&quot;.</title>
<headline>Casket may hold Scotland's true &quot;Braveheart&quot;.</headline>
<byline>James Forrester</byline>
<dateline>EDINBURGH 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Archaelogists digging in an abbey destroyed by the English 400 years ago think they have found the heart of Robert the Bruce, the king who secured Scotland's independence with a victory at Bannockburn in 1314.</p>
<p>King Robert I, with only 6,000 soldiers and 500 horse, routed King Edward II and his army of 20,000. The two-day battle forced England to drop its claim to Scotland, though peace was not signed until Robert The Bruce was near death 14 years later.</p>
<p>Legend has it that his doggedness was inspired by watching a spider weave its web as he sat in a cave. His perseverance gives him as much right to the title Braveheart as his predecessor William Wallace, portrayed on film last year by Mel Gibson.</p>
<p>A 10-inch (25 cm) lead cylinder was dug from the foundations of Melrose Abbey late on Wednesday, not far from a plaque saying Bruce's embalmed heart was buried nearby.</p>
<p>The sealed red cylinder, apparently about 70 years old, was being opened in an Edinburgh laboratory on Friday to see if it holds the ancient lead casket with the heart. Earlier excavations found a casket believed to contain the heart but it was reburied in 1921 without the precise spot being noted.</p>
<p>&quot;The cylinder certainly feels heavy enough to contain another casket,&quot; said Doreen Grove of Historic Scotland, the organisation that cares for ancient monuments.</p>
<p>Grove said dating tests would be carried out to see if any casket found could be linked to the time of Bruce's death.</p>
<p>There were no plans to open the casket and because it is made of lead, it cannot be X-rayed to reveal the contents.</p>
<p>Historic Scotland intend to return the casket to Melrose Abbey and mark the site with a memorial.</p>
<p>Bruce's dying wish was that his heart should be taken to Jerusalem on a crusade against the Saracens.</p>
<p>The king was buried in Dunfermline Abbey and his trusted companion Sir James Douglas -- knighted at Bannockburn for bravery -- set off with the embalmed heart in a lead casket. Douglas was killed battling against the Moors in Spain and the heart was brought back to Scotland to be buried in Melrose Abbey.</p>
<p>Melrose, dating back to the Seventh Century, was one of Scotland's wealthiest and most powerful abbeys. It was destroyed by England's King Richard II about 50 years after Bruce's heart was buried there.</p>
<p>A new Gothic abbey was built on the site, only to be destroyed by marauding English in 1545. The stone ruins were further pillaged for building materials, used last century in many neighbouring mansions including the novelist Sir Walter Scott's imposing home at nearby Abbotsford.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EDINBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
