<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26903" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Casket said to hold heart of Scotland's Bruce.</title>
<headline>Casket said to hold heart of Scotland's Bruce.</headline>
<dateline>EDINBURGH 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Archaeologists on Monday discovered a mediaeval casket which they believe contains the embalmed heart of Robert the Bruce, the king who secured Scotland's independence from England</p>
<p>In a two-hour operation, two experts drilled through a modern lead casket found last week during excavations at Melrose Abbey in the Scottish Borders.</p>
<p>Inside was an ancient cone-shaped casket believed to contain Bruce's heart.</p>
<p>King Robert I of Scotland, with only 6,000 soldiers and 500 horse, routed English King Edward II and his army of 20,000  at Bannockburn in 1314.</p>
<p>The two-day battle forced England to drop its claim to Scotland, though peace was not signed until The Bruce was near death 14 years later.</p>
<p>Legend has it that his doggedness was inspired by watching a spider weave its web as he sat in a cave.</p>
<p>The ancient inner casket was discovered in 1921 at the abbey and found to contain an embalmed heart thought to have belonged to The Bruce, who wanted to be buried there. It was later reburied and its exact location was not known until last week.</p>
<p>Monday's operation was carried out by experts from the government body Historic Scotland at a laboratory in Edinburgh.</p>
<p>Doreen Grove of Historic Scotland said: &quot;It is definitely what we are looking for and it looks as if we will be able to take it out of the outer container. It looks strong enough.&quot;</p>
<p>The inner casket would not be opened because that was done in 1921 and there was no reason to repeat the operation.</p>
<p>Experts could not be certain it contained The Bruce's heart, but his was the only heart known to have been buried at Melrose.</p>
<p>Historic Scotland intends to return the casket to Melrose Abbey and mark the site with a memorial.</p>
<p>Bruce's dying wish was that his heart should be taken to Jerusalem on a crusade against the Saracens.</p>
<p>He was buried in Dunfermline Abbey and his trusted companion Sir James Douglas set off with the embalmed heart in a lead casket. Douglas was killed fighting the Moors in Spain and the heart brought home to be buried at Melrose.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EDINBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
