<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43329" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Prehistoric man played the blues, says scientist.</title>
<headline>Prehistoric man played the blues, says scientist.</headline>
<byline>Paul Mylrea</byline>
<dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bone flutes and wooden pipes found by archaeologists show ancient musicians deliberately played slightly off-pitch or &quot;blue&quot; notes like modern jazz and blues musicians, a scientist said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>First results from a study of how ancient instruments were actually used show the prehistoric players used techniques like sliding fingers over flute holes to &quot;bend&quot; notes.</p>
<p>Some flutes, made from bird and sheep bones as well as wood, were also carefully tuned to make these evocative sounds.</p>
<p>&quot;They were playing &quot;blue' notes in the jazz sense, notes which are slightly off line,&quot; Doctor Graeme Lawson of the University of Cambridge, head of the study, told reporters at Britain's main science festival.</p>
<p>The research, which is currently concentrating on mediaeval and Roman era flutes, could eventually yield details of ancient musicians' favourite harmonies, said Lawson, trained as both an archaeologist and a musician.</p>
<p>Studying the instruments alongside 12th century music notations from, for example, the troubadours in France could eventually even give clues to prehistoric melodies.</p>
<p>&quot;That is work for the future, but it does seem that some of the rather archaic melodies within those repertories lie comfortably within the compass of some of these simple instruments,&quot;said Lawson.</p>
<p>The breakthrough came when researchers realised that some of the flutes they were looking at had been discarded by their makers because they could not be tuned correctly.</p>
<p>Working out which instruments were tuned to their maker's satisfaction meant researchers were able to study microscopic signs of wear on flutes that were actually played to show where and how fingers were placed.</p>
<p>The researchers used carefully crafted replicas to test the sounds made by flutes, prototypes of the modern-day recorder.</p>
<p>Lawson's team hopes eventually to work out how bone pipes from the old stone age more than 20,000 years ago were played.</p>
<p>But Lawson said he believed that even stone age musicians were playing &quot;blue&quot; notes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIRMINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
