<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49463" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: English settler's fort discovered in Virginia.</title>
<headline>English settler's fort discovered in Virginia.</headline>
<dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C. 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Archaeologists have discovered the original Jamestown Fort built in 1607 on the site of the first permanent English settlement in North America, Virginia governor George Allen said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have discovered the birthplace of America,&quot; Allen said in a statement.</p>
<p>The dig team also found the remains of one of the first English settlers.</p>
<p>Archaeologists have been searching for two years for the remains of the wooden fort built by Captain John Smith, who earned lasting fame from his relationship with Indian maiden Pocahontas.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, palisade walls have been excavated. More than 1,000 artifacts were discovered from England, Spain, Scotland, Ireland, Germany, the Netherlands, Italy, Portugal and China.</p>
<p>&quot;We are all reminded that on this unequalled hallowed ground, the foundation of free people and free enterprise was begun. From this birthplace our spirit formed a great state, nation and ideals emulated by people across the world,&quot; Allen said.</p>
<p>He was speaking at a ceremony complete with actors in period dress and with a full-scale replica of a settler's ship anchored off-shore.</p>
<p>Archaeologists on Wednesday announced they had discovered the remains of an early settler at Jamestown.</p>
<p>The Virginia newspaper Daily Press quoted forensic anthropologist Doug Owsley of the Smithsonian Institute as saying the skeleton was of a white male in his early 20's.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a violent death,&quot; Owsley was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>He had a wound to his right leg caused by a musketball and also a defect in his right shoulder which could also be from a musketball, Owsley said.</p>
<p>He dated the death to the settlement's earliest period.</p>
<p>The remains were believed to be of an important figure as he was buried in a coffin, which was rare in early settlements, Oswley added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHARLOTTE, N.C."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
