<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53140" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Tomb of pharaoh found near Valley of Kings.</title>
<headline>Tomb of pharaoh found near Valley of Kings.</headline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Egyptian authorities have found the tomb of a pharaoh near the Valley of the Kings in the ancient capital Luxor, the government newspaper al-Ahram said.</p>
<p>The pharaoh has not yet been identified but he belonged to the 19th dynasty, which ruled Egypt between 1320 and 1200 BC -- the &quot;silver age&quot; of the pharaonic empire.</p>
<p>The tomb contains a sarcophagus and a mummy, probably of the pharaoh itself, the Saturday edition of the newspaper reported.</p>
<p>It did not say if the tomb. like those of most pharaohs, was robbed in ancient times but the list of contents suggested most of the burial goods had disappeared.</p>
<p>A man who works for the state antiquities department discovered the tomb 10 years ago but instead of reporting it to the authorities, he built a house over the entrance in the hope of finding treasures inside, it said.</p>
<p>The underground tomb contains a large hall with 10 columns, six of them marble, statues of the pharaoh and his wife and a burial chamber with the large red granite sarcophagus and the complete mummy nearby, swaddled in its linen wrappings.</p>
<p>The sacrophagus, two metres (six feet) long and one metre (three feet) tall, has a complete lid and is decorated with hieroglyphic writing and drawings in colour, it added.</p>
<p>It said the burial chamber lay at the end of a spiral corridor 100 metres (yards) long, leading off the pillared hall.</p>
<p>The house is in the village of Gurna, about 2 km (one mile) from the Valley of the Kings, the graveyard of most pharaohs throughout the second half of the 2nd millenium BC. The valley contains the famous tomb of Tutankhamun, which British Egyptologist Howard Carter found intact in 1922.</p>
<p>The Egyptian authorities have tried for years to move people away from the Gurna area because of the tombs but they have met stiff resistance from families which have profited from the antiquities business for generations.</p>
<p>Al-Ahram said the man who built the house had been planning to sell the contents of the tomb abroad through a brother who lives in Europe. He had been excavating the site with the help of his father and his brother, both of whom work or have worked for the Antiquities Department.</p>
<p>The case is bound to put the spotlight back on the security of Egyptian antiquities after this week's attempt to steal some of Tutankhamun's treasures from the Egyptian Museum in Cairo.</p>
<p>A young unemployed Egyptian man spent Wednesday night inside the museum and managed to remove 24 objects from the showcases. He was caught as he tried to leave the museum in the morning.</p>
<p>On Thursday Prime Minister Kamal Ganzouri appointed a new secretary general of the Supreme Council for Antiquities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
