<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60110" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: FEATURE - Portugal displays unique array of stone age art.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Portugal displays unique array of stone age art.</headline>
<byline>Richard Waddington</byline>
<dateline>VILA NOVA DE FOZ COA, Portugal 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Far from the urban bustle, down a long, dusty mountain track in northern Portugal lies one of the world's largest art displays.</p>
<p>None of the artists is known nor has any received a fee or made a sale, and their anonymous work is scattered over several kilometres (miles) of riverside rocks.</p>
<p>On show along the banks of Portugal's river Coa are the scratched rock drawings of stone age hunters who inhabited the rolling hills and deep river valleys more than 10,000 years ago.</p>
<p>Foz Coa, 350 km (220 miles) northeast of Lisbon, is regarded as the world's largest open-air collection of Paleolithic art, with a thousand drawings already catalogued on 36 rock &quot;canvasses&quot; in one site alone.</p>
<p>Archaeologists say the numbers will multiply as investigations intensify in the 14 sites so far identified and extend into fresh areas, including some across the nearby border with Spain.</p>
<p>&quot;Many more are going to appear when we begin to study the rest of the valley and other (river) tributaries,&quot; said archaeology professor Joao Zilhao, who heads the research effort.</p>
<p>The pictorial treasure trove featuring horses, cattle, deer and some animals long since extinct was nearly lost before its full extent had been appreciated.</p>
<p>The Portuguese state electricity company EDP had planned an hydro-electric dam across the river Coa that would have turned the whole area into a large reservoir.</p>
<p>But the scheme was shelved by the new Socialist government in November last year after archaeologists, alerted by initial finds, orchestrated an international campaign on behalf of the rock drawings.</p>
<p>Tensions were exacerbated by the fact that an archaeologist contracted by EDP discovered the first paintings in 1992 while carrying out a study, but their existence was kept secret for more than two years.</p>
<p>The decision to halt work on the dam was preceded by an highly vitriolic and public battle between archaeologists and the state electricity company which at one point sought to prove that the drawings were not as old as claimed.</p>
<p>EDP issued extracts of studies by four international dating experts appearing to cast doubt on the age of the drawings. But two of the experts have subsequently said that the extracts misinterpreted their conclusions.</p>
<p>Officially, the dam project is only on hold, awaiting a definitive report on whether the drawings belong to the upper Paleolithic period, 10,000-30,000 years ago.</p>
<p>But Zilhao, who is coordinating work on the report, says there is absolutely no doubt about what its conclusions will be.</p>
<p>&quot;(The argument) is all over and done with. I do not know anybody that doubts the age of the drawings,&quot; he told journalists.</p>
<p>The government also seems to have no doubts because it is helping finance an archaeological park in the area.</p>
<p>The park is part of a 32-billion-escudo ($207 million), three-year development project for the Coa area, drawn up speedily to compensate local people who feared that loss of the dam could mean lost jobs.</p>
<p>Limits on the availability of transport and guides will restrict the number of visitors to around 30,000 a year -- so people will probably have to book in the peak summer season, Zilhao said.</p>
<p>Since the park opened its doors a couple of weeks ago, some 1,500 visitors have paid the 500 escudos entrance fee and taken the bumpy jeep ride down to the riverside art show.</p>
<p>On one such trip, a group of journalists was taken to a site called Penascosa, one of three out of the 14 that can currently can be visited.</p>
<p>The site contains some 15 engravings of differing degrees of clarity collected on three rock surfaces, with the star exhibit being a drawing that the archaeologists jokingly refer to as the &quot;Benetton Ad.&quot;</p>
<p>The picture shows two horses mating -- a theme adopted by the Italian clothes firm in its latest controversial publicity campaign.</p>
<p>One curious aspect of the rock carving is that the head of the male horse is shown in three different positions as if the stone age artist was attempting to give the impression of movement.</p>
<p>&quot;And we thought animated drawing was a 20th century invention,&quot; joked Zilhao, who acted as guide on the tour.</p>
<p>Archaeologists believe the explanation for the preservation of the art lies in the dry climate and the resistant schist rock which abounds in the area.</p>
<p>The same rock is also responsible for the special soils on which the port grape, used for the country's most famous wine, flourishes in this part of the country.</p>
<p>For the archaeologists, the paintings are far more than museum pieces. They offer the opportunity to seek answers to questions about the beliefs and habits of stone age man.</p>
<p>Why were certain rocks chosen, with often several overlapping drawings being done on the same surface, when other seemingly just as suitable sites were ignored?</p>
<p>&quot;We have a wonderful chance to study what they considered important, whether it be for economic, social or religious reasons,&quot; said Zilhao. ($1=154.7 Escudo)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VILA NOVA DE FOZ COA, Portugal"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
