<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68718" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australians say art find may rewrite history.</title>
<headline>Australians say art find may rewrite history.</headline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian archaeologists have found aboriginal stone tools and rock art they claim date back more than 116,000 years and could rewrite conventional theories of prehistory.</p>
<p>Research team leader Richard Fullagar said on Saturday the stone chips found at a dig in Australia's remote northwest showed humans lived there between 116,000 and 176,000 years ago, around the time of the emergence of modern human form in Africa.</p>
<p>&quot;The initial samples were taken four to five years ago now, and we were so shocked with the results that we have been trying to go over them and trying to disprove these things, and we can't do that,&quot; Fullagar said in a radio interview.</p>
<p>The artefacts dramatically push back the earliest human occupation of Australia and roughly coincide with the emergence of homo sapiens in Africa, Fullagar and the Sydney Morning Herald newspaper said.</p>
<p>&quot;This almost doubles the previous estimates of the age of aboriginal occupation on the continent,&quot; the research team said in a short statement issued on Saturday morning.</p>
<p>The discoveries, at a site dubbed &quot;Australia's Stonehenge&quot;, also include rock engravings dating back 58,000 to 75,000 years, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is also some ochre (commonly used in aboriginal art) at the slightly higher level than the stone artefacts. Up at the level which is around about 58,000 to 75,000 years ago, there is an (engraved) sandstone slab,&quot; Fullagar said.</p>
<p>The age of the engravings was determined by dating the sediments in which they were found, he said. &quot;They are perhaps the oldest rock art anywhere in the world,&quot; Fullagar said.</p>
<p>The team of four archaeologists from the Australian Museum and University of Wollongong plan to publish their findings in British science journal &quot;Antiquity&quot; in December, the Herald said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
