<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70303" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Sept 24.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Sept 24.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Following a surprise, and so far unannounced, decision by the Reserve Bank of Australia to adopt new rules making it easier for banks to invest in mortgage-based securities, the country's home loan war will get a large injection of funds which will almost certainly result in a reduction in lending interest rates. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian Wheat Board yesterday dropped its expected return for the coming big harvest by another A$10 a tonne, the latest revision to the benchmark Australian Standard White grade to A$195 a tonne meaning the estimate has shed A$50 since growers were planting four months ago, taking it below the psychologically critical A$200 mark and eroding much of the rural buoyancy generated by the forecast 19 million tonne harvest. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Health Minister Michael Wooldridge has told The Australian Financial Review the Federal Government has lowered its expectation that all States would agree to take more responsibility for health and family services. He revealed that Western Australia and Victoria are keen to have more control over key health areas, while the remaining States still have doubts. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Following research conducted by Newspoll and Macquarie University's Professor Murray Goot and commissioned by the Labor Council of New South Wales after the Federal election, a further fall in union membership in the wake of the Coalition's industrial reltions reforms has been predicted. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Responding to Prime Minister John Howard's claim that Australian people can now &quot;talk about certain things without fear of being branded as a bigot or as a racist&quot;, Independent MP Pauline Hanson, who caused a stir with her maiden speech which called for a review of Australia's immigration policy and the abolition of multiculturalism, endorsed Howard as a &quot;strong leader&quot;. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Leading archaeologist Mike Morwood, who was appointed to authenticate and comment on a scientific paper on the recently discovered ancient rock carvings and stone artefacts at Jinmium in the Northern Territory, has attacked key aspects of research underpining the age of the find, and has recommended against publication. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The New South Wales Government's forestry package, which includes plans for the creation of 10 new national parks and 12 new wilderness areas, was yesterday hailed as a blueprint for national reform after a delicate balancing act secured the national park while providing 10-year guarantees for the timber industry. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Speaking at the &quot;Managing Higher Education in a Changing Environment&quot; conference in Sydney, Education Minister Amanda Vanstone said universities are supposed to lead the community, but instead they feel helpless and totally dependent on Government and are&quot;afraid of the dark&quot;. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>In announcing his Government's interim forests and wilderness package yesterday, New South Wales Premier Bob Carr revealed the plan would incorporate 10 new national parks, 12 new wilderness areas and provide the timber industry with renewable five-year cntracts. Carr said the State would now have the best national park system in the world. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Herald has learnt from police sources, Paul Green, who was shot dead by police during a drug raid at Newcastle last Friday, had not fired a shotgun at detectives as police initially claimed. Last week, police claimed Green had been killed in an &quot;exchange of fire&quot; when Drug Enforcement Agency officers raided the house. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>After a team of scientists from Wollongong University and the Australian Museum found a rock site in the Northern Territory last week that was thought to be at least 75,000 years old, massive archaeological excavations are to begin across the Territory in an attempt to find further evidence of Australia's ancient human occupation. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Amid growing criticism across the political spectrum of Prime Minister John Howard's response to overt racism in Independent MP Pauline Hanson's comments on multiculturalism and immigration, former Prime Minister Malcolm Fraser yesterday branded the politcal attacks on Asians and Aborigines &quot;totally obnoxious&quot;. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>Uniting Church leadership was split last night after a shock vote by the Synod to reject Reverend Jenny Byrnes, the sole candidate for the position of State regulator. The decision left several people attending its policy-making council in tears. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission chairman Allan Fels, the man most likely to oversee the imminent shake-up in media ownership, last night warned the Howard Government not to scrap existing laws banning cross-media ownership without reinforcig other barriers against an undesirable dominance, as he said the present anti-monopoly rules were not designed to enforce social goals such as media diversity. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to a Monash University Accident Research Centre study, alcohol was the most significant factor contributing to a surge in single vehicle fatalities this year. In rural areas however, police warned that carelessness and inexperience had led to a 0 per cent increase in fatalities. Page A3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>After an 18-month-old baby and two toddlers, who were left in the care of neighbours whose house was connected by an inside door, were rescued from their burning house in Port Fairy, the Royal Children's Hospital Safety Centre warned parents not to leave their children alone. Page A3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
