<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73431" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Palestinians call Jerusalem tunnel a crime.</title>
<headline>Palestinians call Jerusalem tunnel a crime.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Angry Palestinians protested after Israeli workmen laboured through the night to open a controversial tunnel on Tuesday beside the Temple Mount, site of Islam's third holiest shrine.</p>
<p>Palestinian merchants in Jerusalem's Old City closed their shops and hundreds of demonstrators condemned the opening of the tunnel, carried out by workmen under heavy guard. There were no immediate reports of violence.</p>
<p>Israel hailed it as an important archaeological site but in the Gaza Strip, Palestinian President Yasser Arafat called it a crime against Moslem holy sites in the heart of the disputed city.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a crime, a big crime against our religious and holy places,&quot; Arafat told policemen in Jabalya camp, terming it a breach of Israeli-PLO peace deals.</p>
<p>However, Deputy Israeli Mayor of Jerusalem Shmuel Meir praised right-wing Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu for deciding to complete the tunnel, which other prime ministers had resisted, apparently for fear of triggering Palestinian violence.</p>
<p>The 488-meter (500 yd) tunnel runs along the Wailing Wall, the retaining wall along the side of the compound housing the Dome of the Rock and Al-Aqsa mosque.</p>
<p>It comes out on the Via Dolorosa, the traditional route of Jesus' walk before his crucifixion, and was immediately opened to tourists.</p>
<p>The Temple Mount compound is sacred to both Jews and Moslems and is the heart of the Old City that Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
<p>The future of East Jerusalem, which Palestinians want as the capital of an independent Palestine, was to be negotiated under an Israeli-Palestinian accord signed in 1993. However, Netanyahu, who took office in June, has refused to discuss relinquishing control of East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Senior Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erekat told Reuters that policies like the opening of the controversial tunnel &quot;push the Palestinians and Israelis towards...confrontation and catastrophe.&quot;</p>
<p>Israeli archaeological digging on the edges of the Temple Mount, including the tunnel, have long aroused charges in the Arab world that they are part of a campaign to strengthen Israeli control and undermine Moslem sacred sites.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
