<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74010" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: People walked Australia for 200,000 years - researcher.</title>
<headline>People walked Australia for 200,000 years - researcher.</headline>
<byline>Mark Bendeich</byline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Claims that humans have walked Australia for well over 100,000 years drew unexpected support on Tuesday when a scientist said he had separately dated human occupation of the continent to as far back as 200,000 years.</p>
<p>Three days after Australian researchers claimed they had found stone artefacts dating back 116,000 to 176,000 years in a discovery they said could rewrite prehistory, a Melbourne scientist said his own research seemed to confirm the findings.</p>
<p>&quot;It confirms their work ...,&quot; said Sander van der Kaars, a research fellow at Monash University, referring to the four-member research team which unearthed the stone artefacts in the country's arid and remote northwest.</p>
<p>&quot;With all the limitations of accuracy and dating, it's more likely that you are talking about the same period,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Van der Kaars, who dated ancient charcoal sediment he believed was left by man-made fire, revealed his findings as members of the Australian scientific community expressed doubt about such an early arrival of humans in Australia.</p>
<p>The stone artefacts, found beneath an ancient rock art site dubbed &quot;Australia's Stonehenge&quot;, and the charcoal imply that humans had arrived here by sea over 60,000 years earlier than thought, the two groups of researchers say.</p>
<p>The two research projects also could support suggestions that modern humans originated in Asia, nor Africa, because the new dates for human occupation of Australia roughly coincide with the emergence of Homo sapiens in Africa, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Because they (the artefacts and charcoal) were dated using two different techniques, they should strengthen the evidence in the eyes of the archaeological world,&quot; van der Kaars told Reuters.</p>
<p>Van der Kaars said he had taken the charcoal sediment from a 11-year-old sea-bed core extracted in Indonesian waters southeast of the resort island of Bali, off northwest Australia, as part of studies into climate change.</p>
<p>The charcoal was swept off the continent and settled on the sea floor along with Australian pollen about 200,000 years ago, he said. The charcoal was likely to have come from man-made fires because of the warm, humid climate at the time, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;It does suggest human impact rather than natural change,&quot; he said. &quot;In itself it's not conclusive evidence ... but it has opened a number of questions and a lot of additional research is needed,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Van der Kaars said he used a dating technique known as oxygen isotope stratigraphy with a margin of error of around 7,000 years.</p>
<p>The thermoluminescence technique used to date the stone artefacts had an error margin of 2,000 to 10,000 years, he said.</p>
<p>The dating of the stone artefacts came under fire on Tuesday from scientists who doubt its accuracy.</p>
<p>The Australian newspaper quoted archaeologist Mike Morwood, appointed to comment on research done at the rock art site, as saying evidence for the claimed antiquity of the stone artefacts was &quot;extremely tenuous&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
