<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78749" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Archeology follows copper trail in Mexico.</title>
<headline>Archeology follows copper trail in Mexico.</headline>
<byline>Joanne Kenen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A copper and bronze trail of bells, tweezers and other artifacts could transform how archaeologists look at the political and cultural powerhouses of pre-Colombian Mexico, researchers said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Research appearing in Friday's edition of the journal Science links metal artifacts from sites as far away as Belize and the Yucatan with mines and ore deposits in western Mexico, long thought to be an ancient backwater.</p>
<p>&quot;Western Mexico had not been considered a major player in Mesoamerican events,&quot; said Dorothy Hosler, an archaeologist and expert in ancient technology at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
<p>&quot;But these findings show that these people were interacting in an intensive and significant way with other political entities,&quot; said Hosler, who with her Florida International University co-author Andrew Macfarlane used lead isotope analysis to analyse the metal alloys in the artifacts and link them to the West Mexican mines.</p>
<p>The archaeologists believe that their findings establish that the peoples of western Mexico, including one group known as Tarascans, were deeply involved in the complex network of trade and commerce across Mexico from around 1200 to 1521 A.D.</p>
<p>By exporting objects that had sacred or political significance, they affected the religious and ritual behaviours of the region, not just the economy, said Hosler.</p>
<p>She would like to turn her attention to finding the worksites or processing centres to learn more about the artisans, culture and trade.</p>
<p>Because of their grand pyramids and architectural monuments, as well as their well-documented contacts with the Spanish conquest, the Aztecs and the Maya have been the most studied.</p>
<p>But the Tarascans, who lived in the highlands of Michoacan &quot;are really considered an empire. They defeated the Aztecs in various skirmishes,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>They controlled some mining sites in Michoacan while sites in nearby Jalisco were &quot;presumably under the control of smaller political entities,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Metallurgy was developed in South America and made its way to Mesoamerica, partly via a coastal maritime route, in around 600 to 700 A.D., she said. It advanced over the next 500 years or so in what is now western Mexico.</p>
<p>Characteristic artifacts included bells, used in healing rituals, shamanistic ceremonies and to communicate with the supernatural and tweezers, particularly oversized tweezers worn as adornments by priests and other members of the elite and probably used to remove facial hair.</p>
<p>&quot;Tweezers have a fascinating history. They were very elaborate and they became some sort of a symbol of political and social power,&quot; added Hosler, who was funded in part by mining and smelting companies in Mexico, Peru and the United States with an interest in uncovering their history.</p>
<p>Hosler believes that her findings will encourage other archaeologists and anthropologists to take another look at the region, and to start looking for further evidence of trade routes.</p>
<p>&quot;I think what will happen is people may start looking for these kind of analogies in other materials, like obsidian, which shows up all over Mesoamerica,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>One question she asks is: If the westerners exported metal products, what did they import in exchange?</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
