<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79369" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Discovery Communications buys Lancit stake.</title>
<headline>Discovery Communications buys Lancit stake.</headline>
<dateline>BETHESDA, Md. 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Discovery Communications Inc said it purchased 6.6 percent of Lancit Media Productions Ltd and may purchase an additional 6.2 percent.</p>
<p>Discovery also said it will fully fund the development and production costs of approved and newly developed Lancit children's programming, interstitial elements and promotional spots for Discovery.</p>
<p>Discovery said it made an initial $5 million investment in Lancit, acquiring 6.6 percent stake, representing 438,116 shares valued at $11.41 per share, and four year warrants to purchase an additional 438,116 shares at $13.00 per share.  </p>
<p>Discovery is a Bethesda, Md.-based media company whose businesses include cable television's Discovery Channel and retailing's The Nature Company, which is owned by Liberty Media Corp, a division of Tele-Communications Inc , Cox Communications Inc, Advance/Newhouse Communications and John S. Hendricks, the company's founder and chief executive.</p>
<p>&quot;This investment makes strategic sense for two reasons -- as the next step in our company's plans to move aggressively across multiple platforms into the children's marketplace.  </p>
<p>&quot;And as a signal that we are actively seeking production partners across a wide range of programming genres with varying target audiences,&quot; said Discovery President Judith McHale.</p>
<p>She said the partnership with Lancit Media is expected to enhance Discovery's recently announced expansion plans into the children's marketplace by creating programming for:</p>
<p>-- a Sunday morning block of children's programs on Discovery Channel debuting in early 1997;</p>
<p>-- a new 24-hour cable and satellite-delivered channel, Discovery Kids, beginning Oct. 20, 1996; and  </p>
<p>-- a Discovery Kids network in Latin America, to launch in November 1996.</p>
<p>Lancit's programs could also strengthen The Learning Channel's award-winning week-day morning programming block entitled Ready, Set, Learn!, McHale said.</p>
<p>Allen &amp; Co Inc initiated the proposed alliance and is acting as financial advisor to Lancit Media.</p>
<p>&quot;The Discovery alliance addresses several strategic objectives that were articulated when we first commenced discussions with Allen &amp; Co,&quot; said Lancit chief executive Cecily Truett.</p>
<p>&quot;The partnership will provide access to a valuable airing venue for future Lancit-produced programs as well as a source of equity capital and positive cash flow to support future growth.&quot; -- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741112">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BETHESDA, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
