<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81084" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FEATURE-King and queen help S.Africa piece together past.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-King and queen help S.Africa piece together past.</headline>
<byline>Richard Meares</byline>
<dateline>THULAMELA, South Africa 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>In rolling hills roamed by lions, South Africa has discovered the citadel of an aloof king and queen that experts say will help rewrite both the distant and near past.</p>
<p>The unearthing of southern Africa's first royal remains, along with gold jewellery, West African-style ornaments and even Chinese pottery, has been hailed as the most exciting find for years.</p>
<p>Archaeologists say Thulamela has given up clues that will help piece together the largely unknown history of the area and its people. The hilltop site, deep in the Kruger National Park bush, was used from 1200 to 1640, then suddenly abandoned.</p>
<p>Its links with Great Zimbabwe, a mysterious ancient city across the present-day border that housed 14,000 people despite arid land, are clear.</p>
<p>Politicians say Thulamela has also given the lie to the apartheid version of history which held that South Africa's interior was empty when the whites arrived at the Cape in 1652 -- and that the blacks who came later were savages.</p>
<p>&quot;We always knew these were lies but we never had the evidence. Now we have that evidence,&quot; Environment Minister Pallo Jordan told some 850 people celebrating Thulamela's official opening on Tuesday, the Heritage Day holiday.</p>
<p>Gold braid, beads and bracelets testify to the king and queen's immense wealth. The Chinese pottery and gongs, believed to be West African, also showed their people traded extensively.</p>
<p>Archaeologist Sydney Miller has spent the last three years scouring the country's remote northeastern corner for &quot;lost cities&quot;, told of in the oral history of tribes banished from their land in 1969 to make way for wild animals.</p>
<p>Thulamela, or &quot;the place of giving birth&quot;, is surrounded by fat 1,000-year-old baobab trees and overlooks a long-distance elephant trail that locals also used as a trade route.</p>
<p>&quot;It is playing an important part in the reconstruction of the history of South Africa,&quot; Miller said.</p>
<p>He climbed its steep hill about 1,000 times to dig under the scorching sun -- protected by armed rangers against lions, leopards and elephants -- before his team's effort paid off.</p>
<p>The first gold beads were unearthed a few months ago.</p>
<p>Beneath two tall grey syringa trees, right on the crest of the hill with views into neighbouring Mozambique, Miller and his team then found the king, who was around 45 to 60 when he died.</p>
<p>They nicknamed him Ingwe (Leopard), after two of the wild cats appeared nearby as the discovery was made.</p>
<p>His body had been dismembered and neatly laid to rest, possibly following a custom in which the leader's bodily fluids would be collected for his successor to drink.</p>
<p>Ingwe's queen, curled in a foetal position denoting respect, was buried separately but still within the high stone walls.</p>
<p>The royal couple are being examined by scientists and will then be reburied where they lay for up to 400 years.</p>
<p>Ethnologists believe they followed the ideology of sacred leadership, meaning the aloof royals would rarely have appeared to the 1,500 or so common folk who lived in thatched huts below.</p>
<p>They appear to be the last rulers of Thulamela before its people -- believed to be the trader-farmer ancestors of the region's Venda tribe -- moved on to a new home.</p>
<p>Experts think that Thulamela itself and several other sites nearby were founded after an exodus of people from Great Zimbabwe as it lost control of its far-flung kingdom.</p>
<p>Life at Thulamela seems to have been peaceful, unlike nearby Makahane whose cruel king, legend has it, made women work naked in the fields and killed any man who objected.</p>
<p>He hung warriors over a cliff by their ankles and dropped them if they failed to catch a vulture or eagle chick.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not clear what happened to the people of Thulamela after the late 17th Century. Further studies will hopefully shed more light,&quot; said a small new exhibition near the site.</p>
<p>The two-metre (six-foot) high walls of the royal compound have just been reconstructed from the stones that lay for centuries just where they had fallen, knocked down by tree roots, wind or clambering impala antelopes.</p>
<p>&quot;This site was known to the old people but they never came because they said the drums spoke here,&quot; Miller said.</p>
<p>The Kruger park, South Africa's largest wildlife reserve, covers two million hectares (nearly five million acres) and is about as big as Belgium. It has more than 250 archaeological or historical sites.</p>
<p>&quot;Thulamela is just the match that will light the fire,&quot; Miller said.</p>
<p>But with five or so field archaeologists in all South Africa, most of the park's secrets will stay as such for a long time.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="THULAMELA, South Africa"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
