<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83284" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Egyptian pyramid site reopens after army pulls out.</title>
<headline>Egyptian pyramid site reopens after army pulls out.</headline>
<byline>Mahmoud Ali</byline>
<dateline>DAHSHOUR, Egypt 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Egypt reopened one of its best endowed pyramid sites to the public on Saturday, 40 years after the Egyptian military turned the area into an army base and sealed it off from the outside world.</p>
<p>The group of five large pyramids, at Dahshour 40 km (25 miles) south of Cairo, are second only to the famous trio at Giza and have the advantage of lying in largely unspoiled desert, away from the traffic and high-rise buildings of Giza.</p>
<p>They also include the world's first true pyramid and the only rhomboidal or &quot;bent&quot; pyramid -- both built by the pharaoh Snerefu at a time of architectural experimentation.</p>
<p>Sneferu, who ruled Egypt in about 2600 BC, was the father of Cheops, the man who built the Great Pyramid at Giza.</p>
<p>&quot;These make it one of the most important archaeogolical sites in the ancient world,&quot; said Ali Hassan, secretary general of Egypt's Supreme Council for Antiquities.</p>
<p>&quot;It is also one of the places which you can smell the history of Egypt. The desert is virgin, there is no invasion of modern building and no pollution. And you can see pyramids from both the Old Kingdom amd the Middle Kingdom,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Bent Pyramid, the shape of which no one has ever explained to the satisfaction of all, contains cedarwood beams imported by ship from Lebanon and still in good condition more than 4,000 years later, he said.</p>
<p>A trickle of foreign tourists came to the site on opening day and were delighted by what they saw.</p>
<p>&quot;I used to come around and look from afar. I always hoped that this day would come, to let people who enjoy pyramids and antiquities come and visit them,&quot; said an Italian visitor.</p>
<p>&quot;This is how we imagined Giza -- pyramids in the middle of nowhere. It's very, very impressive,&quot; said an Englishwoman.</p>
<p>Culture Minister Farouk Hosni, who formally opened the area, said that after long talks the antiquities department persuaded the army to evacuate the site two years ago and had spent the time since then preparing the area for visitors.</p>
<p>&quot;No buildings will be allowed for a good distance all around. We have agreed that with the military,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In the case of Giza, the antiquities department has fought a running battle with developers to protect the site from encroachment. Last year the government eventually abandoned plans to build a ring road right across the Giza plateau.</p>
<p>But perhaps the biggest gain will be to archaeologists, who have hardly touched the site.</p>
<p>&quot;Almost nothing has been done since (British Egyptologists) Perring and Vyse came in the 1830s,&quot; said Hassan.</p>
<p>A new wave of achaeologists will want to find out why there is no burial chamber and no trace of a burial or a mortuary temple in Snerefu's true pyramid, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;A door has been opened for scholars to come and work. The elements of this pyramid have not yet been completely found. We need excavations to explain the unknown. There is work here for years and years to come,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dieter Arnold, the curator of Egyptian art at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, told reporters he would be interested in the three Middle Kingdom pyramids at Dahshour, built by the Pharaohs Senusert III, Amenemhat II and Amenemhat III about 800 years after Sneferu.</p>
<p>He said he believed the ruined mortuary temples at these pyramids may have been the prototype for the giant temples which stand intact on the west bank of the Nile near the southern town of Luxor, capital of Egypt another 300 years later.</p>
<p>Visitors will eventually be able to enter almost all the Dahshour pyramids, once they are clear of the damage caused by grave robbers and by time.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DAHSHOUR, Egypt"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
