<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13685" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Ford says hopes &quot;to be best&quot; in India auto market.</title>
<headline>Ford says hopes &quot;to be best&quot; in India auto market.</headline>
<dateline>NASHIK, India 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chief of U.S. car giant Ford Motor Company said on Monday that it was bracing itself to face India's competitive automobile market and hoped to be &quot;the best among competitors&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It is going to be a very competitive market, but we are confident given the people, technology and quality we are going to be the best among competitors,&quot; Alex Trotman said.</p>
<p>Asked if there was room for everyone in India's crowded car market where several foreign manufacturers are pitching in to grab a share of the growing demand, he said: &quot;Probably not.&quot;</p>
<p>Trotman was speaking to reporters at this western Indian city of Nashik, 225 km (140 miles) northeast of Bombay, at a ceremony to mark the launch of Ford's first Indian made car at the company's joint venture plant.</p>
<p>The Ford Escort is produced by a joint venture between Ford and India's Mahindra &amp; Mahindra, each owning 50 percent equity.</p>
<p>The Ford chief said the company had no plans to raise its holding in Mahindra Ford India Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;We are satisfied with equity relations with the partner and don't wish to change that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Responding to a reporter's query if Ford has plans to launch an Asia-specific vehicle, Trotman said:</p>
<p>&quot;We are studying that kind of vehicle. Yes, quite a bit of advanced work is going on, on that kind of vehicle.&quot;</p>
<p>The firm expects to put a price tag on the Ford Escort next week, John Parker, president and managing director of the joint venture firm said.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be competitively priced with Ceilo and Esteem,&quot; Parker said.</p>
<p>Ceilo is manufactured by DCM-Daewoo, a joint venture between India's DCM group and South Korea's Daewoo Motor, a unit of Daewoo Group.</p>
<p>Esteem is produced by Maruti Udyog, a venture between the Indian government and Japan's Suzuki Motor Corp.</p>
<p>The Mahindra Ford plant has a capacity to make 25,000 cars annually and it has plans to set up a second unit in southern Tamil Nadu state.</p>
<p>It is initially launching four models of Ford Escort followed by Siesta.</p>
<p>&quot;We haven't decided,&quot; said Trotman when asked if more models would be launched. &quot;In ten years we would have half a dozen of Ford vehicles in India.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Bombay newsroom +91-22-265-9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NASHIK, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
