<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17217" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Global car makers seen overcrowding Indian market.</title>
<headline>Global car makers seen overcrowding Indian market.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Global auto giants are rushing into India's car market, lured by rising demand, but industry analysts said on Tuesday that they may find the going tough.</p>
<p>Demand is forecast to treble from current levels to one million units by the year 2000. But analysts said demand was growing at the cheaper end of the price spectrum while most companies are raising capacity for mid-range vehicles.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no place for more than three or four car makers in the middle and premium segment,&quot; said Rohit Rana, an analyst with Hoare Govett (India) Securities.</p>
<p>In the Indian market, cars priced below 400,000 rupees ($11,205) make up the economy segment of the market while cars costing between 400,000 and 700,000 rupees belong to the mid-sized segment, industry officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;A major share in the market belongs to the economy models. The middle segment will have about 30 percent of market share,&quot; said Shripad Bhat, assistant director of the Association of Indian Automobile Manufacturers.</p>
<p>A host of foreign companies led by Daewoo and Hyundai of South Korea, General Motors and  Ford Motor Company of the United States, Japan's Honda and Germany's Daimler Benz have set up ventures to grab a slice of the India's mid-priced auto market.</p>
<p>The domestic car market in India, the world's second most populous nation, is forecast to grow to around one million units by fiscal 2000/01 compared to 345,355 in 1995/96 (April-March), analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;In the middle segment the demand will be about 200,000-250,000 units while the total capacity will be 550,000-600,000,&quot; Rana said.</p>
<p>This could force a shakeout in the Indian auto industry, which could force some companies to fold, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Margins will be tight and producers will have to look at volumes,&quot; Rana said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is going to be a very competitive market, but we are confident, given the people, technology and quality, we are going to be the best among competitors,&quot; Alex Trotman, chairman of Ford Motor Company, said on Monday at the launch of Ford's first Indian-made car.</p>
<p>Asked if there was room for everyone in India's crowded car market, where several foreign manufacturers are muscling in to take advantage of the growing demand, he said: &quot;Probably not.&quot;</p>
<p>Trotman was in the western Indian town of Nashik, 225 km (140 miles) northeast of Bombay, the country's commercial capital, for the launch at the company's joint venture plant.</p>
<p>The Ford Escort is produced by a joint venture between Ford and India's Mahindra &amp; Mahindra, each owning 50 percent.</p>
<p>Analysts said that some global car makers are setting up ventures in India to use it as an export base, and this may help them overcome a glut in the domestic market.</p>
<p>&quot;Some car makers will use India as an export base, so they are putting up large capacities,&quot; Bhat said. ($1=35.70 rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
