<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24446" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chrysler car and light truck sales seen strong in August.</title>
<headline>Chrysler car and light truck sales seen strong in August.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Buyers continued to snap up Chrysler Corp.'s minivans and pickup trucks in August, which should lead the No. 3 automaker to another double-digit increase in monthly sales results, analysts said Friday.</p>
<p>General Motors Corp., which had strong passenger car sales a year ago, has been telling analysts its sales will come in under those of August 1995. Ford Motor Co.'s sales will be unchanged to slightly below year-ago levels as light trucks again outpace car sales.</p>
<p>Results from GM and Ford are expected to drag down the light vehicle sales total on a daily selling basis. But most analysts expect the seasonally adjusted selling rate to finish in the healthy mid-15 million range.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, I think the SAAR (seasonally adjusted annual rate) will look fine,&quot; said Mike Luckey, president of Luckey Consulting Group. &quot;The daily rate will be down a little bit, but I don't think it's anything to get alarmed about because you're up against a strong month last year.&quot;</p>
<p>The seasonal rate is computed using factors from the Commerce Department. The July rate was 14.3 million units.</p>
<p>Last year, August sales ran at a 15.7 million seasonal rate, the second-highest of calendar 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;It sounds to me like a mixed month,&quot; said John Casesa, an analyst with Schroder Wertheim.</p>
<p>Chrysler, the only one of the Detroit's Big Three with a four-door minivan, continues to benefit from the popularity of those vehicles. But its total light truck percentage increase from August 1995 will be helped by exceptionally low numbers a year ago, when a model changeover held down production of minivans and Ram pickups.</p>
<p>Chrysler announced Thursday that it sold 2,189,420 vehicles in the first 11 months of the 1996 model year ending Aug. 28. That beats the previous record for a full model year -- Oct. 1 through Sept. 30 -- of 2,186,128 units.</p>
<p>Analysts predict Japanese automakers will have a big month in August. Toyota Motor Corp. typically uses the month to launch aggressive late model-year inventory clear-outs. Honda Motor Co. Ltd. also pushes retail sales in August.</p>
<p>Strong sales of the Honda Accord sedan could pose a problem for the Ford Taurus, which is battling to stay ahead of the Accord in the race for the best-selling car in the United States for 1996.</p>
<p>Chrysler is scheduled to report sales Sept. 3 and GM will report Sept. 4. Ford and Toyota are expected to announce their sales results Sept. 5.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
