<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25467" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Qingling aims to survive as China Big 10 automaker.</title>
<headline>Qingling aims to survive as China Big 10 automaker.</headline>
<byline>Kathleen Kearney</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Analysts say Chinese automaker Qingling Motors Ltd is in a major growth phase and making strong gains at the expense of a Ford Motor Co protege on the mainland.</p>
<p>However, one said Friday that both management and investors were expecting too much from the small-scale manufacturer of light duty trucks.</p>
<p>Those in favour of the stock believe the company can meet its production target of 100,000 vehicles a year by 2000.</p>
<p>The skeptics say this is too ambitious as the firm's current production is too small and inefficient and its base of operations in southwestern Sichuan province, far from the biggest domestic markets, a drawback to development.</p>
<p>&quot;Qingling is the most profitable light truck manufacturer in China,&quot; said one research analyst with an international brokerage house.</p>
<p>&quot;But the company is too small-scale,&quot; objected Wang Qi, senior investment analyst with CEF GC Brokerage Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;Could Qingling survive if a larger, more ambitious manufacturer set up in central China, threatened its market share, like Qingling grabbed Jiangling's this year?&quot; Wang asked. &quot;I don't think so,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Jiangling Motors Corp, which produces light trucks and diesel engines, reported a 77 percent fall in net profit to 3.385 million yuan in the first half of 1996. In 1995, the company reported earnings of 7.73 million yuan, a 93 percent decline over the previous year.</p>
<p>Ford of the U.S., the world's second largest automaker, bought a 20 percent stake in Jiangling Motors Corp in September 1995, by taking up 80 percent of the Jiangxi-based company's B share offer.</p>
<p>Jiangling, like Qingling, uses parts, equipment and technology imported from Japan's Isuzu Motors.</p>
<p>China's National Automobile Industry policy, announced in mid-1995, mandated that China's 200 or more motor vehicle manufacturers bring the designed capacity of their production facilities up to 100,000 vehicles per year by 2000.</p>
<p>Any that could not meet this target would be forced to merge with other firms to create 10 large manufacturers.</p>
<p>Under the policy, manufacturers with production capacity of 100,000 or more units will be allocated industry finance, although at market rates, and other types of support.  </p>
<p>According to industry policy, by 2010 the government hopes to reduce the 10 manufacturers to three or four giants that can compete in international markets with U.S., Japanese and European automakers.</p>
<p>Qingling has the year 2000 in sight.</p>
<p>The company reported a 520 percent increase in profit after tax of 183.01 million yuan for the first six months of 1996, compared with 29.65 million yuan in the corresponding period last year.</p>
<p>First-half 1995 results, however, had been depressed by an 109.48 million yuan exceptional loss.</p>
<p>&quot;The loss was derived from the group's early repayment of a yen-denominated loan at an exchange rate of US$1.00 to 85 Japanese yen,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>The 1996 earnings performance is more normal, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Actually, 1996 operating conditions did improve. Look at turnover. It rose 40 percent,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The turnover increase came on the back of a 38.3 percent increase in production output, to 16,600 vehicles, compared with 12,002 units in first half 1995, according to company reports.</p>
<p>In the second half of 1995, the company produced 18,004 vehicles.  </p>
<p>The company has orders-on-hand for 35,000 vehicles to be produced in 1996, said director and deputy general manager Pan Yong at a press conference in Hong Kong on Thursday.</p>
<p>An analyst with a US brokerage house, who firmly believes that Qingling can be among the top 10 manufacturers, is only forecasting a 14.3 percent rise in output to 40,000 vehicles in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;Current production is about 3,000 per month,&quot; the U.S. analyst said.</p>
<p>But all the facilities that the company is putting in now, the paint and coating plant, gearbox factory, and moulding plant will all have the required capacity, he said.</p>
<p>The company's growth rates over the past years, especially as compared to its chief competitors and the national industry as a whole, show that it is an industry leader, the U.S. analyst added.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6933</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
