<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="32579" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Car sales drop hurts GM August U.S. results.</title>
<headline>Car sales drop hurts GM August U.S. results.</headline>
<byline>David Lawder</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>General Motors Corp. hurt by a precipitous drop in passenger car sales, said its total August U.S. vehicle sales fell 7.9 percent from a year ago.</p>
<p>GM sold a total of 411,294 cars and trucks during the month, down from 446,394 a year ago.</p>
<p>The world's largest automaker's total U.S. car sales fell 13.8 percent to 241,237 units from 279,855 a year ago, while truck sales rose 2.1 percent to 170,057 units from 166,539 a year ago.</p>
<p>All of GM's six domestic car divisions posted sales declines, with Chevrolet off 3.3 percent, Pontiac off 10.5 percent, Oldsmobile off 27.6 percent, Buick off 24.6 percent, Cadillac off 33.9 percent and Saturn off 3.8 percent.</p>
<p>GM spokesman Dean Rotondo blamed the car sales decline on a sluggish luxury car market and consumers who have decided to take a pass on current models in anticipation of new car model introductions later this year.</p>
<p>GM is introducing four new mid-size sedans over the next several months, as well as a trio of new minivans.</p>
<p>&quot;As soon as those vehicles start getting into the market, we anticipate a spike&quot; in car sales, Rotondo said.</p>
<p>Despite bigger-than-expected sales decline for GM, analysts still expect the industry to post a healthy seasonally adjusted annual sales rate of 15.4 million to 15.5 million units for the month. In August 1995, the rate was 15.7 million.</p>
<p>With all automakers except Ford Motor Co. and its Jaguar Cars Ltd. luxury car unit reporting, industry sales were running 1.0 percent below a year ago.</p>
<p>Chrysler Corp. reported a 9.2 percent increase in August vehicle sales on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Michael Luckey, president of the Luckey Consulting Group, said he expects Ford on Thursday to report an overall sales decline of 2 percent to 3 percent.</p>
<p>He said the industry's performance should continue to meet expectations. &quot;The industry is having a good year, and I think it will continue,&quot; he said. &quot;I don't see the economy slowing down through the end of this year.&quot;</p>
<p>Japanese automakers reported mild August sales gains, except for Honda Motor Co. Ltd., which saw its sales fall 13.7 percent to 75,680, partly because of a shortage of Civic models. Honda's North American-built car sales rose 10.9 percent to 60,740.</p>
<p>Toyota Motor Corp.'s overall August sales rose 1 percent to 128,216 units, but its domestic car sales fell 10.1 percent, due partly to impending introduction of a redesigned Camry model.</p>
<p>Nissan Motor Co. Ltd. said its August sales rose 5.8 percent to 82,068, with domestic car sales up 11.3 percent, while Mazda Motor Corp. reported a 3.0 percent sales gain to 24,151 units, despite a 16.2 percent drop in domestic car sales.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
