<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33767" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ford August sales fall 6.3 percent.</title>
<headline>Ford August sales fall 6.3 percent.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co.'s sales tumbled 6.3 percent in the month of August as the No. 2 automaker reported worse-than-expected results Thursday in both its car and normally strong light truck business.</p>
<p>Ford reported U.S. sales of 297,726, down from 317,621 in the year-ago month. Sales of domestically produced cars fell 6.8 percent on a daily selling basis to 134,110. Sales of its pickup trucks, minivans and sport/utility vehicles totaled 161,549, a decline of 4.4 percent.</p>
<p>In a slight to Ford's quest for its Taurus to be the best-selling car for 1996, its sales for the first eight months slipped behind those of its nemisis, Honda Motor Co.'s Accord, by 1,409 units.</p>
<p>Results from Ford, the last automaker to report, capped a mixed month for Detroit's Big Three and contributed to a 2.3 percent total industry decline to 1,307,858 units for August.</p>
<p>Total sales of North American-built cars were off 6.7 percent to 608,140. That was partially offset by a 3.7 percent increase in domestically produced light trucks, to 513,376.</p>
<p>The seasonally adjusted annual selling rate finished the month at a healthy 15.8 million units. However, analysts said factors provided by the U.S. Department of Commerce to compute the rate artifically inflated it by about 500,000 units.</p>
<p>Those same factors made the July rate seem weak at 14.3 million units, analysts said. In August 1995, the rate was 15.7 million units, the second-highest of the year.</p>
<p>Ford portrayed its August sales slump as part of the expected drop-off in second-half sales for 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;As anticipated, the automotive market has slowed somewhat since earlier this year,&quot; said Robert Rewey, Group Vice President of Marketing and Sales. &quot;In recent months we've seen interest rate increases for automotive financing that clearly have influenced industry-wide demand.&quot;</p>
<p>Ford said vehicles sold at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 15.8 million unit sales for the first five months of 1996. The automaker continues to forecast 1996 total industry U.S. sales at 15.4 million to 15.5 million units. Sales for all of 1995 were 15.1 million.</p>
<p>At least one analyst welcomed the lower August industry numbers, saying they might make the Federal Reserve Board re-think any possible interest rate hikes.</p>
<p>&quot;The lower the better,&quot; said Lehman Brothers analyst Joeseph Phillippi. &quot;Maybe they'll keep the Fed quiet.&quot;</p>
<p>In August, Ford's normally strong light truck business was hurt by a decline in government sales, competitive pricing pressures and production shortages of key F-150 models.</p>
<p>F-Series sales inched up 1.7 percent to 58,095.</p>
<p>Explorer sales, which have fallen in recent months due to the production startup of its sister, the Mercury Mountaineer, were down almost 11 percent to 27,615.</p>
<p>On the car side, Contour sales sank 35 percent to 10,487, while Mystique sales were down 18 percent to 5,041. Taurus sales were 25,570, a 2 percent increase, which brought total sales this year to 250,212. But that was not enough to top the Accord, which sold 251,621 cars year-to-date.</p>
<p>Ford said it has scheduled a nearly 14 percent increase in fourth-quarter North American truck production, to 632,000 units, to meet expected future demand for its popular F-Series.</p>
<p>Car production is scheduled to fall 4 percent to 431,000 for the same period. Total fourth-quarter North American output is forecast at 1,063,000, an increase of about 5 percent from the fourth quarter of 1995.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, General Motors Corp. said total car and truck sales fell 7.9 percent, led by a nearly 14 percent drop in passenger car sales.</p>
<p>Chrysler Corp. was the only one of the Big Three to post a sales increase. It reported earlier this week that sales rose 9.2 percent, helped by a strong performance from minivans, sport/utilities and pickup trucks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
