<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36588" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysia to sign vehicle deal with Hyundai, Renault.</title>
<headline>Malaysia to sign vehicle deal with Hyundai, Renault.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three Malaysian companies are set to sign on Friday agreements to build a plant for commercial vehicle production in a joint venture with South Korean and French car makers.</p>
<p>The deal with Korea's biggest car maker Hyundai Motor Co Ltd and France's Renault SA will be signed with the Malaysian partners and a joint venture company, Industri Otomobil Komersial (Malaysia) Sdn Bhd (Inokom).</p>
<p>Hyundai and Renault will each hold a 15 percent stake in the venture.</p>
<p>The Malaysian partners are Berjaya Group Bhd with a 35 percent stake, a unit of police cooperative Koperasi Polis DiRaja Malaysia (30 percent) and Hyumal Motor Sdn Bhd (five percent). Hyumal is the franchise holder of Hyundai cars in Malaysia.</p>
<p>The vehicles will be assembled at Inokom's 100 million ringgit ($40 million) plant which will be ready by the end of the year, Inokom's senior manager Ikmal Hisham told the New Straits Times in an interview published on Friday.</p>
<p>The plant, located in Kulim in northern Kedah state, will be built on a 80.8 hectare site and have a workforce of about 600.  </p>
<p>Inokom is set to roll out a van based on Renault's Trafic van by October next year, he said.</p>
<p>A light truck based on Hyundai's Porter truck will be launched in mid-1998, Ikmal said.</p>
<p>A Hyundai official said in Seoul on Tuesday that the venture aims to produce 20,000 commercial vehicles a year with production starting from the second half of next year.</p>
<p>Truck production would increase from 1,500 units in 1998 to 7,000 by 2000, he said.</p>
<p>Ikmal said the Inokom vehicles will be distributed by Hyumal and Quasar Carriage Sdn Bhd, the local franchise holder of Renault cars.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I65100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
