<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43868" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ford warns of Brazil losses, sees UAW pact.</title>
<headline>Ford warns of Brazil losses, sees UAW pact.</headline>
<byline>David Lawder</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co. warned Tuesday that its losses in Brazil are bigger than expected, but added that it should reach a favourable labour contract deal with the United Auto Workers by a weekend deadline.</p>
<p>Ford Chief Financial Officer John Devine said in an interview that due to a slower and costlier launch of small car production in Brazil, Ford's losses in Latin America during the second half of 1996 will be roughly double the company's first half loss of $130 million in the region.</p>
<p>Following the 1995 breakup of Ford's Autolatina joint venture with Volkswagen AG, the Dearborn, Mich.-based automaker was left without a domestic entry in the critical small car market in Brazil.</p>
<p>It has scrambled to start production of its European-designed Ford Fiesta in Brazil, but the project has run into problems.</p>
<p>On Aug. 27, Ford replaced the head of its Brazilian and Argentinian operations, Gurminder Bedi, with James Padilla, a vehicle line director with a reputation as a problem solver.</p>
<p>Ford plans an unspecified number of job reductions and other restructuring actions within the operations.</p>
<p>&quot;Effectively, we've had to re-launch the company in Brazil and Argentina,&quot; Devine said. &quot;It's going to take us longer and it's tougher and more expensive, but that's the car business these days.&quot;</p>
<p>Ford had previously expected Brazil and Argentina to break even in the second half of the year, contributing to a dramatic improvement in earnings for the automaker.</p>
<p>The bigger loss will reduce Ford's third and fourth quarter earnings slightly but is &quot;not a catastrophic event,&quot; said Burnham Securities analyst David Healy.</p>
<p>Ford shares closed off 37.5 cents at $31.625 Tuesday on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>In the United States, Devine said he sees a &quot;positive tone on both sides&quot; of the bargaining table as labour negotiations barrel toward the current UAW contract's Sept. 14 expiration date.</p>
<p>He said he expected a deal by the deadline, but added that &quot;the issues are still tough and large and a lot of things have to be discussed yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Ford, which is the lead company in the UAW's triennial negotiations with Detroit's Big Three automakers, is aiming to tailor the labour pact to its needs while addressing the UAW's concerns, Devine said. But the pact won't necessarily help rivals General Motors Corp. and Chrysler Corp.</p>
<p>&quot;Our first priority is Ford Motor Co. Make something that works for Ford Motor Co. and works for the UAW. That's our clear No. 1 focus,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked if the resulting pact also would likely benefit GM and Chrysler, he chuckled and said, &quot;They're going to have to worry about that.&quot;</p>
<p>Devine declined to comment about specific issues being discussed in the negotiations.</p>
<p>People familiar with the talks have said the UAW is seeking a base wage increase of 2 percent per year over the life of the contract, guarantees of specific employment levels and elimination of a lower starting wage rate for new hires.</p>
<p>The two sides also are discussing a four-year contract -- a year longer than the traditional pact -- which would allow Ford to stabilise its future costs and thereby better evaluate future vehicle programmes and foster labour peace.</p>
<p>High level, &quot;main-table&quot; negotiations, in which final details are worked out, are expected later this week.</p>
<p>Lower-level negotiations are continuing at GM and Chrysler.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
