<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47712" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Ford Ka makes early raid on minicar market.</title>
<headline>Ford Ka makes early raid on minicar market.</headline>
<byline>Neil Winton</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co's new minicar, unveiled Wednesday, gives it an inside track in what will be a burgeoning new segment of the European new car market, analysts said.</p>
<p>The Ford Ka is 21 cm (seven inches) shorter than Ford's current smallest car, the big-selling Fiesta.</p>
<p>Ford said its marketing studies showed public enthusiasm for the name. A spokesman said &quot;Ka&quot; means &quot;vitality&quot; in ancient Egyptian.</p>
<p>The Ka will be shown to the public for the first time at the Paris car show early next month. It will go on sale in Europe later in the month, Ford said in a statement.</p>
<p>Ford declined to reveal the capital cost of the project but it has said the plant which will make the Ka, in Valencia, Spain, cost $201 million to build.</p>
<p>Ford is not first in the minicar field. The sector currently accounts for about 500,000 sales a year in western Europe, mainly by Italy's Fiat SpA with the Cinquecento, and Renault of France's Twingo, according to McGraw Hill's automotive researcher DRI.</p>
<p>But Ford has stolen a march over its biggest competitors like Germany's Volkswagen AG and Daimler-Benz's Mercedes, and General Motors Corp's Opel subsidiary, DRI said.</p>
<p>European car manufacturers will be producing up to one million minicars a year over the next five years, DRI said, with Ford making up to 200,000 Kas a year.</p>
<p>&quot;All the big car manufacturers are heading into this Twingo type segment,&quot; said DRI automotive analyst Arthur Maher.</p>
<p>&quot;VW will have a cutback Polo in one to two years, Mercedes has the more expensive &quot;A&quot; class and the cheaper Smart car, and GM is looking at a sub-Corsa,&quot; said Maher.</p>
<p>And just because it is a minicar, don't expect prices to be tiny.</p>
<p>&quot;Historically, this segment of the market has been for first time ownership, like the Fiat Panda. But now the manufacturers are hoping they can appeal to families which already have cars. This will supplement the executive saloon, the four wheel drive vehicle, and will be used for shopping, taking the kids to school, and city travel,&quot; said Maher.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be affordable but not cheap,&quot; Maher said.</p>
<p>Ford said the Ka will not represent the bare essentials of motoring. It will have the space, features and equipment normally associated with larger cars.</p>
<p>The Ka, which will have a 1.3 litre engine, was designed and developed in just over two years. Ford declined to state its price.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
