<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76103" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lear sets first China joint venture.</title>
<headline>Lear sets first China joint venture.</headline>
<dateline>SOUTHFIELD, Mich. 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lear Corp., marking its first expansion into the Chinese vehicle market, said Wednesday it signed a letter of intent to form a joint venture with state-owned Jiangling Motors Co. Ltd.</p>
<p>Financial details were not disclosed.</p>
<p>The 50-50 venture, Jiangling-Lear Interior System Co. Ltd., will will provide seats and interior trim for trucks from Isuzu Motors Ltd. and transit vans from Ford Motor Co.</p>
<p>Lear said the new company will operate from an existing facility in Nanchang, China, and make seats for 150,000 vehicles a year.</p>
<p>The companies held a signing ceremony at Lear's Ford division headquarters in Allen Park, Mich.</p>
<p>Lear said annual vehicle sales in China are expected to triple over the next few years to more than three million from a current 1.2 million.</p>
<p>Lear is the world's largest independent supplier of automotive interior systems, with 1995 sales of $4.7 billion.</p>
<p>Jiangling makes light trucks for Isuzu. It will begin production in late 1997 of a light truck for Ford that will be sold in Europe.</p>
<p>Lear's stock rose 62.5 cents to $34 on the New York Stock Exchange at mid-afternoon.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOUTHFIELD, Mich."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
