<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79404" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Johnson Controls in China, India ventures.</title>
<headline>Johnson Controls in China, India ventures.</headline>
<dateline>PLYMOUTH, Mich. 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Johnson Controls Inc said Thursday it formed a venture in China to supply seating and interior systems and another venture in India to make vehicle seat systems and related components.</p>
<p>Johnson Controls said it formed the venture in China with Beijing Automotive Industry Corp and called it Beijing Johnson Controls Automotive Trim Co.</p>
<p>Johnson Controls said the venture in China gives it its first automotive manufacturing operation in China.  Johnson Controls said it is the world's largest producer of automotive seating and interior systems.  </p>
<p>Beijing Johnson Controls will operate an existing 42,000 square foot plant in Beijing that produces seat systems and other interior components for five major auto companies. These companies are Beijing Jeep Corp, a Chrysler Corp /Beijing Automotive joint venture; Beijing Light Automobile Co ; Beijing Tour Bus Co ; Jiangling Motor Co and Guangzhou Peugeot Automobile Manufacturing Co..</p>
<p>&quot;Our company will be the number one automotive interior systems supplier in Asia -- and this joint venture is just the beginning of our major expansion in this vitally important region,&quot; John Barth, executive vice president, said.  </p>
<p>Beijing Johnson Controls will supply complete seats for Jeep Cherokees, BJ2020 small sport-utility vehicles, Isuzu light trucks, and tour buses, as well as components for Peugeot 500 series sedans.</p>
<p>It also will manufacture additional vehicle components for China-based automakers, including metal seat frames, trim covers, door panels, soft tops, interior trim and an array of molded plastic parts.</p>
<p>Under terms of the agreement, Beijing Johnson Controls also assumes ownership of a 25 percent share of Beijing Yanxi Automotive Decoration Co, which makes foam seat cushions.  </p>
<p>In India, Johnson Controls is making vehicle seat systems and related components for Ford Motor Co cars built in India through its new joint venture with Indian automotive supplier Tata Auto Comp Systems Ltd.</p>
<p>The venture, called Tata Johnson Controls Automotive, launched production at a 22,000-square-foot plant in Pune in late August, giving Johnson Controls its first manufacturing operations in India.</p>
<p>The new Pune plant supplies complete seats, foam pads and trim covers for 1996 Ford Escort vehicles produced by Mahindra-Ford, a joint venture between Ford Motor Co and India-based Mahindra &amp; Mahindra Ltd.</p>
<p>The facility will produce about 20,000 Escort seat sets for for delivery to Mahindra-Ford's assembly plant in Nashik, near Bombay. The plant is expected to build additional seat systems and related components for future vehicle programs in India.</p>
<p>&quot;Our entry into the Indian market is part of our overall global strategy for leveraging our strengths and established business relationships in emerging markets,&quot; Barth added in a statement.</p>
<p>The India-market 1996 Ford Escort also features batteries manufactured by Johnson Controls.</p>
<p>Reuters Chicago Newsdesk - 312-408-8787</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34320">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PLYMOUTH, Mich."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
