<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85642" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ford puts incentives on '97 Taurus.</title>
<headline>Ford puts incentives on '97 Taurus.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co. is preparing to add further incentives to its Taurus, including a $500 rebate on 1997 models of the car, the company and dealers said Monday.</p>
<p>Starting Oct. 2, the standard rebate for a 1996 Taurus reverts to $1,000 from $1,500. But dealers can choose an incentive program offered by Ford that gives them another $1,000 to offer customers for a total of $2,000.</p>
<p>In addition, the U.S. No. 2 automaker is telling certain owners of 1990-94 Tauruses that they may be eligible for a $500 rebate if they buy a new Taurus under a loyalty program.</p>
<p>The latest incentive program indicates Ford is determined to keep the Taurus the best-selling car in the United States. Ford sold 250,212 Tauruses through the first eight months of 1996 -- 1,409 fewer than the Accord from Honda Motor Co. The Taurus is also sure to see more competition from the redesigned 1997 Camry from Toyota Motor Co.</p>
<p>&quot;Based on what's happening in the market, it's really not that much of a surprise,&quot; said Wesley Brown, director of global product analysis at CSM Forecasting, a Farmington Hills, Mich.-based consulting firm. &quot;If they intend to be No. 1, they've got to do what they can.&quot;</p>
<p>Ford spokeswoman Joy Wolfe said incentives were not unique to vehicles in the mid-size car segment.</p>
<p>&quot;We're either comparable with or behind what other people have been doing with their vehicles,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Because dealers are being offered a choice of incentives, the new program does not represent an increase in what Ford previously planned to spend on incentives in the fourth quarter, she said.</p>
<p>Last year, Ford used hefty incentives to clear out 1995 model Taurus cars ahead of the redesigned 1996 model. Dealers predicted that will work again.</p>
<p>&quot;This will detonate every '96 Taurus out there in 30 days,&quot; said John Sinclair of Sinclair Ford in Festus, Mo.</p>
<p>In addition to the Taurus, Ford will offer $500 rebates on the 1997 Escort, and another $500 on the 1997 supercab four-by-four Ranger, bringing that rebate to $1,000.</p>
<p>The incentive programs run through Jan. 3.</p>
<p>Separately, analysts expect that cars and light trucks in September sold at an even to slightly higher daily rate compared with a year ago.</p>
<p>Chrysler Corp. is expected to report Tuesday that it had higher sales of both cars and trucks in the month. General Motors Corp., also due to report Tuesday, will have flat to lower sales as it battles slow car sales.</p>
<p>Ford is scheduled to report sales on Oct. 3. Analysts expect it to also have a flat to down month.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
