<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15606" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Grand Casinos taking $12 million charge.</title>
<headline>Grand Casinos taking $12 million charge.</headline>
<dateline>MINNEAPOLIS</dateline>
<text>
<p>Grand Casinos Inc. said Tuesday it expects to record a non-cash charge of more than $12 million due to much higher-than-expected losses at the new Stratosphere casino in Las Vegas.</p>
<p>Grand Casinos, which owns about 42 percent of Stratosphere Inc., said it expected to take a charge of between 55 and 60 cents a share, which would total between $12.3 million and $13.4 million, in the second half of the year.</p>
<p>Tom Brosig, executive vice president of investor relations, said the expected loss was 10 times the amount originally anticipated by Grand Casinos.</p>
<p>Stratosphere said last week that it was revamping operations at its four-month-old hotel and casino -- the tallest building in Las Vegas -- after it failed to attract hotel customers or gamblers in the numbers it had anticipated.</p>
<p>The company, which had been anticipating a profit, said its operations lost $7.8 million, or 19 cents a share, in the three months ended June 30, after pre-opening costs, on $30 million in sales.</p>
<p>Grand Casinos, which is based in Minnesapolis, also owns and operates the three largest casino hotel resorts in Mississippi and manages two land-based casinos in Louisiana and two casino hotels in Minnesota.</p>
<p>It said business at those properties was stable and growing and the company believes their results will be within the range of expectations.</p>
<p>The company also said that it was comfortable with analysts' expectations that it will earn $2.27 a share next year.</p>
<p>Grand Casinos' stock gained $1.375 to $17.375 in early trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINNEAPOLIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
