<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17078" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: FEATURE - Canadian gambling fever hotter than U.S..</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Canadian gambling fever hotter than U.S..</headline>
<byline>Randall Palmer</byline>
<dateline>HULL, Quebec 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>For John and his new wife, they should have been the golden years. They both had good jobs, no debt and 14 years to save before he would retire from his job in the federal government.</p>
<p>The trouble was, John could not stay away from the racetrack. A compulsive gambler who goes by his first name as is customary in Gamblers Anonymous, he reckons he blew at least $100,000 Canadian ($70,000 U.S.) over seven years and nearly destroyed his marriage.</p>
<p>He piled up debt, separated from his wife, sold his house and gambled away the money. Eventually he and his wife got back together and worked to rebuild their lives, their futures and their bank balances.</p>
<p>&quot;It was very hard to get the trust back,&quot; he said penitently, recalling the years of turmoil. He has not placed a bet for nine years, but his story puts a human face on the gambling fever sweeping Canada even faster than the United States. Provincial governments across the country are promoting gambling in virtually every form imaginable, relying on the revenue to plug budgetary gaps or fund tax cuts.</p>
<p>&quot;Governments should go to Gamblers Anonymous. They have become addicted to gambling,&quot; said Tibor Barsony, executive director of the Canadian Foundation on Compulsive Gambling.</p>
<p>Here in Hull, across the Ottawa River from Canada's capital, the Quebec government in March opened a flashy casino that has already drawn 1.5 million visitors, rivaling Parliament for as region's premier attraction.</p>
<p>More than 10,000 people a day sit at row upon row of slot machines with names like &quot;Rich and Famous&quot; and &quot;Jackpot Jewel&quot; where you can drop $100 or $500 a shot. Most are older men and women, none looking too rich, who seem fixated by the spinning wheels, the ringing bells and the clattering coins. Some keep three machines whirring at once, stopping only to withdraw more money from automatic teller machines.</p>
<p>At the gaming tables, players plunk down as much as $2,000 a hand at blackjack or play the whole table for $10,000.</p>
<p>Ads on buses for the Casino de Hull show a young couple delightedly hugging as they watch a roulette wheel spin.</p>
<p>Bettors lost more than $10 billion Canadian ($7.3 billion U.S.) in a year on all forms of gambling in Canada, including casinos, lotteries and bingo halls, according to Ivan Sack, editor of Canadian Casino News.</p>
<p>That averaged about $1,000 per household ($730 U.S.) and may have risen to as high as $1,200 per household as casinos and video lottery terminals sprouted around Canada. Since many do not gamble, such figures mean some households are losing a lot more each year. Americans, in comparison, lost about $500 per household last year.</p>
<p>Seven of Canada's 10 provinces have casinos, most started in the last few years, and eight have video lottery terminals -- a video version of the one-armed-bandit slot machines. Ontario's Conservative government has plans to flood the province with 20,000 video lottery terminals.</p>
<p>&quot;In three years, Ontario will have gone from very little gaming to saturation gaming,&quot; Sack said.</p>
<p>The gambling business had a net profit of $3.3 billion Canadian ($2.4 billion U.S.) in 1994-95, provincial governments using much of it for things like health care.</p>
<p>For governments gambling can raise money without increasing economic distortions from hiking tax rates -- though economists view it as a regressive &quot;voluntary&quot; tax since the poorer and less educated tend to bet more.</p>
<p>Big casinos like the one in Hull or one opening soon at Niagara Falls provide between 1,000 and 3,000 jobs. But the gaming boom may also cause a rise in gambling addiction. &quot;The more exposure there is, the more people are going to get hooked,&quot; said John of Gamblers Anonymous.</p>
<p>Ontario's Addiction Research Foundation estimates one percent of Ontario adults are pathological gamblers and gambling causes problems for 10 percent.</p>
<p>One in nine Ontarians surveyed said they had a family member with a gambling problem, and the Canadian Foundation on Compulsive Gambling has found teens four times as likely to have problems as adults.</p>
<p>Studies have found gambling leads to divorce, job loss, fraud, bankruptcy and suicide, to say nothing of depriving families of their grocery money. Yet many politicians and businessmen argue that some people are simply prey to addictions and in communities like Ottawa they promote their own gambling interests to counter the drain to neighboring jurisdictions like Quebec.</p>
<p>&quot;What we have is the casino on the north side of the river with any financial benefits and Ottawa on the south side of the river with the social problems if any,&quot; said Ottawa Mayor Jacquelin Holzman, advocating an up-market casino.</p>
<p>Some businessmen and academics say that in addition to the social costs of addictions, gambling may in some cases just drain money from other parts of the economy. In this case other industries risked being cannibalized, said University of Winnipeg economist Phil Cyrenne. &quot;You're just shuffling the spending around.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HULL, Quebec"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
