<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38068" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Conn. sees strong Aug revenues for Foxwoods casino.</title>
<headline>Conn. sees strong Aug revenues for Foxwoods casino.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Connecticut said Friday that Mashantucket Pequot Foxwood Resort Casino enjoyed a near-record month in August, although the state's share is running a little shy of forecasts for the 1997 fiscal year.</p>
<p>&quot;It's slightly below what we had projected, but certainly within reasonable limits,&quot; said an official with the state Division of Special Revenue, who declined to be named.</p>
<p>The state, which collects 25 percent of the &quot;net win,&quot; defined as how much the casino keeps as a percentage of the total amount that is bet, looks for Foxwoods to achieve a win of just over $547 million in this fiscal year.</p>
<p>If this forecast is met, Connecticut would collect almost $137 million for the 1997 fiscal year.</p>
<p>The state expects the Foxwoods casino and a new one, that the Mohegan tribe plans to open on September 12, to send the state approximately $200 million for the 1997 fiscal year.</p>
<p>But the state official cautioned that the projection might not be met if the Mohegan Indians do not open their new casino on time, or if the new casino, which will be located only 10 miles away from the four-year old Foxwoods casino, cuts into the older resort's business.</p>
<p>In August, the net win achieved by Foxwoods was $63.5 million, just under July's record of $64.4 million.</p>
<p>The state gets to keep 15 percent of its share for the General Fund, and sends the rest back to the local towns, the agency official said.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
