<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53345" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY Senate poll says voters back environmental bond.</title>
<headline>NY Senate poll says voters back environmental bond.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most voters surveyed at the New York State Fair by the state Senate approve of the $1.75 billion environmental bond act that will be on the November ballot, the Senate Majority Leader said on Friday.</p>
<p>The survey, which was conducted from August 22 to September 2, found that 70 percent of the almost 11,000 respondents said they would support such a proposal, while 30 percent would oppose it.</p>
<p>A majority of the people who were surveyed did not think the state should continue to ban casino gambling, which has provided handsome revenues for other states, with 61 percent opposed to the prohibition and 39 percent approving of it.</p>
<p>The survey also found strong support for strict time limits on welfare payments to &quot;single, employable adults&quot; that were proposed by the Senate, which is led by Republicans, and Gov. George Pataki, who also is a Republican.</p>
<p>The survey found that 69 percent agreed with cutting off benefits to such individuals after 60 days, with 31 percent against.</p>
<p>The Assembly, which is led by Democrats, opposed some of the big cuts in welfare that were proposed by the Senate and Pataki, and they did not become law.</p>
<p>A task force set up by the governor now is grappling with the issues raised by the dramatic changes imposed by the new federal welfare bill. The governor has said he might call for a special legislative session to deal with these questions after the November elections.</p>
<p>Substantial support also was found in the survey for giving tax breaks to businesses that promise to create new jobs, as 79 percent of the respondents favored the idea, with 21 percent against.</p>
<p>The survey showed a majority favored a plan approved by the Senate in early May, but not voted on by the Assembly, which would give $810 million in state aid to school districts that voluntarily freeze local real property taxes.</p>
<p>About 62 percent of the people surveyed said they supported the idea, while 38 percent said they were opposed.</p>
<p>School districts in New York, as in many states, rely heavily on property taxes, but this method of financing can give wealthier cities and towns an edge over poorer areas. &quot;This reinforces my belief that we must reduce the huge burden caused by unfair and regressive school taxes,&quot; said Joseph Bruno, Senate Majority Leader, in a prepared statement.</p>
<p>The Senate's survey also showed that the voters believed judges were too lenient in sentencing criminals, with 86 percent in agreement and 14 percent in disagreement.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
