<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="57152" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China betting $200 million on new casino resort.</title>
<headline>China betting $200 million on new casino resort.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>China is betting that a planned $200 million casino and seaside resort will propel the communist nation into the ranks of free-wheeling gambling spots such as Macau, officials said on Monday.</p>
<p>The luxury entertainment complex is to be built on a peninsula near the northern port city of Tianjin, said Waysun Liao, general manager of Tianjin Xiang Dao Resort and Casino Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Construction of the casino, to cost $20-$30 million, would start on September 20 and was expected to begin trial operations in March 1997. The resort would also include a hotel, a stage for shows and a water sports centre, Liao said by telephone.</p>
<p>Beijing hopes to draw foreign tourists and businessmen living in China who in the past have travelled abroad for such entertainment, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;They won't have to commute, go to Hong Kong, Macau or other places,&quot; Liao said.</p>
<p>Although China's ruling Communist Party has maintained a strict ban on gambling, rapid economic growth had created huge demand for casinos and luxury pleasure centres, and prompted the government to back this first gambling venture, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have all kinds of hotels but we don't have resorts, international, five star-type resorts,&quot; he said of China's tourist industry.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue is not whether you like it (a gambling resort) or not, but it's a necessity that they must accommodate such kind of service,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The government had set up Tianjin Xiang Dao to build and oversee the resort, while funding and management of the facility was being handled by Farside International, a subsidiary of Hong Kong's Gala Corp, he said.</p>
<p>Farside was talking to casino firms from Hong Kong, Macau and Australia to handle management of the gambling operation but had not yet reached a final decision, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
