<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58137" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico proposal would require casinos to go public.</title>
<headline>Mexico proposal would require casinos to go public.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A proposed law to allow casino gambling in Mexico would require gaming halls to issue publicly traded stock equal to at least 20 percent of their capital, according to a draft of the legislation.</p>
<p>The Casino Regulating Council would require gaming companies &quot;to issue not less than 20 percent of their capital for public investment,&quot; the proposed legislation says.</p>
<p>The document, written by officials from the finance, tourism and interior ministries, would allow foreign companies to operate casinos, but they would need permission from a special commission.  </p>
<p>The draft of the law, however, restricts the location of casinos to tourist centers. Permits to operate casinos would be issued for 25 years at a time.</p>
<p>&quot;Casinos can only operate when they form part of the Integrated tourist centers that the council determines, based on the Federal Tourism Law,&quot; the document says.</p>
<p>Existing tourist centers that want to add casinos must control at least a 25 percent interest in the gambling halls, according to the draft.</p>
<p>The proposed law includes a number of measures to guard against money laundering. It would require casinos to identify gamblers who buy extraordinary amounts of gambling chips.</p>
<p>Opposition legislator Rene Arce of the leftist Democratic Revolutionary Party (PRD) opposes the law, saying Mexico is not prepared to regulate the gambling industry.</p>
<p>&quot;First we have to reform some (government) institutions so that the casinos don't become a security problem, including a national security problem,&quot; Arce told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Casino gambling was outlawed in 1938 by President Lazaro Cardenas.</p>
<p>--Claudia Villegas, Mexico City, (525) 728-9549</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
