<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61561" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Initial report issued on impact of Illinois gaming.</title>
<headline>Initial report issued on impact of Illinois gaming.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>An initial report released Wednesday indicated that riverboat casinos in Illinois had an economic and fiscal impact of an estimated $2.2 billion between 1991 and 1995.</p>
<p>The report, issued by the Illinois Gaming Commission, said that in 1995 alone the 10 floating casinos in the state had a direct economic impact of an estimated $763 million.</p>
<p>As for wagering and admissions taxes, the report said that casinos paid $749.3 million in those taxes during the 1991-95 time period, with tax collections reaching nearly $293 million in 1995 alone.</p>
<p>However, the report by the state agency pointed out that an upward trend in the annual level of direct economic impact ended in 1995 &quot;largely as a result of diminished capital outlays and a relatively static revenue base&quot; for the 10 casinos.</p>
<p>Indirect impact from the casinos, on the other hand, has fallen short of expectations, the report said. Specifically, anticipated increases in local retail trade and tourism have not materialized.</p>
<p>The report said that while revenues generated by casino gaming have exceeded expectations made in 1990, some predictions have not come true.</p>
<p>&quot;It is evident that additional research is nedded before the experience with riverboat casino gaming can be declared an economic plus or minus for Illinois,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>--Karen Pierog, 312-408-8647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
