<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76605" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New Mexico tribe has to close casino, will appeal.</title>
<headline>New Mexico tribe has to close casino, will appeal.</headline>
<dateline>SANTA FE, N.M. 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>A New Mexico tribe was forced to close its casino Tuesday but vowed to challenge the shutdown order as the fight over gambling operations on Indian reservations in the state brought a flurry of legal actions.</p>
<p>Mescalero Apache Indians closed the doors at their Inn of the Mountain Gods casino hours after a federal judge ruled against letting them keep it open until an appeals court decides whether or not the state's Indian casinos are illegal.</p>
<p>But the Mescalero vowed to take their case to the 10th Circuit Court of Appeals in Denver Wednesday morning.</p>
<p>&quot;We have closed down today, but we are going to try to open up again tomorrow,&quot; said a spokeswoman for the inn, which lies on the Mescalero reservation in southeast New Mexico.</p>
<p>Tribe president Wendell Chino said his people would not give up the fight. &quot;If we have to go all the way to the Supreme Court, we will do it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Although the Mescalero lost their battle in a Santa Fe court Tuesday, the Jicarilla Apache tribe in northern New Mexico went straight to the Denver appeals court and won a temporary stay on the closure order against its Apache Nugget casino.</p>
<p>Jicarilla leaders celebrated the temporary victory and said they would also fight to keep the casino open.</p>
<p>&quot;If we are challenged again, we'll just stand our ground like we did today,&quot; Gary Simpson, general manager of the Apache Nugget, said.</p>
<p>A total of 11 New Mexico tribes have opened 24-hour casinos since reaching gambling agreements with Gov. Gary Johnson last year.</p>
<p>But the federal government says Johnson did not have the authority to approve gambling operations, and a federal judge ruled all the casinos illegal in July.</p>
<p>Until Tuesday no tribe had been forced to close its casino doors. Nine of the 11 tribes were given permission to stay open while an appeals court considered the issue, but the Mescalero and Jicarilla were not included in that ruling.</p>
<p>It appeared that the Mescalero might have been forced to close their casino simply because they picked the wrong court on the wrong day, but it was not clear whether the appeals court in Denver would rule for them Wednesday.</p>
<p>Tribal leaders say that they spent millions of dollars building the casinos and that the gambling operations provide them with a unique chance to improve the quality of life on their dirt-poor reservations.</p>
<p>Some reacted angrily to the closure of the inn Tuesday. &quot;The white man has done it to us again just when we were beginning to prosper,&quot; one Indian woman told a state television station.</p>
<p>Bill Colwell, a white gambler who had to leave the casino when the closure order came down, agreed. &quot;This is Indian land. This is more 'White man speak with forked tongue' as far as I'm concerned,&quot; Colwell said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA FE, N.M."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
