<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80477" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Gaming industry slams Turkish casino ban on Turks.</title>
<headline>Gaming industry slams Turkish casino ban on Turks.</headline>
<byline>Suna Erdem</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gambling industry officials on Friday protested an order stopping Turks from entering the country's casinos, which they say will lead to a huge loss of foreign investment and only benefit illegal gambling joints.</p>
<p>&quot;I caution the government officials to reconsider their actions,&quot; Steve Karoul, manager of the five star Ciragan Palace casino in Istanbul, told reporters in a news briefing.</p>
<p>The interior ministry of Turkey's Islamist-led government this week told provincial governors to exclude Turks from casinos while the industry is reorganised.</p>
<p>The ministry says this is to prevent families being broken up amid moral concerns heightened by media reports of suicides reportedly linked to unpaid gambling debts. There are also wide concerns the gambling industry is used for money laundering.</p>
<p>&quot;Punishing all casinos for the past abuses of the few bad operators is not the answer. And closing casinos to Turkish citizens is not the answer,&quot; Karoul said.</p>
<p>&quot;The gambling will continue -- either in illegal underground casinos with no tax benefits to the country or in foreign casinos outside the country.&quot;</p>
<p>The order has so far only been implemented in parts of the country, including Antalya, a Mediterranean resort town popular with Israeli gamblers fleeing gaming restrictions at home.</p>
<p>The tourism ministry is expected in October to announce a reorganisation of gambling in Turkey, possibly limiting casinos to three regions -- Antalya, central Anatolia and the Yassiada island near Istanbul.</p>
<p>Erhan Akbulut, chairman of the Turkish Association of Independent Gaming Operators (TOMI), said about 70 percent of gaming income came from Turks, but that as individuals foreigners risked greater sums.</p>
<p>&quot;So foreigners lose more money as Turks only do it for entertainment,&quot; Akbulut said. &quot;The loss will be Turkey's.&quot;</p>
<p>He slammed the plans as confused and legally dubious: &quot;That is why some city governors have not begun to enforce it.&quot;</p>
<p>Foreign gaming officials said their companies had invested in five-star hotels in Istanbul on condition that they would come with casinos, which were indispensible if they were to survive competition with the many luxury hotels in the city.</p>
<p>&quot;We would not have invested so much money if we had know the rules and regulations would change so often,&quot; said Joep Bakx, general manager of Istanbul's Conrad hotel.</p>
<p>The casino officials said the latest decision added to a series of events that led to foreign investors shunning Turkey, including an economic crisis in 1994 and a nine-month government search that ended in June this year.</p>
<p>Turkey's economy is struggling under high inflation and and huge fiscal deficits, and the new government has so far failed to instil confidence that the future will be any more stable.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
