<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41556" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Caribbean states &quot;face disaster&quot; in WTO banana row.</title>
<headline>Caribbean states &quot;face disaster&quot; in WTO banana row.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Officials representing Caribbean banana-exporting states said on Monday their fragile economies would be devastated if the European Union were forced to drop preferential tarrifs on import of the fruit.</p>
<p>The officials were speaking at a news conference before the first meeting of a panel of the World Trade Organisation set up to consider a United States' complaint, backed by some Latin American countries, that the EU is violating free trade rules.  </p>
<p>&quot;It is a matter of life and death to many of the Caribbean states that the preferences are maintained,&quot; said Gordon Myers, European representative of the Caribbean Banana Exporters Association (CBEA).</p>
<p>&quot;Our economies are largely dependent on bananas,&quot; said Edwin Laurent, ambassador in Brussels for several eastern Caribbean states, in many of which the industry provides employment for around 25 per cent of the population.  </p>
<p>&quot;Our producers could not survive at world market prices because these are below the cost of production in our region where we cannot get the economies of scale possible in Latin American plantations....</p>
<p>&quot;Without the provisions which are under attack, the Caribbean industry would collapse, with disastrous economic and social consequences,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Myers and Laurent said it was unjust that Caribbean states had not been allowed to take full part in the hearings by the three-man WTO panel, to continue over the next six months, and only sit in as observers.  </p>
<p>Myers said they had been barred at the insistence of the United States, which brought the case to the trade watchdog following a complaint to Washington by Chiquita, a U.S. company that produces bananas in Latin America.</p>
<p>The EU's banana import regime, twice condemned as illegal under the old General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade which was replaced by the WTO in 1995, is linked to Brussels' &quot;Lome Convention&quot; treaty with former European colonies.  </p>
<p>The Convention, which has existed in various forms since World War Two, provides for special treatment for goods from these countries to enable them to compete with produce from other states with more developed economies.</p>
<p>The Convention -- giving special treatment to some 70 countries in the so-called African, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) group -- was given a waiver from normal rules by the GATT in 1994 after the earlier panels said they recognised the problems of the West Indian banana producers.</p>
<p>But the United States, which does not export bananas of its own, Ecuador, the world's largest exporter, Guatemala, Hunduras and Mexico argue that the preferences are illegal.</p>
<p>Chiquita, based in Cincinatti, convinced former U.S. Trade Representative Mickey Kantor that EU tariffs and quotas favouring ACP bananas amounted to discrimination against U.S. companies and had led to a drop in its own EU market share.</p>
<p>Neutral trade diplomats say there seems little doubt that the WTO panel, which under the rules of the watchdog's Dispute Settlement Body should make its report by February next year, will follow its GATT predecessors in finding the EU regime against the rules.</p>
<p>At this point, the EU can appeal, but under the WTO cannot block a final ruling as it could, and did, under the GATT.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CARIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100206">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
