<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44221" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Caribbean legal advisers barred in WTO banana row.</title>
<headline>Caribbean legal advisers barred in WTO banana row.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Advisers to Caribbean banana-producing countries were on Tuesday barred from a hearing in the World Trade Organisation after the United States protested at their presence, an official said.</p>
<p>Gordon Myers, European representative of the Caribbean Banana Exporters' Association (CBEA), told Reuters he and two legal advisers had to leave a WTO panel session looking into a complaint Washington has brought against the European Union.</p>
<p>The three were officially accredited by St Lucia but are informally representing 12 countries in the Africa, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) group that currently export bananas to the EU under preferential arrangements.</p>
<p>The United States -- backed by four Latin American countries including Ecuador which is the world's leading banana exporter -- argues that aspects of the arrangements are violations of WTO agreements on open trade.</p>
<p>Myers said U.S. officials argued that only permanent government employees were allowed to sit in on panel hearings. Edwin Laurent, ambassador of East Caribbean states to Brussels, was allowed to stay.</p>
<p>The Caribbean producers have already complained that they have only been allowed to attend the panel, whose hearings began on Tuesday and are likely to continue for up to six months, as observers although their economies are at stake.</p>
<p>Myers said the action against the lawyers &quot;further diminishes the Caribbean producers' rights to defend themselves when 60 per cent of their export earnings are risk.&quot;</p>
<p>One of the lawyers asked to leave, Chris Parlin of a Washington legal firm, said the refusal to allow them to sit in had major implications for developing countries in the WTO and its dispute settlement mechanism.</p>
<p>&quot;Big trade powers like the United States, the European Union and Japan can afford to employ full-time trade lawyers. Small countries cannot, and this ruling could have a serious effect on their ability to defend themselves in the WTO,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Parlin himself is a former U.S. trade diplomat who worked in the U.S. Trade Representative's mission to the WTO's predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT).</p>
<p>Laurent said it had been essential to have legal advisers because it was not possible for small states like St Vincent and St Lucia and the Grenadines -- to whom the three were also accredited -- &quot;to employ the necessary expertise on a permanent basis.</p>
<p>&quot;This decision would place such countries in a continuing disadvantage in disputes in the WTO,&quot; he declared in a formal press statement.</p>
<p>&quot;It also raises questions about the discretion of sovereign states to determine who should represent them at international meetings,&quot; Laurent added.</p>
<p>At a news conference on Monday, Laurent and Myers said the fragile economies of the Caribbean banana producing states would be devastated if the panel decision went against Brussels and the EU were forced to drop its preferential treatment.</p>
<p>Caribbean leaders have warned Washington, which says U.S. marketing companies and especially Chiquita are put at a disadvantage by the EU banana import regime, that it could face a flood of economic refugees if the region's banana industry is destroyed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CARIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLUC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100206">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
