<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46122" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: WTO head says progress made in tough China talks.</title>
<headline>WTO head says progress made in tough China talks.</headline>
<byline>Jason Webb</byline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>World Trade Organization chief Renato Ruggiero said progress had been made in talks for China to join the group but added that the going was tough.</p>
<p>&quot;Much progress has been made in this negotiation but certainly this is a very difficult negotiation. Both for China and for the members of the WTO,&quot; he told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a strong hope that this negotiation can be positively concluded as soon as possible,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>Ruggiero said &quot;I strongly believe there is no one, I say no one, in the WTO, who opposes China's entry on the basis of political considerations.&quot;</p>
<p>Ruggiero was in Buenos Aires to brief Argentine officials on the implementation of GATT's Uruguay Round and proposals to discuss issues such as environmental and labor standards in the WTO's first ministerial conference in Singapore in December.  &quot;We believe we have to talk about the relationship between trade and the environment, how to be sure that the trade legislation and the environmment legislation are mutually supporting and not conflicting,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Another big issue in Singapore will be the relationship between regional trade blocs such as South America's Mercosur and free trade on a global scale.  Also on the agenda will be rules for investment, competition and transparency, especially of government procurement, as well as more trade liberalization.</p>
<p>Ruggiero said he did not think that moves by the United States and Japan to bypass the WTO and seek a bilateral resolution to their trade quarrels undermined the authority of his fledgling organization.  </p>
<p>The WTO was set up after the conclusion of the Uruguay Round of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade in 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not want to make rules.  We want to solve the disputes, so I don't think that if the United States and Japan try to settle their disputes bilaterally this is a threat,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked about the United States' clash with the European Union over the Helms-Burton act to sanction companies doing business with Cuba, Ruggiero said that the two sides were apparently toning down the dispute.  </p>
<p>&quot;I think that on the Helms-Burton law there have been some changes or some interpretations made by the president of the United States. The first stage of the procedure, the bilateral one, is now finished but I do not have any information about a European Union request for a panel,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ruggiero said the cut in farm subsidies agreed under GATT was going according to plan and he was hopeful for the second phase of negotiations scheduled to begin in 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;Everything is going without any major complaint, and as far as I know everybody is fulfilling his obligation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The WTO boss finished his comments to reporters by stressing that while trade disputes may still occur, the world will never be able to reverse the trend to globalization and free trade. &quot;This is a one-way street. A bumpy road but a one-way street.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0655</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
