<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52721" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: WTO prepares for first summit without consensus.</title>
<headline>WTO prepares for first summit without consensus.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA, Brazil 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The global trading community is readying for the first big meeting of the World Trade Organisation, still far from a consensus but gradually building bridges, the WTO's head said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Renato Ruggiero, visiting Brasilia to inform Brazilian officials on the likely agenda for December's first ministerial WTO meeting, said the issue linking labour rights to trade, in particular, remained, highly controversial.</p>
<p>&quot;There is not a consensus on how to deal with this problem,&quot; he told reporters. &quot;It seems to me that some common ground begins to exist on some important points.&quot;</p>
<p>Ruggiero's said most WTO members seemed to agree that labour standards were a commitment under the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. But they also agreed the issue was &quot;the primary responsibility&quot; of the International Labour Organisation.</p>
<p>In addition he sensed a consensus in that trade restriction measures were not the answer to the problem and that the discussion about tying trade to workers' rights should not put into question the comparative advantage of low-wage countries.</p>
<p>Washington and Paris have led calls for labour standards to be placed firmly on the agenda of the WTO, much to the chagrin of many less-developed countries that fear an attempt to erase their low-wage-based international competitivity.</p>
<p>The head of the world trade watchdog, which replaced the old General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade and came into being in January this year, said another contentious issue was whether the WTO should accelerate the process of trade liberalisation.</p>
<p>&quot;The free trade system has as its primary objective further liberalisation, which means we recognise we are not yet, perhaps we are still far, from a perfect free trade world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But liberalisation is not just the only objective of our activity,&quot; he added, saying the establishment of rules and disciplines went hand in hand with fair commerce.</p>
<p>Brazil, among other nations, says it senses an attempt by the United States to speed up market openings in areas that would disadvantage less-industrialised nations.</p>
<p>&quot;Brazil is not comfortable with this type of proposal,&quot; said the head of the Brazilian Foreign Ministry's Economics Department, Jose Alfredo Graca Lima.</p>
<p>Lima said the WTO had enough on its hands to fulfil the obligations already agreed to my its member states.</p>
<p>Ruggiero played down suggestions that disagreement over December's summit in Singapore and the large number of trade disputes that have already arisen in the WTO's first year of existence -- 53 -- boded ill for the body's future success.</p>
<p>&quot;The real difference between our organisation and the previous organisation is not that now we have no more trade disputes and before we had trade disputes. The difference is that now we have an automatic and binding system for settling the disputes,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA, Brazil"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
