<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59518" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: North, South still apart on agenda for WTO meet.</title>
<headline>North, South still apart on agenda for WTO meet.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Developed and developing states remain far apart on including labour conditions and investment on the agenda for a key meeting of the World Trade Organisation (WTO) in December, diplomats said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>But emerging economies who oppose discussion of either issue at the WTO's first ministerial gathering in Singapore sense the tide is running in their favour -- partly due to differences among the industrialised trading powers.</p>
<p>The wide gap between major countries in the South and North was underscored over the past week as envoys to the WTO resumed contacts after the summer break with only three months left before the week-long session.</p>
<p>At an informal meeting of WTO ambassadors on Monday, and at a two-day seminar last week, diplomats from Asia, Africa and Latin America were almost unanimous in insisting &quot;new issues&quot; should be left for other organisations.</p>
<p>&quot;If we agree to discussion of even one of these, the big powers will use it as a lever to prise open the door to more concessions in every area,&quot; said one Asian participant in the seminar, to general approval from the hall.</p>
<p>But the United States, which has some backing from the European Union and especially France as well as from international labour union groupings, insists that the link between trade and working conditions is a WTO problem.</p>
<p>Norway has proposed what it has billed as a &quot;third road&quot; under which there would be only exploratory discussion of the link -- which developing countries see as a device that if formalised under WTO rules could be used to deprive them of the advantage they have in producing goods at lower labour costs.</p>
<p>The EU is seeking discussion in Singapore of national policies on investment with the eventual aim of an accord supported by WTO open trading rules that would ensure at least equal treatment for foreign companies.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment, there seems little meeting of minds,&quot; said one envoy whose country professes to have no strong feelings on either side.</p>
<p>Complicating the scenario is the reluctance by some richer countries -- trading powers Australia and New Zealand among them -- to push the labour issue. Japan also stands on the sidelines.</p>
<p>On investment and the related issue of competition policy, Washington is far less enthusiastic than Brussels for a WTO role, arguing that these issues are best left at present to the Paris-based club of the richer countries, the OECD.</p>
<p>At Monday's WTO meeting, the fledgling body's Director General Renato Ruggiero, fresh from talks in Latin America and contacts with leaders in other regions over the summer, signalled concern that time was running out.</p>
<p>Agreement on the agenda for the ministers at their first meeting since the WTO was launched in January 1995 would demand &quot;an intense effort on all sides,&quot; he told the envoys.</p>
<p>&quot;This means not only an effort in terms of time and comitment but, above all, a shared effort to find common ground and compromises, where needed, on some difficult issues.&quot;</p>
<p>Diplomats say that there is almost total accord among the WTO's currently 123 members that the main focus in Singapore from December 9-13 should be on reviewing the extent of implementation of the 1994 world trade treaty.</p>
<p>But even here, North and South have a different approach.</p>
<p>The United States, the European Union and Canada want to see faster action by emerging economies in opening up their markets as agreed in the treaty, signed in Marrakesh, Morocco, at the end of the seven-year Uruguay Round negotiations.</p>
<p>Developing countries argue that it is the industrialisd powers that are lagging in implementing their liberalisation commitments, especially in the area of textiles and of helping the world's poorest countries develop their trade muscle.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFRICA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DEVGCO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LAM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
