<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65311" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ruggiero sees Helms-Burton row coming to WTO.</title>
<headline>Ruggiero sees Helms-Burton row coming to WTO.</headline>
<byline>David Fox</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of the World Trade Organisation said on Thursday that the WTO was prepared to mediate in an international row over U.S. trade legislation, but added he hoped the issue never made it that far.</p>
<p>WTO Director-General Renato Ruggiero told a news conference that the row over Washington's Helms-Burton Act and D'Amato Bill -- which seek to quash trade with Cuba and Iran and Libya respectively -- was likely to go to the WTO to settle.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't want to see it ... I don't like to see it, but I think it will happen,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ruggiero, attending a meeting of European Union Trade Ministers, said settling international disputes was precisely what the WTO was created for.</p>
<p>&quot;Some think that if there is a dispute, you should blame the WTO. But the fact that the WTO is where the disputes are heard shows that it is working,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The EU and U.S. have been at odds for months over the Helms-Burton Act and D'Amato Bill, and the European Commission is considering escalating its grievances with the WTO.</p>
<p>If this happens, a WTO disputes settlement panel would decide whether the EU's complaints that the laws were extra-territorial are justified.</p>
<p>Outlining his ambitions for the WTO ministerial meeting in Singapore in December, Ruggiero said it was important to keep the agenda focussed on the progress the organisation had made in wrapping up global deals left over from its predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.</p>
<p>He said the so-called &quot;new issues&quot; -- which include labour standards and environmental concerns -- should be put aside or tackled at a differant forum.</p>
<p>Ruggiero, speaking the day after a tyre-factory closure here was blamed partially on cheaper imports from Eastern Europe, said trade liberalisation almost always created rather than cost jobs.</p>
<p>The German rubber giant Continental AG announced on Wednesday that it was closing its Semperit tyre factory in Ballyfermot with the loss of over 600 jobs.</p>
<p>&quot;This unfortunate matter is one for the Irish government or the EU,&quot; Ruggiero said. &quot;But normally multilateral trading and liberalisation is an engine for growth.&quot;</p>
<p>Ruggiero said erecting trade barriers was an outdated philosophy. &quot;The road (to trade liberalisation) is bumpy ... but it is a one-way street,&quot; he said. &quot;Anyway, people are not proposing anything else.&quot;</p>
<p>He called on the EU to send a &quot;strong political signal&quot; to developing nations at the Singapore meeting to encourage them to further open their markets.</p>
<p>But he cautioned the EU against pushing controversial issues too far, saying this could merely polarise the West from developing nations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LIBYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
