<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67433" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: US to seek WTO panel against Japan in Kodak case.</title>
<headline>US to seek WTO panel against Japan in Kodak case.</headline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States on Friday asked the World Trade Organisation (WTO) to set up a dispute settlement panel to investigate Eastman Kodak Co's allegations of anti-competitive practices by Japan and its giant Fuji Photo Film Co, trade sources said.</p>
<p>Neither U.S. nor Japanese trade officials in Geneva could be reached immediately for comment on Friday evening.</p>
<p>A WTO spokesman confirmed that U.S. trade officials in Geneva had filed a request for a dispute panel late on Friday, but he had no details on the complaint.</p>
<p>A special meeting of the WTO Dispute Settlement Body is to be held on October 3 to consider the U.S. request, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;The United States has requested a panel against Japan concerning the Kodak-Fuji dispute,&quot; a WTO spokesman told Reuters. &quot;It was in the goods dispute case.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. also submitted a request for further consultations on the dispute involving the services aspect of the case,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Washington last June said it would investigate alleged Japanese market barriers to photo film and paper which discriminate against treatment of imported goods.</p>
<p>Then-U.S. Trade Representative Mickey Kantor acted on a petition by American photography giant Eastman Kodak which charged anti-competitive practices by Japan and Fuji.</p>
<p>Kodak at the time said Japanese market barriers have cost it an estimated $5.6 billion in lost sales since the mid-1970s.</p>
<p>Kantor's office said that, according to Kodak's petition, Fuji enjoys a 75 percent share of the Japanese market for photographic film, while Kodak's share is ony seven percent.</p>
<p>Kodak's petition cited decades of exclusionary practices, largely involving Fuji, including price-fixing in trade associations and trying to control financially struggling wholesalers and retailers through cash payments to them.</p>
<p>WTO director-general Renato Ruggiero, who will attend the annual meeting of the World Bank and International Monetary Fund in Washington next week, will meet U.S. Trade Representative Charlene Barshefsky on Monday, a WTO spokesman told a regular news briefing earlier in the day.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
