<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68756" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan wants October start WTO talks with U.S..</title>
<headline>Taiwan wants October start WTO talks with U.S..</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan, hoping to join the World Trade Organisation in 1997, said on Saturday it wanted to start talks on its entry with the United States in October.</p>
<p>&quot;We have proposed to the U.S. side to hold talks regarding our WTO entry next month in Taipei,&quot; a Board of Foreign Trade official, who declined to be identified, told Reuters by telephone.</p>
<p>&quot;But so far we have not received any response from them.&quot;</p>
<p>The last time Taipei and Washington held WTO negotiations was in June 1995, the official said. He said the island had so far had talks with 10 of the 26 WTO members.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't have a timetable for joining the WTO, but we would like to become a member as soon as possible,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Taiwan officials say it will be difficult for Taiwan to join the world trade body if China, which views Taiwan as a renegade province, joins first.</p>
<p>In 1990, Taiwan applied to join WTO's predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, under the name of Chinese Taipei.</p>
<p>China's demand to join GATT by the end of 1994 was rejected.</p>
<p>GATT was replaced by WTO in January 1995.</p>
<p>In the most senior U.S.-Taiwan contact in nearly two years, visiting U.S. Deputy Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers last week hailed the island's powerhouse economy and said he looked forward to Taiwan joining the WTO.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
