<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80891" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: WTO 'admission fee' must be fair - China's Wu.</title>
<headline>WTO 'admission fee' must be fair - China's Wu.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Trade Minister Wu Yi said China was ready to be flexible in negotiations to join the World Trade Organization but warned Friday if &quot;our admission fee is too high, we cannot afford it.&quot;</p>
<p>Wu said China should be admitted under the more lenient rules offered to developing nations.</p>
<p>U.S. Commerce Secretary Mickey Kantor, appearing at a news conference with Wu, said China should join on a basis that takes into account its large economy.  </p>
<p>&quot;We are prepared to show greater flexibility&quot; in upcoming negotiations on WTO accession, Wu said, adding China had no timetable for when it would join WTO.</p>
<p>&quot;China needs to join the WTO and the WTO needs China,&quot; Wu said, describing China as the 11th largest trading nation.</p>
<p>Wu also criticized the U.S. position on Chinese textile exports. The United States has expressed concern that some goods were being transshipped through other nations as a way to evade import limits.  </p>
<p>It was a &quot;big shortcoming&quot; and &quot;unfair&quot; to exclude China from WTO, Wu said, adding Beijing was ready to pay an &quot;admission fee.&quot;</p>
<p>But, she said, WTO membership &quot;must be in line with our economic development. If the request for our admission fee is too high, we cannot afford it. I do not have so much money in my pocket.&quot;</p>
<p>One day ago, Acting U.S. Trade Representative Charlene Barchevsky said China failed to show &quot;a serious interest&quot; in joining WTO and was &quot;treading water&quot; on economic reform.  </p>
<p>Washington wants China to undertake a number of reforms to open its markets to imported goods as a condition for joining WTO.</p>
<p>&quot;Whether or when China joins WTO, China will not stop its reform and opening-up policy,&quot; Wu said.</p>
<p>China is the fifth largest U.S. trade partner and ranks second to Japan in running a massive trade surplus in dealings with the United States.</p>
<p>As part of two days of trade meetings, the United States announced $495 million in loan guarantees for sales of U.S. aircraft and three contracts for software to Chinese agencies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="WORLD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
