<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50474" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Moroccans vote Friday on changing constitution.</title>
<headline>Moroccans vote Friday on changing constitution.</headline>
<byline>John Baggaley</byline>
<dateline>RABAT 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>After weeks of political party activity, millions of Moroccans are to vote on Friday on change to their 1992 constitution which would set up a powerful second house of parliament.</p>
<p>Last minute appeals for the more than 12 million eligible Moroccans to vote &quot;yes&quot; dominated the media on Thursday, after pro-government and opposition parties alike almost unanimously urged their supporters to back King Hassan's proposals.</p>
<p>The king, whose paramount powers will not be touched, said the change would split the present 333-seat Majlis Anuwab (Chamber of Representatives) into two to strengthen regional representation.</p>
<p>The second house, indirectly elected mainly through local councils, professional bodies and trade unions, will have power to force a vote of no-confidence in the government.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very rare for a second chamber to have such power,&quot; one Western diplomat commented.</p>
<p>&quot;On balance, what the new constitution does allow -- though I don't expect this for some time -- is more democracy if the authorities decide not to interfere (in the indirect elections).&quot;</p>
<p>The official news agency MAP said the new house, the Majlis al-Mustasharin (Consultative Chamber), would be elected for nine years but renew one-third of members each three years.</p>
<p>The lower house, now with one-third of its members elected indirectly, will be elected directly. The opposition, with more than one-third of present MPs, has long called for total direct elections to the existing parliament.</p>
<p>Morocco's main opposition parties, the old-guard Istiqlal party with 52 seats, and Socialist Union of People's Forces (USFP) with 56 seats, have, despite reservations, called for a &quot;yes&quot; vote.</p>
<p>&quot;Our 'yes' vote will enable the country to get out of the political impasse and the wait and see situation,&quot; Mohamed Guessous, a leading USFP figure said earlier this week.</p>
<p>And one senior Moroccan official, commenting on the 'yes' call, said: &quot;It should be noted that this is the first time that there is a general consensus and a positive approach on constitution reforms proposed by the royal palace since 1961.&quot;</p>
<p>Several small parties have, however, called either for a boycott or a 'no' vote. And on Wednesday, the Avant-Garde Democratic and Socialist Party said police had arrested five of its members while they campaigned for a boycott.</p>
<p>The Interior Ministry said it was not aware of the arrests.</p>
<p>Another party, the Democratic Organisation of Peoples' Action, with two seats in parliament, said in its mouthpiece Anwal on Thursday: &quot;The constitution (changes) do not take account of genuine public opinion and...will keep citizens far from taking political decisions.&quot;</p>
<p>The employment ministry has called on employers to ensure everyone has chance to vote.</p>
<p>Another constitutional change will set up a watchdog to oversee the budget -- seen as vital to help spread development to the countryside.</p>
<p>In a recent report, drawn up with the United Nations, Rabat drew a bleak picture of rural life -- high female illiteracy, children absent from schools, little drinking water, poverty.</p>
<p>Moroccans registered for the referendum include more than 118,000 people in the disputed Western Sahara.</p>
<p>Voting stations open at 8 a.m. (0800 gmt) and are due to close at 6 p.m. (1800 GMT). First results are expected around 10 p.m., with final results on Saturday.  REUTER JFB/BA</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
