<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="12658" id="root" date="1996-08-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Adventurers start Canadian wilderness race.</title>
<headline>Adventurers start Canadian wilderness race.</headline>
<dateline>PEMBERTON, British Columbia 1996-08-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>About 350 adventurers from nine countries set out on Saturday to climb, raft, bike and run in a 323-mile (517-km) endurance race through the Canadian wilderness.</p>
<p>The event, called the Eco-Challenge, is part of a growing sport known as adventure racing in which competitors test their limits for days over a perilous wilderness course.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm looking forward to this race. I think it will be more physically challenging and we'll have to go up against more diverse situations due to the terrain,&quot; said Dr. Michael Stroud, a veteran Eco-Challenge participant.</p>
<p>The Eco-Challenge has been staged twice before -- in Utah and Maine last year -- and is modelled on similar races overseas.</p>
<p>The 70 teams in this year's race will will trek glaciers, climb mountains, whitewater raft, horseback ride, canoe and mountain bike along the grueling course.</p>
<p>This year's race, the route of which was keep a secret until Friday evening, is being held near Pemberton, British Columbia, about 100 miles (160 km) northeast of Vancouver. The area is filled with treacherous mountain peaks, ice fields and frigid waters.</p>
<p>Organisers expect about two-thirds of the participants to drop out or be disqualified before the finish. The hardy ones are expected to complete the course in about six days, with first-place finishers receiving $10,000 in prize money.</p>
<p>In the Eco-Challenge, competitors race in teams of five which must include both men and women. Team members must remain within 100 yards (metres) of each other at all times and finish together.</p>
<p>With racers carrying about 40 pounds (18 kg) of gear on their backs, broken bones, sunstroke, dehydration and exhaustion are common.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PEMBERTON, British Columbia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
