<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="12855" id="root" date="1996-08-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Hindu pilgrims stranded in Himalayas after 84 die.</title>
<headline>Hindu pilgrims stranded in Himalayas after 84 die.</headline>
<byline>Sheikh Mushtaq</byline>
<dateline>SRINAGAR, India 1996-08-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>At least 84 Hindu pilgrims braving snow and rain have died from exposure in the Himalayan mountains along a rugged route to a 3,880-metre (12,725-ft) high cave, officials said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Nearly 70,000 pilgrims, including many naked devotees, were stranded and authorities in Kashmir have suspended the annual pilgrimage, the officials said.</p>
<p>The trek through India's only Moslem majority state began last week and had been scheduled to end next Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;At least 84 pilgrims have died of cold so far,&quot; said K.B. Jandial, a spokesman for Jammu and Kashmir. &quot;We have suspended the movement of pilgrims who are stranded at different places in the state.&quot;</p>
<p>On Friday, police in Srinigar, the state's summer capital, said 24 devotees had died since Thursday.</p>
<p>Jandial said the pilgrimage had not been cancelled but could not say when it might be resumed.</p>
<p>Officials said some 112,000 Hindus had arrived in Kashmir this year to visit the Amarnath cave, where devotees worship an ice stalagmite believed to be a manifestation of the &quot;lingam&quot;, or phallus, of the Hindu god Shiva.</p>
<p>Floods and landslides caused by torrential rains have forced authorities to close the 300-km (200-mile) highway between Srinaga and Jammu in the south.</p>
<p>Around 25,000 pilgrims were stranded in Jammu, the state's winter capital, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have advised all pilgrims stranded in Udhampur and Jammu to go back because it will take more than three days to clear the Jammu-Srinagar highway,&quot; Jandial said.</p>
<p>Police said they expected more deaths as incessant rain and snow were hampering rescue operations.</p>
<p>&quot;At least 5,000 people are stranded in the higher reaches of Pahalgam, where the temperature has fallen to freezing,&quot; a senior official said. &quot;The pilgrims  are not equipped to handle the weather situation.&quot;</p>
<p>From Pahalgam onwards, the pilgrims have to use ponies or trek 50 km (30 miles) through the mountains to get to the cave. The rains had flooded all the roads to Pahalgam, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;The main reason for these deaths is that the pilgrims were not equipped with warm clothing and most of the holy men who died were trekking naked,&quot; Asrar Ahmad, a doctor at a pilgrim camp in Anantnag, 50 km (30 miles) south of Srinagar, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Last year the pilgrimage was threatened by Moslem separatist guerrillas, who staged two bomb attacks on the heavily guarded pilgrims. A state civil servant was killed in one of the blasts.</p>
<p>Some 20,000 people have died since a separatist revolt broke out in 1990 in Jammu and Kashmir, police and hospital sources say.</p>
<p>This year guerrillas issued no ban on the pilgrimage. Instead, the weather has proved an obstacle, with snow a foot (30 cm) deep at some points on the pilgrims' route, officials said.</p>
<p>Authorities are making arrangements to fly out some of the stranded pilgrims to Jammu or the Indian capital New Delhi, Jandial said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRINAGAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
