<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13382" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Himalaya pilgrims stranded as death toll hits 116.</title>
<headline>Himalaya pilgrims stranded as death toll hits 116.</headline>
<byline>Sheikh Mushtaq</byline>
<dateline>SRINAGAR, India 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian army and paramilitary forces battled on Sunday to rescue thousands of Hindu pilgrims stranded along a rugged Himalayan mountain path after at least 116 died from cold, officials said.</p>
<p>The troops were close to 70,000 devotees strung along the 50-km (30-mile) route to the holy Amarnath cave, officials said. The cave is 3,880 metres (12,725 ft) high.</p>
<p>&quot;At least 116 yatris (pilgrims) have died so far,&quot; spokesman K.B. Jandial told Reuters. &quot;Now there is no one left at the cave. The army helped to guide the pilgrims down to safety.&quot;</p>
<p>Officials said some 112,000 Hindus had arrived in Kashmir this year to visit the cave, where devotees worship an ice stalagmite believed to be a manifestation of the &quot;lingam&quot;, or phallus, of the Hindu god Shiva.</p>
<p>There were many naked &quot;sadhus&quot;, or Hindu holy men smeared only in ash, among the dead, relief officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;The main reason for the deaths is that the pilgrims had no warm clothing. Many were were old people. The holy men were trekking naked,&quot; said a doctor at a pilgrim camp in Anantnag, 50 km (30 miles) south of Srinagar.</p>
<p>The taxing trek across India's only-Moslem majority state had to be halted soon after unexpected heavy rain and snow falls last week. It had been scheduled to end this Wednesday.</p>
<p>Indian troops based at Pahalgam, the base camp for the trek, had swung into action to guide pilgrims off the slopes and carry the ill and injured to safety, an army spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have moved almost 30,000 people out of the vicinity of the cave, removing them from the highest sector of the trek since yesterday,&quot; the spokesman told Reuters in New Delhi.</p>
<p>The army has made arrangements to distribute food and fuel to the trekkers. It has also set up eight medical camps.</p>
<p>Officials said prospects for a successful, full-scale relief operation had brightened with an improvement in the weather which had hampered rescue work on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;Today we will fly helicopter sorties and try to airlift ill and injured pilgrims from Sheshnag, Panchtarni and other places,&quot; a defence official in Srinagar said.</p>
<p>Both points are more than 3,000 metres (9,840 ft) high, about a day's trek from the holy cave.</p>
<p>Heavy rains had stranded the 30,000 trekkers who managed to struggle back to the base camp at Pahalgam, officials said. Approach roads in and out of the town were all flooded.</p>
<p>Moslem villagers have also come forward to help the stranded pilgrims. They had taken them into their homes and given them food and warm clothing, officials said.</p>
<p>In Jammu to the south, teams of paramilitary forces were busy clearing the 300-km (200-mile) highway to Srinagar, an operation which is expected to take another day or two.</p>
<p>About 25,000 people had been stranded in Jammu, the state's winter capital, after floods and landslides caused by torrential rains blocked the highway, officials said.</p>
<p>Last year the pilgrimage was threatened by Moslem separatist guerrillas who staged two bomb attacks on the heavily guarded pilgrims. A state civil servant was killed in one of the blasts.</p>
<p>Some 20,000 people have died since a separatist revolt broke out in 1990 in Jammu and Kashmir, police and hospital sources say. This year guerrillas issued no ban on the pilgrimage.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRINAGAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
