<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14752" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Harrowing scenes in Kashmir town after 127 die.</title>
<headline>Harrowing scenes in Kashmir town after 127 die.</headline>
<byline>Sheikh Mushtaq</byline>
<dateline>PAHALGAM, India 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rows of ill and distraught Hindus, survivors of a harrowing pilgrimage during which at least 127 died, lay exhausted on Monday in tents clustered around the Himalayan foothill town of Pahalgam.</p>
<p>More than 60,000 pilgrims gathered in Pahalgam after spending up to four days on an exposed mountainside at the mercy of bitter wind, rain and snow.</p>
<p>Authorities said 127 people trekking to a holy cave 3,880 metres (12,725 feet) high in the Himalayas died last week in below-freezing temperatures that followed unusually heavy rains. The Press Trust of India put the toll at 160.</p>
<p>Some 112,000 Hindus came to Kashmir for this year's pilgrimage to the holy Amarnath cave, where devotees worship an ice stalagmite believed to be a manifestation of the &quot;lingam&quot;, or phallus, of the Hindu God Shiva.</p>
<p>Among the dead were naked &quot;sadhus&quot;, or Hindu holy men who smear their bodies with ash.</p>
<p>The pilgrims were marooned at Pahalgam, the base camp for the five-day, 50-km (30-mile) trek, because all roads to the town were cut off after last week's torrential rains.</p>
<p>&quot;There were long lines of 3,000 to 4,000 people queued up outside the food tents,&quot; said Fayyaz Kabli, a local photographer who visited the town on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;They were many women and children crying. Sadhus were sitting silent by the roadside and not saying anything.&quot;</p>
<p>Many of the pilgrims were angry at what they described as poor arrangements by the government for the pilgrims.</p>
<p>&quot;'We were sent here to die,'&quot; Kabli quoted one of them as saying. &quot;'The government has not helped us. When we were dying they did not help us. Now what is the point of sending helicopters?'&quot;</p>
<p>Military helicopters plucked 2,000 pilgrims from the mountainside on Sunday after the weather cleared for the first time in four days. Between 300 and 400 soldiers escorted several thousand more, who had climbed above the base camp, to safety.</p>
<p>Kabli travelled along the pilgrimage route, interviewing returning pilgrims. Many were frantic with grief or worry over the fate of family members, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;At the police station in Pahalgam, we met a man whose brother had died,&quot; said Kabli. &quot;He was crying, shouting: 'I am ready to pay three million rupees ($85,000) to anybody who can help me transport my brother's body to New Delhi.'&quot;</p>
<p>Further along the pilgrims' route at Chandanwadi, 12 km (eight miles) beyond Pahalgam, Kabli said he saw rows of corpses laid out beside the road.</p>
<p>&quot;There were lots of dead bodies in terrible condition,&quot; Kabli told Reuters. &quot;Many had no clothes. Occasionally there was the corpse of a dead pony or two. Army troops came, loaded the bodies into trucks and took them away to be cremated.&quot;</p>
<p>At Pissu Top, about 12 km (eight miles) from the Amarnath cave, Kabli said he saw army and paramilitary troops leading corpse-laden ponies down the steep slope.</p>
<p>&quot;Rakesh, a 30-year-old man from Hyderabad, said he had seen a group of about 100 people walking along a glacier when the glacier suddenly collapsed, burying them all alive,&quot; Kabli said.</p>
<p>&quot;'Nobody is talking about all those deaths. I saw them with my own eyes,'&quot; he quoted Rakesh as saying.</p>
<p>The spokesman for the Jammu and Kashmir state government, K.B. Jandial, said numerous unclaimed bodies had been cremated by the authorities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PAHALGAM, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
