<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17505" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Alaska park section closed after fatal bear mauling.</title>
<headline>Alaska park section closed after fatal bear mauling.</headline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A section along the banks of the Noatak River in Alaska's remote Gates of the Arctic National Park was closed Monday, three days after a grizzly bear killed a hiker there, the National Park Service said.</p>
<p>Robert Bell, 33, of Washington, D.C., was mauled to death Friday by a grizzly sow in the far-north park. It was the first known fatal bear mauling in the park's 18-year history.</p>
<p>Bell had been hiking with a companion during a stop in a nine-day float trip when they surprised the bear guarding a young cub in heavy brush, Park Service officials said.</p>
<p>The men were talking loudly and wearing bells to alert bears to their presence while hiking, said Steve Ulvi, a Gates of the Arctic biologist. But perhaps due to wind patterns, they were not noticed by the sow until they were within about 10 feet and therefore surprised it, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It appears that the contributing factors are all natural and not human-caused,&quot; Ulvi said. &quot;From all we can tell, these fellows acted in a perfectly appropriate manner.&quot;</p>
<p>Bell's companions, Bill Rehm of San Francisco and Jonathan Butters of Chapel Hill, N.C., were evacuated from the area by a local pilot Friday. They had used equipment and clothing to spell out the word &quot;Help&quot; on the ground.</p>
<p>The Park Service was allowing rafters to continue floating down the river, but advised them to avoid landing on the banks for a 10-mile stretch around the bear attack site, Ulvi said.</p>
<p>&quot;It appears that there are a larger than normal number of grizzly bears along the Noatak River at that stretch,&quot; Ulvi said, attributing it to a larger-than-normal chum salmon run.</p>
<p>He said the Park Service was not looking for the bear that killed Bell. Park rangers and Alaska State Troopers investigated the accident.</p>
<p>Gates of the Arctic lies above the Arctic Circle in Alaska's remote Brooks Range. At eight million acres, it is the second largest U.S. national park, but was visited by only a few thousand people each year, Park Service officials said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
