<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19705" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Nearly 200 dead in Himalayan pilgrim tragedy.</title>
<headline>Nearly 200 dead in Himalayan pilgrim tragedy.</headline>
<byline>Sheikh Mushtaq</byline>
<dateline>SRINAGAR, India 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian search parties on Wednesday discovered more bodies of Hindu pilgrims along the route to a holy cave in the Himalayas, raising to 194 the number who died on the annual trek, authorities said.</p>
<p>&quot;The death toll in the Amarnath tragedy has risen to 194,&quot; K.B. Jandial, a spokesman for India's Jammu and Kashmir state, told Reuters.</p>
<p>More than 500 policemen and paramilitary troops fanned out along the 48-km (30-mile) route to the Amarnath cave, 3,880 metres (12,725 feet) high in the mountains, to search for any remaining bodies, Jandial said.</p>
<p>Some 70,000 pilgrims found themselves at the mercy of the weather for three days last week when bitter winds and heavy snow lashed the trail to the mountain cave.</p>
<p>&quot;It is possible that more bodies could be found,&quot; Jandial said.</p>
<p>Some 112,000 Hindus came to Kashmir for this year's trek to the cave, where devotees worship an ice stalagmite regarded as a symbol of the Hindu God Shiva.</p>
<p>Jandial said the search parties were trying to verify eyewitness reports by pilgrims that 30 people had died when a glacier collapsed, burying them alive.</p>
<p>Many distraught pilgrims had left for home, giving up hope of ever finding the bodies of their relatives, police officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are facing difficulties in identifying the dead as most of their relatives have left without informing us,&quot; a senior police official told Reuters. Police were unable to identify more than 70 of the bodies, he added.</p>
<p>Helicopters lifted many of the stranded pilgrims to safety as soon as the weather cleared on Sunday and on Monday dropped food, medicines and blankets. Troops helped hundreds of others down the freezing slopes to the base camp at Pahalgam.</p>
<p>Almost 60,000 people had been marooned at Pahalgam, about 100 km (60 miles) from the state's summer capital of Srinagar, after floodwaters blocked all roads to the town for three days. Thousands started driving out in buses on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Some pilgrims said they were unable to locate their companions in the confusion that followed their rescue.</p>
<p>&quot;We were all together trekking when bad weather caught us,&quot; said Ashok Kumar as he sat in a Srinagar hotel waiting for news of a missing friend.</p>
<p>Officials said that the &quot;charri mubarak&quot;, two silver maces symbolising Lord Shiva and his wife Parvati, arrived at the Amarnath cave on Tuesday evening.</p>
<p>Rituals marking their arrival at the cave signalled the formal end of the pilgrimage, the authorities said.</p>
<p>&quot;Since all the rituals have been performed in the holy cave, that technically concludes the annual pilgrimage,&quot; Jandial said.</p>
<p>Traditionally, the pilgrimage is wound up two or three days after the maces arrive at the cave.</p>
<p>The ascetic in charge of the maces vowed he would not be deterred by the tragedy. &quot;I will prefer to trek,&quot; said Deependra Giri.</p>
<p>The federal government has said it would order an inquiry into the deaths, but Home (Interior) Minister Indrajit Gupta said it appeared that adequate arrangements had been made.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRINAGAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
