<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24483" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>NORWAY: Doomed Russian plane's flight recorder found.</title>
<headline>Doomed Russian plane's flight recorder found.</headline>
<byline>Rolf Soderlind</byline>
<dateline>LONGYEAR, Norway 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Accident investigators working on an Arctic mountain recovered the flight data recorder from the wreck of a Russian airliner on Friday, hoping it could provide vital clues to the disaster in which 141 people died.</p>
<p>The Tupolev Tu-154 bringing Russian and Ukrainian coal miners to work on the remote Arctic island of Spitzbergen crashed into the mountain on Thursday as it was about to land, killing all on board.</p>
<p>&quot;The flight recorder has been found,&quot; a spokesman for the island governor's office told reporters.</p>
<p>The recorder could tell Norwegian and Russian investigators whether the plane was off course or flying too low. The spokesman said he did not know the condition of the recorder.</p>
<p>A team of police, investigators and doctors also began the perilous and grisly task of recovering bodies from the snowbound crash site. They were flown there by helicopter once a break in bad weather allowed them to start work.</p>
<p>&quot;We came to a small area where there were parts of the plane and they were completely destroyed,&quot; said Tore Dahlberg, a doctor who went to the scene.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a terrible sight,&quot; he told Norwegian television. &quot;We saw the mangled remains of people in the wreckage.&quot;</p>
<p>Getting the bodies down from the mountain is a priority.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing is that the dead will be counted and tagged. Then the victims will be bagged, sent by helicopter to Longyear and afterwards flown to Tromsoe (in mainland Norway) for autopsy,&quot; said police coordinator Ivar Follestad.</p>
<p>Most of the three-engined plane, smashed and broken, is stranded on a mountaintop some seven km (four miles) east of Longyear. The tail section broke off and slid down the steep mountainside, scarring the surface and blackening the snow.</p>
<p>The windblown, chilly streets of this tiny Norwegian mining town were all but deserted and flags flew at half-mast beneath a brooding, clouded sky on Friday.</p>
<p>The close-knit, hardy Norwegian and Russian mining communities on the island were plunged into grief and shock by the worst air disaster in Norway's history.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a sight I will never forget. I will remember it for the rest of my life,&quot; said Stig Onarheim, one of a handful of rescuers who raced to the scene of the crash in a helicopter on Thursday, hoping in vain to find survivors.</p>
<p>&quot;Imagine a big plane with a lot of luggage and people on board. Think of all that mixed together, with twisted, wrecked parts on the slope,&quot; Onarheim, 29, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The crash site is inaccessible by land and there is danger from avalanches and polar bears, rescue officials said.</p>
<p>Officials said it could take days or weeks to bring all the bodies down from the mountain. Police said mountain climbers could be needed to reach the tail section of the plane.</p>
<p>The plane was bringing miners and some of their families, 76 of them from Ukraine, to work in a Russian open-cast mine. Spitzbergen is governed by Norway but Russia has rights of access under an international treaty from the 1920s.</p>
<p>The miners were on their way to start work in the Russian towns of Barentsburg and Pyramiden. Fewer than 3,000 people live on Spitzbergen, which has one of the world's harshest climates and lies some 500 miles (800 km) off the northern tip of Norway.</p>
<p>In Kiev, Ukrainian President Leonid Kuchma declared Friday a national day of mourning for the dead miners and their families.</p>
<p>Russian emergency service officials arrived on Friday, in an identical plane to the one that crashed. Almost 100 miners, due to be relieved by the miners who perished, flew back to Moscow on the plane later on Friday.</p>
<p>Western aviation experts have raised questions about the safety of Russian airline operations following the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. But the pilot was experienced and did not report any trouble before the plane crashed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONGYEAR, Norway"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NORWAY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
