<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24492" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>NORWAY: Risky search starts for Arctic crash bodies, clues.</title>
<headline>Risky search starts for Arctic crash bodies, clues.</headline>
<byline>Rolf Soderlind</byline>
<dateline>LONGYEAR, Norway 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Searchers began a perilous task on Friday to recover bodies from a Russian airliner that crashed into a mountain on the Arctic island of Spitzbergen, killing all 141 people aboard.</p>
<p>Police and an accident inquiry team went by helicopter to the inaccessible crash site on this remote Norwegian island and officials said mountain climbers might even be called in.</p>
<p>The victims were mainly Ukrainian and Russian coalminers and their families.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing is that the dead will be counted and tagged. Then the victims will be bagged, sent by helicopter to Longyear and afterwards flown to Tromsoe (in mainland Norway) for autopsy,&quot; said police coordinator Ivar Follestad.</p>
<p>Norwegian police also began interviewing residents of the close-knit communities to seek witnesses who may have seen or heard the blue, brown and white Tupolev Tu-154 jet plough into a mountain on Thursday as it prepared to land.</p>
<p>Most of the three-engined plane, smashed and broken, is stranded on a mountaintop some seven km (four miles) east of Longyear. The tail section broke off and slid down the steep mountainside, scarring the surface and blackening the snow.</p>
<p>The windblown, chilly streets of this tiny Arctic town were all but deserted and flags flew at half-mast.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a sight I will never forget. I will remember it for the rest of my life,&quot; said Stig Onarheim, one of a handful of rescuers who raced to the scene of the crash in a helicopter on Thursday, hoping in vain to find survivors.</p>
<p>&quot;Imagine a big plane with a lot of luggage and people on board. Think of all that mixed together, with twisted, wrecked parts on the slope,&quot; Onarheim, 29, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The crash site is inaccessible by land and there is danger from avalanches and polar bears, rescue officials said.</p>
<p>Local government officials and police were guarding the site around the clock to keep animals away and a small hut had been erected to house accident investigators.</p>
<p>But officials said it could days or weeks to bring all the bodies down from the mountain.</p>
<p>Police said mountain climbers could be needed to reach the tail section of the plane, which slid down the steep mountainside after the crash.</p>
<p>All 129 passengers and 12 crew were killed.</p>
<p>The Tupolev Tu-154 was bringing miners and some of their families, 76 of them from Ukraine, to work in a Russian open-cast mine. Spitzbergen is governed by Norway but Russia has rights of access under an international treaty from the 1920s.</p>
<p>The cause of the crash remains a mystery. Police and local officials declined to speculate at a news conference on Friday whether the plane flew off course or was coming in too low.</p>
<p>Russian emergency service officials arrived on an identical plane to the one that crashed. Some 91 miners, due to be relieved by the miners who died, were due to fly back later.</p>
<p>Investigators are hoping to recover the plane's flight data recorders from the crash site.</p>
<p>Western aviation experts have raised questions about the safety of Russian airline operations following the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. But the pilot was experienced and did not report any trouble before the plane crashed.</p>
<p>Yevgeny Buzny, an official of the Russian mining company which chartered the plane, said there were seven children and 4O women on the plane.</p>
<p>The miners were on their way to start work in the Russian towns of Barentsburg and Pyramiden.</p>
<p>Harsh, remote conditions mean that few other than miners from the former Soviet Union, pressed by job losses and falling wages at home, would brave Spitzbergen.</p>
<p>Fewer than 3,000 people live on the island which has one of the world's harshest climates and lies some 500 miles (800 km) off the northern tip of Norway.</p>
<p>Arktikugol (Arctic Coal), the Russian firm that works the Barentsburg and Pyramiden open-cast pits on the island, sends its 2,000 workers there on contracts of up to three years at a stretch.</p>
<p>Stig Kristiansen, a shopowner in Longyear, said some of those waiting to leave had come into his shop just before Thursday's accident.</p>
<p>&quot;They were smiling,&quot; he told Norwegian television. &quot;Then, half an hour later, they were crushed.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONGYEAR, Norway"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NORWAY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
