<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24598" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Death toll in Himalayan pilgrimage climbs further.</title>
<headline>Death toll in Himalayan pilgrimage climbs further.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The number of Hindu pilgrims killed in ferocious weather during an annual trek to a holy cave in the Himalayas has risen to 226, officials said on Friday.</p>
<p>Police and paramilitary troops continued searching the rugged and mountainous terrain for more pilgrims on Friday, but officials said they doubted they would find more bodies.</p>
<p>Last week, strong winds, heavy rain and snowfall lashed a 48 km (30-mile) pilgrimage route to the 3,880-metre (12,725 feet) high holy Amarnath cave, stranding almost 70,000 people in freezing temperatures for three days before help could be sent.</p>
<p>Many of the dead included naked &quot;sadhus&quot; or Hindu holy men who smear their bodies only with ash.</p>
<p>India's Home (Interior) Minister Indrajit Gupta said a further 13 pilgrims who arrived in Kashmir had died of heart attacks and other problems before beginning the trek, putting total deaths from the annual event at 239.</p>
<p>&quot;The number of deaths has today gone to 239,&quot; Gupta told lawmakers.</p>
<p>Officials said 205 pilgrims died of exposure when temperatures dropped to freezing. Other casualties included 17 pony drivers and guides and four security personnel, Gupta said.</p>
<p>More than 112,000 people had arrived in Kashmir this year to participate in the annual pilgrimage to the cave, where a naturally occurring ice stalagmite is venerated as a symbol of the Hindu God Shiva.</p>
<p>Gupta said an inquiry into events surrounding the deaths, which the federal government announced early this week, would be headed by a senior administrative or judicial official.</p>
<p>The inquiry would also suggest measures and remedies to prevent future recurrences, Gupta said.</p>
<p>The pilgrims were stranded on the mountainside for three days before the weather cleared sufficiently to allow military helicopters to rescue some of them and air drop food, medicine and blankets.</p>
<p>Thousands of others were guided down by soldiers. Many struggled down alone to the base camp, Pahalgam, 100 km (60 miles) away from Srinagar, the summer capital of India's northern state of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
<p>They were forced to spend three more days there following their ordeal because roads in and out of the town were blocked by floods. Buses full of pilgrims began driving out on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Gupta told parliament that the last stranded group, of 8,000 pilgrims, drove out of Pahalgam on Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
