<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26578" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NORWAY: Norway, Russia settle row over Spitzbergen crash.</title>
<headline>Norway, Russia settle row over Spitzbergen crash.</headline>
<byline>Rolf Soderlind</byline>
<dateline>LONGYEAR, Norway 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Norway and Russia settled a dispute over jurisdiction on Sunday and agreed to cooperate in recovering the 141 victims of a Russian plane crash on the Norwegian Arctic island of Spitzbergen.</p>
<p>Officials from both sides said they agreed the operation would continue under the leadership of Norway, which governs the coal-rich island, after two Russian rescue workers were handcuffed and detained by Norwegian police on Saturday.</p>
<p>The incident delayed Russian assistance in the difficult salvage operation in tough terrain and unpredictable weather by about 24 hours and illustrated the distrust between NATO member Norway and the former Communist superpower that is rooted in the Cold War.</p>
<p>Russia and Norway share the island's coal resources under a treaty dating back to the 1920s.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russian rescue workers will be put to work again on the crash side,&quot; Spitzbergen governor Ann-Kristin Olsen told a news conference. &quot;It is accepted that Norway leads the operation.&quot;</p>
<p>Olsen on Saturday ordered the two Russian mountaineers to be detained after they were found off limits on the mountain into which the TU-154 slammed last Thursday. They were released after explaining they had not meant to violate Norwegian authority.</p>
<p>Ironically, the Russians found the voice recorder of the doomed plane before being hauled off the plateau. Norwegian rescue workers last Friday recovered the flight recorder. The boxes, which could help explain the accident, will now be flown to Moscow for examination.</p>
<p>Russian Deputy Crisis Minister Aleksander Moskalets said the 11-member Russian team of mountaineers, who were ordered by Norwegian authorities to leave their base camp at the crash site the day before, would return in the afternoon to resume work.</p>
<p>He said he accepted Norway's explanation that the men would not have been detained had the Norwegian police realised immediately that they were rescue workers.</p>
<p>&quot;The episode is over and forgotten. I will refrain from taking diplomatic steps,&quot; Moskalet said. &quot;Common sense shall prevail in this investigation. Russia will respect Norwegian law, customs and tradition. Our only wish is to get started as soon as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>Norwegian police investigator Arne Bjoerkaas said the Russian mountaineers would be assigned to &quot;climb up and bring down the dead who are hanging near the top of the slope. We can see those bodies from the valley.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Norwegian workers were continuing to collect human remains further down the slope in a grisly operation that could take weeks. Twenty bodies have been flown in green bags to the northern Norwegian city of Tromsoe, 500 miles (800 km) to the south, for formal identification.</p>
<p>&quot;We have decided to use DNA technology to identify the dead because they are so badly crushed, you can forget about recognising anyone at all,&quot; Bjoerkaas said. &quot;Dental methods are traditionally used in this kind of work but the bodies have enormous damage to the jaws. The number of bags does not necessarily equal the number of bodies.&quot;</p>
<p>The dead were Russian and Ukrainian miners, some with their families, who were on their way to work in the coal mines on the island. Fewer than 3,000 people live on Spitzbergen, which has one of the world's harshest climates.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONGYEAR, Norway"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NORWAY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
