<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49230" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Hortense grows stronger, death toll climbs to 22.</title>
<headline>Hortense grows stronger, death toll climbs to 22.</headline>
<byline>Manuel Jimenez</byline>
<dateline>SANTO DOMINGO, Dominican Republic 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A stronger, more powerful Hurricane Hortense headed toward the open Atlantic early on Thursday after dousing Puerto Rico and the Dominican Republic with deadly floodwaters that killed at least 22.</p>
<p>During the night, Hortense's maximum sustained winds strengthened to 115 mph (185 kmh), becoming a dangerous Category Three hurricane, the third one this month after Hurricanes Edouard and Fran.</p>
<p>Forecasters said the storm was not expected to strike the U.S. mainland or the central Bahamas, thanks to a cold weather front pushing Hortense north. But some of the tiny southern islands in the archipelago were pelted with rain and gusty winds as Hortense skirted near.</p>
<p>At 11 p.m. EDT (0300 GMT), Hortense's centre was at latitude 22.9 north and longitude 71.3 west, about 75 miles (120 km) northeast of the Caicos, moving northwest at 12 mph (19 kph), the National Hurricane Centre said. The storm was becoming more defined, having developed an eye as it gained strength, but appeared to be headed into the open Atlantic, forecasters said.</p>
<p>At least eight deaths were reported on Wednesday night in the Dominican Republic's eastern province of Altagracia after swollen rivers burst out of their banks, sending floodwaters down mountains and valleys. Amable Aristy Castro, president of the Dominican senate, said some of the deaths occurred in Higuey, where he lived.</p>
<p>&quot;Entire families have disappeared&quot; in the village of Palmarito, he said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>Local officials declared the area an emergency zone after Higuey was hit by winds of 75 mph (120 kph) and up to 20 inches (50 cm) of rain on Wednesday. The Duey River, on the eastern side of Higuey, destroyed houses and fields, said Catholic Bishop Ramon de la Rosa y Carpio.</p>
<p>Tourist resorts in Bavaro and Punta Cana were cut off by flooding from the river, reported local Radio Popular. The resorts are popular among European and Canadian tourists.</p>
<p>The flooding deaths pushed the Spanish-speaking nation's total storm death toll to 10, including two fishermen who were lost at sea as Hortense approached on Tuesday and presumed dead.</p>
<p>Hortense battered the low-lying Turks and Caicos Islands throughout the night as the storm moved toward the Bahamas.</p>
<p>Early information about damage in the Turks and Caicos, a British colony of about 13,000 residents, was sketchy because of poor communications. A wind gust of 101 mph (163 kmh) was reported in the Turks before telephone lines blew down.</p>
<p>&quot;Just now, it appears that the eye is passing just to the north of Grand Turk ... We're at a very active part of the thing right now,&quot; said an employee at Blue Water Diving Ltd. on Grand Turk Island as Hortense's winds and pouring rains lashed his shop and just before telephone service was cut off. The island had been without electric power for hours.</p>
<p>In Puerto Rico, the death toll rose to 12, mostly due to raging floodwaters and mudslides. At least two people remained missing on Wednesday evening, police said.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Wednesday declared Puerto Rico, a territory of the United States, a disaster area. Homeowners and business owners in Guyama, Loiza, Ponce and Toa Baja will be eligible for low-interest loans and assistance.</p>
<p>&quot;Hortense has strengthened quite a bit, but we don't think it will get that much stronger,&quot; said John Kaplan of the National Hurricane Centre in Miami. &quot;It's too early to let down our guard yet but it looks like Florida, Georgia and the southeastern coast is in pretty good shape.&quot;</p>
<p>By Saturday evening, Hortense was expected to be off the coast of Massachusetts, forecasters said, but it remained unclear whether the storm would actually strike the coast there.</p>
<p>Among the deaths in Puerto Rico were two women swept away by the swollen Guayami River. Their bodies were found in the southeastern town of Guayama some 10 miles away, police said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PURI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTO DOMINGO, Dominican Republic"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DOMINICAN REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
