<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67280" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian TV shows film of secret Dutroux cell.</title>
<headline>Belgian TV shows film of secret Dutroux cell.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian television showed pictures for the first time on Friday of the secret cell in a house owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux where two girls starved to death and from which two others were rescued.</p>
<p>A heavy, soundproofed steel and concrete door set in the wall in the basement and disguised as shelves hid the tiny one metre by three metre (three feet by nine feet) dungeon of death in the Marcinelle suburb of the city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>The door was hung on a complicated system of overhead steel sliding rails and counterbalances. It took two people to pull it open.</p>
<p>Inside was a rusty steelmesh door to the cage which had a bare concrete floor and ceiling and blank yellow painted walls.</p>
<p>Police found a video game, contraceptives, traces of food, a mattress and shelves.</p>
<p>Eight-year-old Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, kidnapped by Dutroux' gang in June 1995, were held there for several months. They died of starvation earlier this year.</p>
<p>Their bodies were found on August 17 in the garden of another house owned by Dutroux at Sars-La-Buisierre, southwest of Charleroi.</p>
<p>Sabine Dardenne, 12, was held in the Marcinelle dungeon for two and a half months. Laetitia Delhez, 14, was imprisoned there for six days.</p>
<p>Both girls were rescued on August 15 when Dutroux showed police the hidden cell. They had both been sexually and mentally abused.</p>
<p>Two other teenage girls, Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal, kidnapped by Dutroux in August 1995, were found dead on September 3 this year at another Charleroi house that was home to Dutroux accomplice Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>Dutroux admits killing Weinstein, whom he accuses of murdering Eefje and An.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
