<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13518" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China futures markets shrink on crackdown.</title>
<headline>China futures markets shrink on crackdown.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's futures markets are shrinking under an official crackdown on the industry, and Beijing remains uncertain what sort of futures industry it wants, analysts said on Monday.</p>
<p>The lack of a futures law despite years of discussion mean that Beijing is forced to use administrative measures to control markets in which irregularities remain rampant, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Many contracts which very much need to be hedged, including those of coal, steel, sugar and petroleum, have been banned,&quot; said one official with a major commodity futures exchange. &quot;This has almost killed off some markets.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There is no sign the long-awaited futures law will be promulgated in the short term, possibly due to different views among the leadership over futures markets,&quot; said a futures analyst. &quot;The poor state of supervision makes China's futures trading more speculation than hedging.&quot;</p>
<p>Official statistics show total futures turnover nationwide fell to 2,690.7 billion yuan ($324.2 billion) in the first half of 1996, about half of that in the same period last year.</p>
<p>In Shanghai, home of some of China's largest futures exchanges, turnover dropped to 606 billion yuan, also about 50 percent of last year's level, the Business News said on Monday.</p>
<p>Trading volume of the most active contract in one of the Shanghai commodity exchanges is only thousands of tonnes, making it hard for the exchange to break even, traders said.</p>
<p>The drop in trading volume is a direct result of measures taken by the national regulator, the China Securities Regulatory Commission (CSRC), analysts said.</p>
<p>In March it banned securities brokerages, trust and investment firms and state-run enterprises from trading commodities futures, forcing many traders out of the industry.</p>
<p>Last year it banned treasury bill futures, the most active futures contracts in China, after a series of trading scandals on the Shanghai stock exchange.</p>
<p>All commodity futures exchanges have been ordered to cap daily price movements and total holdings.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite the crackdown, irregularities are rampant, ironically because major contracts have been banned,&quot; said the exchange official. &quot;The lower turnover on the market makes it easier for major investors to manipulate the markets.&quot;</p>
<p>In addition, analysts said, the use of state funds to speculate in futures markets is still common practice in China.</p>
<p>&quot;Many of us have little sense of responsibility,&quot; said one trader. &quot;We get something if we gain and lose nothing if we lose money, because we trade with public funds.&quot;</p>
<p>Industry analysts said the key to healthy development of futures markets depended on Beijing deciding what types of markets it wants, if any.</p>
<p>China revived the markets in the early 1990s after a ban of about four decades. At their peak in 1992 and 1993, hundreds of unauthorised futures exchanges were set up, offering everything from beer bottle tops to shoes.</p>
<p>The chaos prompted Beijing to launch a crackdown in early 1994. But it has failed to solve the fundamental issue of what kinds of futures markets it wants, analysts said.</p>
<p>($1 = 8.3 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
