<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14556" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. rejects Chinese call to scrap Taiwan arms deal.</title>
<headline>U.S. rejects Chinese call to scrap Taiwan arms deal.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States on Monday again rejected a demand by China that it scrap a planned sale of Stinger anti-aircraft missiles and other arms to Taiwan.</p>
<p>Calling the hardware &quot;purely defensive,&quot; the State Department said the sale was consistent with a 1982 U.S.-Chinese joint communique on arms sales to Taiwan and was proceeding. &quot;We certainly don't expect that this will result in a marked further deterioration in our relations,&quot; said Glyn Davies, the department's acting chief spokesman.</p>
<p>Earlier in the day in Beijing, the Chinese foreign ministry warned that the sale, notice of which was sent to Congress last week by the Pentagon, would cause &quot;new damage&quot; to slowly improving U.S.-Chinese relations.</p>
<p>It involves 1,299 lightweight Stinger missiles, 74 trainer missiles, 74 launchers, 96 Humvee military vehicles and 500 rounds of .50 calibre ammunition valued at about $420 million.</p>
<p>Separately, Davies said the United States was looking into reports that China is helping Pakistan build a factory for medium-range missiles in possible violation of international arms control pacts.</p>
<p>The Washington Post, citing U.S. intelligence officials, said over the weekend that the factory in a Rawalpindi suburb was expected to be capable of producing most major components of a missile modelled after the Chinese-designed M-11.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking into it, obviously, because it's an important matter,&quot; Davies told a regular news briefing.  &quot;But we're not at the stage where we can say anything definitive.&quot;</p>
<p>China and Pakistan each denied any such missile factory was being built. If it is, China would be violating commitments it made to the United States not to deploy M-11s in Pakistan. The United States has twice imposed limited economic sanctions on China for sharing weapons technology with Pakistan, lifting them after China vowed to stop.</p>
<p>Davies said he knew of no U.S. willingness to halt the planned sale of military hardware to Taiwan, which China considers a renegade province, in exchange for an end to Beijing's reported role in building the suspected missile factory in Pakistan.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not aware of any linkage between the two,&quot; he said. &quot;There shouldn't be.&quot;</p>
<p>The U.S. Congress now has 30 days to either reject the sale or allow it to go through. Defence officials told Reuters they expected the sale to be completed.</p>
<p>Beijing has regarded Taiwan as a renegade province since the end of China's civil war in 1949.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
