<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14655" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. official says Taiwan arms sale will go through.</title>
<headline>U.S. official says Taiwan arms sale will go through.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. defense officials on Monday rejected China's request to cancel a planned sale of Stinger anti-aircraft missiles and other arms to Taiwan and insisted the deal would go through.</p>
<p>&quot;The sale will go ahead. We don't anticipate any problems from Congress,&quot; said an official who requested anonymity.</p>
<p>The official was responding to a statement on Monday by a Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman urging the United States to cancel the sale if it wished &quot;to prevent creating new damage to Sino-U.S. relations.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pentagon last week said Taiwan wanted to buy 1,299 Stinger missiles, 74 guided missile launchers, 74 flight trainer Stingers, 96 jeep-like Humvee vehicles and 500 rounds of .50 calibre ammunition for an estimated $420 million.</p>
<p>The U.S. Congress now has 30 days to either reject the sale or allow it to go through. Defense officials told Reuters they expected the sale to be completed.</p>
<p>The United States officially recognizes only one Chinese government, based in Beijing, and has agreed to reduce weapons sales to Taiwan. But Washington has continued to sell defensive arms to Taipei's military.</p>
<p>Beijing has regarded Taiwan as a renegade province since the end of the civil war in 1949. It opposes the sale of weapons to the island by any country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
