<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15074" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: China helps Pakistan build missile plant - report.</title>
<headline>China helps Pakistan build missile plant - report.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. intelligence officials have concluded that Pakistan was secretly building a factory to make a medium-range missile using blueprints and equipment supplied by China, the Washington Post reported on Sunday.</p>
<p>U.S. government officials would not confirm the report, which quoted an intelligence report as concluding Pakistan may have developed nuclear warheads to be placed atop the M-11 missiles. Pakistan was not a declared nuclear power but U.S. experts believe it capable of producing nuclear weapons quickly.</p>
<p>The existence of such a missile plant would add a new dimension to collaboration between the two states, including the military and nuclear fields. This has troubled Washington and was a factor in a souring of Sino-U.S. relations last year.</p>
<p>A White House spokesman said he could not confirm the story but said the United States took such reports seriously.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not believe it is in the best interests of the United States or of any other country to supply Pakistan with the capacity to manufacture or deploy weapons of mass destruction,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>The Washington Post said the partially completed factory in a suburb of the northern city of Rawalpindi was expected to be capable of producing most of the major components of a missile modelled on the Chinese-designed M-11 in a year or two.</p>
<p>The same newspaper reported in June that U.S. intelligence agenices had &quot;unanimously concluded&quot; that Pakistan had already obtained complete M-11 missiles from China, but both China and Pakistan denied that report.</p>
<p>The United States has twice imposed limited economic sanctions against China for selling M-11 missile launchers and missile components to Pakistan, but withdrew them after China promised to stop such deliveries.</p>
<p>Washington recently settled another dispute with China over a sale to Pakistan of nuclear-related equipment.</p>
<p>U.S. Vice President Al Gore said the United States had an &quot;active, vigorous programme of monitoring all exchanges of technology from China or any other country that might violate&quot; international agreements or treaties.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect that they will comply with the provisions of the laws and treaties involved,&quot; Gore said in an interview on ABC's &quot;This Week with David Brinkley&quot; programme.</p>
<p>The Post quoted officials as saying the construction of the missile factory raised the possibility that broad economic sanctions eventually could be imposed on both countries.</p>
<p>However, the White House spokesman suggested sanctions were not immediately in the offing. &quot;We have not come to any conclusions that would warrant sanctions at this time with respect to Pakistan or China,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Washington Post said the existence of the Pakistani factory had been known to U.S. intelligence officials since last year when construction evidently began.</p>
<p>The White House has sought better relations with China after months of disputes over Taiwan, trade and human rights. Gore said a visit to Beijing by U.S. National Security Adviser Tony Lake last month resulted in a &quot;much more productive and open&quot; dialogue.</p>
<p>Pakistan has depended increasingly on Chinese help to meet its defence needs because of virtual rupture in military ties with the United States since 1990 due to suspicions about Pakistan's nuclear programme.</p>
<p>The sanctions were eased this year when the U.S. Congress approved delivery of some blocked equipment that was already paid for.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
