<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16992" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Britain urges India, Pakistan to sign CTBT.</title>
<headline>Britain urges India, Pakistan to sign CTBT.</headline>
<byline>Alistair Lyon</byline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Visiting British Foreign Secretary Malcolm Rifkind urged threshold nuclear powers India and Pakistan on Tuesday to sign the global test ban treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been huge progress on the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT). We are very close to agreement. We, like other countries, regret India's decision not to sign. We hope that India will reconsider that,&quot; he told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Rifkind, on the first leg of a five-nation Asian tour, held talks in Islamabad with President Farooq Leghari, Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto and Foreign Minister Assef Ahmad Ali.</p>
<p>India blocked adoption of the draft test ban treaty at negotiations in Geneva this month, saying the five declared nuclear powers -- the United States, Russia, China, France and Britain -- should agree to a timetable for nuclear disarmament.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope that both Pakistan and India will endorse the draft treaty,&quot; the British minister said.</p>
<p>Rifkind, due to fly to New Delhi on Wednesday, said the treaty would now go to the United Nations and appealed to India to join &quot;a very great international consensus&quot; on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;Other countries, not only nuclear powers, but other potential nuclear countries, all expressed their willingness to cease nuclear testing and we hope that India, after proper reflection, will agree that it's highly desirable for the international community to take a major step forward,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Pakistan said on Tuesday it backed the aims of the treaty, but would not sign unless India does so. &quot;Pakistan supports the objectives of the CTBT, but it has taken a principled position not to sign it unilaterally,&quot; a foreign ministry statement said.</p>
<p>India and Pakistan deny possessing nuclear arms, but Western officials believe they could quickly assemble them.</p>
<p>Rifkind called on the two regional rivals, at bitter odds over disputed Kashmir, to resolve their differences.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that the best interest of the region, of South Asia as a whole, lies in political dialogue and reconciliation between Pakistan and India,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Together the region has a huge potential for economic and social progress, but that will only happen if there is progress on some of the outstanding issues.&quot;</p>
<p>He said next month's planned elections in Indian-held Kashmir would be welcome if they were free and genuine.</p>
<p>&quot;Elections would normally be seen as a desirable and attractive step forward,&quot; he said. &quot;But if they are to be respected and welcomed, they have to be genuine, free elections. Otherwise they will not command public support.&quot;</p>
<p>India plans to hold state assembly elections next month in the disputed territory of Jammu and Kashmir, the first such polls there since a Moslem separatist revolt erupted in 1990.</p>
<p>Islamabad has bitterly criticised the plan, saying such polls cannot substitute for a U.N.-mandated plebiscite to allow Kashmiris to choose whether to join India or Pakistan.</p>
<p>India controls two-thirds of Kashmir and Pakistan the rest.</p>
<p>Rifkind said Britain had no word on the fate of four Westerners abducted in Indian-ruled Kashmir in July 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;There have been various claims and various counter-claims and sometimes reports of sightings,&quot; he told a news conference. &quot;I regret to say that at this moment in time we have no hard evidence as to the welfare of the hostages.</p>
<p>&quot;We will continue doing all within our power to continue searching for them until either they are released or their fate is established beyond doubt,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Two Britons, Keith Mangam and Paul Wells, are among four Western tourists still missing more than year after they were kidnapped in the mountainous Himalayan region.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
