<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17004" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan aggrieved at latest U.S. missile report.</title>
<headline>Pakistan aggrieved at latest U.S. missile report.</headline>
<byline>Alistair Lyon</byline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan, stung by a new U.S. report that China is helping it build a missile plant, feels Washington should be even-handed in its bid to halt missile and nuclear proliferation in South Asia, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The latest row is another bump in the road towards a better U.S.-Pakistani relationship, a key objective for Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto's 34-month-old government.</p>
<p>The Washington Post said on Sunday that U.S. intelligence officials believed Pakistan was secretly building a medium-range missile plant in Rawalpindi, near Islamabad, with Chinese help.</p>
<p>China and Pakistan have both denied the report, the latest of many allegations over the years that Beijing has aided alleged clandestine Pakistani nuclear and missile programmes.</p>
<p>Islamabad insists it has no nuclear bombs and says it has received only short-range missiles from China that do not break limits set by an international agreement known as the Missile Technology Control Regime (MTCR).</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Assef Ahmad Ali, describing the Post story as a &quot;figment of its unlimited imagination&quot;, said Pakistan would do whatever it felt necessary for its self-defence.</p>
<p>&quot;Let me clearly put it on record that Pakistan reserves the right to develop anything for its defence with its own resources,&quot; he told reporters on Monday.</p>
<p>U.S. officials believe both Pakistan and India could assemble nuclear arms quickly if they have not already done so.</p>
<p>Pakistan reluctantly endorsed a draft global nuclear test ban treaty at talks in Geneva earlier this month, but said it would only sign if India did so, too. India drew criticism by blocking the adoption of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty.</p>
<p>Many Pakistanis feel that the United States, obsessed by the old spectre of an &quot;Islamic bomb&quot;, is too ready to punish their country and turn a blind eye to India's military expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;At the centre of the whole controversy lie the lopsided MTCR provisions which only penalise technology transfers but condone indigenous production of the deadly weapon by any state,&quot; wrote the English-language daily The Frontier Post.</p>
<p>Conversely, Indian opinion is convinced that U.S. policy is biased towards Washington's once-close Cold War ally Pakistan.</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times published from New Delhi said on Tuesday the United States was pressing India not to deploy its short-range Prithvi missile.</p>
<p>&quot;It, however, seems comfortable with the conclusion that Pakistan acquired nuclear capability because India forced it to, and will now argue that Islamabad will produce M-11 missiles at the Rawalpindi factory to meet the Indian threat from Prithvi.</p>
<p>&quot;It is futile to expect a fair and impartial attitude from the Clinton Administration. Worse, the tilt in favour of Pakistan seems to absolve even China of responsibility of supplying nuclear and missile technology to Pakistan.&quot;</p>
<p>Washington views South Asia as a potential nuclear flashpoint, blaming India and Pakistan for failing to fully implement bilateral agreements aimed at reducing tension.</p>
<p>&quot;While the likelihood of a fourth war between India and Pakistan is small, the possibility of a war in the region going nuclear (is) perhaps higher than anywhere else in the world,&quot; the U.S. Arms Control and Disarmament Agency said this month.</p>
<p>The agency said China and Pakistan had accepted the idea of a regional security dialogue, but India had rejected it.</p>
<p>&quot;Regional instability, and therefore proliferation, continue to be driven by Indo-Pakistan tensions, particularly over Kashmir, and by underlying issues of status-seeking and the Indian desire to be viewed as a major world power,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Former Pakistani foreign minister Abdul Sattar said it was no secret that Pakistan was developing short-range Hataf missiles. But he said Beijing had in the past modified missiles sent to Pakistan to ensure they were within MTCR limits.</p>
<p>&quot;I would be extremely hesitant to believe that China was now breaching its MTCR commitments,&quot; Sattar told Reuters.</p>
<p>The U.S. administration has not confirmed the Washington Post story but says it takes such reports seriously.</p>
<p>The United States has twice imposed limited economic sanctions against China for selling M-11 missile launchers and finished missile components to Pakistan, but withdrew the curbs after Beijing promised to stop such deliveries.</p>
<p>Washington halted aid to Pakistan in 1990 over suspicion of its nuclear programme. It eased sanctions this year, deciding to deliver $368 million worth of blocked military equipment, but not 28 F-16 fighter planes Islamabad had also paid for. The first batch of released equipment reached Karachi on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
