<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="23121" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - August 29.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - August 29.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>Chinese Premier Li Peng urged local officials and residents in central China's flood-stricken Hebei province to step up reconstruction work in the area.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY OVERSEAS EDITION</p>
<p>The Asian Development Bank held a six-country conference on economic cooperation in southwestern China's Kunming city.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>Chinese President Jiang Zemin thanked visiting Nepali King Birendra Bir Bikram Shah Dev for supporting Beijing on Tibet.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>China's State Planning Commission said the economy showed strong growth in the first seven months of 1996, especially in fixed asset investment, consumer spending and investments from abroad.</p>
<p>News analysis assesses the growing trend of mergers as way to rescue ailing state enterprises.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BEIJING DAILY</p>
<p>China held a Beijing-Taiwan economic cooperation seminar for a high-profile group of visiting Taiwanese businessmen as well as local businessmen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
