<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25392" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - August 30.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - August 30.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>A front-page commentary urged Japan not to act foolishly over the disputed Diaoyu islands, also known as the Senkaku Islands. China reiterated it had sovereignty and warned Japan not to instigate discord by challenging China.</p>
<p>Standing Committee of National People's Congress, or parliament, passes law on coal industry and amendments to minerals law.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>President Jiang Zemin said China would not let political differences affect business with Taiwan during a meeting with prominent Taiwanese business leaders and economists.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>China has scrapped a ban by local governments on the use of small passenger cars to fight regional protectionism.</p>
<p>Li Ruihuan, chairman of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference, an advisory group to the government, will visit five European nations.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>China promulgated a new set of stock market regulations, removing from local governments the power to manage and supervise markets and giving the power to the China Securities Regulatory Commission.</p>
<p>Financial analysts call for urgent development of China's foreign currency interbank market.</p>
<p>China to clamp down on irregularities in the accounting sector.</p>
<p>China National Metals and Minerals Import and Export Corp issues $100 million worth of commercial bills in the United States.</p>
<p>A farm in China's southern province of Hainan becomes largest shareholder of Xindazhou motorcycle.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
