<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="28141" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 2.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 2.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>A front-page commentary said the popularisation of science and technology was crucial for raising the quality of China's workforce.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>The first passenger train on the much publicised Beijing-Shenzhen line left China's capital on Sunday. The rail link is designed to boost economic ties with Hong Kong, which lies across the border from Shenzhen.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>The director of the State Administration of Foreign Exchange control said China's income under the capital account has been the major contributor to China's rapidly growing foreign exchange reserves.</p>
<p>Vice Minister of the State Economic and Trade Commission Chen Qingtai said now is the time to push reforms of state enterprises but they cannot be given to the private sector.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>Governor of China's central bank Dai Xianglong said China's retail price inflation could be controlled at around seven percent this year.</p>
<p>Dai said the recent interest rate cut did not signal a relaxation of China's tight monetary policy.</p>
<p>He attacked some listed firms and monopoly industries for making usurious loans amid China's tight monetary policy.</p>
<p>China would set up a unified network for different bank cards.</p>
<p>State Statistical Bureau predicts China's grain output at 475 million tonnes in 1996, cotton output at 3.5 million tonnes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
