<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29535" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 3.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 3.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>China expressed grave concerns over South Africa's recognition of China and rival Taiwan, saying it would be impossible for a normal relationship if it insisted on &quot;dual recognition&quot;.</p>
<p>China's President Jiang Zemin thanked visiting President Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo of Equatorial Guinea for supporting the &quot;One China&quot; policy.</p>
<p>Jiang also said China wanted to step up cooperation with African nations.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>More than 2,600 delegates from 130 countries came to Beijing to attend the 13th International Congress on Archives, which China's Premier Li Peng called an important safeguard of the state's historical records.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>The China Securities Regulatory Commission fined China Securities, one of the country's top securities brokerages, two million yuan and suspended it from underwriting business for two months for irregularities.</p>
<p>It also fined Shengli Oil Field Daming Group Co, an A share company listed on the Shenzhen stock exchange, one million yuan for a share consolidation that violated its regulations.</p>
<p>An editorial lashed out on irregularities in share issue and listing.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>China tightens control of state-assets in the government's administrative units.</p>
<p>China and Britain signed a double taxation protocol.</p>
<p>Editorial warned of possible illegal fund-raising after the central bank's recent interest rate cuts.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>Experts said the government should sell more houses to private individuals to push housing reforms.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
