<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33391" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 4.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 4.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>China expressed grave concern and deep regret over cruise missile attacks on Iraqi targets by the United States and urged both countries to practise restraint to prevent the situation in the Gulf from worsening.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>China officials expressed hopes for increased consultation and cooperation with Britain over handover of Hong Kong in July 1997 during a visit by Jeremy Hanley, Britain's minister of state for foreign and commonwealth affairs.</p>
<p>China's Premier Li Peng told visiting former Japanese Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita that Japan should remain clear-minded about history of Sino-Japanese relations, which must be based on correct judgement on history of Japanese aggression.</p>
<p>Central government vowed to boost funding to fight against the spread of HIV virus.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>China announced establishment of rural cooperative banks in selected areas on a trial basis.</p>
<p>Financial experts said China's firms would pay 30 billion yuan ($3.6 billion) less in interests in the rest of 1996 after the central bank cut its rates for the second time this year in August.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>The central bank said it would push forward unified accounting practices that were compatible with international standards.</p>
<p>China planned to issue regulations to protect the patent rights of famous brands.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>China was expected to issue guidelines to improve the quality of its engineering, service and manufacturing industries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
