<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38684" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 6.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 6.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>China would strengthen legislation to protect the interests and rights of its ethnic minorities.</p>
<p>China reaped bumper early rice harvest.</p>
<p>A commentary said the U.S. missile attack on Iraq was designed to boost Clinton's popularity before the November presidential election.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>China's President Jiang Zemin told visiting ex-U.S. President George Bush that Taiwan was the major issue affecting the development of Sino-US relations.</p>
<p>China reiterated its displeasure over the repeated U.S. missile attacks on Iraq, saying Iraq's sovereignty and territorial integrity must be respected and called for the immediate halt of militariy action.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>Shenzhen's stock exchange aimed to become one of the top international bourses in the next 15-20 years.</p>
<p>The stock exchange was expected to generate 72.37 million yuan in profits in 1996, up two percent from 1995.</p>
<p>China's listed companies had raised 52.3 billion yuan through share offers by the end of July.</p>
<p>An official said the overhaul of state firms had given rise to 9,000 limited share-holding companies.</p>
<p>China would regulate its property rights market to eradicate irregularities.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>The 17-billion yuan Guangdong Maoming ethylene project, with an annual production capacity of 300,000 tonnes, began trial production.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC INFORMATION DAILY</p>
<p>China's Shaanxi province would start piping natural gas to Beijing on September 30, 1997.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
