<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="42245" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>China's new mineral resources law is to take effect on January 1, 1997.</p>
<p>Qiao Shi, Chairman of National People's Congress, or parliament, praised Fiji for its &quot;one China&quot; stance and said he hoped China could increase cooperation with South Pacific nations.</p>
<p>A commentary praised Mao Zedong, who died 20 years ago today, and current paramount leader Deng Xiaoping for their service to the people.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>The Ministry of Foreign Trade and Economic Cooperation has protested against a U.S. reduction of import quotas for Chinese textiles.</p>
<p>China said the U.S. missile attacks on Iraq were another example of U.S. hegemonism and had infringed on Iraq's sovereignty and territorial integrity.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>Experts have urged adjustment in blue-chip shares in the Shanghai stock exchange's new index.</p>
<p>China analysts are urging commercial property developers to lower prices to make housing affordable to wage-earners.</p>
<p>The State Commission for Economic Restructuring says there will be a further overhaul of state firms.</p>
<p>Sluggish sales were a major factor contributing to the poor performance of listed firms in the first half.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>Northwestern Xinjiang region's oil production capacity is to hit 17 million tonnes in 1996, up from 15 million tonnes in 1995.</p>
<p>Steel production capacity of Baoshan Iron and Steel Corp to reach 11 million tonnes a year after completion of third phase of expansion project in December.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC INFORMATION DAILY</p>
<p>China should take greater steps to combat fires in top coal mines that burn out 200,000 to 300,000 tonnes of coal a year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
