<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44187" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Treaty banning atomic blasts to move through U.N.</title>
<headline>Treaty banning atomic blasts to move through U.N.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>After 40 years of debate, the U.N. General Assembly on Tuesday was expected to approve and open for signature a draft treaty that would ban nuclear explosions from the world forever.</p>
<p>While the outcome of the vote was assured, the assembly's action was not sufficient to implement the treaty because India has vowed to block its ratification.</p>
<p>But 126 nations led by Australia co-sponsored a resolution approving the treaty and asking that it be open for signature as soon as possible in the hopes India will eventually change its mind. India was nearly isolated in objecting to it.</p>
<p>Supporters argue that without the treaty nuclear proliferation will continue unabated and no country will have an incentive to move towards disarmament. Australian delegate Richard Butler said a prohibition on testing by all states &quot;would mightily affect whatever plans they might have to develop the quantity and quality of nuclear weapons. And that's part of what is being sought here.&quot;</p>
<p>All five declared nuclear powers -- the United States, Russia, France, Britain and China -- support the document, known as the Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban Treaty (CTBT). But the treaty does not come into force until 44 states with a nuclear potential sign it. This includes India, which exploded a device in 1974 and is considered a non-declared nuclear state along with Pakistan and Israel.</p>
<p>Pakistan said it would vote for the resolution endorsing the treaty but would not sign it unless India, its chief rival, did so. Israel was among the resolution's sponsors.</p>
<p>So far, India has not budged, insisting it will not sign a treaty unless it is part of a plan for global nuclear disarmament. It also maintains that the treaty would prevent it from responding to threats from neighbouring China and from Pakistan, which may have a covert nuclear and missile programme.</p>
<p>&quot;The nuclear weapons states have no intention of giving up their dependence on nuclear weapons, nor do they have any intention of letting the CTBT become an impediment in their pursuit of the qualitative improvement of nuclear weapons, &quot; India's Ambassador Prakash Shah told the assembly on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Countries around us continue their weapons programmes either openly or in a clandestine manner,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Usually a treaty is adopted first by the conference that drafted it and submitted to the U.N. General Assembly for approval. It is then open for signature, with ratification from a specified number of states required to become international law.</p>
<p>In this case, the resolution before the assembly is an attempt to rescue the treaty from oblivion after India last month vetoed the text at the 61-nation Conference on Disarmament in Geneva. Conference rules required unanimity whereas the General Assembly can approve resolutions by a majority vote.</p>
<p>The treaty bans any kind of nuclear weapons explosions, whether in the atmosphere or underground. It also set up a monitoring system to verify compliance or spot violations.</p>
<p>It would enter into force 180 days after it was signed and ratified by 44 countries that have nuclear reactors of some kind. If at the end of three years the treaty does not get the required signatures, a conference will be held to evaluate and possibly change the requirements.</p>
<p>Since the United States exploded the world's first atomic bomb on July 16, 1945 in the New Mexico desert there have been 2,045 known nuclear tests, 1,030 of them American and 715 in the former Soviet Union.</p>
<p>Many nations during the assembly debate agreed with India's criticism and said the treaty was too late to prevent proliferation through computer testing and other means. But almost all said it should be supported.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
