<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45050" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 10.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 10.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>The China Securities Regulatory Commission has started to handle the listing of 32 companies which were delayed for so-called historical reasons.</p>
<p>A securities watchdog in China's Sichuan province is investigating a company for the unauthorised issue of 14.8 million A shares.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>The China Securities Regulatory Commission has asked stock and futures exchanges to strengthen checks and supervision to curb irregularities.</p>
<p>The China Construction Bank has signed a long-term cooperation agreement with an electricity transmitting company to handle power generated by the Three Gorges dam.</p>
<p>An editorial says comprehensive opening-up to foreign insurance companies would destroy domestic insurers.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>The China Daya Bay nuclear plant has been granted certification by the State Nuclear Security Bureau.</p>
<p>A Chinese company is to set up a VSAT network using satellite communications.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY - People's Bank of China Deputy Governor Chen Yuan welcomes the Bank of International Settlements decision to admit China along with central banks and monetary authorities of eight other countries and territories. He said this will significantly improve the bank's cooperation with the BIS and other member banks.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY - Chinese President Jiang Zemin meets President Alpha Oumar Konare of Mali.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
