<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45221" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: United Nations could end era of nuclear testing.</title>
<headline>United Nations could end era of nuclear testing.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia, trying to override an Indian veto and backed by 126 states, asked the U.N. General Assembly on Monday to approve and open for signing a treaty banning all nuclear test explosions.</p>
<p>&quot;We ask for deep reflection upon the milestone in history this action will lay down -- agreement that there shall never again be nuclear explosions,&quot; Richard Butler, Australia's U.N. ambassador, said in introducing his resolution on the treaty.</p>
<p>Passage is expected on Tuesday. The treaty would then be open for signature when world leaders come to the United Nations later this month. The document is supported by all declared nuclear powers -- the United States, Russia, China, France and Britain.</p>
<p>After three years of negotiations, the 61-nation, Geneva-based Conference on Disarmament was unable last month to approve the treaty, because India refused to give its consent. Under that conference's rules, decisions must be by consensus. The General Assembly can vote by a two-thirds majority or a simple majority.</p>
<p>To circumvent the conference, Australia asked the assembly to approve the treaty in a legal manoeuvre never tried before.</p>
<p>The treaty, known as the Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban Treaty (CTBT), would not come into force until 44 states with a nuclear potential signed and ratified it. These states include India, which exploded a device in 1974.</p>
<p>But most diplomats believe that once a country signs and ratifies the accord, it must abide by it.</p>
<p>India has said since the mid-1960s that it would not give up its nuclear option until the nuclear powers adopted a timetable for eliminating their existing arsenals.</p>
<p>During Monday's debate, most nations agreed with India that the treaty alone would not wipe out the danger of atomic bombs. But unlike India, they felt the treaty would limit the arms race by making it more difficult for countries to develop or improve their arsenals.</p>
<p>Indian Ambassador Prakash Shah said, &quot;The nuclear weapons states have no intention of giving up their dependence on nuclear weapons, nor do they have any intention of letting the CTBT become an impediment in their pursuit of the qualitative improvement of nuclear weapons.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that in this day and age, the treaty should have banned not only underground and atmospheric explosions but all kinds of nuclear computer tests that could upgrade weapons.</p>
<p>Consequently, he said, India would maintain the nuclear option. In an apparent reference to China and Pakistan, he said that &quot;countries around us continue their weapons programmes either openly or in a clandestine manner.&quot;</p>
<p>But Pakistan's Ambassador Munir Akram said that &quot;any step of nuclear escalation in our region will find a matching response.&quot; He said Pakistan would vote for the resolution but would not sign the treaty because of India's position.</p>
<p>Since the United States exploded the world's first atomic bomb on July 16, 1945, in the New Mexico desert, there have been 2,045 known nuclear tests, 1,030 of them American and 715 in the former Soviet Union.</p>
<p>China's delegate, Sha Zukang, told the assembly that the test ban should not be an ultimate objective, calling it &quot;one step forward to the complete prohibition and thorough destruction of nuclear weapons.&quot;</p>
<p>The future of the treaty also depends on a quick signature from President Bill Clinton, who is expected to visit the United Nations later this month, and Senate ratification. The platform adopted by the Republican Party last month at its convention says the United States needs &quot;development of nuclear weapons and their periodic testing&quot; for its security.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
