<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47899" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan silent on reported new anti-China missile.</title>
<headline>Taiwan silent on reported new anti-China missile.</headline>
<byline>Joyce Liu</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan officials on Wednesday would not confirm or deny a newspaper report that the island soon would test fire a new surface-to-surface missile with sufficient range to strike targets in China.</p>
<p>The China Times said designers had nearly completed development of the missile, whose range of 300 km (186 miles) would enable it to hit many coastal military installations in China, Taiwan's rival since a civil war split them in 1949.</p>
<p>&quot;The surface-to-surface missiles...are scheduled to be test fired this year,&quot; the mass-circulation daily quoted unidentified military officials as saying.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Chiang Chung-ling declined to comment.</p>
<p>&quot;I have nothing to tell you,&quot; Chiang told reporters.</p>
<p>When asked if the missile would help Taiwan's defence significantly. he also declined comment.</p>
<p>Other officials would not confirm or deny the report.</p>
<p>China mounted war games and missile tests in waters near Taiwan in a long intimidation campaign that peaked during the island's historic popular presidential election in March, highlighting Taiwan's growing vulnerability.</p>
<p>Some analysts say China's manoeuvres backfired, angering the United States and other Western powers and strengthening Taiwan's assertion that it needs advanced Western defences.</p>
<p>The newspaper, quoting unnamed officials, said Taiwan now hoped to buy from Washington a long-distance weapons system from which to fire the missile and would make the request in 1997.</p>
<p>If the U.S. purchase and missile deployment proceeded smoothly, Taiwan would be able to strike China's coastal airports and military bases when necessary, it said.</p>
<p>The state-run Chungshan Institute of Science and Technology, Taiwan's main weapons research centre, has said it was capable of developing such surface-to-surface missiles, but declined to say whether any project was under way.</p>
<p>Since the 1980s, the institute has developed first and second generation versions of anti-ship Hsiung Feng missiles, anti-aircraft Sky Bow and Sky Sword missiles.</p>
<p>The new missile is based on Sky Bow II, the report said.</p>
<p>Taiwan began developing advanced weapons after the United States and other supporters switched diplomatic ties to Beijing, which has increased pressure on its diplomatic partners to stop arming what it regards as a renegade province.</p>
<p>Beijing maintains a standing threat to recover the island by force if it opts for independence, prompting Taiwan to spend huge sums on advanced weapons and on the military in general.</p>
<p>Both governments say they want reunification, but under different terms.</p>
<p>Citing China's military buildup, Taiwan in 1992 managed to order 150 F-16 and 60 Mirage 2000 fighters from the United States and France. Deliveries started in mid-1996.</p>
<p>Taiwan's state-funded television reported on Tuesday that the island would begin mass-producing a new generation of the Sky Sword II missiles by July 1997.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640026">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
