<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49980" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan says will not sign CTBT without India.</title>
<headline>Pakistan says will not sign CTBT without India.</headline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan on Thursday welcomed the nuclear test ban treaty endorsed by the United Nations but said Islamabad would not sign it because of perceived dangers from arch-foe India, which opposes the document.</p>
<p>A foreign ministry spokesman told reporters that Pakistan joined other countries in adopting the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT) because it was in line with Islamabad's &quot;commitment to promoting the goals of nuclear disarmament and non-proliferation&quot;.</p>
<p>But Pakistan says it will not sign the treaty unless India does. The two countries have fought three wars since they gained independence from Britain in 1947, two of them over the disputed Himalayan region of Kashmir.</p>
<p>The U.N. General Assembly on Tuesday adopted and opened for signature a treaty that would ban nuclear explosions forever.</p>
<p>The vote on the resolution was 158 in favour, three against -- India, Libya, Bhutan -- and five abstentions.</p>
<p>All five declared nuclear powers -- the United States, Russia, France, Britain and China -- support the document but the treaty does not come into force until 44 states with nuclear potential sign it.</p>
<p>&quot;Pakistan cannot be oblivious to threats to its security which are intensified by India's position on the nuclear test ban treaty,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We reserve the right to respond adequately to any nuclear escalation by India,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Pakistan, in view of its security concerns, cannot accept unilateral commitments.&quot;</p>
<p>India exploded a nuclear device in 1974 but says it has not built the bomb. Experts believe both India and Pakistan could quickly assemble nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>India has called the treaty discriminatory because it would permit the nuclear powers to perfect their weapons with non-explosive techniques, and objected to a provision that would require India to ratify the accord for it to take effect.</p>
<p>New Delhi has insisted that the five delared powers agree to dismantle their arsenals over a set time.</p>
<p>&quot;Its (India's) opposition to CTBT is essentially due to its political ambitions and technological considerations rather than moralistic arguments over nuclear disarmament,&quot; the Pakistani spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is evident that India's opposition to the treaty emanates from its nuclear ambitions and its reluctance to forgo further development of its nuclear and ballistic missile programme, which poses a real threat to the security of its neighbours.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
