<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50029" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India flays nuclear test ban treaty.</title>
<headline>India flays nuclear test ban treaty.</headline>
<byline>Nelson Graves</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>India closed ranks on Thursday against a global nuclear test ban treaty as resistance increased to Western suggestions that a foreign defence umbrella would allay New Delhi's security concerns.</p>
<p>&quot;Farcical Finale&quot;, &quot;Flogging a Dead Document&quot;, &quot;Not Now, Not Later&quot; read editorial headlines in major daily newspapers denouncing the accord, which won overwhelming endorsement at the United Nations on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The editorials underscored strong domestic backing by political parties and public opinion for the government's lonesome stance over the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT).</p>
<p>India single-handedly blocked adoption of the treaty by disarmament negotiators in Geneva last month.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, it was one of three U.N. member states that voted against the accord. The others were Libya and Bhutan, which is sandwiched between nuclear power China and nuclear capable India.</p>
<p>The Indian government showed no signs of backing down. &quot;We will maintain our position and not sign the CTBT,&quot; Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral told parliament late on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show firm public support for the government's main objections to the treaty, which will be open to signature by individual nations later this month.</p>
<p>New Delhi has insisted that the five declared nuclear powers -- Britain, China, France, Russia and the United States -- agree to dismantle their arsenals over a set time.</p>
<p>India has called the treaty discriminatory because it would permit the nuclear powers to perfect their weapons with non-explosive techniques, and objected to a provision that would require India to ratify the accord for it to take effect.</p>
<p>India exploded a nuclear device in 1974 but says it has not built the bomb. Experts believe both India and neighbouring Pakistan could quickly assemble nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>&quot;It comes as no surprise at all that countries which voted to legitimise nuclear weapons should have replayed the sham through this treaty and perpetuated the international divide between the five nuclear hegemons and the rest of the international community,&quot; the Times of India said.</p>
<p>The newspaper said the accord marked the beginning of a new arms race through advanced technologies that are only within reach of the existing nuclear powers.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a sad day for the U.N. and the international community, but a proud day for India,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times said the &quot;treaty does not dissolve the nuclear weapon states' club, but only makes it more exclusive&quot;.</p>
<p>The Pioneer said a dangerous precedent had been set because the treaty was brought to the U.N. through a procedural loophole, bypassing the Conference on Disarmament in Geneva.</p>
<p>Political leaders and analysts dismissed a suggestion by U.S. President Bill Clinton and French Foreign Minister Herve de Charette that Western powers could overcome India's objections by providing a security guarantee.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe we can find a way for the Indians to have their security concerns met,&quot; Clinton said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>While New Delhi believes Pakistan has a secret nuclear weapons programme, Indian leaders say the nation's major security concern is China, a declared nuclear power.</p>
<p>&quot;A nation like India cannot depend on the security goodwill or offers of others,&quot; Jaswant Singh, the opposition Bharatiya Janata Party's (BJP) deputy leader, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Our experience with security guarantees and our historical experience do not lend great credibility to such offers,&quot; he said, citing U.S. security guarantees for Taiwan.</p>
<p>Jasjit Singh, director of the Institute for Defence Studies and Analyses, said: &quot;It's not credible to think the United States would risk a nuclear attack on Washington or Los Angeles because New Delhi was threatened.&quot;</p>
<p>But both the BJP leader and the defence analyst said the suggestion should be pursued if Washington and Paris were implying they might stake out middle ground with India on global nuclear disarmament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
