<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58913" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Bhutto urges India to stop blocking test ban pact.</title>
<headline>Bhutto urges India to stop blocking test ban pact.</headline>
<byline>Alistair Lyon</byline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistani Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto called on neighboring India on Tuesday to drop its opposition to the global nuclear test ban treaty, but said Islamabad could not sign the pact until New Delhi did the same.</p>
<p>&quot;Given our own security concerns, we are not in a position to sign unless India does, but we urge India to review its approach and to go with the rest of the world,&quot; she told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>India, a threshold nuclear power like Pakistan, has refused to endorse the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT) because the five declared nuclear powers -- the United States, Russia, China, France and Britain -- have not agreed on a timetable for nuclear disarmament.</p>
<p>The U.N. General Assembly overwhelmingly endorsed the CTBT last week. But India vowed it would never sign or ratify the agreement and would thus prevent it from coming into force.</p>
<p>Pakistan and India both deny possessing nuclear weapons, but say they have the capacity to make them.</p>
<p>Describing the CTBT as one of the most significant developments of the post-Cold War era, Bhutto said Pakistan fully supported a global approach to nuclear non-proliferation.</p>
<p>&quot;Some short-sighted elements in the sub-continent, in India and Pakistan, have opposed CTBT, saying that the West has a greater arsenal and we are lagging behind.</p>
<p>&quot;But I often say that it is not a fair world and if we don't get around to the business of putting an end to the weapons of mass destruction then the gap is going to continue to increase.&quot;</p>
<p>She said India, which exploded a nuclear device in 1974, should reject any pressure from its scientific or military community to carry out a second nuclear test, suggesting that computer simulation could provide an adequate alternative.</p>
<p>&quot;The computers are still there and the scientists will continue to play with computers if they want to,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;I would urge India not to complicate the situation in the continent and put pressure on other countries that are resisting pressures of their own by indulging in any act that can be misconstrued as an act of adventure,&quot; she declared.</p>
<p>India and Pakistan have been at odds since they won independence from Britain in 1947, fighting three wars, two of them over the disputed Himalayan territory of Kashmir.</p>
<p>Bhutto, condemning &quot;so-called elections&quot; taking place this month in Indian-ruled Kashmir, did not rule out a resumption of long-stalled peace talks between India and Pakistan.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope we would be able to assess the situation after the elections are concluded and then take a decision,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;It all depends on the aftermath of the so-called elections. Seven previous elections have not won over the Kashmiri people so an exercise for an eighth election seems rather futile,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>India says Kashmir, of which it rules two thirds and Pakistan the rest, is an integral part of its territory. Islamabad wants mainly Moslem Kashmir to be allowed to vote whether to join Islamic Pakistan or Hindu-majority India.</p>
<p>New Delhi said on Monday the second leg of state elections in Indian-ruled Kashmir was generally peaceful, but separatist groups opposing the polls accused authorities of coercion.</p>
<p>The first day of voting in other areas of the state was on September 7, and the last two days will be on September 21 and 30. The results are expected in the first week of October.</p>
<p>The state, torn by a six-year separatist revolt, is holding its first assembly elections since 1987. The last assembly was dissolved in 1990 after an outbreak of rebellion in which more than 20,000 people have died.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
