<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71564" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - Sept 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>Chinese President Jiang Zemin, on an inspection of poor regions along the new Beijing-Kowloon railway, said poverty was not just an economic problem but a political one and that the opening of the railroad would stimulate growth in those areas.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>An international seminar on the debts of China's state enterprises concluded in Haikou in Hainan province.</p>
<p>The Industrial and Commercial Bank of China can now allow customers in eight cities to make deposits and withdrawals in any of the cities.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>China has begun state purchases of cotton for the buying season starting in late September.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>China's State Environmental Protection Agency has ordered the closure of 15 kinds of heavy polluting small-scale businesses such as paper-makers, dye factories and leather tanners.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>China's Foreign Trade Minister Wu Yi is to visit the United States on September 26 and 27 to discuss bilateral trade issues with U.S. Secretary of Commerce Mickey Kantor.</p>
<p>Chinese Foreign Minster Qian Qichen is expected to sign the Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban Treaty in New York on September 24.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
