<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75327" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China defense chief blasts 'China threat' theory.</title>
<headline>China defense chief blasts 'China threat' theory.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's Defense Minister, Chi Haotian, on Wednesday dismissed the idea that Beijing posed a threat to other nations and said any attempt to contain or isolate China would fail.</p>
<p>&quot;Some Western countries view China from a wrong perspective and spread the 'China threat' fallacy in an attempt to contain or isolate China,&quot; Chi said in a meeting with Australian armed forces chief John Baker.</p>
<p>&quot;China should not be contained or isolated, and such a policy will not succeed,&quot; the official Xinhua news agency quoted Chi as telling Baker, in Beijing on an official visit.</p>
<p>Beijing is deeply suspicious that Western countries, most notably the United States, are pursuing a strategy of trying to contain China's economic and military rise.</p>
<p>Washington denies it fears China's ascension to the world stage, saying it upholds a policy of engagement towards Beijing. But some U.S. officials have said a need to contain China may arise in the future.</p>
<p>Chi said Beijing was willing to hold dialogues and forge friendly ties with other nations while reserving differences.</p>
<p>&quot;Development of friendly relations and cooperation between China and Australia...will not only benefit the two countries but will be conducive to peace in the region and the world as a whole,&quot; Chi said.</p>
<p>Beijing's ties with Canberra have taken a chilly plunge since Australian Prime Minister John Howard announced he would meet exiled Tibetan leader the Dalai Lama on Thursday.</p>
<p>While Australia has been eager to play down the visit, Beijing, which regards the Dalai Lama as a pro-independence campaigner bent on splitting China, has hinted at possible political and trade reprisals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
