<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79604" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US, China see relations much improved.</title>
<headline>US, China see relations much improved.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Worsnip</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher and Chinese Foreign Minister Qian Qichen on Wednesday hailed a significant improvement in Sino-U.S. relations after a long period of tension over trade, Taiwan and human rights.</p>
<p>Christopher, noting it was his third meeting with Qian in the last five months, said their frequent encounters &quot;seem to me to have paid off in the marked improvement in our ties in recent months.&quot;</p>
<p>Qian, appearing with Christopher at a brief news conference before the meeting on the fringes of a U.N. General Assembly session, agreed that there had been &quot;positive progress&quot; and that the atmosphere had &quot;improved significantly.&quot;</p>
<p>Only six months ago, the two nuclear powers were at loggerheads over Taiwan, Chinese sales of nuclear technology to Pakistan and piracy by Chinese companies of U.S. compact disks and computer software.</p>
<p>But Qian noted that since then, a dispute over export of ring magnets -- used in making nuclear weapons -- to Pakistan had been resolved, intellectual property rights agreements had been reached and Washington had renewed China's most-favored nation trade status.</p>
<p>U.S. Assistant Secretary of State Winston Lord cautioned after the meeting that despite the upbeat tone, some problems between the two countries were far from bring resolved.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not naive or complacent. We know there's difficult issues out there,&quot; he told reporters, mentioning specifically non-proliferation and human rights.</p>
<p>As well as long-standing U.S. concerns over Chinese sales of missiles and nuclear power technology to Iran, recent U.S. press reports have said China is thought to have supplied Pakistan with technology to make M-11 ballistic missiles.</p>
<p>&quot;They have made some progress, but there are remaining problems,&quot; Lord said. &quot;There are continuing concerns about their dealings with Iran and Pakistan, and these refer to both nuclear areas and missile areas and even some conventional areas.&quot;</p>
<p>On human rights, Lord said Christopher raised with Qian the release of people imprisoned for expressing their views, access to prisons and prisoners and the situation in Tibet, which the United States recognizes as part of China.</p>
<p>The Christopher-Qian meeting came one day before U.S. and Chinese trade officials meet in Washington to follow up a June agreement aimed at resolving a long dispute on intellectual property rights.</p>
<p>Christopher told journalists it was &quot;critically important that China implement these new agreements.&quot;</p>
<p>Qian said remaining problems included Taiwan, although tensions which reached a peak last March during presidential elections on the island -- considered a renegade province by Beijing -- have abated.</p>
<p>Lord said Qian raised U.S. arms sales to Taiwan, with which Washington has only unofficial relations.</p>
<p>Lord said Qian sounded a conciliatory note over the British colony of Hong Kong, which reverts to Chinese rule next July, in particular over the appointment of a new chief executive to succeed the present governor-general.</p>
<p>&quot;He thought that the appointment, which he didn't in any way foreshadow ... would be reassuring to the people of Hong Kong and to the outside world,&quot; Lord said.</p>
<p>Earlier, Qian dodged a question over Beijing's approach to the election of a U.N. secretary-general at the end of this year. Washington says it will not allow the current incumbent, Boutros Boutros-Ghali, to serve a second term.</p>
<p>The Chinese minister said Beijing was satisfied with Boutros-Ghali, but was waiting to hear the views of the Organization of African Unity.</p>
<p>If Boutros-Ghali, an Egyptian, cannot be re-elected, first priority in finding a successor is expected to be given to another candidate from the African continent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
