<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79669" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. ponders next step with India on test ban.</title>
<headline>U.S. ponders next step with India on test ban.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>With U.N. members now lining up to sign the landmark nuclear test ban treaty, the United States aims to keep pressure on key holdout India to reverse it's adamant refusal to join.</p>
<p>Some U.S. officials insist this is a realistic goal despite New Delhi's seemingly intractable opposition to the pact. But more pessimistic experts worry that too heavy-handed a U.S. approach could backfire in ominous ways.</p>
<p>&quot;We're only beginning to develop a longer-term plan (for India),&quot; one administration official told Reuters. &quot;But we can't let the pressure off. It has to be clear that there's a price in terms of self-isolation that they are paying.&quot;</p>
<p>Assistant Secretary of State for Political-Military Affairs Thomas McNamara, meanwhile, told defence writers:</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know how its going to change, I don't know when it's going to change and in fact I cannot even be certain whether it's going to change. But I think there will be a number of internal and international pressures that will build on India to change its position.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the terms of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which the United States and the other four nuclear powers signed on Tuesday in New York, the international community has two years to persuade India to come on board.</p>
<p>India's signature is vital. The pact -- outlawing all atomic weapons tests -- cannot take effect with its monitoring provisions without ratification by the five nuclear powers, which also include Britain, France, China and Russia, and the three nuclear threshold states -- India, Pakistan and Israel -- deemed to be capable of building nuclear weapons quickly.</p>
<p>New Delhi has declared unyielding opposition to the treaty, saying it undermines Indian sovereignty and preserves an elite nuclear &quot;haves&quot; club by not setting a date for disarmament.</p>
<p>India took the unusual step of facing down the world by blocking the Conference on Disarmament in Geneva, which negotiated the treaty, from sending it to the United Nations for signing. But supporters still took the pact to New York.</p>
<p>While India won in the obscure Geneva process, its isolation at the U.N., where only Bhutan and Libya joined New Delhi in opposing the treaty, prompted new soul-searching at home on whether the decision really served Indian interests.</p>
<p>This suggests India may be more receptive to pro-treaty arguments. Washington has told India it will not be sanctioned but officials say there are &quot;consequences.&quot;</p>
<p>India is seeking a rotating seat on the U.N. Security Council later this year but almost certainly will not get it, in part because of its position on the test-ban pact, officials said. Japan is more likely to be given the seat.</p>
<p>Also, U.S. officials say while India and the United States have recently improved ties, there could be even more economic and other cooperation if India signed the nuclear accord.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton addressed one of India's main concerns in a U.N. speech on Tuesday by reasserting his aim to negotiate with Russia deeper cuts in their nuclear arsenals.</p>
<p>There is no date set for such talks and one is unlikely until the START 2 arms reduction treaty, languishing in Moscow, is ratified by the Russian parliament.</p>
<p>George Perkovich, an arms expert and director of the non-profit W. Alton Jones Foundation in Charlottesville, Virgina, agrees a new intense debate is raging in India over the treaty but told Reuters &quot;it is extremely unlikely India is going to sign&quot; this treaty.</p>
<p>The debate pits Indians who now want to pursue a nuclear programme with vigour, including testing, versus those who say the test ban treaty loss isolated India and testing should not go forward.</p>
<p>The two sides reflect a fundamental strategic choice.</p>
<p>&quot;Does India concentrate on becoming a major international power through its economic power (which means you don't test nuclear weapons or deploy missiles because there is an economic cost to that) or does it become a major power the way other major powers did -- through military capability,&quot; Perkovich said.</p>
<p>Most Indian prime ministers have viewed economic progress as the best route. But Perkovich said provocations by China or Pakistan or excessive U.S. pressure on India could force New Delhi to launch an atomic test or deploy the Prithvi missile.</p>
<p>U.S. officials do not expect India to test but are worried about possible new missile deployments. &quot;Right now the goal is to make sure India doesn't exacerbate the situation,&quot; one official said. The next step is to defuse tensions with Pakistan and finally to &quot;go down a different path that's going to make it easier for India to sign the treaty,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
