<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81408" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China, U.S. warned of repeat of Cold War.</title>
<headline>China, U.S. warned of repeat of Cold War.</headline>
<byline>Graham Earnshaw</byline>
<dateline>NANJING, China 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>China and the United States were urged on Friday to not let an &quot;arrogance of power&quot; lead them into a new Cold War.</p>
<p>Speakers at a symposium at the Center for Chinese and American Studies at Nanjing University, northwest of Shanghai, said relations between Beijing and Washington were coloured by China's growing economic strength.</p>
<p>The speakers, including senior diplomats, academics and businessmen, were attending a symposium to mark the 10th anniversary of the centre.</p>
<p>Paul Wolfowitz, a former U.S. assistant secretary of state, said China's growing strength made some people think of the bipolar superpower confrontation that existed between the United States and the former Soviet Union and of a possible return of the Cold War.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be a terrible tragedy for both countries and the world if that happened,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Li Shenzhi, president of the Chinese Association for American Studies, said that the concept of the need to &quot;contain China&quot; was increasingly common in American thinking, and that this was not helpful to the development of Sino-US relations.</p>
<p>&quot;All elements of the relationship are negotiable except the Taiwan issue,&quot; Li said, referring to China's policy that Taiwan is a renegade province that must be reunited with the mailand. &quot;No Chinese government would dare retreat on that issue.&quot;</p>
<p>Steve Levine, professor of history at Duke University, said skilful political leadership was needed by both sides of the relationship, which has been dogged by a range of differences including Taiwan, human rights and protection of intellectual property.</p>
<p>He said the United States suffered on occasion from what he called &quot;the arrogance of power,&quot; and that China's increasing strength and confidence could be leading it down the same path.</p>
<p>&quot;There are the early warning signs of the arrogance of power (with the Chinese), for instance in their handling of Taiwan and the South China Sea issue,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>China claims a vast area of the South China Sea, despite opposing claims from other countries in the area.</p>
<p>Former U.S. ambassador to China Arthur Hummel said one of the fundamental reasons for the strains in Sino-American relations was that China's political reforms had lagged far behind economic development.</p>
<p>&quot;Evidence of strains caused by this imbalance are visible both in Chinese society and in foreign policy,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A senior Chinese official at the meeting, who asked not to be named, said later that he agreed with Hummel that the lack of political reform was a serious issue for China.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing has happened on that front at all, it is very simple. It is at a total standstill,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Asked how the Chinese system should be changed, he said: &quot;I would not dare to answer that. I do not have that much freedom, there is a problem with human rights as you know.&quot;</p>
<p>But the official said there was no point in the United States trying to force its views with regard to democracy and human rights onto China. &quot;That is counter-productive,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NANJING, China"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
