<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19488" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Smashing Pumpkins rule out taking drummer back.</title>
<headline>Smashing Pumpkins rule out taking drummer back.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Smashing Pumpkins, who went on the road this week for the first time since the U.S. band's keyboardist died of a drugs overdose, has ruled out rehiring the drummer fired in connection with the tragedy.</p>
<p>Billy Corgan, the popular rock band's vocalist and main songwriter, told Rolling Stone magazine he sometimes wished the original line-up could be back together again to continue their assault on the world's music charts.</p>
<p>&quot;But there's that sentiment in my heart where I feel I've really turned a corner on it. I still believe he's (Jimmy Chamberlin) got God's gift. But it would take a lot of tea in China to go back to that,&quot; the magazine quoted him as saying in its upcoming Sept. 3 issue.</p>
<p>Touring keyboard artist Jonathan Melvoin overdosed on a mixture of alcohol and heroin in a New York hotel room on July 12, the day the band was scheduled to begin a sold-out two-night stand at Madison Square Garden.</p>
<p>The band's drummer, Jimmy Chamberlin, who was with Melvoin at the time, was charged with possession of controlled substances. The band, despairing of his well-documented history of drug abuse, fired Chamberlin five days later.</p>
<p>The band resumed their tour in Las Vegas on Tuesday night with Matt Walker of techno-punk band Filter on drums and Dennis Flemion of underground duo the Frogs on keyboards. Both are considered temporary replacements.</p>
<p>Chamberlin, meanwhile, faces a court date on Sept. 25 and a maximum term of one year in jail if convicted.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
