<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26322" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Last Cali drug lord gives Colombia &quot;gift&quot; - himself.</title>
<headline>Last Cali drug lord gives Colombia &quot;gift&quot; - himself.</headline>
<byline>Tom Brown</byline>
<dateline>BOGOTA, Colombia 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Helmer &quot;El Pacho&quot; Herrera, the last Cali cartel drug kingpin still at large, surrendered to police in southwest Colombia on Sunday in a gesture he described as &quot;a gift&quot; to the nation.</p>
<p>A National Police spokesman said Herrera, a master of disguise and the target of a nationwide manhunt for more than a year, surrendered shortly after noon (1700 GMT) at a prearranged meeting place outside the southwestern city of Cali, where his criminal drug syndicate was based.</p>
<p>The police spokesman said Herrera, the object of a recent U.S. extradition request, had surrendered in the presence of National Police director Gen. Rosso Jose Serrano and other senior security force members.</p>
<p>Wearing a blue business suit and glasses and looking more like a successful bank executive than a dangerous fugitive, Herrera told reporters shortly after his arrest that his surrender was &quot;a gift.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I believe in Colombian justice and its institutions,&quot; he said. &quot;It was time to give the country a truce. This is a gift to the country that has suffered and been so stigmatized because of drug trafficking.&quot;</p>
<p>Six of the seven top leaders of the cartel were arrested last summer in an unprecedented crackdown on what has often been described as the world's leading drug trafficking organisation. The 45-year-old Herrera, considered highly dangerous, was the only cartel heavyweight who remained at large.</p>
<p>A reported billionaire, Herrera recently rose to the No. 3 position within the cartel after the shooting death in March of Jose Santacruz Londono, his closest partner inside the drug organisation.</p>
<p>U.S. drug experts maintain that brothers Gilberto and Miguel Rodriguez Orejuela -- the undisputed leaders of the Cali drug mob, arrested in June and August 1995 -- continue to run their criminal empire from inside Bogota's La Picota prison.</p>
<p>But the experts had also been working on the assumption that Herrera was taking care of a lot of cartel business on the outside, and his arrest could deal a serious setback to the syndicate's daily operations.</p>
<p>President Ernesto Samper, who has been accused of using a fortune in Cali cartel narcotics money to finance his 1994 election campaign, has denied that drug lords are able to continue operating from inside any Colombian jail.</p>
<p>In brief remarks to reporters in Bogota, he said the Cali cartel was now &quot;finished&quot; and the country had closed the book on one of its most notorious criminal gangs.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Herrera) was the only person from the Cali cartel's leadership who hadn't been submitted to justice,&quot; Samper said.</p>
<p>U.S. Ambassador Myles Frechette also welcomed Herrera's arrest, saying the United States was &quot;delighted that the unrelenting pressure of the Colombian police&quot; had finally made it happen.</p>
<p>That pressure included nearly 400 raids on apartments, farms, houses and business linked to Herrera during a manhunt that began 16 months ago, a police statement said late on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;Pacho was the last of the Cali kingpins still at large,&quot; Frechette said in a statement. &quot;The United States government is gratified by his arrest.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. Attorney General Janet Reno formally requested the extradition of the Rodriguez Orejuelas, Herrera and Juan Carlos Ramirez Abadia, a cartel enforcer, in June.</p>
<p>The government has refused to act on the extradition requests, arguing that to do so would violate a ban on extradition written into Colombia's constitution in 1991.</p>
<p>Legislation introduced under Samper's predecessor, Cesar Gaviria, offers substantial sentence reductions to drug lords who turn thmeselves in and confess to their crimes.</p>
<p>That legislation, known as the &quot;law of submission,&quot; is expected to be rewritten in the current session of Congress to ensure tougher sentences for drug traffickers. It could still benefit Herrera, however, since government sources say the new legislation would not take effect retroactively.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA, Colombia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
