<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41487" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Another study points to rising U.S. drug problem.</title>
<headline>Another study points to rising U.S. drug problem.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than one in five U.S. teenagers say they expect to try illegal drugs in the future, double last year's number, and nearly half of baby boomer parents expect their children to try drugs, according to a study released on Monday.</p>
<p>Similarly, the number of young people who said they would never try illegal drugs dropped from 86 percent to 51 percent. According to 43 percent of the youths surveyed, it is easier to buy marijuana than cigarettes or beer. A quarter of the 12-year-olds reported that their schools are not drug-free, while 69 percent of the 17-year-olds made that assessment.</p>
<p>The survey, released by the National Centre on Addiction and Substance Abuse at Columbia University, was the latest in a recent spate of studies and reports that show rising drug experimentation by teenagers. One highly publicised study released by the Clinton administration last month showed that drug use among teenagers had doubled since 1992.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue isn't whether our children are going to be tossed into this sea of drugs, the issue is how well we can teach them to swim,&quot; said former Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare Joseph Califano, president of the substance abuse group. He said parents' attitude of resignation about their children's drug use was &quot;infuriating.&quot;</p>
<p>Nearly half the parents -- 46 percent -- expected their teenage children to try drugs, and the figure was higher -- 65 percent -- among parents who were &quot;regular&quot; users of marijuana when they were young.</p>
<p>Almost all parents surveyed said they had spoken to their children about the dangers of drugs but only 64 percent of the children said their parents had such a discussion with them.</p>
<p>The survey of 1,200 teenagers and 1,166 parents was done by Luntz Research Companies in July and August. The addiction centre said some family &quot;warning factors&quot; were no curfews for teens, no involvement in religion and rarely eating dinner together as a family.</p>
<p>Risk factors for teens included smoking cigarettes, having friends who drink alcohol, smoke marijuana or use other drugs, knowing drug dealers, being able to buy marijuana easily and saying he or she expects to try illegal drugs in the future.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
