<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43962" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: &quot;Date rape&quot; drug blamed in death of Texas girl.</title>
<headline>&quot;Date rape&quot; drug blamed in death of Texas girl.</headline>
<dateline>LA PORTE, Texas 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Texas teenager was killed earlier this month by an overdose of a &quot;date rape&quot; drug slipped into her drink at a local dance club, police in this refinery town near Houston said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Local police have opened a homicide investigation into the death of 17-year-old Hillory Janean Farias after medical examiners discovered traces of the synthetic weight-loss drug gamma hydroxybutyrate, or GHB, in the high-school senior's body.</p>
<p>&quot;To our knowledge, she's the first fatality in the United States and hopefully the last from this stuff,&quot; said La Porte police chief Bobby Powell.</p>
<p>A depressant, GHB is one of the so-called date rape drugs, substances which cause euphoria, memory lapses or unconciousness in their victims and have been tied to a series of rapes in the United States, particularly in Florida.</p>
<p>Abuse of Rohypnol, the best known of the date rape drugs, has led to calls in Congress for stiffer penalties to halt increased smuggling of the drug into the United States, where it has not been approved for use as a sedative.</p>
<p>Police said there were no traces of alcohol or other drugs in the body of the Texas teenager, a varsity volleyball player and model student who died two weeks before the start of her senior year at La Porte High School.</p>
<p>&quot;When this young lady passed away, the medical examiner found no medical reason. The toxicology exam found no narcotics, no alcohol, nothing,&quot; Powell said.</p>
<p>Farias had left the dance club early Saturday night, Aug. 4, complaining of a severe headache. She died the next day in a local hospital after her grandmother, who was raising her, found her lying unconscious in her bed and not breathing.</p>
<p>Police first suspected GHB may have been involved in her death after receiving a report from a regional crime task force of a new date rape drug showing up at area clubs, Powell said.</p>
<p>Police Tuesday were tracking down the girl's friends and other teens to determine who may have slipped the drug into Farias' drink at the club, which police declined to name.</p>
<p>&quot;There were two or three hundred in that club that night, and some of them are already talking to us,&quot; Powell said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LA PORTE, Texas"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
