<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46422" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton would tie prison funds to drug programs.</title>
<headline>Clinton would tie prison funds to drug programs.</headline>
<byline>Arshad Mohammed</byline>
<dateline>PUEBLO, Colo 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton proposed on Wednesday making states set up drug programmes for prisoners in order to receive about $7.5 billion in federal funds to build new prisons.</p>
<p>The proposal, floated in the middle of a three-day campaign trip to key Western states, allowed Clinton to marry two issues popular with the electorate -- fighting crime and fighting drugs -- all without spending any new federal money.</p>
<p>&quot;It's time to say to inmates, if you stay on drugs, you'll stay in jail. If you want out of jail, you'll have to get off drugs,&quot; Clinton told a campaign rally in Pueblo. &quot;It's time to say to parolees, if you go back on drugs, you'll go back to jail. If you want to stay on the street, stay off drugs.&quot;</p>
<p>The campaign of Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole, who has criticised Clinton's record on the drug war, said Clinton's proposal was &quot;simply a shameless attempt to cover his failed liberal drug policy.&quot;</p>
<p>Dole spokesman Nelson Warfield pointed to new government statistics that said drug abuse among teenagers had risen since Clinton took office. In recent days Clinton and Republican House Speaker Newt Gingrich have sparred publicly over who is more concerned about drug abuse in America.</p>
<p>A senior White House official said Clinton's proposal was for states to set up drug testing and treatment for prisoners and parolees in order to have access to $8 billion to build prisons contained in the 1994 crime bill. Bruce Reed, White House domestic policy adviser, said about $500 million of this had already been disbursed to states, leaving $7.5 billion.</p>
<p>Clinton also announced on Wednesday he was releasing $27 million in federal money to states for drug programmes. But this money, like the prison construction funds, was already in the 1994 crime bill so its release involved no new federal money.</p>
<p>The twin proposals were vintage Clinton campaign technique -- involving limited federal action and little federal money while allowing him to appear tough on crime and drugs. He has floated a series of such small-scale proposals this year as he has campaigned against Dole in the Nov. 5 election.</p>
<p>In announcing the ideas on Wednesday, Clinton unveiled a study showing sharp declines in repeat offences when such programmes break drug habits.</p>
<p>The study, carried out in Delaware, showed that of offenders who followed drug treatment programmes in prison and after their release, 75 percent were drug free and 70 percent arrest-free after 18 months. Of those who did not follow the programme, 83 percent returned to drug use and 64 percent were arrested for new crimes.</p>
<p>Leading by 15 to 20 percentage points in national opinion polls, Clinton appeared to be using his latest trip to solidify his support in states like Missouri, Colorado and California while trying to undermine Dole in traditionally Republican states like Arizona.</p>
<p>In 1992 Clinton carried Colorado, a Rocky Mountain swing state, beating Republican George Bush 40-36, with independent Ross Perot winning 23 percent of the vote.</p>
<p>Campaign officials said recent polls show the president leading in all four states he was visiting, including Arizona, which has gone Republican in the last 11 presidential races. The last time a Democrat won there was in 1948, when Harry Truman was elected.</p>
<p>Clinton was to fly to Phoenix later on Wednesday for a speech on health care for the aged at a recreation centre that serves 45,000 elderly people in the region.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PUEBLO, Colo"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
