<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="48692" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: SURVEY FINDS S.AFRICANS RELUCTANT TO HELP POLICE.</title>
<headline>SURVEY FINDS S.AFRICANS RELUCTANT TO HELP POLICE.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many South Africans would not coorporate with police to solve criminal cases, despite unacceptably high levels of crime, a survey commissioned by a non-governmental monitoring agency found on Thursday.</p>
<p>The survey, commissioned by the Institute for a Democratic Alternative for South Africa (Idasa), polled 500 people mostly on the Cape Flats, a mixed-race working class area of Cape Town wracked by gang violence, drugs and alcohol abuse.  </p>
<p>&quot;While majorities feel that cooperating with the police and courts would increase the chances of apprehending, charging and convicting criminals, significant minorities think it would make no difference,&quot; the survey report said.</p>
<p>&quot;Moreover, majorities say they would not feel safe actually giving information to the police or testifying in court.&quot;</p>
<p>Idasa Public Information Sector manager Warren Krafchik said the survey focused on Cape Town because of recent events related to crime and policing.</p>
<p>Last month, militant Moslems in the grouping People Against Gangsterism and Drugs (Pagad), publicly shot and burned to death an alleged drug merchant and gang leader, Rashaad Staggie. </p>
<p>The group has given drug peddlars in the Cape an ultimatum to stop dealing or face the brunt of its anger.  </p>
<p>&quot;The survey was an effort to look at community perceptions towards the police, courts, crime and their responses to these,&quot; Krafchik told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We were concerned about the limited information base we have to debate these issues,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A lack of faith in policing was underscored in the survey, which found that 75 percent of people polled felt there was at least &quot;some&quot; corruption within the police force. Only four percent doubted there was corruption.</p>
<p>Fifty-two percent said some judges and prosecutors were also corrupt.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only do people judge their law enforcement institutions poorly with regard to what they do, they also give it poor ratings with regard to how they do their jobs,&quot; said the report.</p>
<p>Despite this negativity, public response and support for Pagad's vigilantism was muted with 29 percent of people sampled in favour and 30 percent opposed. However, 59 percent saw Pagad's campaign as effective in fighting drugs and gangsterism.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
