<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54695" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dole says to announce new anti-drugs, crime plan.</title>
<headline>Dole says to announce new anti-drugs, crime plan.</headline>
<byline>Randall Mikkelsen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hammering away on an anti- drugs theme that has become a campaign pillar, Republican Presidential candidate Bob Dole said Saturday he would propose a tough drug- and crime-fighting programme next week.</p>
<p>&quot;On Monday, I will be joined by many of America's outstanding Republican governors in announcing our action plan to combat drugs and violent crime,&quot; Dole said his weekly radio address.</p>
<p>Elements of the plan include ending the release of violent criminals who have only partially completed their sentences, making violent juveniles &quot;accountable for their crimes,&quot; and requiring convicts to work while in prison and pay compensation to their victims, Dole said.</p>
<p>It also includes a nationwide instant check system to stop criminals from buying guns.</p>
<p>The announcement is to be made at a meeting with a group of Republican governors in Philadelphia.</p>
<p>Perceiving a potential vulnerabilty in Clinton's admission of past -- though famously not inhaling -- marijuana use, and by revelations of past drug use by some Clinton staff members, Dole has sought to highlight the issue of America's drug problem.</p>
<p>And he spent much of the radio address attacking Clinton's record on drugs.</p>
<p>&quot;We will renew our commitment to a drug-free America -- a commitment that has been lost during the Clinton administration,&quot; Dole said.</p>
<p>&quot;Drug use among our youth has more than doubled since President Clinton took office. And since drugs lead to violence, it's no surprise that youth violence is also on the rise. In fact, many experts predict that juvenile arrests will double within the next 15 years,&quot; Dole said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is much that I would do as president that Bill Clinton has not done to stem the tide of violent crime and drugs, including appointing judges and federal prosecutors who will protect the rights of crime victims, and not expand the rights of criminals,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton has fought back against such criticisms, proposing this week that prison inmates and parolees be required to undergo drug testing and treatment, and releasing already- authorised spending for state drugs programmes.</p>
<p>That brought retorts from Dole that Clinton had appropriated his ideas and that his attention to the issue has come too late in his administration to be effective.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
