<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55797" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dole unveils plan to fight drugs, crime.</title>
<headline>Dole unveils plan to fight drugs, crime.</headline>
<byline>Randall Mikkelsen</byline>
<dateline>VILLANOVA, Pa 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole on Monday unveiled his plan to fight drugs and crime with more money for prisons, stiffer punishments for young offenders and more vocal use of the White House pulpit.</p>
<p>&quot;It is time to get serious about violent crime and drugs in a way that we have not seen in our government over the last four years,&quot; Dole said in a speech at Villanova University.</p>
<p>Dole, who was joined by his running mate Jack Kemp and several Republican governors, put aside the economic and tax cut issues that have fuelled his campaign and kicked off a week of running on the drugs and crime theme.</p>
<p>Dole said violent crime rates soared in the first two years of the Clinton administration. Drug use by teenagers more than doubled from 1992 to 1995, after falling by half in the previous 13 years, he said. He said the two are linked.</p>
<p>&quot;The country is reaping the bitter harvest of what this administration's liberal policies have sowed,&quot; Dole said.</p>
<p>Perceiving a potential vulnerabilty in President Bill Clinton's admission of having tried -- but not inhaled -- marijuana once, and in revelations of past drug use by some White House employees, Dole has sought to highlight the issue of America's drug problem.</p>
<p>&quot;I will change the message coming from the White House,&quot; he said. &quot;Teen-agers who have been deceived into believing that drugs are something you experiment with will hear a very different message from me ... There is right and there is wrong, and drug use is wrong.&quot;</p>
<p>Element's of Dole's plan included:</p>
<p>-- Using the White House to &quot;renew our commitment to a drug-free America.&quot; Dole, who speaks nostalgically of former first lady Nancy Reagan's &quot;just say no&quot; campaign, aims to cut teenage drug use in half by the end of his first term. The White House would assist the creation of local anti-drug organisations and encourage the entertainment media to embrace an anti-drug message.</p>
<p>-- Doubling federal aid to states for prison construction, now about $405 million annually, to make sure there is enough capacity for offenders to serve their full sentences. Dole would encourage states to end parole for violent criminals.</p>
<p>-- Prosecuting as adults juveniles older than 13 who are charged under federal laws with violent crimes and allowing sentencing courts to consider previous crimes of juvenile offenders.</p>
<p>-- Making prisoners work 40 hours per week, with earnings going to offset cost of imprisonment and paying restitution to crime victims.</p>
<p>-- Hastening development of an instant background check of gun purchasers.</p>
<p>In a preemptive strike against the Dole initiative, Clinton travelled to Cincinnati on Monday to be endorsed by the Fraternal Order of Police, the nation's largest police union.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very proud to have the endorsement of an organisation representing 270,000 rank and file members of law enforcement who put their lives on the line every single day for the rest of us,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Clinton also proposed doubling the statute of limitation on certain violent crimes to 10 years from five years.</p>
<p>Republican Pennsylvania Gov. Tom Ridge said of the FOP endorsement, &quot;By and large it's misguided and misleading. If you ask the men and women who are wearing uniforms in our communities ... you'll find most of them support Bob Dole and Jack Kemp.&quot;</p>
<p>This week's crime and drugs theme gives a temporary back seat to the tax-cutting economic plan that has been Dole's campaign foundation, but which has yet to generate momentum to pull him closer to Clinton in the polls.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll talk about that all week long,&quot; Dole spokesman Nelson Warfield said of the anti-crime message. &quot;We think that the economic plan is still our most compelling argument,&quot; he said. &quot;But the Clinton administration's failure in the war on crime and drugs cries out for commentary as well.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VILLANOVA, Pa"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
