<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55914" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Gingrich and Lott to move against drug smugglers.</title>
<headline>Gingrich and Lott to move against drug smugglers.</headline>
<byline>David Morgan</byline>
<dateline>MARIETTA, Ga 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gingrich Monday said he and Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott would introduce a bill imposing life sentences on first-time drug smugglers and the death penalty on repeat offenders.</p>
<p>In a campaign speech intended to augment a drug-fighting plan unveiled by Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole, Gingrich also proposed establishing a 24-hour national hotline for addicts who need help kicking their drug habits.</p>
<p>&quot;You'll have the Senate majority leader and the House speaker introducing a bill that says: If you cross the American border carrying a commercial quantity of illegal drugs and a jury finds it's your first time doing it, you get life without parole,&quot; Gingrich told cheering supporters.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the jury finds out that you are a professional narcotics trafficker who has repeatedly brought drugs in to destroy our children, you get a mandatory death penalty.&quot;</p>
<p>Gingrich said Dole already had indicated his readiness to use the military and National Guard to seal the U.S. border with Mexico. &quot;And I think we have to more effectively go for the source,&quot; he said. &quot;We have a real reason morally, involving drugs and our children, to make sure we win.&quot;</p>
<p>The Georgia Republican has long advocated a get-tough policy against drug traffickers but did not indicate when the anti-drug bill would be introduced.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, in Villanova, Pennsylvania, Dole unveiled a plan to fight drugs and crime with more money for prisons, stiffer punishments for young offenders and more vocal use of the White House pulpit. The Republicans were waging a campaign against President Bill Clinton that criticised the White House for its performance on the crime issue.</p>
<p>Dole Monday said violent crime rates soared in the first two years of the Clinton administration. Drug use by teens more than doubled from 1992 to 1995, after falling by half in the previous 13 years, he said. He said the two were linked.</p>
<p>Aside from moral leadership from a Republican White House, Gingrich said the drug crisis in America would require a campaign to get churches involved in the struggle. &quot;We need a campaign, I think, to reach out through churches and synagogues to help people who are drug addicts get off of drugs,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very very important that we have a hotline, an 800 number, where anyone in America who's on drugs can call at any time of the day or night, and somebody who cares about saving people shows up within an hour to help them.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARIETTA, Ga"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
