<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60227" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dole says &quot;Just don't do it,&quot; hits drug films.</title>
<headline>Dole says &quot;Just don't do it,&quot; hits drug films.</headline>
<byline>Randall Mikkelsen</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole on Wednesday criticised the entertainment industry for glorifying drug use and unveiled a new anti-drug slogan -- &quot;Just don't do it.&quot;</p>
<p>Speaking at the Chaminade College Preparatory High School, a Roman Catholic school that uses drug-sniffing dogs to help keep the campus drug-free, Dole sought to reignite both a public crusade against drug use and his struggling campaign.</p>
<p>&quot;I have a message to the fashion, music and film industries,&quot; he said. &quot;Take your influence seriously, you have a lot of it. Respect your talent and power. Stop the commercialization of drug abuse. Stop the glorification of slow suicide.&quot;</p>
<p>The speech was the latest salvo in Dole's effort to win votes with an anti-drugs, anti-crime programme launched on Monday in Philadelphia. The entertainment and fashion industries shared in the responsibility for shaping attitudes among teenagers, whose rates of drug use have more than doubled since 1992, Dole said.</p>
<p>&quot;The marijuana leaf and the heroin needle have become the symbols of fashionable rebellion, and two of the most widely praised movies of the past two years, 'Pulp Fiction' and 'Trainspotting,' feature the romance of heroin,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Fashion magazines feature models with what is known as the 'junkie look.' Rock musicians create and celebrate a culture of heroin. And some have become role models, even in death,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dole has seen neither &quot;Trainspotting,&quot; about Scottish heroin addicts living in squalor, or &quot;Pulp Fiction,&quot; about American heroin addicts living the fast life, Dole spokesman Nelson Warfield said. But he has read reviews of both films, including one calling &quot;Trainspotting&quot; a &quot;funny, upbeat look at heroin addiction,&quot; Warfield said.</p>
<p>Dole criticised President Bill Clinton for sowing &quot;moral confusion&quot; by making light of his own past, non-inhaling, expermentation with marijuana -- citing an MTV music television interview in which Clinton said he would inhale marijuana if given another chance.</p>
<p>He harkened back to the 1980's anti-drug campaign of former first lady Nancy Reagan, with its slogan &quot;Just say no,&quot; in leading the students in his new slogan, &quot;Just don't do it.&quot; The line also evokes Nike's shoe slogan, &quot;Just do it.&quot;</p>
<p>Dole also received the endorsement of the 7,000-member California Narcotics Officers Association, another shot in the law-and-order endorsement battle with Clinton, who snared the backing of the 270,000 member Fraternal Order of Police.</p>
<p>Dole has criticised the entertainment industry before for contributing to a moral decline in America, but in July he cast his goals for the industry in a postitive light, going to California to thank filmmakers for several uplifting movies.</p>
<p>That was in recognition of the industry's importance in California, the largest state in terms of electoral votes, with 54 of 270 needed to win.</p>
<p>At a later rally in the Studio City area of Los Angeles, he said despite polls showing him behind in California, he represented real people of the state, which he contrasted with Clinton's celebrated courting of the entertainment industry.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe California will be ours if we go out and work and spread our message to working people in California ... not the elite ... not the Hollywood set, that's where President Clinton picked up $4 million in one little event,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd like to have an event like that sometime, but nobody's asked me to come out,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
