<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70629" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Colombia's Samper hits back on drug issue at UN.</title>
<headline>Colombia's Samper hits back on drug issue at UN.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombian President Ernesto Samper, facing fresh embarrassment in the war on drugs, launched an impassioned defence of himself and his country before the world community on Monday.</p>
<p>Just days after heroin was found stashed on his presidential jet, Samper urged the 185-nation U.N. General Assembly in a speech to set up a &quot;grand alliance&quot; to fight the scourge of drugs.</p>
<p>&quot;Colombia wants to be part of the solution,&quot; Samper said. &quot;We do not want to continue to be demonised when, in fact, we are all victims.&quot;</p>
<p>Samper has endured repeated calls for his resignation and the humiliation of seeing his country decertified as a partner of the United States in its war against drugs.</p>
<p>Colombia is the world's largest exporter of cocaine, a multibillion-dollar business run by powerful drug cartels. Thousands have died in drug-related violence in Colombia.</p>
<p>Washington has been concerned by charges that Samper personally approved the use of millions of dollars in drug money to finance his 1994 electoral campaign.</p>
<p>Samper used his speech to the United Nations to hit back at his critics, although he did not attack the United States or any other country by name.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been the nation that has suffered the most, invested the most and paid the highest economic and social price in this war against criminal drug organisations,&quot; Samper said.</p>
<p>He said 20,000 Colombians had died as a result of drug wars over the past decade and noted that he too had been scarred, since he still carries four of the 11 bullets fired at him by right-wing hitmen linked to the drug trade in March 1989.</p>
<p>Giving thanks to God for his own survival, he said the smuggling of heroin onto the presidential plane was a failed plot to undermine the Colombian government.</p>
<p>&quot;I am here today, before this world assembly, because nobody will stop me from making Colombia's proposal to fight the global criminal drug organisations,&quot; Samper said.</p>
<p>He gave few concrete details of how a global alliance to fight drugs should work, but said unilateral intervention in the affairs of others or judgmental attitudes should be left aside -- an oblique reference to U.S. criticism of Colombia.</p>
<p>There should be economic incentives for countries to replace drugs with other crops and tighter controls on money laundering in industrialised countries, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;You cannot let all the weight of fighting drugs fall on the producer countries, which are the weakest link in the chain,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Colombian radio said on Monday Samper would issue a statement after his speech, expressing tentative support for efforts to lift his country's ban on the extradition of drug lords.</p>
<p>There was no immediate sign of such a statement, and no one was available for comment at the Colombian mission to the United Nations.</p>
<p>As president Samper was humiliated when Washington revoked his U.S. visa in July because of allegations that he was linked to drug traffickers and as a sign of Washington's displeasure over a move by Colombia's Congress to clear him of drug corruption charges a month earlier.</p>
<p>The travel restriction does not apply to visits to U.N. headquarters, which is international territory.</p>
<p>Eleven members of the Colombian Air Force, including several officers, have been arrested in connection with the heroin found aboard Samper's presidential jet.</p>
<p>More than eight pounds (3.7 kg) of heroin was discovered aboard the Boeing 707 on Friday night as it was being readied at a military air base on the outskirts of Bogota for the flight to New York.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
