<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70643" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Colombia's Samper says world losing drug war.</title>
<headline>Colombia's Samper says world losing drug war.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombian President Ernesto Samper asked the world community on Monday to stop &quot;satanizing&quot; his embattled homeland, saying it was more a victim than a villain in the losing battle against drugs.</p>
<p>&quot;Colombia wants to be part of the solution,&quot; he said in an address to the U.N. General Assembly. &quot;We don't want to continue being satanized in the face of the world because of a problem of which we, like all of you, are victims.&quot;</p>
<p>Samper was speaking at the United Nations two days after 7.4 pounds (3.4 kg) of heroin was found hidden in the presidential jet that was to fly him to New York. He called the incident an &quot;outrageous and dastardly&quot; act and took a commerical flight on Colombia's Avianca airline instead.</p>
<p>He has endured repeated calls for his resignation and the humiliation of seeing his country decertified as a partner in the U.S. drug war because of charges he personally approved the use of millions of dollars in narcotics money to finance his 1994 electoral campaign.</p>
<p>Some Western diplomats had suggested Samper might use his address to say he &quot;decertifying&quot; the United States, since its lack of effective drug treatment and prevention programmes had gone a long way toward creating the world's single largest market for Colombian cocaine and heroin.</p>
<p>But he stopped short of singling out any country by name, saying he was convinced &quot;the world is losing the battle against drugs&quot; because too little had been done to fight drug consumption and money laundering.</p>
<p>&quot;As long as demand is not reduced, the task of fighting supply will be innocuous in a definitive solution of the problem. You cannot let all the weight of fighting drugs fall on the producer countries, which are the weakest link in the chain,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In his U.N. address he turned defiantly from accused to accuser, saying he had been cleared of any wrongdoing by Colombia's Congress and represented a country that had suffered more than any other because of a seemingly insatiable demand for illicit drugs in the world's richest countries.</p>
<p>He said 20,000 Colombians had died as a result of drug wars over the past decade and noted that he, too, had been scarred by drug-related violence. He still carries four of 11 bullets fired at him by right-wing hitmen linked to the narcotics trade in March 1989.</p>
<p>Calling drug trafficking &quot;the most sinister trans-national enterprise,&quot; Samper added that it moves &quot;nearly $500 billion dollars a year&quot; through the world banking and financial system. He said much tighter controls were needed to fight money laundering in industrialised countries.</p>
<p>With the Cold War over, he said, the United Nations and the international community should set their sights on the drug war and develop a global strategy to fight &quot;the greatest threat against world security and stability of our time.&quot;</p>
<p>Speaking as the head of a country torn by drug-related violence and narcotics corruption at all levels of society, he said drugs were &quot;an epidemic that can undermine ... the moral structure sustaining the governability of democratic states.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
