<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72605" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Justice minister says Colombia to okay extradition.</title>
<headline>Justice minister says Colombia to okay extradition.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombia has no interest in harbouring drug lords and will move to lift a constitutional ban on extradition in effect since 1991, Justice Minister Carlos Medellin said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Drug traffickers will not take refuge in Colombia,&quot; Medellin said in a speech at Bogota's Modelo prison.</p>
<p>&quot;They have tarnished the name of honest people who have fallen in this fight,&quot; he added, referring to the thousands of Colombians who have died fighting Colombia's U.S.-backed drug war over the past decade.</p>
<p>&quot;Countries have the right to demand (control over) people who have committed crimes in their territory, that's called extradition,&quot; Medellin said, adding that it would be welcome as part of a series of measures aimed at strengthening Colombia's judicial system.</p>
<p>In subsequent remarks to reporters, Medellin added that the government would only move to lift Colombia's constitutional ban on extradition once Congress approved legislation submitted in mid-July that would stiffen prison sentences for drug trafficking and permit the confiscation of drug baron's property.</p>
<p>It was not clear how soon the legislation might win passage, but President Ernesto Samper asked lawmakers last week to give the measures top priority.</p>
<p>In a speech to the U.N. General Assembly in New York Monday, Samper proposed the creation of a world court for the handling of drug-related crimes and terrorism and said Colombia would back extradition as part of an international agreement on judicial cooperation.</p>
<p>He fell short of saying that the Colombia would approve extradition without such an agreement, but suggested that it would in subsequent remarks to Colombian television.</p>
<p>The 1991 ban was passed after hundreds of people -- including three presidential candidates, a justice minister, high court judges, journalists and scores of police officers -- were killed in a campaign of assassinations and bombings that drug lords waged against extradition in the late 1980s and early 1990s.</p>
<p>Colombia, the world's leading exporter of cocaine and a top supplier of heroin to the United States, is under heavy U.S. pressure to step up its war with drug mobs.</p>
<p>Samper, whose 1994 election campaign allegedly received millions of dollars in financing from the Cali cartel, has insisted repeatedly that Colombians are more victims of the drug trade than its villians.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
