<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73988" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Gold smugglers reap profits despite clampdown.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Gold smugglers reap profits despite clampdown.</headline>
<byline>Brian Spoors</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gold is the perfect commodity for smuggling. It has been smuggled for centuries.</p>
<p>Last month three women were arrested at New Delhi airport as they staggered off a plane from Kazakstan burdened with nearly 32 kg (70lb) of gold between them worth nearly half a million dollars.</p>
<p>Earlier this year members of a UK-based gold smuggling ring were jailed after they had brought gold worth $30 million into the country hidden in cars with the intention of profiting from Britain's 17.5 percent Value Added Tax (VAT) when they sold it.</p>
<p>But according to market watchers, the number of smugglers caught is tiny while, every day, gold stuffed into washing machines and other imaginative hiding places, or in the hold of a night-flying private planes, moves into the shadows.</p>
<p>&quot;Gold's value to weight ratio is higher than anywhere else and the cost of production is a fraction of the price. It's a perfect item for smuggling,&quot; said one industry watcher, who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>It's origins are virtually impossible to detect and precise figures on world demand and supply are hard to pin down.</p>
<p>Stewart Murray, chief executive of the authoritative gold industry research group Gold Fields Mineral Services (GFMS) admits the level of gold smuggling cannot be quantified &quot;without a wide error band&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Our numbers are indicating a significant amount of smuggling in the first half of the year,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>GFMS put 1995 world gold demand at 3,355 tonnes of which 1,890 tonnes was newly mined.</p>
<p>The rest came from sales from the former Communist bloc, sales from central banks, recycled scrap gold and &quot;forward sales&quot; from mines borrowing gold from banks and selling it using their mine reserves as collateral.</p>
<p>The largest producer is South Africa despite producing just over 522 tonnes last year, its lowest output in 40 years.</p>
<p>Losses through theft and smuggling from the South African mines are big scale and highly organised. Earlier this year the third largest producer, Gengold, admitted recovering 70 kg (154.3 lb) of stolen gold during a four-month dragnet at two of its mines.</p>
<p>A Gengold official said at the time that thefts from the mines could total five to 10 percent of production, although industry observers say 10 percent is too high.</p>
<p>According to the South African police, 20 tonnes of precious metals worth around $350 million disappear from mines every year despite stringent security.</p>
<p>Semi-refined gold vanishes into the townships for re-refining -- using mercury also stolen from the mines -- before the syndicates move it, complete with forged documents, to lucrative European and eastern black markets.</p>
<p>&quot;Smugglers have thieves in each and every mine. If we look at the big diamond and gold syndicates, there are seven operating at the moment,&quot; Willem Minnaar, director of the police's Organised Crime Unit, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The South African gold smugglers are higher profile than might be imagined.</p>
<p>Minnaar described them as &quot;rich and well established in society&quot; and a mining offical said &quot;a few millionaires&quot; were closely involved in the business.</p>
<p>&quot;The mining companies obviously thought they had to bite the bullet here. They are spending a lot of money on security and detecting thefts,&quot; said Murray.</p>
<p>Much of gold's illegal activity does not go away, it becomes legitimised. Small unlicensed mines often lead to high investment, fully authorised and capitalised large-scale mines.</p>
<p>Often the illegal mines are a significant size themselves.</p>
<p>China was the sixth largest producer last year, officially mining 108 tonnes of gold, although GFMS put the figure at more than 136 tonnes.</p>
<p>During the first half of 1996, the Chinese government shut down 430 illegal mines, throwing 13,000 people out of work and impounding 9,000 pieces of equipment in the process.</p>
<p>It also seized 332 guns and broke up eight armed gangs used to guard the illegal mining facilities.</p>
<p>Ironically the governments which try to stamp out smuggling often set the smugglers' profit margins.</p>
<p>Often the local central bank is the only authorised buyer from the mines and it buys at a discount to the world price.</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank of South Africa and most gold producing countries in Latin America work on similar systems.</p>
<p>If the discount is too deep, smuggling gears up. &quot;There is much less of that now from Latin America where the central banks are offering a fairer price,&quot; said one industry observer.</p>
<p>The incentive for the illegal importer is to avoid local import or sales taxes set by the host government.</p>
<p>&quot;It's all a question of price. Taxes and special import levies give the smuggler the profit margin he can expect,&quot; said one industry source.</p>
<p>Britain is the only country in the European Union charging VAT on gold sales. Any British citizen can go to continental Europe and buy VAT-free gold &quot;for personal use&quot;.</p>
<p>If it is then sold in Britain, 17.5 percent VAT is payable -- hence the incentive to smuggle a few Krugerrand or stuff a BMW's bumpers with small bars.</p>
<p>India, the largest gold importer, is a classic case. &quot;It has been partially opened but that was partially paced by the smugglers,&quot; an observer said.</p>
<p>India scrapped the Gold Control Act in June 1990 and opened its bullion market to imports three years later. In 1993, it allowed Indian expatriates to bring in gold freely, subject to duty.</p>
<p>&quot;There has always been smuggling into India. Currently it imports about 300 tonnes a year officially and 100 tonnes unofficially (which) is about the usual level of Indian smuggling. The Indian authorities watch this closely,&quot; another industry source said.</p>
<p>Most of the gold reaching India comes from the Gulf states hidden in containers inside inside consumer goods but it might also origniate legitimately in Dubai or Turkey before looping through the southern CIS (Commonwealth of Independent States) republics.</p>
<p>Non-resident Indians are allowed to import five kg (11.02 lb) gold every six months. Some 1,142 kg (2,518 lb) of smuggled bullion was confiscated by customs officials in 1995 and 517 kg (1,140 lb) so far this year.</p>
<p>Nepal is a growing smuggling base, getting some gold from the CIS republics and some from Singapore and Hong Kong.</p>
<p>There is less smuggling than in its &quot;golden age&quot; in the 1960s, 70s and 80s because of liberalisation in traditional gold affinity countries such as Taiwan, Thailand and Indonesia as well as India, another gold industry insider said.</p>
<p>China is different because of various and legitimate joint ventures set up outside the country to produce jewellery, some of which may go back into China officially, legitimately carried by non resident Chinese, or unofficially.</p>
<p>&quot;No official figures exist for the amount of gold smuggled into China but the inflow is not as big as it was when there was a local premium (charged by the central bank on its gold sales to fabricators)&quot;, said an industry source.</p>
<p>Gold industry insiders were quite clear that smuggling would continue as long as there was a tax incentive to do it.</p>
<p>&quot;The countries likely to target smugglers are ones which continue to have a premium over world prices because of some local tax situation,&quot; one source said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
