<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76779" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: EU ministers to clamp down on drugs traffickers.</title>
<headline>EU ministers to clamp down on drugs traffickers.</headline>
<byline>Carmel Linnane</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union justice ministers will discuss tougher drugs laws in Dublin on Thursday, close to a spot where angry citizens took the law into their own hands and beat to death a suspected drug pusher with baseball bats.</p>
<p>Over a two-day informal meeting in Dublin Castle, they will debate how to satisfy a general outcry across the 15-nation bloc against the spread of drugs and try to persuade parents, citizen groups and social workers that vigilante justice is unnecessary.</p>
<p>The brutal murder in Dublin last May of AIDS sufferer, heroin addict and minor criminal Josey Dwyer illustrated the depth of the problem.</p>
<p>A further reminder came in June when contract killers, thought to have been hired by a drugs baron, shot dead the country's premier investigative journalist for knowing too much.</p>
<p>Ireland's Justice Minister Nora Owen, whose country is current EU president, said she was pushing for uniform sentencing at the top end of the scale for drugs traffickers and increased cooperation across borders.</p>
<p>&quot;I am confident that...as a result of some initiatives I have taken as President of the Council and from proposals being put forward by other countries, that we will make progress in trafficking laws whether it is drugs, children or women,&quot; Owen told reporters at a briefing ahead of Thursday's meeting.</p>
<p>Owen said Ireland already had tough legislation in place, allowing for life sentencing of drugs traffickers.</p>
<p>&quot;I want each minister to commit themselves in their own countries to bring in such legislation, if they have not already got it in place. Basically their laws should contain in them a sentence (for drugs traffickers) that reflects the most serious sentence that they give for crimes,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>She said such legislation did not conflict with allowing people to smoke cannabis in cafes in countries like the Netherlands. &quot;That is not trafficking,&quot; Owen said.</p>
<p>She said other ministers had asked for &quot;a great deal of discussion&quot; of man-made drugs being manufactured in European and neighbouring countries such as Poland and Hungary.</p>
<p>&quot;Fast and furious we are now becoming producers of drugs ourselves. Man-made drugs are becoming more and more of a problem as they are seen as almost respectable, just like popping a tablet,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The advancement of drug profiling can help track down where a drug was made, she said. The European Drugs Unit, based in the Hague, has identified chemical imprints on drugs which reveal their origin.</p>
<p>&quot;By doing a chemical analysis on these drugs and profiling the chemicals that go into them, one can say these originated in Holland or Poland or wherever,&quot; Owen said.</p>
<p>&quot;This may identify regular routes for traffickers and may also lead to blacklisting or controlling of some of the substances which are now being used to make these man-made drugs.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
