<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78418" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST - Australian General News - Sept 27.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST - Australian General News - Sept 27.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Australian Bureau of Statistics job vacancy figures suggest the labour market weakness is set to continue. A large fall in the number of public sector jobs vacancies led the push behind a 1.2 per cent seasonally adjusted fall, with job vacancies for the sctor falling 19.9 per cent in the three months to August. Page 2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Transport Minister John Sharp has announced any bidder for Australian National's assets, which employed Government consultant John Brew, would be immediately disqualified following allegations that Brew, who recommended to the Government to sell o close down AN, was also employed as an advisor to a major prospective buyer for AN. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The latest salary survey for solicitors by the New South Wales Law Society has reversed the image of law being a lucrative industry. Figures reveal more than 40 per cent of New South Wales solicitors earn less than A$50,000, with just 9.7 per cent earning over A$150,000 annually. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Trade Minister Tim Fischer told an APEC business forum in Sydney yesterday that Australia endorsed proposals for the World Trade Organisation to take on the market-access goals of the Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation forum, involving a global target of fee and open trade and investment by 2020. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Australia has been polarised by the 66-year old man who chose to kill himself under the controversial Northern Territory euthanasia law. Darwin GP Philip Nitschke, who helped former carpenter Bob Dent to be the first in the world to die by legally sanctioed euthanasia, said his action was an act of love. Meanwhile politicians and church groups have condemned the action, claiming the Territory law-makers should have Dent's death on their conscience. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Broadcasting Corporation executives have announced the national broadcaster will have to slash over 900 jobs from a total workforce of 5400 and axe some radio programs following Federal Budget cuts. One in six staff will lose their job within to years as the ABC will be forced to borrow up to A$30 million next year for redundancy payouts. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard yesterday defied suggestions of economic threats by China and met with the exiled Tibetan spiritual leader the Dalai Lama for over half and hour in Sydney yesterday. Howard avoided discussions with the media to avoid further aggravating China who warned of diplomatic and economic reprisals. Page 2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Shipping companies and maritime unions yesterday announced a landmark deal which sees the softening of the long-standing union-imposed ban of foreign flagged ships carrying cargo between Australia and New Zealand. The deal, which sees BHP take over ANL's rans-Tasman routes and use the foreign-flagged vessels in its fleets, has the Federal Government declaring a major victory over the future of waterfront reform. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>Australia's media recorded a long handshake between the exiled Tibetan spiritual leader the Dalai Lama and the Australian Prime Minister John Howard in yesterday's meeting in Sydney. To try to alleviate growing diplomatic tension between China and Australa as a result of the meeting, the Federal Government insisted that the meeting would strictly be conducted in a religious capacity. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Emotions in the euthanasia debate reached overdrive yesterday as deputy Prime Minister Tim Fischer declared the first mercy killing under the controversial Northern Territory law as heralding the &quot;culture of death&quot;, while anti-euthanasia politicians brushd aside the death bed plea of the first man to legally die, Bob Dent, to reverse the push to outlaw the Territory Bill. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Doctors at Sydney's Liverpool Hospital have agreed to blackban the new A$183 million, 240-bed clinical services block, unless the New South Wales Government increases Health Funding by an extra A$17 million. Dr Eugene Moylan, the chairman of the hospital' medical staff council, said the doctors' decision had the backing of the nursing staff and allied health professionals. Page 2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Prior to gaining approval from the Federal Government's drug watchdog, the Therapeutic Goods Administration, supplies of a new class of HIV-AIDS drug, virmune, are being released for the first time in Australia.  The drug reduces the virus in the body to ndetectable levels when used in combination with other treatments and is supported by key organisations, including the National Association of People Living With HIV/AIDS, the AIDS Council of New South Wales and the Australian Federation of AIDS Organisatons. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>According to Darwin doctor Philip Nitschke, two more Northern Territory people and three from interstate are waiting to die under the Territory's Rights of the Terminally Ill Act, following the first death under the law on Sunday.  Nitschke said the killig of Bob Dent on the weekend proved to be a very tense time for those around him, but the patient had reminded them all that it was an act of love. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Because of a A$55 million drop in funding revealed in the Federal Budget and a A$13.5 million budget blowout last year, ABC managing director Brian Johns told a Senate committee yesterday that at least 900 jobs would be cut from the national broadcaster oer the next two years and many programs would be scrapped or merged with others. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victoria experienced hundreds of mini-earthquakes yesterday - one every five minutes on average - with some measuring up to 2.5 on the Richter scale.  The aftershocks are expected to continue for at least a few days, following Wednesday's 5.2 earthquake, hich is the biggest yet recorded within a 125-kilometre radius of Melbourne. Page A2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Although the Chinese yesterday issued a statement saying Prime Minister John Howard's meeting with the Dalai Lama would produce a negative impact on relations between China and Australia, the Dalai Lama said Howard was positive about pressing China into tlks on the Tibetan issue. Page A3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
