<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79605" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: &quot;Frasier&quot; star Grammer checks into clinic.</title>
<headline>&quot;Frasier&quot; star Grammer checks into clinic.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kelsey Grammer, star of the NBC hit comedy &quot;Frasier&quot;, has checked himself into the Betty Ford Centre for substance abuse after his arrest for alleged drunken driving.</p>
<p>The &quot;Frasier&quot; show issued a statement on Wednesday saying Grammer &quot;voluntarily admitted himself&quot; to the famed clinic and that production of the show was put on hold as a result.</p>
<p>&quot;'Frasier' is currently on hiatus and will resume production in October,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>There was no immediate word on how long Grammer would stay at the Betty Ford Centre near Palm Springs, California, which has provided treatment to numerous Hollywood celebrities trying to overcome alcoholism and drug addiction.</p>
<p>Grammer, who plays a psychologist turned radio talk show host on the Emmy Award-winning show, was booked on suspicion of drunken driving after crashing his sports car outside his suburban Los Angles home last weekend.</p>
<p>The 40-year old actor was hospitalized for a head injury sustained in the crash. He agreed to a blood-alcohol test but results have not yet been released, officials said. Prosecutors will decide later whether to charge him formally with drunken driving.</p>
<p>Grammer has a history of substance abuse and has been convicted of drunken driving and cocaine possession.</p>
<p>&quot;The producers and cast of 'Frasier', as well as Kelsey's friends and colleagues ... support his decision and wish him a speedy recovery,&quot; the show's statement said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
