<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="84892" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>KYRGYZSTAN: FEATURE - Kyrgyz drug squad, a long way from Miami Vice.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Kyrgyz drug squad, a long way from Miami Vice.</headline>
<byline>Brian Killen</byline>
<dateline>KARA-BOLTA, Kyrgyzstan 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The drug squad in this Central Asian country call him &quot;Papa&quot; because they respect him like a father.</p>
<p>Timur Timurbekov, a senior detective, is like an older, less glamorous version of Sonny Crockett -- the stylish, freewheeling character in the U.S. television series &quot;Miami Vice&quot;.</p>
<p>As usual, television police have little to do with reality. And reality in Kyrgyzstan is as far removed as you can get from flashing neon lights and pulsating background music.</p>
<p>Timur, 41, leads a team of professionals in the frontline of a battle to stem a tide of opium from Afghanistan that is feeding crime, especially organised crime, in this former Soviet republic, and threatening Russia and Europe.</p>
<p>The entire police force here is suffering from a chronic cash shortage. Salaries have not been paid for two or three months. In the circumstances, it is remarkable that the anti-drug fighters having any success at all.</p>
<p>&quot;Drug prices are rising, so this means that some measures are being taken,&quot; said Timur Issakov, deputy head of the Kyrgyz Interior Ministry's anti-drug department. &quot;At the moment, the situation is under control.</p>
<p>&quot;But if we talk about equipment, it's just a joke,&quot; he sighed.</p>
<p>Only a few senior officers enjoy the luxury of a car, so there are no high-speed car chases through the not so mean streets of Kara-Bolta, about 60 km (40 miles) northwest of the capital Bishkek, where horses and carts are a common sight.</p>
<p>Police radios are also a rare luxury, and there are no closed frequencies. Anyone can listen in, including the increasingly sophisticated crime syndicates involved in the lucrative drug business.</p>
<p>In Kara-Bolta, a town of about 70,000 best known for its vodka, Timur lives in a modest three-room flat with his wife and three children.</p>
<p>His working clothes -- track suit trousers, T-shirt and worn sneakers -- are classic Soviet-style casual wear. No designer jackets or sunglasses.</p>
<p>But when Timur goes on a raid he carries it out with a panache that would do Miami Vice proud. &quot;You'll probably go down for 15 years,&quot; he told one suspected dealer.</p>
<p>&quot;No, please, I've got a young kid,&quot; the man pleaded. In front of him Timur clapped handcuffs onto two young men suspected of buying opium, several doses of which lay on the kitchen table next to a half-eaten watermelon.</p>
<p>The two bleary-eyed men admitted that they were addicts. Timur held up their arms and showed the injection marks.</p>
<p>&quot;Look at him. You might think he was a sportsman,&quot; said the grey-haired detective. &quot;And this one, he could be a doctor,&quot; he added, turning to the other.</p>
<p>There was another man with a bit-part in this drama, an odd-looking character in a striped suit and sunglasses, but his role was unclear.</p>
<p>&quot;I was just standing by the car and they brought me in here,&quot; he said. Timur was unconvinced but didn't arrest him.</p>
<p>On the whole, he was sympathetic. He understood that drug addiction was more of an illness than a crime. &quot;I would sometimes like to release them. I think about the children.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Kyrgyzstan's economic problems, including unemployment, had contributed to an increase in drug use and trafficking. &quot;If they had jobs, they would not do this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Oleg, 26, one of those arrested by Timur's team, said he started taking drugs when he was 17. &quot;I tried hashish and liked it. Now I take opium every day, once a day.&quot;</p>
<p>He was unemployed and depended on his wife for cash to pay for his habit. A typical dose of opium costs about 20-40 som ($1.50-3.50) -- a sizeable amount in a country where the average monthly wage is only about $50.</p>
<p>Most addicts &quot;shoot up&quot; every day, some three times a day.</p>
<p>Oleg's wife, perhaps expecting the inevitable, showed surprisingly little emotion when she arrived later and watched him being led away.</p>
<p>Sergei, 22, the second addict, was in a similar position, unemployed and using drugs for three months, often paid for by his wife.</p>
<p>Timur's partner, Agzam, gathered the evidence against the two men in a polythene bag. A stocky close-cropped bull of a man, with a pistol tucked inside his belt, he said nothing and let Timur do the talking.</p>
<p>Agzam was one of the few members of the 180-man drug squad here carrying a gun.</p>
<p>Kyrgyzstan, one of the poorest former Soviet republics, cannot afford to issue weapons to all its policemen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KIRGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARA-BOLTA, Kyrgyzstan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KYRGYZSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
