<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19480" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Blazes cause critical firefighter shortage in U.S..</title>
<headline>Blazes cause critical firefighter shortage in U.S..</headline>
<byline>Adrian Croft</byline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rash of new wildfires caused by lightning in the Western United States has caused a critical shortage of firefighters and equipment, officials said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>A thunderstorm moved across eastern Idaho, western Wyoming and western Montana late on Tuesday, sparking many new lightning fires in tinder-dry trees and brush, said Don Smurthwaite, a spokesman for the National Interagency Fire Centre in Boise, Idaho.</p>
<p>The new fires had created &quot;a critical shortage&quot; of firefighting resources, the fire centre said.</p>
<p>A fire weather watch was posted in eastern Montana and eastern Wyoming, where dry lightning and gusty winds were forecast for Wednesday.</p>
<p>The fire centre said 18,610 firefighters were battling 52 major blazes that have charred more than 490,000 acres (200,000 hectares) of timber, grass and brush in California, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, Oregon, Utah, Washington and Wyoming. Dozens of smaller lightning-sparked fires were also burning.</p>
<p>Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt said on Wednesday the fires were not likely to be contained soon and he would ask Congress for millions of dollars to get them under control.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be a long, tough summer because there is no real relief in sight,&quot; Babbitt, who is in the West assessing the situation, said on NBC's &quot;Today&quot; Show.</p>
<p>Smurthwaite of the National Interagency Fire Centre said firefighting resources were stretched thin. &quot;We don't have a lot of room left to move people around,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Many firefighters from Eastern states are already helping out and a battalion of U.S. Marines from Camp Pendleton in southern California has been put on alert. &quot;They may be asked to come in and support the effort,&quot; Smurthwaite said.</p>
<p>He said this year was among the worst for wildfires in the last 50 years. Some 4.8 million acres (1.9 million hectares) have burned so far this year compared with 1.6 million (650,000 hectares) at the same point last year.</p>
<p>While the lightning added to firefighters' woes in some states, the firefighters were making good progress in other areas such as southwestern Idaho and Oregon, officials said.</p>
<p>A 45,000-acre (18,000-hectare) blaze burning in parts of Yosemite National Park and Stanislaus National Forest in California was 55 percent contained by Wednesday, officials said.</p>
<p>Almost 3,000 firefighters, backed by 133 fire engines, 17 helicopters and two air tankers, were battling the fire, which is approaching the Hetch Hetchy Reservoir, officials said.</p>
<p>Some 1,440 firefighters managed to build fire lines around 40 percent of the Ambrose Complex fire which has charred 15,000 acres (6,000 hectares) of brush and timber in Modoc County in northern California, fire information officer Jenny Farenbaugh said.</p>
<p>Four major powerlines and two natural gas pipelines remain threatened by the lightning-caused fire but they have not been damaged, she said.</p>
<p>The Marple Fire, burning near Lake Castaic about 50 miles (80 km) north of Los Angeles, has blackened 16,100 acres (6,500 hectares) and was only 15 percent contained, the National Interagency Fire Centre said.</p>
<p>The 64,000-acre (26,000-hectare) Salt Complex fire burning in the Hells Canyon National Recreation Area is the largest of a dozen large wildfires burning in Oregon.</p>
<p>A dozen fires have charred 28,430 acres (11,500 hectares) in Idaho while 13 fires have burned 96,240 acres (39,000 hectares) in Nevada, officials said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
