<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19505" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Officials see long haul for western forest fighters.</title>
<headline>Officials see long haul for western forest fighters.</headline>
<byline>Maggie McNeil</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt said on Wednesday raging fires in the Western United States are not likely to be contained soon and he would ask Congress for millions of dollars to get them under control.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be a long, tough summer because there is no real relief in sight,&quot; Babbitt said on NBC's Today Show.</p>
<p>Babbitt, who is in the West assessing the situation, said he would report back to President Bill Clinton and in the next 30 days he will make additional budget requests &quot;in the tens of millions of dollars&quot; to bolster the fire-fighting efforts.</p>
<p>He estimated that $2 million to $3 million is currently being spent daily to fight the fires burning on more than 300,000 acres (120,000 hectares) across Oregon, California, Washington, Idaho, Arizona, Utah, Nevada, Montana and Wyoming.</p>
<p>Babbitt and other officials said the blazes were due in part to a buildup of fuel in forests because of a policy of suppressing fires and that a preventive system of &quot;controlled&quot; fires should be implemented once this fire season is over.</p>
<p>Some officials said it was too late for an infusion of extra resources and longterm forest management in the United States needed to be addressed or the forest fire problem will only worsen in coming years.</p>
<p>Henson Moore, president of the American Forest &amp; Paper Association, a major timber industry group, told a news conference some 47 million acres (19 million hectares) of federal forests were at high risk and urged the passage of so-called forest health legislation to help the U.S. Forest Service manage forests more effectively and cut government red tape.</p>
<p>Moore said forests needed to be thinned of dead and dying trees to reduce dangerous fuel supplies but half of all timber sales on public lands were being delayed by lawsuits and appeals from environmental groups and this has had a detrimental impact on forest management.</p>
<p>He charged that there is a direct cause and effect between lower timber sales and the recent higher rate of forest fires. &quot;Timber sales are being blocked beyond what it takes to help the environment.&quot;</p>
<p>Moore singled out the Sierra Club and what he called other &quot;extremist&quot; environmental groups for stopping timber sales and helping to create a dangerous situation.</p>
<p>Sierra Club officials responded that Moore's group and the timber industry were using a fear of fires to cut more trees. &quot;They are doing some despicable fear-mongering,&quot; said Debbie Sease of the Sierra Club.</p>
<p>She said the environmental group agrees that current forest management policy needs to be changed and the thinning of forests and the use of controlled fires should be started.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
