<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25765" id="root" date="1996-08-31" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-&quot;WE COULDN'T LOSE AT ELLIS PARK&quot; CLAIM SPRINGBOKS.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-&quot;WE COULDN'T LOSE AT ELLIS PARK&quot; CLAIM SPRINGBOKS.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-08-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Springbok coach Andre Markgraaff insisted after his side's 32-22 third test win against New Zealand that South Africa had never contemplated defeat at Ellis Park, scene of their World Cup triumph last year</p>
<p>&quot;We knew for a fact there was no way that New Zealand could beat us at Ellis Park,&quot; said Markgraaff. &quot;We certainly weren't outplayed or outmuscled in the previous two tests and our display today was deserved.&quot;</p>
<p>Captain Gary Teichmann echoed his coach. &quot;The guys played really well and we took our chances...that was the difference from the other two tests. Each test we've got better and better.&quot;</p>
<p>New Zealand coach John Hart refused to be too downbeat. &quot;We won the series and that's what we came here to do. But psychologically the players knew the trip home was there and it was difficult to lift our game at Ellis Park. They deserved to win.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought the referee had a disappointing game, especially in in his interpretations of rucks and mauls. But that didn't cost us the game...the problem was we didn't take our chances.</p>
<p>&quot;Joubert sparked the South African backs and they certainly used the ball a lot more. The South African backs have got heaps of skills, they've just got to be encouraged to use the ball.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-31"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
