<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27814" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Rockslide closes trail in Yosemite National Park.</title>
<headline>Rockslide closes trail in Yosemite National Park.</headline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rockslide brought debris crashing down on a popular hiking trail in California's Yosemite National Park Sunday, but no one was injured, officials said.</p>
<p>The slide occurred less than two months after a powerful rockslide killed one person and injured 14 at Yosemite, a vast, scenic wilderness area 150 miles (240 km) east of San Francisco.</p>
<p>In Sunday's rockslide, stones slid down from a hillside, littering a 200-foot (60-metre) section of the Upper Yosemite Falls trail with debris, rangers said.</p>
<p>Park ranger Kendell Thompson said searchers with dogs had gone through the rockslide area and found no victims. No one was injured or missing, he said.</p>
<p>The trail winds up from the Yosemite valley floor to the top of Yosemite Falls.</p>
<p>Thompson agreed that it was lucky no one was hit by the rockslide. The trail is one of the most popular in the park, but Thompson said it was less busy in late summer than earlier in the year, when Yosemite Falls is running more strongly and is more of a magnet for tourists.</p>
<p>The Labour Day weekend is a peak tourist period at Yosemite National Park.</p>
<p>The trail was closed to hikers and people at the top of the trail, above the rockslide, were led to safety by another route.</p>
<p>The trail will remain closed at least until Tuesday, when experts will be brought in to assess the damage and the debris will be cleared from the trail, Thompson said. The rest of the park is open.</p>
<p>Park ranger Chip Jenkins said the rockslide was &quot;relatively small&quot; and, unlike the July fall, in which a huge section of granite gave way, involved smaller rocks. Rockslides are part of a natural process in Yosemite and happen often, he said.</p>
<p>In the July 10 rockslide, a 31,500-ton slab of granite broke away from a cliff, uprooting about 2,000 trees. Emiliano Morales, a 20-year-old tourist from southern California, was killed by a falling tree, and 14 tourists were injured.</p>
<p>More than 4 million people visit the 1,170-square-mile park each year to see its spectacular mountain scenery and waterfalls, hike, climb, or camp. The park receives about 20,000 visitors per day in summer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
