<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="35053" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pulp mill contract debate divides Alaska town.</title>
<headline>Pulp mill contract debate divides Alaska town.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>The threat of a pulp mill closure has injected fierce emotion into the debate over a controversial long-term timber supply contract.</p>
<p>&quot;Some people are getting real close to losing their livelihood that they've been at for 20 or 30 years and it probably causes them to do something they shouldn't,&quot; said Dick Coose, head of an advocacy group seeking to extend the contract held by Louisiana-Pacific subsidiary Ketchikan Pulp Co.</p>
<p>Coose, a retired government forester now heading Concerned Alaskans for Resources and Environment (CARE), said strong action is needed to reverse decades of logging restrictions in southeast Alaska's Tongass National Forest.</p>
<p>His organization has hired Chuck Cushman, a founder of the radical anti-environmental &quot;Wise Use&quot; movement, to galvanize local action.</p>
<p>&quot;Compromise is probably not a word that we're thinking of right now, because we're the ones that have been compromising for the last 15 or 20 years,&quot; Coose said.</p>
<p>Just ask Jackie Canterbury, a Ketchikan ornithologist who works for an environmental advocacy group. Recently she had a pellet shot into her front window, a brush fire lit in her backyard and a series of harassing telephone calls.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of us have become almost like lepers,&quot; she said of her fellow environmentalists.</p>
<p>She attributes the increased hostility to Cushman's arrival in Ketchikan, a city on the southern tip of the southeast Alaska panhandle.</p>
<p>&quot;When all of these things happen in a period of about six months, and it's never happened before, you can kind of correlate it,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Ketchikan Pulp, which operates a large pulp mill in Ketchikan and saw mills in southeast Alaska, dominates the timber business in the Tongass, a rain forest comprising most of southeast Alaska.</p>
<p>The company says that unless Congress extends the company's 50-year Tongass timber supply contract by October, it will close the pulp mill. The contract is due to run out in 2004, but Ketchikan Pulp says it needs a 15-year extension to secure financing for needed environmental improvements at the aged mill.</p>
<p>If Ketchikan Pulp closes its pulp mill and local saw mill -- both fed with timber from the long-term contract -- the city will lose more than 1,200 jobs and $48 million in payroll, according to a study commissioned for the Ketchikan Gateway Borough.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
