<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39864" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Flood crest closes Washington area roads.</title>
<headline>Flood crest closes Washington area roads.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rising floodwaters in the Potomac River forced the closing of streets near the Lincoln Memorial and throughout Washington on Sunday as the aftermath of Hurricane Fran punished the area.</p>
<p>Electric service had been restored in most of Washington, Maryland and Virginia after being out for nearly 24 hours for thousands of customers, but many roadways had to be closed as the already swollen Potomac crested Sunday evening.</p>
<p>Parks along the Potomac and streets throughout the Mall area of the nation's capital were closed as the flood crest from Hurricane Fran passed through the area, the National Park Service said.</p>
<p>Damage estimates were not immediately available, because park areas were still underwater.</p>
<p>Potomac Electric Power Co. reported 2,400 customers were still without electricity on Sunday afternoon.</p>
<p>After Fran dumped 4 inches (10 cm) of rain in the capital city and up to 14 inches (36 cm) in outlying areas, forecasters said the Potomac would rise 13 feet (four metres) to 15 feet (five metres) where it passes the Georgetown section of Washington and up to 34 feet (10 metres) at Harpers Ferry, West Virginia.</p>
<p>Thousands were forced out of their homes in the Shenandoah Valley region of Virginia over the weekend as the Shenandoah River rose 20 feet (six metres) above flood level.</p>
<p>Rising floodwaters forced the closure late on Sunday of most of the George Washington Parkway, a key route to National Airport on the west bank of the Potomac. Portions of other highways had been closed since midday.</p>
<p>Several national parks in the area remained closed on Sunday, the National Park Service said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're expecting flooding from Theodore Roosevelt Island all the way down the river,&quot; Park Service spokesman Earle Kittleman said. &quot;We also have high tide tonight at six o'clock, and the high tide is going to make it worse.&quot;</p>
<p>The Park Service said it expected heavy damage at the C&amp;O Canal National Historic Park, which reopened in August after $25 million worth of flood damage from snowstorms in January was repaired.</p>
<p>All park areas along the 184-mile-long canal, which stretches from Cumberland, Maryland, to Georgetown, had been closed to the public, the Park Service said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
