<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41320" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Flood takes lives along East Coast, hits Washington.</title>
<headline>Flood takes lives along East Coast, hits Washington.</headline>
<byline>Susan Cornwell</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Washington's memorials were threatened by water on Monday and workers sandbagged a street a few blocks from the White House as the East Coast suffered from the flooding aftermath of Hurricane Fran.</p>
<p>Authorities reported 34 deaths related to Hurricane Fran in five states from South Carolina to Pennsylvania. Rising water from torrential rains swept cars and trucks off roads, washed away storm sewers and trapped people in basements.</p>
<p>With the cleanup still underway, Hurricane Hortense gathered force in the Caribbean, and hurricane warnings were in effect for Puerto Rico and the U.S. and British Virgin Islands.</p>
<p>In Washington, the brown, swirling waters of the Potomac River overflowed the Tidal Basin, crept up 17th Street to a statue of U.S. naval hero John Paul Jones and cut off road access to the Jefferson Memorial.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't get to the Jefferson Memorial by car ... There's water on the roads all around it,&quot; said Earle Kittleman, a spokesman for the National Park Service.</p>
<p>On the bright side, he said a sandbag levee that had been hastily constructed across 17th Street, in the shadow of the Washington Monument, had not been challenged.</p>
<p>&quot;We had been worried that if we didn't put a dike across 17th street, it would flood the Ellipse by the White House. But it never got as high as the levee,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton toured flooded areas of the Potomac by helicopter on Monday afternoon and afterwards added five Virginia counties to those receiving individual aid from the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</p>
<p>&quot;Virginia has been severely affected,&quot; he said. &quot;I want to reassure the people who have suffered that we will provide quick action to help in their urgent time of need.&quot;</p>
<p>The president's helicopter circled over swamped parts of the George Washington Parkway, a key route to National Airport on the west bank of the Potomac. Water was also lapping at the edge of the Watergate complex, the riverside residence of Bob Dole, Clinton's opponent in the November election.</p>
<p>But Clinton said he had been most impressed by scenes upriver at Great Falls, Maryland, where he and Vice President Al Gore had helped clean up debris from flooding earlier this year, and at Washington's Hains Point, where he likes to jog.</p>
<p>&quot;To see it all underwater again ... it really reminds you of the incredible impact that a hurricane and its storm center can have, even in areas where it doesn't directly hit.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton said a main concern now was for Puerto Rico, which was threatened by Hurricane Hortense. Asked whether the U.S. government could afford all these storms, he said, &quot;We'll have to afford as many as we have to sustain.&quot;</p>
<p>He also said much repair work would have to be redone along the C&amp;O Canal National Historic Park on the Potomac, a popular hiking and biking trail which suffered $25 million of flood damage from snowstorms last January.</p>
<p>Hurricane Fran dumped four inches (10 cm) of rain in the U.S. capital on Friday and up to 14 inches (36 cm) in outlying areas. All weekend, the water in area rivers rose. Key roads into the capital were closed on Monday morning and traffic gridlock on the remaining routes was intense. Some commuters in carpools got out and walked.</p>
<p>The Potomac River crested at midnight. Its peak on Washington's outskirts was 7.8 feet (2.4 metres) above flood stage, said Donovan Kelly of the U.S. Geological Survey. But the water was only receeding slowly.</p>
<p>Things were worse in the Shenandoah River valley, said Jim Gerhart, also of the U.S. Geological Survey. At Millville, West Virginia, the water in the Shenandoah was 13.5 feet (4.1 metres) above flood stage, he said.</p>
<p>Track washouts and signal problems forced Amtrak to cancel service on Monday on two East Coast trains: the Silver Meteor from New York to Miami, and the Auto Train between Virginia and Florida, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>He said service on the Silver Meteor would resume on Tuesday, but that it was expected passengers would have to get out of the train at Richmond, Virginia, and be bussed to Florence, South Carolina, where they would re-board.</p>
<p>In North Carolina, which was hit hardest by the hurricane, state emergency office officials said housing losses would amount to $900 million plus business losses of $30 million. More than 965,000 people remained without power in the state.</p>
<p>Fran took the lives of 15 people in North Carolina, and two in South Carolina. In Virginia, 12 died -- eight of them in vehicles swept off the road, and four while working on a storm sewer.</p>
<p>In Pennsylvania, three people died, including two trapped in a basement by rising floodwaters in a Philadelphia suburb. Two people died in West Virginia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
