<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50327" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Flood of comment delays U.S. plan on Tongass forest.</title>
<headline>Flood of comment delays U.S. plan on Tongass forest.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Forest Service's proposal to reduce logging in the nation's largest national forest led to a record number of comments that will take extra time to evaluate, officials said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Forest Service expected to release a final Tongass management plan later this month, Forest Service spokeswoman Pamela Finney said, but it was wading through nearly 22,000 letters, cards and questionaire forms received on the Tongass Land Management Plan.</p>
<p>Now, &quot;What we're looking at is sometime later in the fall (autumn),&quot; Finney said.</p>
<p>It received more letters on Tongass than for any single forest plan in the nation, exceeding even the 14,000 comments on the recent plan for reintroducing wolves to the Yellowstone National Park area, the Forest Service said.</p>
<p>Earlier this year the Forest Service released its plan to reduce allowable logging in the Tongass and impose new protections for wildlife, salmon and caves.</p>
<p>The 17 million-acre Tongass, which sprawls over islands, mountains, glaciers, includes most of the southeast Alaska panhandle. Its rain-drenched old growth stands are home to plentiful wildlife and ancient archaeological artifacts that have been found in caves.</p>
<p>Environmentalists believe the ecological and cultural resources are threatened by logging.</p>
<p>Logging supporters argued that the Tongass plan will stifle their industry and harm the region's economy.</p>
<p>They sought a delay in adoption of the final Tongass plan to allow more arguments on behalf of the timber industry.</p>
<p>In addition, Ketchikan Pulp Co., a wholly owned subsidiary of Louisiana-Pacific Corp, sought a 15-year extension of its long-term supply contract for Tongass timber.</p>
<p>The dominant company in the Tongass timber business, Ketchikan Pulp holds a 50-year supply contract that runs out in 2004. The company said it would have to close its Ketchikan, Alaska, pulp mill this year if it did not get a contract extension.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
