<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52215" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ketchikan Pulp may turn to Clinton for help.</title>
<headline>Ketchikan Pulp may turn to Clinton for help.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>With little support emerging in U.S.. Congress for extending Ketchikan Pulp Co's controversial timber supply contract, the company may turn to President Bill Clinton to prop up its ageing southeast Alaska pulp mill.</p>
<p>On behalf of the company, Alaska Governor Tony Knowles has arranged a meeting next week between top Agriculture Department officials and Louisiana-Pacific Corp, Ketchikan Pulp's owner, to discuss a possible administrative act extending the contract 15 years past its scheduled 2004 expiration.</p>
<p>But compromises are needed to reach any agreement that would extend the deal that provides low-priced timber from the Tongass National Forest, said Bob King, press secretary for Democrat Knowles.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not up to us to negotiate that. It's up to the two parties involved to reach that agreement,&quot; King said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Critics of the proposed extension say it would continue an anti-competitive, taxpayer-subsidised &quot;sweetheart deal&quot; for logging that damages the environment of the Tongass, the largest U.S. national forest.</p>
<p>Clinton last month vowed to veto contract-extending legislation authored by Frank Murkowski, the Alaska Republican who chairs the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
<p>The company says it needs the contract extension by next month, to justify modernisation, or it will close its mill in Ketchikan, Alaska.</p>
<p>That would wipe out 30 percent of the city's jobs, Ernesta Ballard, a Ketchikan Pulp consultant and president of the Ketchikan Chamber of Commerce, said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;When you have a well-integrated community and the lifeblood is taken out of it, that has a devastating effect,&quot; Ballard told the Resource Development Council of Alaska, an Anchorage-based pro-industry group.</p>
<p>The legislative director of Taxpayers for Common Sense, a nonpartisan Washington, D.C. group that opposes the contract extension, rejected Ballard's contention.</p>
<p>The Forest Service lost $102 million between 1992 and 1994 on Tongass logging, &quot;so it's hardly a break-even deal,&quot; said Jill Lancelot. &quot;It's a taxpayers' nightmare. It's an environmental nightmare. For those who care about the free market, it flies in the face of that.&quot;</p>
<p>Alaska's all-Republican Congressional delegation is seeking to attach a Ketchikan Pulp amendment to the Omnibus Parks Bill pending in Congress.</p>
<p>Lancelot said passage through that or any other major bill was unlikely. &quot;But we're ever vigilant and ever watchful. We'll fight like hell to keep it out.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
