<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55848" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton deciding whether to protect Utah canyons.</title>
<headline>Clinton deciding whether to protect Utah canyons.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton is weighing whether to proclaim a scenic southern Utah redrock area a national monument, potentially fending off a huge proposed coal mine, an administration official said Monday.</p>
<p>Clinton may announce a decision on a plan to protect the land from mining, road-building and other development when he speaks at the Grand Canyon Wednesday, the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;The president has not made a decision on whether to designate the area as a national monument. But he'll be at the Grand Canyon and he'll be talking about the environment,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>The proposal would safeguard 1.7-1.8 million acres including Grand Staircase adjacent to Bryce Canyon National Park, Kaiparowits Plateau adjacent to Glen Canyon National Recreation Area, and Esclante basin adjacent to Capital Reef National Park, according to the Southern Utah Wilderness Alliance, which backs the plan.</p>
<p>Utah's congressional delegation opposes the idea, saying it would lock up resources including a tract of high-quality coal that Andalex Resources Corp. -- a Dutch-owned company -- wants to mine.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a trial balloon they've sent up without any specific details. What's frustrating thing about this executive branch land-grab is it's being done without public hearings or congressional input,&quot; said an aide to Utah Republican Sen. Orrin Hatch.</p>
<p>Hatch sponsored a bill that would have designated a portion of this land as protected wilderness, but environmentalists said the bill would have opened other huge tracts of the state's scenic rockrock lands to development.</p>
<p>Hatch and other Utah lawmakers complained the White House plan being considered could stymie the Andalex mine, cutting off a source of jobs and revenue for the schools.</p>
<p>Andalex has mining leases that would not be affected, but government and environmental sources said the designation would draw far more government scrutiny on roads and other necessary infrastructure.</p>
<p>&quot;The proposal and the option is to create a national monument that would protect one of the most beautiful and culturally and scientifically important places in the United States forever,&quot; the administration official said.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of people are focused on the Andalex mine because it seems to be the nearest threat,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The underground mine would have minimal effect on the surface, an Andalex spokesman said. But the Southern Utah Wilderness Alliance called it &quot;a 39-sq-mile sinkhole waiting to happen.&quot;</p>
<p>Mike Matz of the alliance said he believed the plan would allow grazing and hunting on the land, but an aide to Representative William Orton, a Utah Democrat, said those issues remained unanswered, along with questions of water rights, lost tax revenues, and access to state lands.</p>
<p>&quot;To curry favour with national environmental groups they want to put a stop to this (Andalex mine) by proclamation, and it would have an incredibly damaging effect on the Utah school system,&quot; Orton's aide said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
