<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58514" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Meeting touted as effort to rescue pulp mill.</title>
<headline>Meeting touted as effort to rescue pulp mill.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Top government and corporate officials will seek to negotiate a reprieve for the troubled Ketchikan Pulp Co. mill at a meeting Wednesday in Washington.</p>
<p>The meeting, between Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman, Alaska Gov. Tony Knowles, Alaska's Congressional delegation and Louisiana-Pacific Corp. Chairman Mark Suwyn, has been touted as a last-ditch effort to avert a shutdown of the pulp mill owned by the company's Ketchikan subsidiary.</p>
<p>Knowles said he is hopeful about a possible compromise.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm an advocate for the comunity of Ketchikan, for the jobs and families of Ketchikan, and I want to see a positive result,&quot; he said last week when he announced he was postponing an Asia trade mission to attend the Washington meeting, which he organized.</p>
<p>Louisiana-Pacific says that unless it gets a 15-year extension of its controversial contract for timber from the Tongass National Forest, and unless there is a repeal of several environmental reforms passed by Congress in the sweeping 1990 Tongass Timber Reform Act, it will close its Ketchikan mill.</p>
<p>Louisiana-Pacific chairman Mark Suwyn said the company needs an extension of the 50-year contract, now due to run out in 2004, and a rollback of environmental regulations, by this month to avert a shutdown.</p>
<p>Louisiana-Pacific has lost money in recent years on its entire pulp division, but mostly on the Ketchikan Pulp facility, which is more than 40 years old, needs at least $180 million in upgrades to meet regulations and the terms of a criminal settlement on pollution charges.</p>
<p>Ketchikan Pulp spokesman Troy Reinhart said the mill anticipates an annual loss of at least $40 million this year. He blamed that record on environmental restrictions wrought by the Tongass Timber Reform Act.</p>
<p>&quot;If it wasn't for the Forest Service's illegal, unilateral contract modification that Congress directed it to do, we would be profitable. We would not be a drag on the company,&quot; Reinhart said.</p>
<p>Critics regard the Ketchikan Pulp contract as an anachronistic subsidy that harms the environment of the Tongass, the largest U.S. national forest, is costly to taxpayers and stifles market competition.</p>
<p>A contract-extending bill authored by Frank Murkowski, the Alaska Republican who chairs the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee, has encountered opposition from both political parties.</p>
<p>Knowles, a Democrat, said the state can do little more to ease Ketchikan Pulp's woes, pointing out that eight years remain on the current contract.</p>
<p>Ketchikan Pulp's fate is ultimately a business decision for Louisiana-Pacific, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no control over the world price of pulp or what their strategy is with their company in terms of what role pulp plays in Louisiana-Pacific's business strategy. You'll have to ask them,&quot; he said in a news conference.</p>
<p>Knowles has been under fire from Alaska Republicans who say he has done too little to protect Ketchikan Pulp from environmental policies of the Democratic Clinton administration.</p>
<p>In a campaign coordinated by a founder of the pro-development &quot;Wise Use&quot;  movement, mill supporters have distributed bumper stickers and buttons that query: &quot;Where's Tony?&quot; -- accusing the governor of being a no-show in the Ketchikan Pulp battle.</p>
<p>Last week, before Knowles postponed his Asia trip, Suwyn joined the criticism of the governor.</p>
<p>&quot;If it were my state, and my constituents were about to have the whole southeastern part of my state to be obliterated economically, i guess I would be extraordinarily involved,&quot; Suwyn told reporters last week in Washington.</p>
<p>--U.S. Municipal Desk, 212-859-1650</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
