<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62212" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton's green rhetoric masks a mixed record.</title>
<headline>Clinton's green rhetoric masks a mixed record.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton will use a visit to the Grand Canyon Wednesday as a vast backdrop to stress his environmental record and announce a plan to protect wilderness in Utah, but analysts described his performance on the environment as mixed.</p>
<p>Wednesday's appearance, where he is expected to proclaim nearly two million acres of Utah redrock canyons and plateaus safe from mining and development, is the latest in a series of postcard-setting events Clinton has used to blast Republicans as anti-environment.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see Bill Clinton as a dyed-in-the-wool environmentalist. I think he understands the power of this issue to mobilize both the mass public and crucial Democratic party constituencies,&quot; said Christopher Foreman, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution.</p>
<p>&quot;The president has discovered he can use the environment as an issue to beat the Republicans with, so the rhetoric is a lot stronger,&quot; said Terry Davies, of Resources for the Future, a Washington-based research institute.</p>
<p>But the plan to protect the scenic Utah lands drew fire from all of Utah's congressmen, who said it would kill development of huge untapped reserves of high-quality coal, costing the state jobs and tax revenue.</p>
<p>An aide to Utah's one Democratic congressman, Rep. William Orton, said Clinton was still undecided on whether to designate the land a national monument.</p>
<p>&quot;He met with (White House Chief of Staff) Leon Panetta today and the congressman is going to be talking with the president at some point this evening. We're hoping we can influence him in a final decision,&quot; Orton's aide said.</p>
<p>In the environmental arena, Clinton mainly has been successful in blocking Republican initiatives, but has failed to pass most of his own, analysts said.</p>
<p>But they said Clinton failed to stop legislation last year that sharply increased logging in national forests, which wilderness advocates said will haunt him even this week at the Grand Canyon.</p>
<p>&quot;From our perspective the drama tomorrow will be Clinton there announcing the new national monument, and a group of forest activists will be nearby to call attention to a new salvage (logging) sale,&quot; said Jim Jontz, executive director of the Western Ancient Forest Campaign.</p>
<p>&quot;The administration admits they dropped the ball on that. Clinton is taking positive steps, but the bleeding from the logging rider certainly mars his record,&quot; Jontz said.</p>
<p>Clinton signed the measure pushed by the timber industry to increase cutting of salvage timber, or sick and dead trees. But the language was broad enough that it allowed logging of green trees, and forced the government to let the timber industry cut ancient trees in the Pacific Northwest that previously had been blocked to protect endangered species.</p>
<p>Clinton later said he regretted signing the measure, which was part of a broad spending bill, and called for its partial repeal.</p>
<p>The Justice Department announced late Tuesday that it had reached agreement with 15 companies to replace the old-growth timber sales with trees from other areas, and said the replacement sales would have to meet all environmental laws.</p>
<p>Clinton balked at later attempts by Republicans to insert into broad spending bills measures to ease pollution rules or give industries more access to natural resources. That contributed to last winter's budget impasse that partially closed the government.</p>
<p>Backed by Republican moderates, Clinton also fended off efforts to weaken the federal government's power to enforce environmental, health and safety regulations, and to gut major pollution laws such as the Clean Air Act.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
