<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62292" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton plans to protect Utah wilderness area.</title>
<headline>Clinton plans to protect Utah wilderness area.</headline>
<byline>Laurence McQuillan</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Promoting his environmental record as a way to court voters, President Bill Clinton on Wednesday planned to protect vast stretches of redrock canyons and plateaus in Utah from development.</p>
<p>Clinton, who was to fly to Arizona early in the day, was the use the majestic panorama of the Grand Canyon to announce a decision already being hailed by environmentalists and denounced by those opposed to curbs on mining and other development.</p>
<p>&quot;I fully expect the president will say ... that he does intend to proceed with the national monument designation for this very pristine and beautiful area,&quot; said a senior administration official, who was accompanying Clinton on a four-day campaign swing through the Midwest and West.</p>
<p>&quot;There are some procedural questions about how to make that announcement that are still being wrestled with,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Clinton was expected to protect the land from mining, road-building and other development in order, as one official said, &quot;to preserve this very beautiful wilderness area for future generations of Americans.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton's action is based on the same legal authority that President Theodore Roosevelt used to safeguard the Grand Canyon itself in 1908, and he planned to stand in roughly the same spot that was used by his predecessor to make his announcement.</p>
<p>The plan would safeguard 1.7-1.8 million acres (about 700,000 hectares), including Grand Staircase adjacent to Bryce Canyon National Park, Kaiparowits Plateau adjacent to Glen Canyon National Recreation Area, and Esclante basin adjacent to Capital Reef National Park, according to the Southern Utah Wilderness Alliance, which supports the move.</p>
<p>Utah's congressional delegation opposes the idea, saying it would lock up resources including a tract of high-quality coal that Andalex Resources Corp. -- a Dutch-owned company -- wants to mine.</p>
<p>Utah Gov. Michael Leavitt, a Republican, met in Washington on Tuesday with White House Chief of Staff Leon Panetta to try and stop or modify the move, as did Representative William Orton, the only Democrat in the Utah delegation.</p>
<p>Utah's congressmen, all of whom oppose the proposal, have said they felt the White House should hold hearings and involve the public before determining the use of an area larger than Grand Canyon National Park.</p>
<p>They also complained the proposal would kill the Andalex plan to develop a huge subsurface mine containing major untapped reserves of high-quality coal.</p>
<p>Clinton has been promoting his record on the environment -- which environmentalists call mixed, but better than the efforts pushed by the Republican-controlled Congress during the past two years.</p>
<p>In one example, the federal government on Tuesday reached a landmark deal with 15 timber companies that averts the sale of old-growth forests in the Pacific Northwest and ensures that alternative timber sales must meet federal environmental laws.</p>
<p>Public opinion polls have found broad support for protecting the environment, with most voters saying they feel Clinton would be more likely to back programmes that do that then Republican rival Bob Dole.</p>
<p>In August, Clinton interrupted a vacation in Wyoming to visit Yellowstone National Park and announce an agreement stopping mining operations at New World Mine, located on the fringe of the park.</p>
<p>That announcement, coupled with Clinton's move to protect lands in southern Utah, has strengthened the president's standing in much of the West -- a region traditionally considered a Republican stronghold.</p>
<p>Clinton, who campaigned on Tuesday in Michigan and Illinois, also planned to visit Oregon, Washington and South Dakota before returning to Washington late on Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
