<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65284" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clintons, Gores back on the bus in Northwest.</title>
<headline>Clintons, Gores back on the bus in Northwest.</headline>
<byline>Steve Holland</byline>
<dateline>SEATTLE, Wash. 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton and Vice President Al Gore and their wives are climbing aboard their bus again on Thursday for a Pacific Northwest tour stressing pro-environment policies popular in this land where the people love their outdoors.</p>
<p>They are calling it a bus tour &quot;on the road to the 21st century,&quot; a Clinton campaign metaphor second only to the president's countless appeals to voters to help him &quot;build a bridge&quot; to the new century.</p>
<p>It will be the second bus tour of this campaign for Clinton and Gore, who made it a staple of their 1992 campaign. It will take them from the busy port city of Seattle through rural towns in western Washington state southward about 175 miles (281 km) to the Oregon city of Portland.</p>
<p>Central themes of the day-long road tour are the environment, Pacific trade vital to this region and the economy. Clinton, who earlier in his term got mixed reviews from environmental groups, told a large crowd in Seattle on Wednesday night that he has a strong record on the environment.</p>
<p>&quot;We are working to save our national treasures,&quot; Clinton told thousands at a Seattle rally.</p>
<p>He had just come from Grand Canyon National Park in Arizona, where on a cliff overlooking the vast canyon he signed a proclamation declaring 1.7 million acres (688,000 hectares) of remote redrock land in southern Utah a national monument and thus protected against coal mining.</p>
<p>He also crowed about a deal his administration struck on Tuesday with 15 timber companies to protect several tracts of old-growth forests in Washington and Oregon in exchange for logging substitute trees in areas less critical to fish and wildlife.</p>
<p>There was also a recent agreement aimed at protecting and restoring salmon in the Northwest's Columbia River, and a tentative deal to keep a gold mine from being developed near Yellowstone National Park in Wyoming.</p>
<p>While Clinton boasts of achievements, Gore is taking on the role of attacking the Republican-led Congress for having &quot;turned its back on the notion of stewardship&quot; of the environment.</p>
<p>&quot;They have broken faith with this vital American tradition,&quot; Gore said at the Grand Canyon. &quot;They've made a mockery of the notion of protection. They've sought not to protect our health or that of the environment but rather to protect those who seek license to pollute.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton has big leads over Republican challenger Bob Dole in Washington, and analysts say Dole seems to be conceding the states to the Democratic incumbent since he is spending no noticeable advertising money here.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEATTLE, Wash."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
