<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71517" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-New South Wales changes timber logging quotas.</title>
<headline>RTRS-New South Wales changes timber logging quotas.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New South Wales state government said on Monday it would replace the current yearly quota allocations for timber logging in the state with five-year term agreements.</p>
<p>&quot;Yearly quota allocations of timber will be replaced by five-year term agreements with scope for an additional five years, conditional on millers demonstrating a commitment to value adding,&quot; lands minister Kim Yeadon said in a statement.</p>
<p>Yeadon said the commitment to timber supply would be underpinned by tradeable five-year term agreements for 50 percent of 1995/96 sawlog quotas.  </p>
<p>Yeadon said there would be no change to supply levels until July 1, 1997 giving industry players time to consider investment options and plan for their futures.</p>
<p>He said the state government would also provide a A$120 million forest industry structural adjustment package.</p>
<p>The government would also embark on an aggressive programme to buy private forested land in order to maintain a guaranteed flow to the timber industry.  </p>
<p>He said this resource will be sustainably harvested and sold to the timber industry at market prices to ensure ongoing abiliy to meet allocations for the next three years and term agreements.</p>
<p>The minister said 10 new national parks would be created under the plan and 12 new wilderness areas.</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
