<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75471" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: National parks bill stalls in U.S. Senate.</title>
<headline>National parks bill stalls in U.S. Senate.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>The White House Wednesday threatened to veto a bill to help raise funds for national parks, complaining the package agreed to by House and Senate conferees would hurt parks and a national forest in Alaska.</p>
<p>Most environmental groups also opposed the bill because it would let the government license corporations to become national parks sponsors and use that in their advertising, a move that critics said would cheapen and commercialize the national treasures.</p>
<p>While the administration had backed corporate sponsorship as a way to help pay for the parks' staggering backlog of repairs, the plan came under increasing fire and was the target of a number of advertisements and editorials.</p>
<p>Eleven Senate Democrats in a letter Wednesday slammed the bill, saying it would introduce &quot;commercialism into one of America's last non-commercial refuges&quot; while raising a tiny fraction of money the parks need.</p>
<p>But backers argued it was an essential tool to raise money, and said the bill had safeguards to prevent businesses from exploiting and commercializing the parks.</p>
<p>The White House did not mention the corporate sponsorship plan in its veto threat, but cited several other complaints.</p>
<p>Those included a plan to continue a logging company's exclusive contract for timber in Alaska's Tongass National Forest, boundary changes in a few parks, erosion of coastal barrier island protections in Florida and changes in regulating rights-of-way across federal lands.</p>
<p>The bill, loaded with projects in some 41 states, also would have let the financially-troubled parks raise entrance fees, create five parks, and set up a trust fund to manage San Fransisco's Presidio national park.</p>
<p>&quot;We contacted the White House and asked for their views. We took out some controversial measures,&quot; said an aide to House Resources Committee Chairman Don Young, an Alaska Republican who was one of the bill's sponsors.</p>
<p>&quot;Now it seems like the president wants to kill the whole thing. So if that's what he wants to do he kills the whole package,&quot; said the aide, who said there were no plans to spin off parts of the bill into other legislation.</p>
<p>&quot;The administration's letter is full of factual errors and appears to be based on the false hope any related bills will move separate from the conference report,&quot; Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Chairman Frank Murkowski, also an Alaska Republican, said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;They had better do their homework and get back to me in the morning,&quot; Murkowski said.</p>
<p>One of the measures conferees dropped would have extended for 15 years an exclusive contract held by the Ketchikan Pulp Co for timber in Alaska's Tongass National Forest.</p>
<p>But the bill would have transferred eight remaining years of the pulp mill's exclusive contract to Ketchikan's sawmills, which environmentalists and the White House also opposed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
