<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75641" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: House-Senate conferees agree on national parks bill.</title>
<headline>House-Senate conferees agree on national parks bill.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>House and Senate negotiators reached agreement on a bill to help fund national parks through corporate sponsorships and to let national parks raise their entrance fees, lawmakers said Wednesday.</p>
<p>The bill, whose final passage remained uncertain in the congressional session's waning few days, also would create five parks, set up a trust to manage the San Francisco Presidio -- a former military installation being turned into a park -- and establish several new memorials.</p>
<p>Alaska Republican Sen. Frank Murkowski, one of the sponsors, told a news conference contentious measures were stripped from the bill in an effort to get it passed in the session's final days.</p>
<p>&quot;In a presidential year, obtaining the votes to override a veto would have been impossible,&quot; Murkowski said. &quot;We made a necessary compromise to save other important measures.&quot;</p>
<p>A spokesman for Senate Democratic Leader Tom Daschle of South Dakota said he was still weighing whether to accept the bill and environmental sources said there were rumblings other senators may move to block it. This late in the session, any opposition likely would kill the bill.</p>
<p>Among measures dropped from the bill was one pushed by Murkowski to extend an exclusive contract held by the Ketchikan Pulp Co for access to timber in Alaska's Tongass National Forest. The bill would transfer eight remaining years of the pulp mill's exclusive contract to timber from the Tongass temperate rainforest to Ketchikan's sawmills, which environmentalists also opposed.</p>
<p>Also dropped was a Republican-backed plan to reform grazing fees on federal land, which the White House rejected, and a measure that would have freed up large tracts of Utah wilderness for development.</p>
<p>California Democratic Sens. Barbara Boxer and Dianne Feinstein said the bill had important benefits for their state and had bipartisan support. But environmentalists opposed corporate sponsorship for parks, saying it would cheapen the national treasures.</p>
<p>&quot;We have grave reservations about anything that would commercialize the parks,&quot; said Chuck Clussen of the Natural Resources Defence Council.</p>
<p>Critics also said the bill would discourage the federal government from funding parks, letting corporations pick up the slack, and would make the Interior secretary regulator of corporations that are raising funds for his deparment's parks.</p>
<p>But backers argued it was essential to get money to refurbish the parks and said the bill had safeguards to prevent businesses from commercializing parks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
