<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76612" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pulp firm's new Tongass offer draws mixed reviews.</title>
<headline>Pulp firm's new Tongass offer draws mixed reviews.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>With the shutdown of its money-losing Ketchikan pulp mill likely, Louisiana-Pacific Corp. has offered to keep its two Alaska saw mills open as long as the federal government keeps a controversial timber-supply contract intact.</p>
<p>That plan, submitted to Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman last week, would save some 500 jobs that would otherwise be lost if Louisiana-Pacific unit Ketchikan Pulp Co. pulls out of southeast Alaska entirely.</p>
<p>&quot;This proposal is offered in good faith as a route to maintain a portion of the economy of southeast Alaska despite the shutdown of the pulp mill which is the centrepiece around which the economy has been built over the past 42 years,&quot; Mark Suwyn, Louisiana-Pacific chief executive, said in a letter to Glickman.</p>
<p>But the proposal contradicts the intent of the contract for timber from the Tongass National Forest, the largest U.S. national forest. The 50-year contract, set to run out in 2004, was set up to guarantee operation of a pulp mill to provide local employment and a market for low-quality wood.</p>
<p>For the rest of Alaska's timber industry, the pulp mill -- not Louisiana-Pacific's saw mills, which use high-grade timber desired by other companies -- is the key benefit of the contract, one official said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Ketchikan Pulp mill has always provided a home for the low-end log, which is a difficult log to get rid of,&quot; said John Sturgeon, chief executive of Anchorage-based Koncor Forest Products. &quot;To have the pulp mill go away is very, very disturbing to us.&quot;</p>
<p>For several weeks, Lousiana-Pacific has been threatening to close the pulp mill unless Congress and the Clinton administration grant a 15-year extension of the timber supply contract.</p>
<p>The Ketchikan plant, the largest private employer in the southeast Alaksa city of 15,000, is expected to lose at least $40 million this year, Ketchikan Pulp spokesman Troy Reinhart said.</p>
<p>Under the new Louisiana-Pacific proposal, negotiations over a possible contract extension would be deferred.</p>
<p>Louisiana-Pacific said its new offer would reduce Ketchikan Pulp's annual timber consumption from 192.5 million board feet to 165 million board feet.</p>
<p>U.S. Forest Service officials have said Ketchikan Pulp is guaranteed only about 150 million board feet a year from the existing contract.</p>
<p>One environmentalist scoffed at Lousiana-Pacific's latest offer.</p>
<p>&quot;KPC is giving up timber that it doesn't have and asking for timber it's not entitled to,&quot; said Buck Lindekugel of the Southeast Alaska Conservation Council.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
