<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78720" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lawmakers try to salvage U.S. national parks bill.</title>
<headline>Lawmakers try to salvage U.S. national parks bill.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>House and Senate Republicans Thursday tried to salvage legislation that would help raise money for national parks and add new parks and memorials after the White House threatened to veto the bill.</p>
<p>With just a few days remaining in the session, congressional sources said pressure was on to reach a deal on the bill that offered parks projects in 37 states.</p>
<p>&quot;We're still working with it,&quot; said an aide to Representative James Hansen, a Utah Republican who chairs a key subcommittee.</p>
<p>&quot;Talks are continuing on the bill and we certainly hope we can reach a satisfactory conclusion,&quot; said an aide to Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Chairman Frank Murkowski, an Alaska Republican.</p>
<p>The bill became a political hot potato as environmental groups blasted its plan to let the government license corporations to be national park sponsors and use that in their advertising.</p>
<p>The White House, which had backed a corporate sponsorship plan to help finance the ailing parks, cited other objections to the bill in its veto threat.</p>
<p>Those included proposed boundary reductions at two Virginia parks, providing national flood insurance for Florida barrier islands to allow increased development, and continuing a logging company's exclusive contract for timber in Alaska's Tongass National Forest.</p>
<p>Environmentalists said those were among the bill's many flaws, which they said included special deals for developers, environmental waivers, and continued favourable treatment of parks concessionares while parks visitors would pay higher entrance fees.</p>
<p>&quot;Most distressing is that these indefensible provisions, which could never pass on their own merits, will likely lead to the demise of a bill that began as a laudable and popular effort to protect the tallgrass prairie in Kansas, the Sterling Forest on the New York, New Jersey border, and the Presidio in San Francisco,&quot; Greg Wetstone, of the Natural Resources Defence Council, said in a statement.</p>
<p>The National Parks and Conservation Association, a parks advocacy group, also backed the White House veto threat.</p>
<p>But it urged that a few measures -- such as establishing a private trust to manage the Presidio and creation of the Kansas prairie reserve -- be rolled into the sweeping spending bill Congress is working on.</p>
<p>However Murkowski has insisted that he would not allow any provisions to be spun off into a separate spending bill, a stand he repeated early Thursday.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott, of Mississippi, said Congress repeatedly accommodated the White House with changes in the bill. &quot;And then the administration shows up and says, oh, well, yes, but.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They're going to stop this many good projects, including the Presidio, over a list of really minor objections?  I have problems with what they're doing here,&quot; Lott said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
