<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80497" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: High level U.S. budget talks go into night.</title>
<headline>High level U.S. budget talks go into night.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The White House has told federal agencies to be ready for possible closure next week even as President Bill Clinton and senior lawmakers promised they would not let that happen.</p>
<p>Clinton and Republican leaders of Congress were late Thursday continuing their intense negotiations on money and policies -- including immigration reforms, banking law reforms, and health care -- which may be folded together into a massive spending bill needed to keep the government running after Tuesday.</p>
<p>White House Chief of Staff Leon Panetta, House and Senate Appropriations Committee leaders of both parties, and a multitude of staff met in the Capitol for a bargaining session that was to last late into the night. Meanwhile, a separate meeting was held to iron out differences on immigration. Democrats object to provisions they say are meanspirited towards legal immigrants.</p>
<p>The budget negotiations were called &quot;feverish&quot; by Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott of Mississippi, who said an agreement was likely soon. &quot;You know, we've basically honoured the bulk of what they've asked for,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The bill will include around $6.5 billion in extra spending Clinton wanted for education, anti-terrorism and to combat illegal drugs. To pay for this, the government plans to auction airwaves for wireless communications and raise thrift reserve deposits.</p>
<p>Office of Management and Budget Director Franklin Raines sent out a letter to agency heads telling them if neither full 1997 funds nor short-term funds were cleared by Oct. 1, &quot;agencies ... will experience a lapse in legal authority to enter into obligations and will be forced to implement their shutdown plans.&quot;</p>
<p>Polls show the public blamed last winter's two partial government closures on Republican congressional leaders and their &quot;shutdown strategy,&quot; designed to force Clinton to accept deep cuts in domestic spending. Republican leaders note Congress will have saved $53 billion in fiscal years 1995, 1996 and 1997.</p>
<p>Both sides are hoping to wrap up this year's round of budget negotiations cleanly and quickly in order to avoid voter wrath on national election day on Nov. 5.</p>
<p>Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin said he could not imagine anyone wanted to see federal agencies closed again and thought all sides would agree on a 1997 spending bill before the Oct. 1 start of the new fiscal year.</p>
<p>&quot;If that didn't happen, you'd obviously have some kind of a short term C.R. (continuing resolution) to carry you through until the final deal is worked out,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Clinton told his Democrats at a rally on Capitol Hill that he believed the public wanted a Congress elected that would &quot;never, ever shut the government down. And I am committed to that and I know they are.&quot;</p>
<p>But top Democrats said any deal on spending was far off.</p>
<p>The House Appropriations Committee's senior Democrat David Obey of Wisconsin called &quot;nonsense&quot; statements by Lott and other Republicans that an agreement was near and said there were 200 outstanding issues.</p>
<p>Democrats said they would push to take guns away from convicted child and spouse abusers and to give doctors a clear right to inform managed care patients of all treatments. They also object to a Republican plan to withhold U.S. aid from international agencies that use private funds to pay for abortion services.</p>
<p>Each year Congress must pass, and the president sign into law, 13 appropriations bills for all the activities of the government except health care, social security and other automatic payments. To date, five have been signed and two more are ready to be signed.</p>
<p>Left unfunded are the military, law enforcement agencies, the White House, the Treasury Department, environmental clean-up, the national parks, U.S. embassies and foreign policy agencies, the National Institutes of Health, and a host of other government agencies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
