<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81592" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Republicans say Clinton playing politics with parks.</title>
<headline>Republicans say Clinton playing politics with parks.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Senate Republicans angrily accused President Clinton Friday of using a national parks bill that would affect 41 states to punish his opponents.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a power-play to punish the states where the president's ratings are not high enough,&quot; Sen. Hank Brown of Colorado said. &quot;This is wrong politics to punish those who won't go along&quot; in Clinton's re-election bid, he said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, talks were continuing to try to salvage the national parks bill after the White House sent its sponsors a long list of objections including provisions for corporations to become licensed national parks sponsors, a parks entrance fee hike and a number of boundary changes and land transfers that critics said gave sweet deals to special interests.</p>
<p>Environmental groups opposed the bill, saying a number of objectionable provisions had been added to it. They also opposed the corporate sponsorship plan, saying it would commercialize the parks.</p>
<p>But Senate Republican aides said the White House was threatening to veto the bill for some provisions that it initially supported -- such as parks fund-raising measures -- and was singling out initiatives sponsored by Republicans.</p>
<p>Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Chairman Frank Murkowski accused the White House of conducting a strategy of &quot;cherrypicking&quot; the items it wanted, then plotting to force Congress to include them in its sweeping spending bill while other measures died.</p>
<p>&quot;Here we are, picking the bones of this legislation,&quot; the Alaska Republican said. He said he opposed efforts to include selected items in a broad spending bill while killing the huge package of projects that House and Senate conferees agreed to.</p>
<p>Reading a list of sponsors of measures the White House sought to delete, Murkowski said, &quot;It's rather intersting to identify who's on these because there's a certain amount of partisanship that you can't help but see as a reality.&quot;</p>
<p>Measures backed by the White House and environmentalists included establishing a trust to manage the former Presidio military installation as a park in San Francisco, protecting the Sterling Forest on the New York-New Jersey border and establishing a tallgrass prairie reserve in Kansas.</p>
<p>Senate aides said talks to break the impasse continued while Democrats used technical procedures to bar Murkowski from bringing the the bill to the floor.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is an agreement in principle on how to solve the problems, then these procedural problems will melt away,&quot; a Republican aide said.</p>
<p>With Congress to adjourn early next week, congressional sources said the House likely would be able to move quickly on the bill if a deal was reached with the administration.</p>
<p>At midday, White House Chief of Staff Leon Panetta told a reporter: &quot;They are still talking but chances have diminished in  the last hour&quot; to include parks measures in the spending bill.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
