<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82966" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>NORWAY: PRESS DIGEST - Norway - Sept 27.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Norway - Sept 27.</headline>
<dateline>OSLO 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the leadong stories in Norwegian papers this morning:</p>
<p>AFTENPOSTEN</p>
<p>- Offshore and construction company Aker ASA has reached a settlement with an insurance group over the sinking of the Sleipner oil platform in Gandsfjorden in 1991. The insurance group had demanded 2.3 billion crowns, Aker will pay 340 million crowns.</p>
<p>- Head of chemicals company Dyno ASA, Arild Ingierd, says he sees no moral problem with Dyno's activities in Vietman although the government is communist and bureaucratic. Dyno is building a glue factory in Vietnam which will be finished in 1997.</p>
<p>- At NATO's defence ministers' meeting in Bergen Norway's Joergen Kosmo has joined forces with the American and Russian defence ministers to sort out the serious enviromental problems stemming from Russia's military activities in the Arctic. The agreement starts with six different projects regarding radioactive waste, which will be carried out within six months to three years.</p>
<p>DAGENS NAERINGSLIV</p>
<p>- A potential merge between Aker ASA and RGI ASA would result in a company with a turnover of more than 20 billion crowns. The merged group would probably be called RGI Aker and concentrate on the fish and oil and gas industries.</p>
<p>- Unemployment fell to 3.9 pecent in September, the lowest jobless rate for six years, according to the Labour Directorate.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OSLO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NORWAY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
