<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83314" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. budget talks go on; Congress to meet Saturday.</title>
<headline>U.S. budget talks go on; Congress to meet Saturday.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>White House and congressional negotiators worked into Saturday morning on the 1997 budget and were reported making progress after Republicans charged Democrats with deliberately raising the threat of another government closure.</p>
<p>The Republican National Committee aired radio ads in Washington and selected Democratic districts charging Democrats of blocking a budget agreement in hopes the public would blame Republicans for the gridlock as they did last winter when the government closed twice.</p>
<p>&quot;That means the government could shut down. Again,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Lawmakers of both parties and White House Chief of Staff Leon Panetta were expressing optimism on the outcome of their marathon talks on a more than 2,000-page spending bill.</p>
<p>During a post-midnight break, Panetta said: &quot;We are getting closer. The general mood is we're making good progress.&quot;</p>
<p>House Appropriations Committee chairman Bob Livingston, R-Louisiana, told reporters, &quot;We're getting there. I think we're coming down to it.&quot;</p>
<p>His Senate counterpart, Mark Hatfield of Oregon, said only 25 of 140 issues in dispute remained.</p>
<p>The House and Senate will hold rare Saturday sessions to vote on the spending bill if it is ready and to do other work to wrap up the year.</p>
<p>Thursday's bargaining session with Panetta, White House budget director Franklin Raines, and Democratic and Republican appropriations leaders broke off at 4 a.m. EDT and resumed a few hours later and continued late Friday. All day lawmakers streamed into the closed session, making their cases for special provisions.</p>
<p>Their intention was to hopefully wrap up the deal for a vote by Monday at the latest.</p>
<p>This massive bill, or a separate version to give the government a few days' funds, must pass before Tuesday's start of the 1997 fiscal year. Without approval to spend money after Oct. 1, many agencies would be forced to close.</p>
<p>A separate negotiation was being held on immigration law reform, with key Republicans voicing harsh words over administration efforts to gain concessions.</p>
<p>Sen. Alan Simpson, R-Wyoming, accused the White House of negotiating in bad faith. &quot;I am sick of it,&quot; he said on the Senate floor.</p>
<p>Both sides have identified many policy issues on which there are deep disagreements, but senators said they were near accord on Oregon Democrat Ron Wyden's plan to eliminate the so-called gag rule and guarantee physicians in health care plans the right to inform patients of all treatments.</p>
<p>The compromise would exempt managed care plans which have clauses against abortion, assisted suicide or other religious objections to a particular treatment.</p>
<p>Democrats are in addition insisting on an amendment to ban gun ownership by convicted spouse abusers. They also object to a Republican plan which they said would deny some elderly and disabled supplemental Social Security benefits.</p>
<p>These and the politically volatile issue of U.S. aid to international family planning agencies that use non-U.S. funds for abortion services will probably be left for negotiations at the highest levels in Congress and the White House.</p>
<p>Republicans, eager to conclude this year's session, agreed to give President Clinton an additional $6.5 billion for education and anti-drug and anti-terrorism efforts. Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott conceded some of his members felt they had given Clinton too much.</p>
<p>The money for these programs would be raised by selling cellular communications airwaves to telecommunications companies, raising thrift deposit insurance reserves and selling oil from the strategic petroleum reserve.</p>
<p>Called an omnibus spending bill, the budget agreement would pay for some of the government's most costly activities -- defense, education, labor, environmental protection, national parks, the White House, the Treasury, foreign aid, law enforcement and a host of others.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
