<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83332" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: White House, Congress reach accord on 1997 budget.</title>
<headline>White House, Congress reach accord on 1997 budget.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>After an all-night bargaining session, the White House and Congress reached a budget agreement early on Saturday that gives President Bill Clinton $6.5 billion more than he wanted in domestic spending.</p>
<p>Republican congressional leaders, who last year pushed the government to shutdown twice rather than accept the administration's budget, stressed that the bipartisan accord ensured the government would stay open next week.</p>
<p>The massive $450 billion spending bill also includes banking regulatory reform, bolsters savings and loan reserves, sells broadcast airwaves, clamps down on illegal immigration and expands anti-terrorism efforts.</p>
<p>Shortly before the president's arrival in Providence, Rhode Island, White House spokesman Mike McCurry said that Clinton was happy with the deal. The administration had wanted the defence department's $245 billion cut by $3 billion and had asked for $10 billion in extra domestic spending.</p>
<p>&quot;He's obviously delighted that bipartisanship has prevailed and that we've reached an agreement that is fiscally prudent and that continues to keep us on a course toward a balanced budget,&quot; said McCurry.</p>
<p>Republicans were in a rush to adjourn so they could begin campaigning. Asked if that meant they gave into Clinton, House Speaker Newt Gingrich, said that wasn't the case but that compromises were made.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the lessons we learned is that you have got to find a way to work together to get things through the Senate. You have got to find a way to get the signature of the president if you want to get it done,&quot; Gingrich, R-Georgia, said of the compromises they made this year.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott, R-Mississippi, added, &quot;If we had the White House, it (the budget) would be different.&quot;</p>
<p>The House of Representatives scheduled a vote on the compromise in a rare Saturday session while the Senate will debate through the weekend and send it to the White House before Monday's midnight deadline. The new fiscal year starts Tuesday, Oct. 1 and without passage of this bill, federal agencies would be forced to close.</p>
<p>A middle-of-night compromise on legislation to impose strict controls on immigration and crack down on illegal aliens cleared the way for agreement on the massive spending bill which funds the largest agencies in the government.</p>
<p>The extra $6.5 billion granted Clinton's request for more money for Head Start and other education programmes. It allows $1.1 billion to fight terrorism, $650 million for fighting fires in Western states, $400 million to aid in recovery from Hurricane Fran, $123 million for troop redeployment in Saudi Arabia and $8.8 billion for the war on illegal drugs.</p>
<p>The extra spending will be paid for with $2.9 billion raised from the sale of cellular communications airwaves, $3.1 billion in higher bank reserves needed to clean-up the last of the savings and loan crisis, and $1 billion from defence.</p>
<p>The more than 2,000 page spending bill -- which likely will not be printed before the House votes -- pays for the Pentagon, the national parks, education, jobs programmes, environmental protection, law enforcement, the White House, foreign aid, health research and a host of other activities.</p>
<p>Congress had approved separately seven of the 13 regular spending bills worth about $150 billion covering housing, energy, water projects, Congress, agriculture, and some other agencies.</p>
<p>Sen. Mark Hatfield, the retiring Republican chairman of the Appropriations Committee, stressed the bipartisan nature of the negotiations. &quot;It has been truly the most bipartisan in my memory,&quot; the Oregon senator told reporters.</p>
<p>This was in sharp contrast to last year's head-on clash between the Republican leaders and the White House. Polls show the public blamed the Republicans for two unpopular government closures and for the threats that brought the government to the edge of closure many more times.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
