<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86878" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: PRESS DIGEST - Cyprus - Sept 30.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Cyprus - Sept 30.</headline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Greek Cypriot press on Monday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>ALITHIA</p>
<p>- The United States is determined to bring about a solution of the Cyprus problem soon.</p>
<p>- Greek ships, Mirages and F-16s will be on military exercise in Cyprus in early October, according to Greek newspaper report.</p>
<p>- Debate on whether the Akamas peninsula is to be turned into a national park is to go to the House of Representatives.</p>
<p>HARAVGHI</p>
<p>- Washington and its European partners push ahead with the idea of confidential talks to resolve the Cyprus problem.</p>
<p>- Turkish Cypriot leader Rauf Denktash sets new conditions for a solution. The right of return is not compatible with the principles of a bizonal, bicommunal federation, he says.</p>
<p>PHILELEPHTHEROS</p>
<p>- Intensive consultations are expected to start on adopting a solution of the Cyprus problem with considerable territorial adjustments, loosely based on a federal system.</p>
<p>- Western diplomats put pressure on the government to suspend its armament programmes.</p>
<p>SIMERINI</p>
<p>- Turkey is looking to a package deal on Cyprus involving simultaneous accession to the European Union, and to link the problem with Greek-Turkish disputes.</p>
<p>- Illegal hunters target the homes of game wardens.</p>
<p>- We accept peace, but not with a Turkish flag flying over us, says President Glafcos Clerides.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
