<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46655" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Santee supplies 700 MW power to Carolina.</title>
<headline>Santee supplies 700 MW power to Carolina.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Carolina-owned utility, Santee Cooper, has been supplying 700 megawatts (MW) of electricity to Carolina Power &amp; Light Co (CP&amp;L) after outages of several CP&amp;L-operated nuclear power plants, Santee Cooper said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have plenty of capacity,&quot; said Santee Cooper spokesman Jerry Stafford, adding the company's generation, transmission and distribution equipment was mostly unscathed by Hurricane Fran last week.</p>
<p>Of the total power to CP&amp;L, 400 MW has come from Santee's own generation and 300 MW from other suppliers but has been transported via Santee's transmission grid, he said.  </p>
<p>CP&amp;L has been purchasing approximately 1,000 MW of power in the daily spot market, said CP&amp;L spokesman Mike Hughes, but declined to comment about the sources of supply.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard to say how long,&quot; Hughes said, when asked the length of time CP&amp;L would continue to buy the current level of spot electricity in the daily market.</p>
<p>The company would continue to shop for power on a spot basis, even if all its nuclear plants were in operation, as long as it deems prices to be attractive, he said.  </p>
<p>Industry sources cited CP&amp;L to be an active buyer of spot electricity in the Southeast after the passage of Fran, which knocked out power service to nearly three-quarters of CP&amp;L's 1.1 million customers.</p>
<p>CP&amp;L's 767 megawatt (MW) Brunswick 1 nuclear power plant is currently at 70 percent power, with the adjoining Brunswick 2, at 754 MW, expected to resume service later this week. Both units were shut Thursday as precaution ahead of Fran.</p>
<p>The company's 880 MW Harris nuclear power plant achieved 73 percent of capacity today after being shut Tuesday Sep 2 due to a failure of a service water pump.  </p>
<p>Furthermore, CP&amp;L's 683 MW Robinson 2 nuclear unit was taken off line Saturday to begin its 40-day refueling outage.</p>
<p>&quot;We had all our power fully restored sundown Saturday (Sept 7),&quot; Stafford said, adding most of the storm-related damages occurred to its distribution system.</p>
<p>&quot;We had lost in 72 hours, mid-Wednesday to Saturday, 11 percent of our power flow (from the previous week's level),&quot; he said. The power loss was equivalent to 16.1 million kilowatt hours, he added.</p>
<p>Electric service to 36,000 of Santee Cooper's 103,893 customers was disrupted during this period, he said.  </p>
<p>Santee Cooper dispatched 45 repair crews and 23 tree-trimming crews to neighboring utilities and electric cooperatives to aid in power restoration efforts.</p>
<p>--R Leong, New York Power Desk +1 212 859 1622</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
