<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60588" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Northeast Utilities shakes up nuclear units.</title>
<headline>Northeast Utilities shakes up nuclear units.</headline>
<dateline>WATERFORD, Conn. 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Northeast Utilities nuclear division Wednesday announced a major reorganization of the company's troubled nuclear plant operation.</p>
<p>Bruce Kenyon, president and chief executive officer of the utility's nuclear division said that three loaned utility executives - all with experience at companies with excellent nuclear operations - would lead the recovery of Northeast Utility's three Millstone nuclear plants.</p>
<p>He named Admiral David Goebel as vice president for nuclear oversight. Goebel replaces Don Miller who is leaving Northeast.  </p>
<p>Kenyon said John Cowan, a vice president at Carolina Power &amp; Light Co, will lead the recovery effort at Millstone 3; Martin Bowling of Virigina Power, a subsidiary of Dominion Resources will help with Millstone 2's recovery and John McElwain of PECO Energy will do the same for Millstone 1.</p>
<p>The Millstone nuclear facility, which has a generation capacity of 2,700 megawatts, has been shut since March 31.</p>
<p>Each of the outside utilities have agreed to lend their executives for six months and that arrangement can be extended, Kenyon said.  </p>
<p>If Connecticut Yankee passes an economic viability review, now underway, Northeast Utilities' Executive Vice President Ted Feigenbaum would serve as recovery officer, Kenyon said. Connecticut Yankee, which was shutdown on July 22, has a generation capacity of 582 megawatts.</p>
<p>He emphasized that the recovery officers have &quot;full authority to take whatever actions are necessary to dramatically move their unit toward a state of nuclear excellence,&quot; according to a statement.</p>
<p>While a recovery officer was not named for the Seabrook nuclear facility in New Hampshire, that plant will also undergo organizational changes, Kenyon said.</p>
<p>And as part of ther reorganization, Kenyon said he was abandoning the &quot;power of five&quot; philosophy that NU had adopted in operating its nuclear power plants, a concept that centralized many functions at all five units.</p>
<p>--Leslie Gevirtz, 617-367-4142</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WATERFORD, Conn."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
