<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78479" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan asks GE to build nuke plant despite impasse.</title>
<headline>Taiwan asks GE to build nuke plant despite impasse.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Taiwan utility has reiterated its resolve to build a controversial fourth nuclear power station, asking U.S. contractor General Electric to start work despite parliament's cancellation of the project's budget.</p>
<p>&quot;After a Taiwan Power board meeting, we sent General Electric a notice telling them to start building,&quot; the state utility nicknamed Taipower said in a statement on Thursday.</p>
<p>General Electric could start construction immediately upon receipt of the notification, Taipower vice president Kuo Chun-hui told a news conference.</p>
<p>But General Electric agreed not to seek compensation if the Taiwan government decided within three weeks to cancel the nuclear power station project, which faces stiff opposition in parliament and among the public.</p>
<p>Taiwan's parliament on May 24 dealt an embarrassing blow to Taipei's nuclear energy policy, voting 76-42 to cancel funding for the 2,700-megawatt plant on the very day that Taipower was holding a final tender for the facility's two reactors.</p>
<p>General Electric won the tender with a bid to supply the two reactors for US$1.8 billion, though its contract can be annulled if project funding is not restored.</p>
<p>Taiwan's cabinet on June 6 appealed the cancellation, heralding a new showdown between the Nationalist government and the politically divided legislature.</p>
<p>Despite the funding cut, Taipower has said it considers the US$4.1 billion project to be alive unless parliament rejects the government's appeal to restore the project.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless the parliament overrules the cabinet's appeal, the Taiwan Power still has the obligation to carry out the fourth nulcear power plant project,&quot; Kuo said.</p>
<p>&quot;Building the fourth nuclear power plant is a vital national policy. We hope the public will support the plan,&quot; Kuo said.</p>
<p>Taipower has poured T$6.1 billion (US$220 million) into the project in Kungliao north of Taipei.</p>
<p>Taiwan approved plans for the plant in 1994 after years of delays and protests triggered mainly by the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear disaster in the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>Taipower produces 21,900 megawatts of power annually, about 23.5 percent of which is generated by nuclear plants.</p>
<p>Experts say total output must rise to 36,000 megawatts by 2002 if power consumption is to keep pace with Taiwan's economic growth.</p>
<p>A growing number of opponents in increasingly democratic Taiwan say nuclear power is dangerous and unnecessary if alternative energy sources are pursued.</p>
<p>Taipower said the nuclear plant is environmentally sound and safe.</p>
<p>&quot;Building the fourth nuclear power plant can not only enhance future power supply but also avoid over dependence on oil imports,&quot; it said, adding that the &quot;technology of nuclear power generation is safe and mature.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
