<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16343" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Sex tourism grows in Romania - child welfare groups.</title>
<headline>Sex tourism grows in Romania - child welfare groups.</headline>
<byline>Karin Popescu</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sex tourism involving abuse of children is spreading to East European countries such as Romania but authorities and public opinion are failing to take the problem seriously, child welfare workers said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>State institutions and the general public refuse to believe there is a growing problem with paedophilia, juvenile prostitution and child abuse in Romania, said George Roman, programme manager for the charity &quot;Save the Children.&quot;</p>
<p>As experts gather in Stockholm for a global meeting to tackle the sexual exploitation of minors, scant public attention is being paid to the subject in places like Romania, where controls on abuse are lax.</p>
<p>&quot;We could face some overwhelming social problems unless Romania issues new laws and reforms old statutes to include new phenomena like paedophilia,&quot; said Roman. &quot;We've already witnessed the start of sexual tourism here.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The support for our work is minimal,&quot; said Roman. &quot;Most people have little sympathy for children living on the streets, the main victims, and say they should be locked up or put to work,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The December 1989 revolt against communism and execution of late Stalinist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu ended strict social controls and led to an explosion in pornography, child prostitution and trafficking in minors.</p>
<p>Bucharest has now become an attractive destination for well-organised paedophiles, with the estimated 2,000 children living in squalor on the city's streets easy prey for visitors.</p>
<p>&quot;In these countries it is easy for a westerner to make himself pleasant and attract children for prostitution gangs under the guise of charity,&quot; said Ecaterina Laudatu, secretary of the National Child Protection Council (CNPC).</p>
<p>Children were invited to Britain and saved only by the police there who recognised their hosts as known paedophiles, Laudatu told the daily Libertatea.</p>
<p>After Romania tightened laws on adoption criminals set up commercial operations inside the country. State childcare agencies have little funding and no programmes to fight them.</p>
<p>Save the Children estimated some 50 paedophiles travel regularly to Romania, posing as tourists or businessmen, and rent apartments where they bribe or force children into appearing in photographs or films.</p>
<p>One particular Frenchman comes every two months with friends to &quot;make pornographic films and shoot pictures,&quot; said Roman. Bribing policemen guarantees impunity, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;The children don't resent these sexual experiences because they earn good and quick money,&quot; Roman said. &quot;They don't realise the damage it is doing to them.&quot;</p>
<p>One formerly sexually abused boy, now 16, has graduated to being a leading supplier of children for French, British and German paedophiles. His case is symptomatic of how sexual abuse will quickly spread, said Roman.</p>
<p>&quot;In four, five years they might develop a whole network, which will be almost impossible to fight against as the country has no controls,&quot; Roman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
