<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16575" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian man faces 850 child sex charges.</title>
<headline>Australian man faces 850 child sex charges.</headline>
<dateline>BRISBANE 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>An elderly Australian man on Tuesday appeared in court charged with 850 child sex crimes in Australia after earlier being charged with committing similar offences in Bangkok.</p>
<p>The 75-year-old man, whose name can not legally be released, faces charges of indecent dealing, sodomy and permitting sodomy with eight children between the 1960s and 1980s.</p>
<p>The eight children were aged between 13 and 16 at the time of the alleged offences, the Brisbane Magistrates Court heard on Tuesday. Police from the Child Exploitation Unit told the court they expected more charges to be laid.</p>
<p>In May, the same man became the second Australian to be charged with sex offences against children in an overseas country, the court was told.</p>
<p>The man was then charged with two counts of sexual conduct involving a child under the age of 16 and one of possessing four rolls of film depicting child abuse acts. It was alleged he had sex with a girl and a boy in Bangkok between 1994 and 1995.</p>
<p>The charges were brought under Australia's tough child sex tourism laws which allows nationals to be charged at home for child sex crimes committed overseas.</p>
<p>The man, who is in custody on remand from the May charges, will appear again in court on September 9.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRISBANE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
