<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25134" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: &quot;Cybercop&quot; a step against Internet child porn.</title>
<headline>&quot;Cybercop&quot; a step against Internet child porn.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The recent establishment of a &quot;Cybercop&quot; to patrol the Internet, seeking out child pornography, is a first step towards banishing such material from the global network, a child sex conference heard on Friday.</p>
<p>Norway's ombudsman for children, Trond Waage, said to date there was very little action that could be taken to stop the distribution of child pornography on the Internet.</p>
<p>But he said the establishment last week of a international body to monitor child pornography on the net, a task taken on by the Norwegian branch of Save the Children, was firm action against paedophiles using the net.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a kind of a cybercop,&quot; Waage told a press conference at the first World Congress Against the Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children.</p>
<p>&quot;We need some visible cops on the net. If you undertake these kinds of criminal activities someone will monitor you.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Save the Children would look out for anything suspicious on the Internet and encourage other users to contact the group's site, children@risk.sn.no, if they came across child pornography on the net.</p>
<p>All information will be handed over to the police and Save the Children would work closely with the international police authority, Interpol, to track the sources down.</p>
<p>Save the Children's programme coordinator, Markus Aksland, said noone had any idea how much -- or how little -- child pornography was available through the Internet.</p>
<p>He said entering the keyword paedophile brought up 5,438 hits on the Internet but this was a dramatic fall from four years ago with paedophiles pulling further back on the net, hiding themselves and using codes.</p>
<p>Aksland said his group had engaged a team of computer experts over the past month to see what they could find and affirm whether or not child porn was a problem on the Internet.</p>
<p>&quot;Even now, they still found a lot of sites with very suggestive names like Barely Legal,&quot; Aksland told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;But the important thing is not to get hysterical and censor the net. The Internet is also open to a lot of good possibilities.&quot;</p>
<p>Waage said the past month's search found child porn on three levels on the Internet; by going into pornography shops and finding the child section, tapping into paedophile networks, and by contacting people in chat forums.</p>
<p>&quot;Some of the material we found, I hope I never see again,&quot; Waage said. &quot;It was four X rated with children of six or seven years old.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the team was unable to confirm rumours that paedophile networks had set up peep shows, attaching small cameras to the side of computers allowing live, two-way vision.</p>
<p>&quot;If it is live and interactive you can ask them to do something,&quot; Waage said. &quot;It starts to be like a video game. You cannot understand the real damage you are doing.&quot;</p>
<p>Waage said a workshop at the five day Stockholm conference, that ends on Saturday, agreed that as well the Norwegian monitor group, a larger international panel was needed.</p>
<p>&quot;(They need to) examine legislative issues involved in cyberspace, balancing freedom of speech with the imperative of protecting children,&quot; Waage said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
