<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25172" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: SE Asia remains in spotlight of child sex campaigners.</title>
<headline>SE Asia remains in spotlight of child sex campaigners.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Southeast Asia remains the centre of the world's child sex industry although a clampdown by some countries is shifting the trade to the region's less developed nations, a global child sex congress heard on Friday.</p>
<p>Campaigners fighting child prostitution and the sale of children for sexual purposes said tighter laws were gradually scaring paedophiles and child sex tourists away from Thailand and the Philippines where the child sex trade has flourished.</p>
<p>But as the spotlight turns to poorer neighbours, such as Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos, trafficking of children for sexual purposes seems to be on the rise in the region.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a big network in our region. It is organised crime worth many billion of dollars,&quot; Thai state attorney Wanchai Roujanavong told Reuters at the first World Congress Against the Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children.</p>
<p>&quot;This seems to be getting worse. We must do everything we can to stop this. Children from southern China, Vietnam, Burma and Cambodia are all at risk.&quot;</p>
<p>The five day conference, that ends on Saturday, has heard that child prostitution has started to emerge in eastern Europe as the tourist industry develops and overseas money pours in.</p>
<p>But Ron O'Grady, head of lobby group End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT), said Southeast Asia remained by far the world's worst affected area with more countries getting involved.</p>
<p>&quot;Paedophiles and child sex tourists are definitely looking for new areas as laws get tighter in these countries,&quot; O'Grady told Reuters outside the Stockholm conference that has attracted over 1,000 delegates from 130 countries.</p>
<p>&quot;As Vietnam and Cambodia develop their tourism industry along the lines of Thailand they are being affected by these problems more and more.&quot;</p>
<p>Cambodian non-government organisation worker, Chhoeurth Sao from Nouvelle Famille (New Family), said there had been a dramatic rise in the child sex trade in Cambodia in the past five years.</p>
<p>He said it began in 1991 after the arrival of a 22,000 strong United Nations peacekeeping force, drafted in to oversee the country's peace process. After the peacekeepers left in 1993, demand continued from Cambodians and overseas tourists.</p>
<p>&quot;The number of prostitutes, and child prostitutes, has grown rapidly with Vietnamese children brought here and children moved from the country to cities,&quot; Sao told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Now tourists can come here and buy a young girl for a week for just $300-400. They all want young girls, virgins, as they are scared of AIDS. It is getting much worse.&quot;</p>
<p>Roujanavong said the shift in focus to Cambodia, Vietnam, and Laos began as Thailand and the Philippines began clamping down on the child sex industry.</p>
<p>New, tough laws to be introduced in Thailand later this year set penalties of up to 20 years jail for anyone procuring children under age 15 for sexual purposes and imprisonment of up to six years for customers.</p>
<p>&quot;Before we could never punish customers,&quot; Roujanavong told Reuters. &quot;Hopefully this will scare people off. We do not want sex tourists in Thailand.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Thailand was joining the long list of countries to introduce extra-territorial laws so it can prosecute its nationals for illegal activities overseas involving children.</p>
<p>&quot;As we're a receiving and sending country, we need not only to protect our own but also our neighbours' children,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chris McMahon from Thailand's Centre for the Protection of Children's Rights said the trafficking of children left the victims helpless in a new country.</p>
<p>&quot;They have no identity cards, they speak very little of the local langugae, their parents aren't there to contract the police and most likely they are illegal immigrants,&quot; McMahon told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;There's really so little they can do to help themselves.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LAOS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
