<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26088" id="root" date="1996-08-31" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Swedish Queen calls for end to child sex slavery. [CORRECTED 06:53 GMT]</title>
<headline>Swedish Queen calls for end to child sex slavery. [CORRECTED 06:53 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sweden's Queen Silvia, who recently caused a storm by publicly critising Sweden's soft child pornography laws, on Saturday called for global action to rescue children from sex slavery.</p>
<p>Closing the first World Congress Against Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children, Queen Silvia urged all sectors of society to join forces on regional, national and international levels.</p>
<p>&quot;We owe this to the children that have been abused, tortured and even killed by sex offenders and to the children who are at risk of becoming victims,&quot; said the queen, patron of the conference.</p>
<p>&quot;This modern form of slavery has to be stopped.&quot;</p>
<p>The five-day conference, overshadowed by a horrific child sex scandal unfolding in Belgium, focused on ways to deal with child prostitution, the sale of children for sexual purposes and child pornography.</p>
<p>The queen, who attacked Swedish politicians in an uncharacteristic outburst last month for not yet criminalising (corrects from decriminalising) the possession of child pornography, kept her comments global.</p>
<p>&quot;Much has been achieved during this congress but the most important work remains to be done,&quot; Queen Silvia told the conference that attracted 1,341 government and non-governmental representatives from some 130 countries.</p>
<p>&quot;We know as long as there is any child who is being sexually exploited, there is work to do.&quot;</p>
<p>The United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) has estimated that every year another one million children worldwide are forced into the sex trade.</p>
<p>The congress, organised by UNICEF, End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT), the NGO Group on the Rights of the Child, and the Swedish government, has drawn up a declaration and agenda for action by the turn of the century.</p>
<p>No decision has yet been made for a follow-up conference but organisers said several countries had already expressed willingness to host a similar event in a few years time.</p>
<p>Child abuse is an issue that the German-born Queen Silvia, 52, who has three children herself, takes to heart.</p>
<p>Last year she shocked a international women's meeting when she announced she had seen some child pornography, seized from the homes of Swedish paedophiles, and it had disgusted her.</p>
<p>Sweden lags behind other countries with its child pornography laws although they are currently under review.</p>
<p>Although Sweden has changed dramatically since the 1970s when it allowed the commercial production of child pornography, possession is still not considered a crime.</p>
<p>Sweden protects possession of child pornography under a constitutional law designed to guarantee freedom of speech and to outlaw possession requires constitutional amendments.</p>
<p>A survey by the University of Minnesta in the United States, presented at the conference, found that 127 countries out of 165 questioned legislated against child pornography.</p>
<p>Of these 46 had specific laws prohibiting child pornography and 81 had a general law prohibiting all forms of pornography.</p>
<p>But 26 countries, including South Africa, had no laws prohibiting any form of pornography.</p>
<p>Twelve countries left sections of the survey blank.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-31"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-31"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
