<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26598" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Child sex congress puts issue on world agenda.</title>
<headline>Child sex congress puts issue on world agenda.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The first World Congress against Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children has highlighted the scale of the problem and the need for vigorous international action to tackle it.</p>
<p>For five days over 1,300 government and non-government representatives from 125 countries discussed ways to combat child prostitution, child pornography and the sale of children for sexual purposes.</p>
<p>The conference coincided with a major child sex scandal in Belgium that pointed to possible cross-border paedophile rings in Europe. The problem, it now seemed, was not confined to developing countries.</p>
<p>Repeatedly organisers of the Stockholm conference dismissed calls by some delegates for broader statements condemning prostitution, pornography or sex tourism as a whole.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to focus specifically on the commercial sexual exploitation of children,&quot; June Kane, spokeswoman for the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), told Reuters.</p>
<p>The conference concentrated on child prostitution, not abuse in families or the sex trade in general.</p>
<p>&quot;(This) constitutes a form of coercion and violence against children and amounts to forced labour and a contemporary form of slavery,&quot; rapporteur general Vitit Muntarbhorn told the conference as it closed on Saturday.</p>
<p>He said all countries involved unanimously accepted a declaration and agenda for action, but now it would be necessary to ensure promises were kept.</p>
<p>The list included legal reforms to protect children and punish offenders, raising public awareness and urging businesses including tourism groups to counter child sexual exploitation.</p>
<p>&quot;But the real test of follow-up will be at the regional, national and local levels,&quot; said Muntarbhorn.</p>
<p>He said it was disappointing that not all countries invited took part in the congress, particularly those that are badly affected by the child sex trade, but they would be encouraged to join if another conference is held in a few years.</p>
<p>&quot;Some countries in my region in Southeast Asia are not here and they have problems too,&quot; said Muntarbhorn, a Thai national.</p>
<p>&quot;Some of their nationals come to my country to perpetuate crimes against children.&quot;</p>
<p>Malaysia and Singapore were not present at the congress.</p>
<p>But organisers agreed that the conference had succeeded in its major purpose -- putting the issue of the commercial sexual exploitation of children on the international agenda.</p>
<p>The international outrage at the horrific child sex case unfolding in Belgium may have contributed to putting the conference in the spotlight.</p>
<p>The discovery of the bodies of two eight-year-old girls, abducted and used for sexual purposes, and the release of two others has triggered a Europe-wide search for a paedophile ring, suggesting child sexual exploitation is a global problem, not confined to developing countries.</p>
<p>Ron O'Grady, coordinator of End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT) and a conference organiser, said his group had been on a lonely road until now.</p>
<p>But following the conference, ECPAT will be expanded globally, keeping its acronym but changing its name to End Child Prostitution, Child Pornograhy and the Trafficking of Children for Sexual Purposes.</p>
<p>&quot;We will monitor what is happening not just in Asia as in the past but throughout the world,&quot; O'Grady told a press conference.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
