<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="37136" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil takes steps to stop widespread child labor.</title>
<headline>Brazil takes steps to stop widespread child labor.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil launched an offensive against child labour on Friday by offering money to stop the exploitation of children and get them back to school.</p>
<p>The government joined forces with labour unions and pressure groups to end abuses in a country where 3.5 million children are being exploited, according to official figures.</p>
<p>President Fernando Henrique Cardoso pledged to pay families about $25 a month for every child they take away from the sugarcane fields or charcoal factories and send to school.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue of child labour seems symbolic to me, because, truly, it is the degradation of mankind. It is not just the child who is condemned by child labour. It's the country, the employers, society, the government,&quot; he said in a speech.</p>
<p>The federal government, states, unions, pressure groups and churches promised in joint statement to work together to end the employment of children under the age of 14.</p>
<p>The official IBGE statistics office puts the number of under-14s who are working at about 3.5 million, out of Brazil's total population of 160 million.</p>
<p>But other independent bodies say as many as 7.5 million young Brazilians are forced by their impoverished parents to contribute to the family income.</p>
<p>A United Nations report in March said child labour remained widespread in Latin America as a whole despite increasing prosperity. It estimated that about 17 percent of Latin American children work, with the proportion in Brazil being one of the highest at 32 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;This has always happened. It used to be a bigger problem. The difference is that now we know it exists,&quot; Cardoso said. &quot;We are fighting it.&quot;</p>
<p>As part of its drive to improve human rights generally, the Brazilian government in recent months has stepped up its efforts to prosecute employers who break child labour laws.</p>
<p>In June, Labour Ministry teams and federal police raided sugar cane plantations in the state of Sao Paulo and found 238 cases of labour code violations. In July, raids in the state of Rio de Janeiro led to 211 criminal cases being taken to court.</p>
<p>A programme in the southern state of Mato Grosso do Sul to end the use of child labour in charcoal factories by paying families to send children to school proved highly successful, and is now being adopted on a national level.</p>
<p>&quot;The government understands it is not sufficient to take children out of the labour market without guaranteeing the means of survival for their families ... and without making it possible for these children to return to the place which they should never have left -- school,&quot; the presidency said in a stament.</p>
<p>The &quot;pay-to-learn&quot; programme will focus on the sugar cane industry, where abuses are most widespread, it added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
