<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39173" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Cardoso vows to end human rights abuses in Brazil.</title>
<headline>Cardoso vows to end human rights abuses in Brazil.</headline>
<byline>William Schomberg</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Fernando Henrique Cardoso vowed on Saturday to end human rights abuses and child labour in Brazil, but landless peasants and labour groups staged protests against continued violations.</p>
<p>&quot;Brazil is tired of tears and rhetoric,&quot; Cardoso said in a speech marking Brazil's Independence Day, flanked by a band of child drummers from a slum.</p>
<p>Cardoso spoke after sending a bill to Congress that would punish the unlicensed use of firearms.</p>
<p>His attempts to reduce gaping inequalities between rich and poor in Latin America's largest country have not convinced the Catholic Church, landless peasants and labour unions that organised demonstrations across the nation to protest what they called another year of poverty and bloodshed.</p>
<p>In Aparecida do Norte, in Sao Paulo state, thousands of worhsippers converged on a massive basilica to hear bishops condemn low wages, unemployment, land expulsions and the marginalization of millions of poor Brazilians.</p>
<p>On a remote highway in the Amazon, demonstrators held a mass on the spot where 19 peasants were mowed down by police machinegun fire in April as they demanded land grants.</p>
<p>Cardoso, a former left-wing sociologist, promised during the 1994 presidential election campaign that he would reduce the gap between rich and poor.</p>
<p>Last week, an official survey showed a slight improvement, with the poorest ten percent accounting for 1.1 percent of Brazil's total wealth in 1995, up from 0.7 percent in 1993. The share of the richest ten percent was 48.2 percent, down 1.6 percentage points from 1993.</p>
<p>During Saturday's Independence Day ceremony, the sister of Brazil's late Grand Prix motor racing idol Ayrton Senna recalled her brother's concern over poverty in Brazil.</p>
<p>&quot;The rich cannot go on living as if on an island surrounded by poverty. We all breathe the same air,&quot; said Viviane Senna, quoting her brother who was killed in a racing accident in May 1994 but is still revered in his country.</p>
<p>Cardoso, who on Friday pledged to pay families $25 a month for every child worker sent back to school, said he took heart from a group of children who swapped smoky charcoal kilns for classrooms under a pilot version of the grant programme.</p>
<p>&quot;Instead of degrading work, they're in school, with a small grant, with the hope of participating in society as citizens instead of watching from the outside,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Official figures show 3.5 million children under the age of 14 are exploited as workers in Brazil.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
