<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49879" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: UN investigator urges fight against child sex.</title>
<headline>UN investigator urges fight against child sex.</headline>
<byline>Stephanie Nebehay</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police should be better paid and trained so as to motivate them to combat sexual exploitation of children, a United Nations rights investigator said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ofelia Calcetas-Santos, a Filipina lawyer who serves as the U.N. special rapporteur on the sale of children, child prostitution and child pornography, also said that most countries were woefully behind on anti-pornography legislation.</p>
<p>The U.N. expert announced she was making a two-week mission to the United States in November -- partly to investigate young people's access to explicit child pornography via the Internet.</p>
<p>She said momentum to combat all forms of child abuse must be sustained after the first-ever World Congress against Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children, held in Sweden last month.</p>
<p>&quot;Stockholm is only the opener,&quot; Calcetas-Santos told a news conference in Geneva.</p>
<p>&quot;We have barely scratched the surface on this thing. We should not let the interest, the awareness, flag,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>The U.N. investigator took part in the week-long meeting which coincided with discovery of a murderous paedophile ring in Belgium. So far investigators have unearthed the bodies of four abducted young girls and confiscated paedophile porn tapes.</p>
<p>Tales of police incompetence, lack of communication and rivalry between different judicial regions have prompted calls for a complete review of the justice system there, as did the arrest in a related inquiry of a chief police detective.</p>
<p>Calcetas-Santos revealed some of the recommendations of her next report to the General Assembly, to be given in November.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing is a review of the compensatory package for law enforcement officers. In a lot of countries they are the lowest in the bureaucratic strata and therefore they justify internally their corruption by saying &quot;You treat us like dirt' or &quot;what do you expect us to do, we have to raise our family, we have to supplement our very meagre income,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;Second is training of law enforcement officers has to be among the top priorities in the agenda of any government -- training on how to deal with children.&quot;</p>
<p>Police need to be sensitised not to treat the child as a criminal, but as a victim, according to the U.N. investigator.</p>
<p>&quot;That means training of policemen and training of all the actors in the criminal justice system -- from the policemen and law enforcement officers to the prosecutors, the lawyers, the social workers assisting (victims) and last but not least the judges themselves,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Calcetas-Santos said that training should lead to more effective law enforcement and successful prosecution.</p>
<p>&quot;A high level of visibility of activity in the prosecution in pursuit of cases will discourage abusers from working in the area of the state limits,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Child pornography was serious, the rapporteur said, adding: &quot;Pornography is one field which is running away from all of us.</p>
<p>&quot;Some countries still have to make any legislation on possession. And of course if there is no legislation on possession, it is not illegal.</p>
<p>&quot;The development generated by the new media is such that practically every government -- all the states -- are behind, even in the field of legislation.&quot;</p>
<p>Traditional legislation covers children mainly depicted in printed material, according to Calcetas-Santos.</p>
<p>&quot;But now, all of a sudden, we wake up to cyberspace. The development in cyberspace has to be addressed very seriously...This is further complicated by constitutional issues in a lot of countries.&quot;</p>
<p>The U.N. investigator said that her U.S. itinerary was still being finalised, but would include Washington and New York.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to see the impact of the Internet and modern technology on young people in a country where this technology is readily available. I have to see it in the context where the computer is part of everyday life.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
