<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58888" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Bangladesh hopes to end child labour by deadline.</title>
<headline>Bangladesh hopes to end child labour by deadline.</headline>
<dateline>DHAKA 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bangladesh hopes to eliminate child labour by October this year, setting a precedent for &quot;the total emancipation of child labour all over the world&quot;, the head of the country's garments association said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Redwan Ahmed, President of Bangladesh Garment Manufacturers' and Exporters' Association, said his organisation, the International Labour Organisation (ILO) and the U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF) were rehabilitating more than 10,500 child labourers under an agreement signed among them in July, 1995.</p>
<p>Bangladesh's garment manufacturers agreed to the terms after the U.S. government threatened to stop importing textiles from countries using workers younger than 14 years of age.</p>
<p>The United States is the largest buyer of Bangladeshi apparel, worth more than $750 million or 54 percent of the country's total annual exports.</p>
<p>Bangladesh earned about $2.5 billion in garment exports in fiscal 1995/96 (July-June) which is roughly 1.33 percent of the total global apparel trade.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not the only country using child labour, even the United States and Britain have them. We are victims of circumstance, because we export $2.5 billion worth of garments,&quot; Ahmed told members of the Overseas Correspondents' Association of Bangladesh (OCAB).</p>
<p>He said Bangladesh's garment industry was the country's biggest employer, offering jobs to 1.2 million people, 90 percent of them women.</p>
<p>He said under the memorandum of understanding reached with the ILO and UNICEF 130 schools for child labourers had been set up and 2,015 of them had already been enrolled.</p>
<p>The children are being given stipends and other facilities besides schooling, he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DHAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
