<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61170" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine government wants variable wages, unions angry.</title>
<headline>Argentine government wants variable wages, unions angry.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Argentine Labor Minister Armando Caro Figueroa said Wednesday he wants future pay deals to make a proportion of workers' wages variable according to the economic climate -- sparking immediate union protest.</p>
<p>&quot;Part of the salary should be variable, taking into account the economic conditions of each company,&quot; he told a news conference, confirming press reports that this would be included in an upcoming bill with which Peronist President Carlos Menem wants to make Argentine labor laws more flexible.</p>
<p>&quot;For example, a company could pay more while a contract lasts, then stop paying it when the contract ends,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Figueroa repeated Menem's threat to force new labor laws through by presidential decree if Congress puts up a fight.</p>
<p>Menem argues that abolishing collective pay negotiations and swapping redundancy payments for unemployment insurance schemes, to be paid for with employer contributions, would help cut Argentina's high unemployment, now 17.1 percent.</p>
<p>But trade unions, who plan a 36-hour general strike on September 26 to follow a 24-hour stoppage last month, oppose the labor flexibilization project.  </p>
<p>Rodolfo Daer, head of the main CGT union federation which is leading the industrial action, said the labor laws &quot;would make employment more precarious and harm our country's economy.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Trying to make salaries a moving target is an insult,&quot; said CGT press chief Carlos West Ocampo. &quot;For a worker to earn so much one day, then half the next month depending on his employer's mood, is outrageous.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Stephen Brown, Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0695</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
