<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66923" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine government defends Menem's labor reforms.</title>
<headline>Argentine government defends Menem's labor reforms.</headline>
<byline>Stephen Brown</byline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Argentine government, facing the second general strike in two months, tried Friday to take the heat out of a row with trade unions over President Carlos Menem's campaign for more flexible labor laws.</p>
<p>With the leader of the main CGT union federation Rodolfo Daer quipping that &quot;if we carry on like this we will have to pay to work,&quot; officials toned down the threat of the laws being pushed through by decree if Congress drags its feet.</p>
<p>&quot;Ideally we would do this by consensus in parliament,&quot; said Menem's Chief of Staff Alberto Kohan.  </p>
<p>But he added: &quot;Taking decisions by decree does not violate the constitution. On labor legislation it is permitted.&quot;</p>
<p>Menem himself, who warned in a newspaper article this week &quot;I have governed and will govern by decree,&quot; told reporters in neighboring Uruguay Friday: &quot;We are not trying to destabilize the job market, as people have been wrongly informed.&quot;</p>
<p>Unions, already on the warpath about austerity measures, are angry about Menem brandishing his power of decree to push through new labor laws if Congress proves reluctant to approve the proposed bill, expected to be submitted in 10 days.  </p>
<p>Kohan, who like Menem was speaking to Argentine radio from Uruguay, tried to counter union protests that the labor reform would undermine job security: &quot;We are worrying about people without work. When we talk of flexibilization we're not talking about a law for people who already have acquired rights, but for those who don't.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Making it easier for companies to take on new employees means we are concerned with solving the problem. The quicker the problems is solved, the better. And if we can do it by law, better still,&quot; said Kohan.</p>
<p>Menem has the backing of business, though Stock Exchange chief Julio Macchi, warned it was &quot;absolutely indispensable&quot; for the bill to be agreed by consensus. Business leaders are also lobbying for redundancy insurance to be financed jointly by contributions from employers and employees.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be a good way to go, to have both employers and employees contributing to a sort of insurance for possible layoffs,&quot; said Enrique Crotto, head of the Rural Society farm lobby and a director of the Group of Eight, a powerful lobby of the eight biggest business chambers.</p>
<p>But Labor Minister Caro Figueroa issued a statement making it clear employees will not have to fund their own redundancy:</p>
<p>&quot;Just as we have said all along, the government proposes an indemnization regime via an individual capitalization fund paid into excuslively by the employer.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0695</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
