<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66961" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine industry leader backs worker layoff fund.</title>
<headline>Argentine industry leader backs worker layoff fund.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Enrique Crotto, a leading member of Argentina's powerful Group of Eight umbrella business association, Friday endorsed a government initiative to have employess finance their own layoff compensation.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be a good way to go,&quot; said Crotto, President of Argentina's Rural Society of agricultural industries, &quot;to have both employers and employees contributing to a sort of insurance for possible layoffs.&quot;  </p>
<p>The initiative is part of the government's ambitious labor market reforms which have become one of President Carlos Menem's top policy priorities.</p>
<p>Crotto said he was all for the government's drive to loosen labor laws and said they were needed to foster employment. Argentine unemployment is currently at 17.1 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;You have to have more flexible laws. People are afraid of hiring because of the lawsuits they face if they decide to fire their employees,&quot; said Crotto. &quot;That needs to be changed.&quot;  </p>
<p>The new labor legislation package will be unveiled shortly and should go to Congress in the next 10 days. Menem warned that he will resort to presidential decrees if lawmakers drag their feet.</p>
<p>Argentine unions have already come out to express their staunch opposition to any change in labor laws that could diminish workers' benefits.</p>
<p>A World Bank report published Thursday said Argentine unemployment could drop to single figures if the government succeeds in implementing labor reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;Unemployment in Argentina could fall eight percentage points ...i f the government moves ahead with a reduction in labor costs and new compensation schemes that are included in the latest government labor flexibilization plan,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Separately, senior Argentine Economy Ministry labor expert Carola Pessino said the reforms could push down unemployment to below 10 percent.</p>
<p>-- Daniel Helft, Buenos Aires Newsroom + 54 1 318 0663</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
