<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70233" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine unions will meet Peronists but strike on.</title>
<headline>Argentine unions will meet Peronists but strike on.</headline>
<byline>Stephen Brown</byline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The heads of Argentina's CGT union federation, leading a 36-hour general strike this week, said on Monday they will attend a meeting of the ruling Peronist Party on Tuesday, but will not call off the strike.</p>
<p>The CGT is traditionally close to Peronism and many top CGT officials hold party posts. But angry at unemployment of 17.1 percent, it is fighting President Carlos Menem's drive for fiscal austerity and more flexible labor laws.  </p>
<p>&quot;The CGT is open to dialogue, but it must be understood there is no possibility of negotiating the strike,&quot; said CGT chief Rodolfo Daer, who will lead a 36-hour general strike on Thursday and Friday to follow a 24-hour stoppage in August.</p>
<p>Menem's close ally Sen. Eduardo Bauza, Secretary General of the Peronist Party, called the party council meeting last week to try to persuade Peronist officials of the virtues of Menem's proposed labor bill.  </p>
<p>It includes proposals to scrap collective pay deals, swap redundancy payments for an unemployment insurance scheme, make a proportion of wages variable depending on the health of the economy and change working hours and vacations.</p>
<p>Menem threatens to push the laws through by decree if the Congress puts up a fight. CGT's press chief Carlos West Ocampo, also the Peronist Party's Social Action Secretary, told a news conference with Daer Monday that &quot;those of us who are part of the Peronist Party will go to the National Council meeting tomorrow, as will the Labor Minister (Armando Caro Figueroa), to discuss the labor flexibilization project.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;And we are convinced the Peronist Party will support the CGT and not approve the bill presented by Caro Figueroa.&quot;</p>
<p>Menem's Cabinet Chief Jorge Rodriguez said the labor minister would be making a last-ditch attempt to hold talks with the CGT about the labor package ahead of the strike and added that &quot;the reasons for the strike are still not clear.&quot;</p>
<p>The World Bank backed the labor law initiative last week in a report saying unemployment &quot;could fall eight percentage points...if the government moves ahead with a reduction in labor costs.&quot; It said a 10 percent cut in labor costs could foster five percent employment growth, while less costly redundancy rules could bring 3.0 percent job growth.</p>
<p>-- Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0695</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
