<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71345" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: ILO seeks to better plight of farm workers.</title>
<headline>ILO seeks to better plight of farm workers.</headline>
<byline>Stephanie Nebehay</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Labour Organisation (ILO) on Monday criticised working conditions in agriculture, singling out pervasive use of child labour, long hours, low wages and slack safety standards.</p>
<p>Despite growth in agricultural production, millions of farm workers earn a subsistence-level living while being exposed to pesticides and other hazards, the United Nations agency said in a hard-hitting report.</p>
<p>The ILO, which promotes social justice and labour standards, called for greater opportunities for collective bargaining to improve conditions in the sector.</p>
<p>The report, &quot;Wage Workers in Agriculture: Conditions of Employment and Work&quot;, will be discussed by government officials, employers' groups and workers' representatives from 30 countries who opened a week-long meeting in Geneva on Monday.</p>
<p>Child labour is pervasive among agricultural wage workers and can reach 30 per cent of the workforce in some countries, according to the 97-page report. Farm workers are also exploited through bonded labour.</p>
<p>&quot;We are talking about 400 to 500 million wage workers in agriculture. That is one-sixth of the world's labour force,&quot; Philippe Egger, author of the report, told a news briefing.</p>
<p>The report said: &quot;Hours of work tend to be long, often over 45 hours per week. The conditions of transport of agricultural workers in several countries are appalling and need urgent attention.</p>
<p>&quot;The presence of child labour in agriculture, either recruited directly or a part of a family team for a full day's work, is widespread.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a trend away from permanent forms of employment to more casual and seasonal employment with little or no social protection. Occupational injury compensation in agriculture is often limited or insufficient, or both,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>While global trade in agricultural commodities has grown by roughly three per cent a year throughout the last decade, the benefits have been unequally distributed, according to the ILO.</p>
<p>Representation of wage workers by workers' organisations in agriculture was very weak. &quot;There is very little collective bargaining,&quot; Egger said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our findings show one worker in two in the agricultural sector in wage employment is in poverty. In 40 per cent of countries that we have documented, workers cannot earn enough to sustain themselves, let alone their families,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Egger said agriculture was a hazardous occupation. ILO findings showed that in three out of four countries, the rate of fatal injuries in agriculture was above the overall average.</p>
<p>The report said pesticide poisoning in some countries accounted for up to 14 per cent of all occupational injuries in the agricultural sector and 10 per cent of all fatal injuries.</p>
<p>&quot;There should be a much stronger application of basic rights of workers, the ILO fundamental human rights standards, to this category of workers,&quot; Egger told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to see much stronger emphasis on collective bargaining to enable workers and employers to collective negotiate terms and conditions of employment. This is a standard ILO  recipe, but it is something not happening at all or very little in the agricultural sector,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
