<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78727" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Reebok invites Nike to stamp out child labor.</title>
<headline>Reebok invites Nike to stamp out child labor.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Athletic shoe maker Reebok International Ltd. Thursday invited arch-rival Nike to team up and stamp out child labour at their factories around the world, particularly in Pakistan.</p>
<p>&quot;This isn't about business principles. This is about making the world a little better,&quot; said Reebok Chairman Paul Fireman after an Executive Forum of the Greater Boston Chamber of Commerce meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;This isn't a challenge. This is an invitation,&quot; he stressed.</p>
<p>Fireman wrote to Phil Knight, his counterpart at Nike, after reading Knight's letter to his shareholders that spoke of an increased commitment to the human rights of workers making Nike products.</p>
<p>&quot;I have a radical idea,&quot; Fireman wrote. &quot;Suppose you and I worked together on this issue... Through your position as leader of the most powerful brand, through our combined market share strength, and through Reebok's own experience in human rights, I think the partnership would be awesome.&quot;</p>
<p>Both firms came under fire after press reports found their Pakistani subcontractors that make soccer balls used child labour.</p>
<p>A company review &quot;found that 20 to 25 percent of the stitchers are between the ages of nine and 13,&quot; said Fireman, whose firm sponsors its own human rights award and various Amnesty International projects.</p>
<p>The Pakistani families count on the children's income, he said, and &quot;are not looking for intervention with their way of life.&quot;</p>
<p>So Reebok, which fired one contractor for using underage labour, &quot;is building a new facility which will be the home for all Reebok ball production, including stitching. We'll support education and vocational training for the children in the area,&quot; Fireman said.</p>
<p>Nike spokesman Keith Peters said Knight was aware of Fireman's letter and &quot;it will take some time to consider it. Obviously, we've been considering a variety of things for weeks now. This is a new wrinkle and it deserves consideration.&quot;</p>
<p>Knight, in a Sept. 16 letter to shareholders dealing specifically with criticism of Nike's labour practices in developing countries, wrote, &quot;For the past 18 months, we have hired Ernst &amp; Young to conduct unannounced audits to ensure adherence to our Code of Conduct.</p>
<p>&quot;Within the next year, we will invite a group other than Ernst &amp; Young to review the factories making Nike shoes. We know these are the best shoe factories in the world, and we will encourage this independent group to make its findings public,&quot; Knight wrote.</p>
<p>Peters said Nike will open five of its own facilities in Pakistan, the first one in Sialkot within the next eight weeks.</p>
<p>Soccer, while still a fledgling sport in the United States, provides a multibillion dollar market worldwide for makers of apparel and sport equipment.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope this proposal will help end the exploitation of children's labour,&quot; said Representative Joseph Kennedy, D-Mass., one of the harshest critics. &quot;These two industry giants working with other labour and human rights organisations along with soccer ball industry could finally put an end to these practices.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I45100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
