<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="783803" id="root" date="1997-08-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Reuters French Advertising &amp; Media Digest - Aug 6.</title>
<headline>Reuters French Advertising &amp; Media Digest - Aug 6.</headline>
<text>
<p>---------------- FAM -------------------</p>
<p>REUTERS FRENCH ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST</p>
<p>--------------- Aug 6, 1997 -------------</p>
<p>News from Reuters and the French press on Advertising,</p>
<p>Marketing, Media &amp; the Internet, Brand-name Products and People</p>
<p>News.</p>
<p>******************************************</p>
<p>ADVERTISING, MEDIA &amp; THE INTERNET:</p>
<p>PARIS - French state airline Air France says it awarded its world advertising business to Ammirati Puris Lintas after a public tender launched in February. It also awarded the purchasing of advertising space to Mediapolis, a subsidiary of Havas Advertising.(Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - French pay-television group Canal Plus is in talks with</p>
<p>newspaper publishers Groupe Amaury to set up a television news channel to rival LCI of TF1, La Tribune newspaper says. A Canal Plus spokeswoman says it is no secret the company is preparing a 24-hour news channel, but has no immediate comment on a partnership with Amaury. There was no immediate comment at Amaury, publisher of tabloid Le Parisien Aujourd'hui and the sports daily L'Equipe. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - Canal Plus has concluded an accord in principle for it to buy Time-Warner's Castle Rock film studio. (La Tribune)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - The groups that represent independent French radio stations want to ensure that the FM frequencies being auctioned by the broadcasting regulator, Conseil Superieur de l'Audiovisuel (CSA), are allocated fairly, rather than given back to the big radio stations which bought them illegally. (Les</p>
<p>Echos)</p>
<p>************** *********************************</p>
<p>BRAND-NAME PRODUCTS &amp; MARKETS: PARIS - The European Commission publishes a table showing that French-made cars are more expensive in France than in other European Union countries. A Renault Twingo costs 14.6 percent more and a Citroen Xantia nearly 30 percent more in France than</p>
<p>in Portugal. (Le Parisien)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - California-based computer technology company Bay Networks Inc., the third-largest maker of computer networking gear, is expecting further rapid sales growth in Europe. Alain Sanchez, marketing director France, says Europe now makes up 22 percent of Bay Networks sales and this number is likely to rise.</p>
<p>(Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - A third of French people believe the quality of a</p>
<p>product made in France is higher than that of a product made outside Europe, and 40 percent are prepared to pay more for a French-made product, according to a recent study by institute Credoc for the Industy Ministry. (La Tribune)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>BOLOGNA - Conserve Italia says it is to acquire France's Verjame</p>
<p>SA, the country's leading fruit conserver. Conserve Italia, which owns the brands Valfrutta, Yoga, Derby, Jolly Colombani and Mon Jardin, says the purchase would create Europe's leading group in the sector. (Reuter)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>PEOPLE NEWS:</p>
<p>PARIS - Francis Morel has resigned as head of TF1 International.</p>
<p>He is being replaced by Didier Sapaut. (Le Figaro)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - Patricia Boutinard Rouelle, head of documentaries at France 3, has been appointed Secretary General at the public television channel, replacing Jean Mino who has joined La Cinquieme. (France 3)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>Paris Editorial, Sue Landau Tel 01.42.21.51.30 Fax</p>
<p>01.42.36.10.72</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>For further information and news, see Reuters Adverising &amp; Media</p>
<p>Briefing. And visit us on the Internet at</p>
<p>http://www.Bizinfo.reuters.com</p>
<p>*****************************************************</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
</newsitem>
