<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="807600" id="root" date="1997-08-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Great-West Life tops Royal Bank bid for London Ins.</title>
<headline>Great-West Life tops Royal Bank bid for London Ins.</headline>
<byline>Andrea Hopkins</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO</dateline>
<text>
<p>Great-West Lifeco Inc. surprised the Canadian stock market on Tuesday with a C$2.9 billion ($2.1 billion) bid for London Insurance Group Inc., topping a bid for the insurer by the Royal Bank of Canada in June.</p>
<p>The Royal Bank, Canada's largest, said it was too early to say whether it would sweeten its C$2.4 billion ($1.7 billion) June bid. Under that offer, Canada's largest bank has three days to respond to a competing offer.</p>
<p>Analysts said the Great-West bid, which carries a 21 percent premium over Royal Bank's, could be the start a bidding war for London Insurance, one of Canada's largest insurers.</p>
<p>&quot;It could go higher, there is room to (top the offer). Whether it will or not depends on the Royal Bank's willingness to go into a public competition for this asset,&quot; said one analyst who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>The Royal Bank deal was thought to have been sewn up after London Insurance's majority shareholder, Trilon Financial Corp., agreed to tender its 57-percent stake to the offer in June.</p>
<p>If London Insurance pulled out of the Royal Bank deal, it would have to pay the bank a C$70 million ($50.3 million) termination fee.</p>
<p>The analyst said both bidders were well-positioned to battle for the insurer.</p>
<p>&quot;Both are well-funded companies with tremendously strong balance sheets...The key difference is that (Great-West) can realize synergies, which means cost savings in a nutshell. The name of the game is whether...the (Royal Bank) is willing to pay a premium to get into a new business,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>If the Great-West bid is successful, Great-West would become the largest insurance group in Canada, with total assets of C$52.8 billion ($37.9 billion).</p>
<p>Great-West promoted its offer as a move to protect the Canadian insurance business from the hungry jaws of Canada's big banks, which have already swallowed up almost every other financial service sector.</p>
<p>&quot;In less than a decade, changes in the Canadian financial services sector have resulted in both the investment banking and trust and loan sectors being largely taken over by the major banks. Great-West's offer, if accepted, will reinforce an independent insurance sector,&quot; Great-West said in a statement.</p>
<p>Canada's insurance business is now dominated by independent companies and subsidiaries of foreign corporations, which have lobbied hard against allowing banks into the insurance sector.</p>
<p>Also participating in the Great-West deal are Power Financial Corp., which holds an 86.5-percent stake in Great-West, and Power Financial's 67.4-percent subsidiary Investors Group Inc.</p>
<p>Power Financial will subscribe for up to C$300 million ($215 million) of Great-West common equity and Investor's Group up to C$600 million ($431 million) in support of the bid. All three companies are ultimately controlled by Montreal's Desmarais family through Power Corp. of Canada.</p>
<p>Shares in London Insurance soared on the Toronto Stock Exchange after the higher bid was announced, jumping 6.30 to 33.35 in heavy trade. The stock was trading below 24 before the Royal Bank bid.</p>
<p>&quot;If this comes to a bit of a spitting match, who knows how high the stock could go,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>((Andrea Hopkins, Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
</newsitem>
