<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="809495" id="root" date="1997-08-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel threatens tough response to rocket attacks.</title>
<headline>Israel threatens tough response to rocket attacks.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-08-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pro-Iranian Hizbollah fighters in Lebanon rained scores of Katyusha rockets on northern Israel on Tuesday, prompting a threat from Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of a tough Israeli response.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is no quiet on the Israeli side of the border there will not be quiet on the Lebanon side,&quot; he told reporters while standing in a rocket-damaged house during a tour of the border town of Kiryat Shmona.</p>
<p>A civilian man was lightly wounded in rocket attacks on the town and other parts of Israel's northern Galilee.</p>
<p>The twin morning barrages, about an hour apart, deepened fears for the future of an agreement last year by Hizbollah and Israel not to target civilians.</p>
<p>Netanyahu appealed to Damascus, the main power broker in Lebanon, to curb Hizbollah attacks, saying: &quot;Syria is able to stop this shooting. It must understand that it is also in its interest. We are in contact with the United States which has already turned to Syria on this issue&quot;.</p>
<p>The Katyusha attacks followed a day of violence on Monday that killed at least 10 civilians in Lebanon, seven in shelling of the southern port city of Sidon by forces of pro-Israeli militia chief Antoine Lahd from their stronghold of Jezzine.</p>
<p>U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan urged all sides to exercise restraint, a call echoed by the European Union hours after the Katyushas struck.</p>
<p>One man on his way to work was slightly wounded, witnesses said. Pro-Israeli militia sources said a 65-year-old woman was wounded in Lebanon.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, already grappling with a security crisis with Palestinian President Yasser Arafat, said he would work to halt the spiralling violence but served notice that he would not tolerate attacks on Israeli civilians.</p>
<p>&quot;Israel will respond severely to attacks on civilian lives, and Israel hopes this message will be absorbed on the other side in all of its meaning,&quot; an official statement quoted Netanyahu as saying.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai, touring the north with President Ezer Weizman, vowed not to let up in the war on Hizbollah.</p>
<p>&quot;I would also appeal to the government of Lebanon and the army of Lebanon to take a good look at their deeds and do what they must to ensure quiet in Lebanon,&quot; Mordechai told reporters.</p>
<p>According to Israeli officials, the Lebanese army on Monday joined in shooting at positions of the pro-Israeli South Lebanon Army (SLA) militia in Jezzine.</p>
<p>The town is just outside a 15-km (nine-mile) deep occupation zone Israel set up in southern Lebanon with the declared aim of preventing guerrilla attacks on northern Israel.</p>
<p>Hizbollah is fighting to oust Israeli troops and the SLA from the zone. Signalling defiance of possible reprisals, it swiftly claimed responsibility for Tuesday's rocket attacks.</p>
<p>&quot;The Islamic Resistance declares openly that it shelled the settlements in north occupied Palestine with a number of Katyusha rockets, causing many casualties,&quot; a Hizbollah spokesman said in Beirut.</p>
<p>Seven Lebanese civilians, including a two-month-old boy, were killed on Monday in the Sidon shelling.</p>
<p>Israel, which said the militiamen in Jezzine are beyond its control, said Lahd's men were apparently avenging the killing of three youths by a roadside bomb in the Jezzine area. The Israeli army accused Hizbollah of carrying out that attack.</p>
<p>The cycle of violence contravenes an agreement not to target civilians which the parties to the conflict reached after Israel launched a bloody offensive in Lebanon in April 1996.</p>
<p>It has also deflected attention from Israel's stand-off with Arafat's Palestinian Authority after a double suicide bombing in Jerusalem last month.</p>
<p>Israel was scheduled on Tuesday to transfer $12 million, or about 30 percent, of funds owed to the Authority which it froze after the bombing as part of an economic and security clampdown.</p>
<p>Netanyahu ordered the payment in response to what Israel says is &quot;partial cooperation&quot; by the Palestinians on security.</p>
<p>The Palestinian Authority said it was still awaiting the money -- and the rest of the funds.</p>
<p>Israel has called on Arafat to launch a tough crackdown on suspected Moslem militants from the Hamas and Islamic Jihad groups, something the Palestinian president has refused to do.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
</newsitem>
