<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17369" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: U.N-Iraq pursue arms talks,Iraqi media slams Ekeus.</title>
<headline>U.N-Iraq pursue arms talks,Iraqi media slams Ekeus.</headline>
<byline>Leon Barkho</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraqi and United Nations arms officials held more closed-door meetings on Tuesday but it was not clear whether progress was made on outstanding differences, U.N. and Iraqi sources said.</p>
<p>U.N. senior arms envoy Rolf Ekeus arrived in Baghdad on Monday for talks on the controversial issue of U.N. occess to inspect Iraqi sites and on banned materials his inspectors suspect Iraq is still hiding.</p>
<p>Days before Ekeus's arrival, the U.N. Security Council demanded Iraq stop blocking searches by his inspectors for concealed weapons. Iraq did not hide its anger at the accusations.</p>
<p>The government newspaper al-Jumhouriya said on Tuesday the council's request was unnecessary and accused Ekeus, who chairs the U.N. Special Commission (UNSCOM), of politicising his mission in Iraq.</p>
<p>&quot;He has immersed himself in a political ploy against Iraq, masterminded by America for known political reasons,&quot; the paper said.</p>
<p>It said Ekeus adopted &quot;practices and activities hostile to Iraq&quot;, in reference to UNSCOM's persistent efforts to gain access to sites which Iraq deems vital to its national security.</p>
<p>Ekeus was not available for comment. U.N. sources said the Iraqis, fearing for his safety  kept him under tight security.</p>
<p>Jumhouriya ridiculed such security concerns which it said were being used by Ekeus and his commission as a means &quot;to incite the U.N. Security Council&quot; against Iraq.</p>
<p>The two sides reached agreement last June on how to inspect facilities which Baghdad regards as symbols of its sovereignty. But the arrangements did not work out, as Iraq balked at several attempts by UNSOM experts to enter such places.</p>
<p>Iraq accuses Ekeus of exceeding the authority given to him under the 1991 Gulf War ceasefire terms, compelling Baghdad to rid itself of weapons of mass destruction.</p>
<p>The ban on Iraqi oil exports, except for the limited sales allowed under a deal Baghdad signed with U.N. last June, will not be lifted until Ekeus certifies that Iraq has fully complied with Gulf War weapons demands.</p>
<p>Ekeus, in remarks made last week, said Baghdad had not yet met its disarmament obligations and charged that the Iraqis were obstructing missions by his inspectors.</p>
<p>Jumhouriya described his remarks as &quot;poisonous...meant only to prolong the unfair sanctions on Iraq.&quot;</p>
<p>UNSCOM says it still believes Iraq hides about a dozen of its long-range ballistic missiles and has not yet provided it with all documents and probably materials concerning its past weapons programmes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
