<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19416" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BAHRAIN: U.N. to test Iraq's pledge before October report.</title>
<headline>U.N. to test Iraq's pledge before October report.</headline>
<byline>Abbas Salman</byline>
<dateline>MANAMA 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Nations will send a weapons inspection team to Iraq next month to test Baghdad's promise to provide unrestricted access, U.N. envoy Rolf Ekeus said in Bahrain on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;September will be crucial. Iraq, after more than five years of work, they gave us the declarations...We will now send our inspectors to verify these declarations,&quot; Ekeus, chairman of the U.N. Special Commission in charge of scrapping banned Iraqi weapons, said after a three-day visit to Iraq.</p>
<p>&quot;The findings...will be very decisive,&quot; he said, adding there would be a report to the Security Council on October 11.</p>
<p>Ekeus was speaking in Bahrain, field headquarters of U.N. missions visiting Iraq.</p>
<p>Earlier in Baghdad he said Iraq had pledged to let U.S. inspectors carry out their task of ridding Iraq of weapons of mass destruction under 1991 Gulf War ceasefire terms.</p>
<p>&quot;We got strong undertaking from the leader of the Iraqi delegation (Deputy Prime Minister) Tareq Aziz that they intended to faithfully and truthfully comply with the statement reached on June 22,&quot; Ekeus told Reuters before leaving Iraq.</p>
<p>In June, Ekeus and Aziz agreed on arrangements to solve the controversial issue of access and also laid down procedures on how to solve the problem of prohibited materials U.N. inspectors suspected Baghdad was still hiding.</p>
<p>But in July and August Iraq barred teams of Ekeus's inspectors from entering several sites it said were vital for its national security.</p>
<p>Ekeus said his talks in Baghdad related to inspections, such as operating helicopters and conducting serious interviews. He said he doubted Iraq was hiding weapons in presidential palaces.</p>
<p>&quot;I would be extremely surprised if they put the sensitive, prohibited items (there). We don't believe that Iraq is hiding things and therefore we have no intention to inspect presidential palaces,&quot; he said in Bahrain.</p>
<p>Aziz said in a statement to the Iraqi News Agency (INA): &quot;We stressed to UNSCOM chairman and we repeat the confirmation with all force again that Iraq does not hide prohibited weapons or banned weapons components or related documents.&quot;</p>
<p>Ekeus said his commission still lacked full accounting of all proscribed items, particularly production materials in the three major areas -- biological weapons, chemical weapons and long-range ballistic missiles.</p>
<p>Before his visit the Security Council issued a statement demanding Iraq fully honour its ceasefire commitments and allow arms experts free access to any facility they wish to see.</p>
<p>Iraq is under U.N. trade sanctions, including a ban on its oil exports, for invading Kuwait in 1990.</p>
<p>The removal of curbs on its crude exports, apart from the partial oil sales deal Baghdad signed with the United Nations in May, depends on testimony by Ekeus that Iraq has fully honoured all weapons demands under the ceasefire.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANAMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BAHRAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
