<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19557" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. denies quashing Gulf chemical report.</title>
<headline>U.S. denies quashing Gulf chemical report.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Defence Department denied on Wednesday that it intentionally quashed a 1991 classified report suggesting that U.S. troops were exposed to Iraqi chemical weapons in the Gulf War.</p>
<p>But the department conceded that &quot;the full relevance of the report ... was not recognised at the time&quot; and it was not investigated until this year, providing indications that perhaps 150 soldiers were exposed to chemical agents when they blew up the Kamisiyah ammunition dump in southern Iraq.</p>
<p>Defence Secretary William Perry, commenting on a New York Times report, said the secret document was circulated within the government and to U.S. military officials at the time and that the &quot;complex&quot; issue was still being investigated.</p>
<p>But the document, based on a visit by U.N. inspectors to the Kamisiyah weapons complex in 1991, was not made available to the U.S. engineer battalion involved or to the public. The U.S. government, on orders from President Bill Clinton, last year mounted a major effort to solve medical complaints from thousands of Gulf War veterans.</p>
<p>&quot;The department flatly denies that there was ever an attempt to withhold information from either the troops or from the public regarding this matter,&quot; Navy Capt. Michael Doubleday, a Pentagon spokesman, said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But &quot;the full relevance of the report, because there was no such thing as 'Gulf War illness' ... was not recognised at the time,&quot; Doubleday told reporters.</p>
<p>The Times said the long-classified intelligence report showed the White House, the Central Intelligence Agency and the State Department were alerted that chemical weapons had been stored in a big Iraqi ammunition depot that was blown up in March 1991 by American troops.</p>
<p>The report was circulated to U.S. military commanders worldwide and then filed away even as the Defence Department repeatedly suggested it had no evidence that large numbers of U.S. troops might have been exposed to chemical arms.</p>
<p>The report was marked &quot;priority,&quot; a designation for intelligence considered of moderate importance, the Times said. But it was never shared with the troops themselves.</p>
<p>Defence officials confirmed the Times report that as many as 150 U.S. soldiers who took part in the 1991 mission to blow up Iraq's Kamisiyah ammunition dump were told only this spring that they may have been exposed to a cloud of mustard gas and sarin, a nerve agent.</p>
<p>But officials denied that many of the soldiers who destroyed the arms depot had since developed debilitating medical problems that they say may be linked to exposure to chemical weapons.</p>
<p>Nearly 60,000 other veterans of the Gulf War have asked for special health screenings to determine if they were suffering from ailments related to their service in the Gulf.</p>
<p>Pentagon officials said much of the material in the November 1991 report came from the U.N. arms inspectors who travelled to Iraq after the war ended in February of that year.</p>
<p>The inspectors had found evidence of chemical weapons at the depot at Kamisiyah when it was destroyed. The report drew little attention when it was circulated.</p>
<p>Doubleday said the U.N. inspectors who visited the area in November, 1991, reported that they were told by the Iraqis that U.S. troops earlier that year had blown up stocks of weapons there.</p>
<p>But he said U.S. officials had reason to be doubtful of those claims.</p>
<p>&quot;Iraq was the one country in the world that we least believed at that time,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1991, the question was not whether (chemical) weapons had been destroyed, but whether they had even existed.&quot;</p>
<p>He said it was only in late 1995, based on a new CIA analysis, that government experts began to understand how the destruction of the Kamisiyah depot might have exposed U.S. troops to chemical weapons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
