<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19877" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Iraq again pledges free access for U.N. arms teams.</title>
<headline>Iraq again pledges free access for U.N. arms teams.</headline>
<byline>Leon Barkho</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>United Nations chief arms official Rolf Ekeus said on Wednesday that Iraq had renewed pledges to give his inspectors unrestricted access to any facility they wanted to search.</p>
<p>But he said Iraq's words would only have weight if they were translated into action as his inspectors carried out their task of ridding Iraq of weapons of mass destruction under the 1991 Gulf War ceasefire.</p>
<p>&quot;We got strong undertaking from the leader of the Iraqi delegation (Deputy Prime Minister) Tareq Aziz that they intended to faithfully and truthfully comply with the statement reached on June 22,&quot; Ekeus told Reuters at the end of his three-day visit to Iraq.</p>
<p>In June Ekeus and Aziz agreed on arrangements to solve the controversial issue of access and also laid down procedures on how to solve the problem of prohibited materials U.N. inspectors suspected Baghdad was still hiding.</p>
<p>But the deal did not work when Iraq barred in July and August teams of Ekeus's inspectors from entering several sites it said were vital for its national security.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not say we came to an agreement but it appears there will be effort from the Iraqi side that these elements will not be repeated...We'll judge in our future work if this renewed undertaking will be honoured,&quot; Ekeus said.</p>
<p>Ekeus, chairman of the U.N. Special Commission (UNSCOM) in charge of scrapping the banned Iraqi weapons, said his talks with Aziz also addressed the issue of some banned materials which his commission believed were still in Iraq's possession.</p>
<p>Hour after Ekeus left for Bahrain, Aziz said in a statement to the Iraqi News Agency (INA): &quot;We stressed to UNSCOM chairman and we repeat the confirmation with all force again that Iraq does not hide prohibited weapons or banned weapons components or related documents.&quot;</p>
<p>Ekeus said his commission still lacked full accounting of all proscribed items, particularly production materials in the three major areas -- biological weapons, chemical weapons and long-range ballistic missiles.</p>
<p>He acknowledged that UNSCOM had accounted for &quot;a large number of banned weapons but still what we are concerned about is quite significant&quot;.</p>
<p>The envoy said he was convinced that security counil members would view Iraq's latest undertaking &quot;with certain scepticism&quot;.</p>
<p>Aziz charged that the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) enlisted agents to mislead Ekeus's commission and the Security Council to prolong trade sanctions on Iraq.</p>
<p>&quot;We maintained (in the talks) that time had come for the (weapons) files, reopened in August 1995, to be closed by focusing on intensive, professional and objective action...and not on the intrigues and lies the United States and its mercenaries propogate,&quot; Aziz said.</p>
<p>Ekeus arrived in Baghdad on Monday. It was his second visit to Iraq in about two months.</p>
<p>Days before his arrival the U.N. Security Council issued a statement in support of his mission, demanding that Iraq fully honour its ceasefire commitments and allow arms experts free access to any facility they wish to see.</p>
<p>Iraq is under U.N. trade sanctions, including a ban on its oil exports, for invading Kuwait in 1990. The removal of curbs on its crude exports, apart from the partial oil sales deal Baghdad signed with the United Nations in May, depends on testimony by Ekeus that Iraq has fully honoured all weapons demands under the ceasefire.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
