<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29668" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Iraq's Saddam defies U.S., gives order to shoot.</title>
<headline>Iraq's Saddam defies U.S., gives order to shoot.</headline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein defied the armed might of the United States by ordering his forces to ignore a &quot;no fly zone&quot; and shoot down intruders.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council, meanwhile, made no change on Tuesday to stiff economic sanctions, including a ban on oil sales, imposed on Iraq since its 1990 invasion of Kuwait.</p>
<p>The decision, made during a routine review, was not directly related to Iraq's weekend armoured assault on a Kurdish-held area in the north of the country which prompted U.S. missile strikes against targets in southern Iraq.</p>
<p>Wearing his field marshal's uniform, Saddam said on state television on Tuesday: &quot;You men of our air defence and falcons of the skies...Hit back with capability and efficiency, relying on God, the Almighty, at any hostile plane the aggressors fly to violate the airspace of your great country throughout Iraq.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry was equally robust, saying Iraq's military offensive against Kurdish rebels posed a &quot;clear and present danger&quot; to neighbouring states and the flow of oil to the West.</p>
<p>The United States, he said, reserved the right to take further action.</p>
<p>U.S. forces struck what Washington said were military targets in southern Iraq with 27 cruise missiles -- retaliation for the capture of the main Kurdish city of Arbil in the north.</p>
<p>Iraq said minimal damage was done and that five people had been killed and 19 wounded. Some casualties were civilians.</p>
<p>The United States also hit at Iraq's already crippled economy, saying Baghdad would not be able to export oil for &quot;some time&quot;, putting on hold a U.N. oil-for-food plan that would have allowed Iraqi crude onto the world market for the first time since the 1990 invasion of Kuwait.</p>
<p>Saddam chaired a meeting in Baghdad of Iraq's ruling body to discuss &quot;details of the unjust U.S. aggression&quot; and it took a number of unspecified decisions in response to the missile attack.</p>
<p>The Iraqi news agency INA quoted a spokesman for the Revolution Command Council meeting as strongly criticising the U.S. decision for freezing the oil-for-food deal.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. is behaving as if it is the decision-maker in the U.N. Security Council and it is the one who launches aggression under the council's resolutions,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council's decision to make no change to sanctions was not unexpected. Even without Iraq's lunge into Kurdish-held territory, the council would still have retained the embargo intact.</p>
<p>A prime condition for any easing is a clean bill of health from the U.N. Special Commission (UNSCOM) in charge of scrapping Iraq's weapons of mass destruction.</p>
<p>UNSCOM chief Rolf Ekeus told reporters he was still far from satisfied that Baghdad had made a full disclosure, citing shortcomings in the areas of missiles as well as chemical and biological programmes.</p>
<p>So far the United States has received open support for its stance on Iraq from Britain and Germany.</p>
<p>China and Russia have urged restraint and France, throughout the past week, has been cautious. Some Arab countries condemned the cruise missile attacks. Saudi Arabia remained silent.</p>
<p>The United States used a 1991 Security Council resolution to justify its missile attack on southern Iraq but it was questionable if the resolution in fact mandated such action.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton announced the expansion of a no-fly zone for Iraqi aircraft in southern Iraq to the outskirts of the Iraqi capital.</p>
<p>&quot;This will deny Saddam control of Iraqi air space from the Kuwaiti border to the southern suburbs of Baghdad,&quot; Clinton said in a statement from the White House.</p>
<p>The U.S. attack sent oil prices soaring to post-Gulf War highs but by late on Tuesday markets had settled back.</p>
<p>In Iraq, the attack and fading prospect of oil exports sent the dinar plummeting to 1,750 from 1,250 dinars to the dollar before recovering to 1,500.</p>
<p>&quot;We must make it clear that reckless acts have consequences or those acts will increase,&quot; Clinton said. &quot;...Our objectives are limited but clear: to make Saddam pay a price for the latest act of brutality, reducing his ability to threaten his neighbours and America's interests.&quot;</p>
<p>Ordinary Iraqis in Baghdad, languishing under sanctions, seemed unconcerned about missile strikes but were dismayed the oil-for-food deal had been scuttled, at least for a while.</p>
<p>&quot;Tell me whether oil will flow or not. I have not seen the missiles and I am not interested to hear about them. Twenty or 30 missiles will scare nobody,&quot; said Fa'ik Alaf.</p>
<p>The White House had said there was evidence that some Iraqi forces were &quot;penetrating deeper&quot; into northern Iraq and threatened Sulaimaniya, stronghold of the rebel Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) which was ousted from Arbil and replaced by its old rival and Saddam's new ally, the Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP).</p>
<p>But Iraq's Deputy Prime Minister Tareq Aziz said Baghdad would complete a withdrawal from the Kurdish north on Tuesday and denied reports Iraq was massing forces close to Sulaimaniya.</p>
<p>The U.S. attack was one of the largest on Iraq since the end of the Gulf War, when a U.S.-led coalition drove Iraq from Kuwait in 1991.</p>
<p>B-52 bombers and American warships in the Gulf unleashed the 27 cruise missiles at about 15 targets identified as air defence radars, missile sites and command and communication centres.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
