<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29889" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: U.N. says Iraq concealing clandestine weapons.</title>
<headline>U.N. says Iraq concealing clandestine weapons.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Goodman</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>After hearing Iraq was still concealing details of its clandestine weapons programs, the Security Council on Tuesday retained intact the stiff economic sanctions imposed on Baghdad since its August 1990 invasion of Kuwait.</p>
<p>The council decision, relayed by diplomats, was made during a review of the sanctions conducted every 60 days.</p>
<p>It was not directly related to Iraq's weekend attack on a Kurdish-held area in the north of the country which drew a response early on Tuesday from the United States in the form of missile strikes against targets in southern Iraq.</p>
<p>But even without Iraq's push into the Kurdish area, where the United States and its Western allies have maintained a no-fly zone since the end of the Gulf war, the council would have retained the sanctions unchanged.</p>
<p>A prime condition for any easing is a clean bill of health from the U.N. Special Commission (UNSCOM) in charge of scrapping Iraq's weapons of mass destruction.</p>
<p>UNSCOM chief Rolf Ekeus, who briefed the council on a recent trip to Baghdad, told reporters he was still far from satisfied Iraq had made full disclosure, citing shortcomings in the areas of long-range missiles, chemical and biological programs and related documents.</p>
<p>&quot;Iraq has not accounted for the missile capability fully,&quot; he said, adding that between six and 16 remained unaccounted for.</p>
<p>When Iraqi deputy Prime Minister Tareq Aziz told him it would make little difference even if Iraq had 10 such missiles, since its neighbors had many more, Ekeus said even one missile with a chemical or biological warhead would cause a &quot;major catastrophe&quot; if it hit a city.</p>
<p>Moreover, Security Council resolutions required all missiles to be accounted for and destroyed, he said.</p>
<p>His latest visit to Baghdad followed several incidents during which Iraq delayed or barred access by U.N. inspectors to sites which it considered especially sensitive.</p>
<p>Ekeus said UNSCOM had documentary evidence Iraq had produced chemical agents &quot;to an extent which is not reflected in its declarations.&quot;</p>
<p>Calling concealment of information the &quot;deepest problem,&quot; Ekeus said Iraq had very recently given &quot;conscientiously misleading statements&quot; regarding the hiding and moving of documents related to its weapons programs -- which he said Aziz himself had admitted.</p>
<p>Because of the outbreak of hostilities in the area, UNSCOM had grounded its flights Tuesday and would probably do so again Wednesday. &quot;That will hamper our mobility and capability to come to the (inspection) sites,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked if Iraq had the capability of hitting countries in the region, such as Israel, with rockets, he said: &quot;We have not accounted for all long-range missiles Iraq has acquired. Those missiles we know, are able, if they exist, to reach as far as Israel.&quot;</p>
<p>Iraq launched some 40 Scud-type missiles, fitted with conventional warheads, against both Israel and Saudi Arabia during the Gulf war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
