<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="32351" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: UN arms inspectors in Iraq put flights on hold.</title>
<headline>UN arms inspectors in Iraq put flights on hold.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.N. weapons inspectors have grounded surveillance helicopters in Iraq, fearing the Iraqis might shoot them down accidently during confrontations wih the United States, a U.N. official said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The (Iraqi) air defense is very alert and trigger happy, so there is a risk that we will be inadvertently shot down from the ground,&quot; said Rolf Ekeus, head of the U.N. Special Commission in charge of scrapping Iraq's dangerous weapons.</p>
<p>The lack of surveillance helicopters means the arms experts are unable to spot Iraqi efforts to move prohibited equipment the commission believes Baghdad is still concealing.</p>
<p>&quot;The search for sensitive items must be kept on hold,&quot; Ekeus said, repeating that &quot;We suspect that Iraq is having an active policy of concealment of these prohibited items.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the new no-flight zone imposed by the United States shortly after it unleashed cruise missiles against targets in southern Iraq now reached the outskirts of Baghdad.</p>
<p>&quot;We have two sides which are facing each other. We are aware these are no ordinary times so I don't want them to fly,&quot; he said, adding: &quot;We have grounded all our air operations for the time being.&quot;</p>
<p>Ekeus said he had 104 inspectors and support staff in Baghdad and all had been told to stay in radio contract in case of an emergency. But he had no plans to withdraw them.</p>
<p>He also denied reports that his commission had helped the United States identify Iraqi targets. He said inspections of Iraqi surface-to-air missiles, some of which Baghdad has been allowed to keep, were done at a special place chosen by Iraqi authorities and not on the site.</p>
<p>Ridding Iraq of its nuclear, ballistic missile, chemical and biological potential is a key requirement before sanctions imposed in August 1990 can be lifted on Iraq's oil exports.</p>
<p>Ekeus earlier said Iraq had not fully documented its missile capability and between six and 16 were unaccounted for. His latest visit to Baghdad followed several incidents during which Iraq delayed or barred access by U.N. inspectors to sites it considered especially sensitive.</p>
<p>Calling concealment of information the &quot;deepest problem,&quot; Ekeus said Iraq had very recently given &quot;conscientiously misleading statements&quot; regarding the hiding and moving of documents related to its weapons programs.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
