<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49904" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Ericsson, Saab defence j/v eyes growth.</title>
<headline>Ericsson, Saab defence j/v eyes growth.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedish telecoms firm LM Ericsson AB said on Thursday that the joint defence venture with Saab Aircraft, announced on Thursday, would strengthen their position in the world defence industry.</p>
<p>Ericsson said earlier its Ericsson Microwave Systems AB division would form a joint venture, called Ericsson Saab Avionics AB, with Saab Aircraft on military aircraft technology.</p>
<p>&quot;The formation of Ericsson Saab Avionics signifies the concentration of a number of key areas for future defence systems,&quot; said Ericsson Microwave Systems president Jan-Ake Kark in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;This means enhanced possibilities for exports and development of our operations.&quot;</p>
<p>The new venture would incorporate Ericsson Microwave Systems operations, the Saab Dynamics equipment division and the Saab Military Aircraft unit, Ericsson said in a statement.</p>
<p>The merger of complementary activities in Saab and Ericsson would &quot;strengthen the companies' positions while structuring the Swedish defence industry in strategically important areas,&quot; Ericsson said.</p>
<p>Ericsson Saab Avionics, which would be consolidated into the Ericsson group, would concentrate on electronic warfare, display and surveillance systems and electromagnetic technology, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;We will strengthen the positions of both Saab and Ericsson in the electronic warfare and MMI (Man-Machine Interface) fields,&quot; said Bjorn Erman, the newly appointed president of Ericsson Saab Avionics, in a statement.</p>
<p>Erman was previously director of Ericsson Microwave Systems.</p>
<p>Several of the new company's products would be used in the Saab-manufactured fighter jet, the JAS 39 Gripen.</p>
<p>Saab and Ericsson will own equal shares in the company, but Ericsson will hold the final vote.</p>
<p>-- Paul de Bendern, Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1006</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
