<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64896" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mesa Air fined, to make safety changes.</title>
<headline>Mesa Air fined, to make safety changes.</headline>
<dateline>FARMINGTON, N.M.</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mesa Air Group Inc. said Thursday it agreed to pay the Federal Aviation Administration a $500,000 fine for maintenance problems, and make major changes to improve airline safety.</p>
<p>The company, based in Farmington, N.M., operates under the names of Mesa Airlines, America West Express, United Express and USAir Express. Its fleet has more than doubled to 175 planes in five years.</p>
<p>The FAA launched an investigation of the company last year and found several maintenance problems that were reportedly similar to those in ValuJet Airlines after one of its planes crashed in the Everglades on May 11, killing 110 people.</p>
<p>&quot;The agreement is intended to ensure the carrier meets or exceeds regulatory requirements during its planned growth and expansion in the future,&quot; Chairman Larry Risley said in a telephone interview. &quot;We have agreeed to improve methods to verify that all our aircraft meet airworthy regulations.&quot;</p>
<p>Risley said Mesa will pay $250,000 of the fine up front, while the other $250,000 will be waived initially.</p>
<p>&quot;And when Mesa has complied with all the parts of the agreement, that remaining $250,000 will be forgiven,&quot; Risley said.</p>
<p>Risely stressed that the FAA found no safety dangers in Mesa's existing air services.</p>
<p>&quot;There is not a concern with the safety of the airline relative to the existing day-to-day operations. The concern that the FAA has expressed is our ability to maintain that level of safety going forward as we continue to grow the airline,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Under the settlement, Mesa will increase its flight maintenance and ground personnel, open a single maintenance control centre and implement new training and internal audit programmes. Some of the changes are already under way and all will be carried through within 12 months.</p>
<p>Mesa Air Group operates 115 19-passenger planes, five 37-passenger turbo-props and 32 30-passenger turbo-props as well as two Fokker 70 jets, which each carry 78 passengers.</p>
<p>It has also ordered 16 50-passenger regional jets and is waiting for their delivery. They will be used for the launch of Mesa's jet service at Meacham Airport in Fort Worth, Texas next May.</p>
<p>Risley said the FAA would announce details of the agreement in Washington later Thursday or on Friday.</p>
<p>Mesa's stock fell 25 cents to $9.375 on Nasdaq in late trading.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FARMINGTON, N.M."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
