<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74605" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mesa Air Group agrees to pay FAA fine.</title>
<headline>Mesa Air Group agrees to pay FAA fine.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mesa Air Group has signed an agreement with the Federal Aviation Administration to pay a $500,000 fine for maintenance problems and to further improve flight safety, the FAA said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>It said $250,000 of the fine would be waived if the new safety steps were implemented according to the approved plan.</p>
<p>The fine and stipulated further safety steps were announced by Mesa last week.</p>
<p>Mesa, with more than 150 planes, is an operator of commuter services under such names as United Express, USAir Express and America West Express, as well as Mesa Airlines.  </p>
<p>FAA officials said an inspection of Mesa began last year and another was continuing now to assure it complied with the new safety standards that commuters must meet by next March to bring their safety level up to that of the big carriers.</p>
<p>The officials said that if Mesa failed to meet the deadlines it would be fined $5,000 for each missed deadline.</p>
<p>They said that Mesa, based in Farmington, New Mexico, had a variety of safety shortcomings, such as faulty maintenance and inadequate flight training manuals.</p>
<p>But they said that all the shortcomings were corrected by the time FAA inspections were completed.</p>
<p>Thomas Stuckey, flight standards manager in the FAA's Dallas-Fort Worth office, said when inspectors went in they found some unsafe conditions in aircraft not in service as well as failures to comply with FAA approved company manual.</p>
<p>He said the $500,000 fine was leveled because of these violations, but &quot;the carrier today is in compliance.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the new standards Mesa must meet included hiring a full-time director of training and more training instructors, using more flight simulators and starting an internal audit and evaluation program.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
