<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77431" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. authorizes ValuJet to resume flying.</title>
<headline>U.S. authorizes ValuJet to resume flying.</headline>
<byline>Robert Trautman</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Transportation Department Thursday gave ValuJet Inc. a green light to resume flying, ending a three-month grounding for safety reasons after a crash in May that killed 110 people.</p>
<p>ValuJet has said it would be ready to fly as soon as possible after Transportation Department certification, but with fewer planes and to fewer cities.</p>
<p>Before its grounding it was one of the fastest-growing low-cost airlines in the country, flying 51 aircraft to numerous southern and southeastern cities.</p>
<p>At first, it will be allowed to fly only 15 planes, and it will need Federal Aviation Administration approval to increase its fleet, the department said.</p>
<p>The low-cost carrier was grounded on June 17 following an ongoing safety inspection of its operations that was intensfied after its Flight 592 crashed in the Florida Everglades near Miami on May 11.</p>
<p>A cause has not yet been determined, but investigators think that oxygen generators being carried in its hold may have ignited, causing a fire that led to the crash.</p>
<p>In the FAA's grounding order, ValuJet was cited for a series of maintenance and operations problems, and its return to flying was conditioned on correcting them.</p>
<p>Industry analysts said ValuJet will face stiff new competition from Delta Air Lines Inc. and Southwest Airlines Co. when it returns to the skies.</p>
<p>Before it was grounded, ValuJet's low costs had attracted many customers and become a nightmare for full-service carriers such as Delta, which like ValuJet is based in Atlanta.</p>
<p>Delta's new low-cost carrier, Delta Express, is to start service next week with 25 Boeing Co. 737-200 aircraft flying daily nonstop service from 10 northern cities to Orlando and four other destinations in Florida.</p>
<p>Florida, always competitive and a prime market for ValuJet in the past, has become even more cutthroat with new low-cost service from Southwest Airlines.</p>
<p>ValuJet said it would resume scheduled flights on Monday between Atlanta and four cities with $19 one-way introductory fares on all nonstop flights.</p>
<p>On Aug. 29, after ValuJet made changes ordered by the FAA, the agency approved it to resume flying and the Transportation Department gave tentative approval. But the department also asked for comment on ValuJet's financial status and whether the management was fit to run a safe airline.</p>
<p>There were few questions about its finances. But department officials said they had received numerous comments on the airline's safety, including one from the Association of Flight Attedants that alleged ValuJet falsified training records.</p>
<p>Officials said, however, the allegations were checked out and found to be without merit.</p>
<p>One official said the department took time with the comments because it wanted to &quot;walk the extra mile&quot; and &quot;to be certain that we looked at carefully and considered anything that had a bearing on Valujet's fitness.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if ValuJet was safe to fly, John Coleman, director of the department's office of aviation analysis, said, &quot;ValuJet has met all the FAA's requirments and they have met all our requirements and we have certificated them to fly.&quot;</p>
<p>The FAA had said that for ValuJet to fly again it must retrain its pilots, instructors and maintenance personnel and reduce the number of outside contractors it uses to be better able to supervise their work.</p>
<p>The department in its approval had to judge if ValuJet's management was capable of running a safe airline, and it concluded that &quot;the company will operate in compliance with safety regulations.&quot;</p>
<p>FAA officials have said the agency allowed the airline to grow too quickly and should have put it under increased safety scrutiny far earlier.</p>
<p>It has started a programme to monitor the safety of start-up and fast-growing airlines.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
