<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85188" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: ValuJet returns to U.S. skies after grounding.</title>
<headline>ValuJet returns to U.S. skies after grounding.</headline>
<byline>David Morgan</byline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>ValuJet Inc., the discount carrier that was once a darling on Wall Street but the bane of other airlines, returned to the skies on Monday for the first time since its grounding three months ago.</p>
<p>A DC-9 with 113 people on board -- including the company's two top executives, a Senator, a Georgia congressman and a smattering of journalists -- left Atlanta for Washington's Dulles airport after midday.</p>
<p>Dixieland jazz music, arches of yellow, blue and white balloons, and a crowd of cheering employees were on hand to greet passengers in the boarding area of Hartsfield International Airport before the flight.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very simply the support you have offered that has kept us going, waiting for this day,&quot; an elated ValuJet President Lewis Jordan told pilots and flight attendants who gathered for the celebration.</p>
<p>The festive mood was in sharp contrast to the gloomy atmosphere on May 11 when ValuJet Flight 592 crashed into the Florida Everglades, killing all 110 people on board.</p>
<p>Jordan said ValuJet would never forget the passengers and crew lost in the disaster. But company employees made little effort to hide their elation at hearing about the latest defeat of the Association of Flight Attendants (AFA).</p>
<p>The union, which since the crash has charged Jordan and ValuJet Chairman Robert Priddy with being unfit to run a safe airline, was denied a motion to stay the jet's takeoff in federal court.</p>
<p>But AFA said it would press ahead with an appeal of federal government approval for ValuJet's return to the skies.</p>
<p>The authorities grounded the airline in mid-June after heightened safety inspections indictated widespread maintenance problems tied in part to an aggressive expansion plan.</p>
<p>Within 2-1/2 years of ValuJet's launch in October 1993, the carrier mastered a strategy of low fares and low operating costs well enough to grow from a tiny startup to a regional operation with 320 daily flights to 31 cities and a payroll of about 4,000 employees.</p>
<p>The intensified Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) scrutiny which followed the May 11 crash turned up widespread maintenance problems at ValuJet. In mid-June, the FAA forced the airline to ground its fleet of 51 planes.</p>
<p>A 15-week project to overhaul the airline's operations ensued and the U.S. Department of Transportation (DOT) finally declared ValuJet fit to fly again last Thursday.</p>
<p>The reborn ValuJet was launched this week with a fleet of only five DC-9s and staff of 400.</p>
<p>But its $19 introductory fares to four U.S. cities, including Washington D.C., were reported to be drawing thousands of bookings each day.</p>
<p>On Friday, Atlanta-based Delta Air Lines Inc. said it would match the $19 introductory fares, which run through Thursday. Kiwi International Air Lines said it also would adopt a similar strategy.</p>
<p>Initially, the carrier will fly to Orlando, Tampa and Fort Lauderdale, Florida. Plans call for the addition of another 12 destinations by Oct. 24, by which time its one-way fares will have risen to $49.</p>
<p>Jordan indicated to reporters on Monday that ValuJet's financial goals have not have changed, saying the airline should still be able to operate near the very low cost level that preceded the crash.</p>
<p>&quot;Seven cents (per available seat mile) is the number I said we should be able to get to by the time we are at steady-state, up in maybe the 30-airplane level or above,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
