<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74800" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Briton hails gene-therapy step in cystic fibrosis.</title>
<headline>Briton hails gene-therapy step in cystic fibrosis.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>A top British geneticist said on Wednesday that he and colleagues had taken a first step towards gene therapy by using genes to treat cystic fibrosis patients.</p>
<p>Dr Chris Higgins, chair of clinical biochemistry at Oxford University, said the tests showed the technique was safe.</p>
<p>The hereditary disease, usually appearing in infancy or childhood, impairs breathing and digestion.</p>
<p>Eight volunteers with cystic fibrosis were given one dose of normal genes to counteract the genetic mutation that causes cystic fibrosis. Six of them were cured, temporarily, of the debilitating symptoms of the disease.</p>
<p>&quot;It worked,&quot; Higgins said.</p>
<p>Higgins said the technique used was not strictly gene therapy. &quot;What we are really doing is gene transfer, not gene therapy. But we believe it can also have clinical benefit.&quot;</p>
<p>True gene therapy would involve permanently altering a patient's genes, not just the genes in a cell that will eventually die. No one has done it yet.</p>
<p>Higgins' group delivered normal DNA to existing cells. To make a more permanent change, stem cells, which give birth to other cells, would have to be changed.</p>
<p>A step further would involve germ cells -- which would permanently alter a person's DNA and allow them to pass on the changes to their children.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only is germ-line therapy not possible, but in many countries, like this one, it is not legal either,&quot; Higgins told a conference organised by Britain's Royal Society -- the country's academy of sciences -- on the moral, legal and ethical questions of gene therapy.</p>
<p>Higgins, who said he was preparing to publish his findings, said the important part was that the therapy was safe. &quot;It did no harm, no damage whatsoever,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But it only worked for three weeks, which did not surprise Higgins. He said the experiment delivered therapeutic genes into the nose, where cells are renewed frequently.</p>
<p>Higgins' team is now analysing the results of a trial involving multiple doses, which could have long-term effects.</p>
<p>One in 20 people of European descent carries the cystic fibrosis gene. CF is one of the most commonly inherited genetic diseases and it is a favourite target for gene therapy.</p>
<p>The CF gene, identified and cloned in 1989, affects an iron channel -- an opening in the cell membrane that lets chloride, essential to cell function, in and out of the cell. That is why cystic fibrosis affects so many different organs, causing a buildup of mucus in the lungs and interrupting digestion.</p>
<p>Most efforts towards gene therapy use viruses. Viruses work by injecting their own genetic material, either RNA or DNA, into a victim cell. They can be manipulated to deliver the correct gene instead, and are extremely efficient.</p>
<p>But viruses can also be dangerous, and the body often develops an immune response that counteracts any good.</p>
<p>So Higgins' team is working with liposomes, fatty molecules that can bind to the cell membrane. They can be manipulated to incorporate whatever DNA the scientists want to deliver to cells, although they are less efficient than viruses.</p>
<p>The volunteers were given a nasal drip of the genetically modified liposomes. The target was the epithelial cells that line the nose. Tests were then done to see whether the cells of the volunteers were working normally. They were.</p>
<p>&quot;We can deliver the DNA, it functions, it makes the protein, the protein works,&quot; Higgins said. But he estimated it would be 10 years before true gene therapy was possible.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to have to get a lot of smart science done, a lot of investment. There are going to be no quick fixes.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
