<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15746" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan insurers may tread carefully in new market.</title>
<headline>Japan insurers may tread carefully in new market.</headline>
<byline>Fumiko Fujisaki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's insurance giants are expected to voluntarily restrain themselves even though they will be allowed to invade each other's turf once the market is deregulated in October.</p>
<p>Industry sources and analysts say it will take at least five years or more for insurers-- now divided into specialist life or non-life insurance companies -- to turn a profit in their new business.</p>
<p>This is partly because the insurers will voluntarily limit the range of business they engage in in order not to jeopardise smaller insurers and foreign insurers in Japan, they said.</p>
<p>Washington has protested Tokyo's newly revised insurance law which it says violates a U.S.-Japan trade agreement, and the dispute overshadows the process of deregulation, they said.</p>
<p>An amendment to a Japanese law on the insurance market took effect in April, allowing insurers to conduct both life and non-life insurance business through subsidiaries.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, 11 Japanese non-life insurance companies and six life insurance firms set up subsidiaries to enter each other's business.</p>
<p>Previously, insurance companies could operate only in one business sector.</p>
<p>&quot;The changes are expected to benefit consumers by making it easier to take out a variety of insurance policies with one insurer,&quot; said one insurance company official.</p>
<p>However, insurers have decided on a &quot;go-slow&quot; approach to avoid any radical change in the business environment, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The gap between big and small insurers is wide and we don't want to see the collapse of small insurers soon after deregulation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Josei Itoh, president of Japan's biggest life insurance company Nippon Life Insurance Co, recently told Reuters that it would take about 10 years for both non-life and life insurance subsidiaries to get under way.</p>
<p>&quot;We are worried about the entry (of non-life insurers) in our fields, and it might become a cause of turbulence in the short term,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On Monday, major Japanese non-life insurance company Yasuda Fire &amp; Marine Co Ltd announced it would take a majority stake in the Japanese unit of U.S. life insurance giant CIGNA Corp, the first time a Japanese non-life insurance company has purchased a life insurance subsidiary.</p>
<p>Industry sources said that Yasuda had avoided establishing a subsidiary as it believed that restrictions would make it less profitable to set up a life insurance arm.</p>
<p>Analysts said that Yasuda Fire made a good move.</p>
<p>Takehito Yamanaka, an analyst at New Japan Securities Research Institute, said Yasuda's purchase of a big stake in INA Life Insurance would probably give it a ready client base and allow it to offer a full range of products.</p>
<p>&quot;While Japan decided to deregulate the insurance industry, the U.S.-Japan insurance talks have not been agreed yet, and some restrictions on subsidiaries' business will remain for some years,&quot; Yamanaka said.</p>
<p>&quot;Yasuda would probably enjoy a wide range of life insurance business through INA than the life insurance arms of non-life insurers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Yasuda president Koichi Ariyoshi said on Monday that he expects Yasuda, through INA, will be able to offer a full range of insurance products, including those in the hotly contested &quot;third-sector&quot; niche market.</p>
<p>Japan and the United States agreed in 1994 that the implementation of the new insurance business law will not lead to any radical change in the third-sector market, which covers such items as personal accident, sickness and nursing care, the stronghold of foreign insurers.</p>
<p>However, Washington is unhappy with the process of deregulation in the third-sector market under the revised insurance law.</p>
<p>Several rounds of talks have been held since January to resolve the situation, and new talks are scheduled for some time in September.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
