<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16900" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French cabinet agonizes over African immigrants.</title>
<headline>French cabinet agonizes over African immigrants.</headline>
<byline>Irwin Arieff</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>France, shaken by immigrant protests including a hunger strike, chided African states on Tuesday for not helping stem the flow of people chasing a mirage of wealth only to end up as poor illegal residents.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Herve de Charette, in a clear jibe at France's former African colonies, told RTL radio they were not doing enough to tackle the problem.</p>
<p>&quot;There are countries which get considerable French aid and do not always give the impression of doing all they could to prevent these unfortunate individuals from ending up adrift in France, and once they are here, to take them back,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>French police last week stormed a Paris church to evict some 300 African immigrant protesters demanding residence permits, 10 of whom were on a hunger strike.</p>
<p>Exposing differences within the cabinet, Xavier Emmanuelli, secretary of state for emergency humanitarian action, said he regretted that the two-month occupation of the Saint-Bernard church had ended in police action rather than negotiations.</p>
<p>&quot;I would have preferred that it happen otherwise, but it was inevitable,&quot; Emmanuelli told the French daily Le Parisien.</p>
<p>Four days after police burst into the church, the Africans were still holding firm on their demands, and the affair kept fuelling a fierce political debate on illegal immigration and government policy.</p>
<p>The opposition Left and labour unions have accused the government of harshly cracking down on helpless immigrants snared by confusing 1993 reforms to France's immigration laws.</p>
<p>The far-right National Front, on the other hand, said that the post-raid confusion and release of most of the Africans shows the government is incapable of dealing with the problem.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing is settled, as just four individuals have been expelled and the search for the others has been abandoned,&quot; Front deputy leader Bruno Megret told a party conference.</p>
<p>&quot;Things are clear. (French President) Mr (Jacques) Chirac has given the signal. The doors are open,&quot; Megret said.</p>
<p>Interior Minister Jean-Louis Debre was quoted as saying that France had so far decided to grant residence permits to 49 of the immigrants.</p>
<p>Jean Kahn, head of the consultative human rights commission, said after meeting Debre that up to 40 percent of the total number of immigrants were expected to be allowed to stay.</p>
<p>Separately, courts were drawn deeply into the controversy as judges tried to sort out a legal tangle posed by many cases.</p>
<p>By late Tuesday, the Paris administrative tribunal had upheld expulsion orders against 61 of 89 Africans involved in the church protest while throwing out 15 such orders.</p>
<p>Four were deported on a military plane on Saturday along with dozens of other illegal African immigrants.</p>
<p>The Paris appeals court ordered the release on technical grounds of six of 13 immigrants still in custody since Friday's raid, but upheld detention of the remaining seven.</p>
<p>The court was still hearing appeals on another 40 Africans ordered freed by a lower court on Sunday but who still may ultimately end up being expelled. It said the hunger strikers, who ended a 52-day fast on Sunday, were too weak to be deported.</p>
<p>The Africans have called for a protest on September 18 in front of the headquarters of the Council of Europe in the eastern French city of Strasbourg.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
