<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="22696" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France says 88 illegal migrants deported to Africa.</title>
<headline>France says 88 illegal migrants deported to Africa.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>France said on Thursday it had sent home 88 Africans despite protests against a crackdown on illegal immigrants.</p>
<p>The Interior Ministry said 35 Malians, 11 Senegalese, 12 Tunisians and 30 Zaireans -- 10 of them expelled from the Netherlands -- were aboard two chartered planes which left on Wednesday night.</p>
<p>The government apparently waited until the flights had reached their destination to confirm they had taken off and disclose who was on board.</p>
<p>The airliners, at least one of them a military plane, left from Evreux air base west of Paris after unionists and human rights activists had urged civilian pilots not to fly deportees.</p>
<p>The air force Airbus A-310 flew to Mali and Senegal, the ministry said. The other plane, a Boeing 737, flew to Tunis and Kinshasa, refuelling on the way in Niger.</p>
<p>French handling of the illegal immigration issue has taken centre stage since a controversial police raid on 300 African protesters, 10 of them on a hunger strike, who had been occupying a Paris church for two months in a symbolic protest.</p>
<p>CIMADE, an organisation looking after immigrants, said three of the church protesters were on the latest deportation flights. This was not confirmed by the ministry.</p>
<p>Four of the church protesters and 53 other Africans had been deported last week on a military aircraft.</p>
<p>Thousands of demonstrators marched through Paris on Wednesday to demand that expulsion orders be repealed and immigration laws reviewed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SENEG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TUNIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
