<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41297" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: UAE set to combat &quot;visa mafia&quot;.</title>
<headline>UAE set to combat &quot;visa mafia&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Youssef Kassem</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Arab Emirates on Monday said it will apply new immigration rules in October in its drive to curb illegal aliens and industry sources said the move would help combat a growing &quot;visa mafia&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Authorities are determined to apply the new law governing foreigners' entry and residency,&quot; said UAE Interior Minister Lt-Gen Mohammed Said al-Badi in a press statement carried by the official WAM news agency.</p>
<p>The new law, which takes effect in October, follows a two-month amnesty period for violators to legalise their stay or leave. It stipulates fines and jail sentences against absconders and illegal residents, as well as their sponsors and employers.</p>
<p>Jail sentences of up to 15 years will also apply to those assisting illegal entry of aliens into the country.</p>
<p>Foreigners account for about 75 percent of the UAE's population of 2.4 million. Regulations governing residency require foreigners to work only for their original sponsors.</p>
<p>Local media has reported several cases of labourers leaving their sponsors due to poor working conditions and low pay.</p>
<p>Labour experts in the oil-rich UAE say a &quot;visa mafia&quot; has made hefty profits by illegally selling entry visas and work permits for up to $2,000.</p>
<p>They said illegal aliens have to pay a similar amount when renewing their visas.</p>
<p>&quot;The visa mafia is well established in the UAE, they have branches and brokers in India, Sri Lanka, Pakistan and the Phillipines,&quot; said one employer.</p>
<p>&quot;They are headhunters for the gullible and the desperate... the time has come to uproot them,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Illegal entry by sea has also become a growing phenomenon, the labour experts said.</p>
<p>UAE officials have said illegal aliens pose a security threat to the UAE and have called for tougher action.</p>
<p>Illegal aliens and absconders are the main offenders in crimes reported by the media.</p>
<p>Analysts said the country's employment market has become tight because opportunities have decreased with the completion of infrastructure projects and an influx of UAE college graduates.</p>
<p>UAE officials frequently urge nationals to join the workforce that attracts foreigners from other Arab states, Asia, India and the former Soviet republics.</p>
<p>Businessmen say the departure of large numbers of labourers could take its toll on businesses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
