<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43886" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton highlights welfare reform as campaign trip starts.</title>
<headline>Clinton highlights welfare reform as campaign trip starts.</headline>
<byline>Gene Gibbons</byline>
<dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton started a cross-country campaign swing on Tuesday highlighting a hard-edged policy popular with middle-class voters, moving poor people from welfare to work.</p>
<p>In this Midwestern city where in 1994 he formally proposed a plan to overhaul the much-despised U.S. public assistance system -- a plan that went nowhere in Congress -- Clinton held a roundtable discussion with six former welfare mothers, who now hold jobs with private firms, and their employers.</p>
<p>&quot;The welfare system is about to change nationwide ... This new welfare reform law fundamentally changes the bargain,&quot; said the Democratic president, who last month signed into law a Republican-sponsored welfare reform plan that ends a 60-year-old guarantee of federal aid to the poor.</p>
<p>He said he was convinced the only way states will be able to move large numbers of people from welfare to work in a short time &quot;is with a partnership with the private sector&quot; -- a plan being tested in Missouri and 11 other states.</p>
<p>Under this plan, funds that used to be spent on public assistance are reallocated to subsidise employers to hire and train welfare recipients. &quot;We're basically trying to break a mindset and an almost physical isolation from the world of work,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Later, in a speech to a meeting of the Southern Governors' Conference, Clinton said state leaders had demanded welfare reform, and it was up to them to make it work. &quot;We have now moved welfare beyond the realm of political rhetoric and blame, and it's no longer a question of who to blame, it is entirely a question of what are we going to do,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're going to have to move about a million people ... from welfare to work by the year 2000 to come anywhere close to meeting the requirements of the law and to avoid causing either a humanitarian crisis for the states or an enormous drain on your resources,&quot; Clinton told the governors. &quot;You asked for this, and now you've got it.&quot;</p>
<p>Leading Republican challenger Bob Dole by a substantial margin in public opinion polls less than eight weeks before the Nov. 5 presidential election, Clinton was clearly determined to maintain his momentum.</p>
<p>In response to a reporter's question, he rejected Dole's criticism of a new federal law that lets workers take time off to care for a new baby or sick family member. Dole said it was unwarranted government intrusion, but Clinton said: &quot;I just respectfully disagree. I think we were right to do it. ... It's not a big radical step. It's pro-family and pro-work.&quot;</p>
<p>But even as his re-election bandwagon rumbled along, two political problems nipped at Clinton's heels -- a sex scandal involving former top campaign aide Dick Morris and Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's penchant for mischief in the Gulf.</p>
<p>White House spokesman Mike McCurry told reporters the White House had known since &quot;sometime in 1995&quot; that Morris, the man behind the president's emphasis on &quot;family values,&quot; had fathered a child in an extramaritial affair six years ago.</p>
<p>And White House Chief of Staff Leon Panetta said the administration was watching Iraqi military activity in southern Iraq. Military moves in northern Iraq triggered U.S. cruise missile strikes last week.</p>
<p>Morris abruptly quit the Clinton campaign two weeks ago after a supermarket tabloid reported that he shared White House secrets with a $200-an-hour prostitute with whom he had a year-long affair in Washington.</p>
<p>Clinton also planned to highlight his education proposals at a campaign rally in St. Louis on Tuesday and was to focus on crime-stopping and health benefits for the elderly at rallies in Colorado and Arizona on Wednesday.</p>
<p>He was to spend Thursday in California, the biggest prize on Nov. 5, with 54 of the 270 electoral votes needed to win the election. The latest survey by a respected independent pollster put Clinton ahead of Dole by 23 percentage points.</p>
<p>Campaign aides said Clinton also enjoyed a double-digit lead in traditionally Democratic Missouri, a state Clinton carried in 1992, and claimed there were signs Dole, from neighbouring Kansas, might write off its 11 electoral votes.</p>
<p>They said Clinton also led in Colorado, a Rocky Mountain swing state whose eight electoral votes he carried in 1992, and in traditionally Republican Arizona, whose eight electoral votes went to Republican President George Bush in 1992.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANSAS CITY, Mo"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
