<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46494" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Democrats protest as U.S. immigration bill advances.</title>
<headline>Democrats protest as U.S. immigration bill advances.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>House Republicans moved ahead on Wednesday on a long-delayed bill to combat illegal immigration as Democrats assailed its plan to allow states to bar illegal immigrant students from public schools.</p>
<p>Democrats opposing this and other provisions in the bill predicted a Senate filibuster and a presidential veto even though the measure as a whole seeks to respond to wide public concern over a flood of illegal aliens into the country.</p>
<p>Both the House of Representatives and Senate have passed separate versions of the measure but further congressional action has been stalled since Senate passage last May because of problems with the schools provision adopted by the House.</p>
<p>The House action on Wednesday sent a compromise bill worked out by Republicans to a Senate-House conference committee expected to consider it next Tuesday.</p>
<p>The chief architect of the bill, Representative Lamar Smith, a Texas Republican, told the House illegal immigration had reached a crisis with one million illegal aliens coming in each year.</p>
<p>He pointed out the bill doubled the number of border agents, made it more difficult for illegal aliens to get jobs and overhauled deportation procedures.</p>
<p>But Democrats complained they had had no voice in crafting the compromise, suggesting Republicans might be seeking a veto by President Bill Clinton to create an election issue.</p>
<p>On Wednesday California's Republican Gov. Pete Wilson met House Speaker Newt Gingrich and other House members to urge support for the schools provision attached to the bill by Representative Elton Gallegly, R-California.</p>
<p>Wilson said education accounted for $2 billion of the $3 billion California spent on benefits to illegal immigrants.</p>
<p>The state is vital to Clinton's election strategy.</p>
<p>Democrats complained that the bill removed safeguards against employer discrimination against Hispanic and Asian Americans who might be denied jobs because of suspicion they were in the country illegally.</p>
<p>&quot;They (the Republicans) systematically weakened or eliminated that which would protect American citizens against discrimination or government error,&quot; Representative Barney Frank, a Massachusetts Democrat, said.</p>
<p>In the Senate, Massachusetts Sen. Edward Kennedy, the Judiciary Committee's senior Democrat said: &quot;This bill will do more harm than good. It doesn't deserve to pass.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
