<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46509" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYC says US welfare bill may violate Constitution.</title>
<headline>NYC says US welfare bill may violate Constitution.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani on Wednesday attacked the new federal welfare bill, saying some of its provisions, like ones denying benefits to future immigrants, raised &quot;serious constitutional questions.&quot;</p>
<p>New York City will be hit particularly hard by the new legislation, which imposes a number of new restrictions, because it has such a large population of immigrants.</p>
<p>In prepared remarks, the mayor, whose grandparents emigrated from Italy, estimated that the city has 400,000 illegal and undocumented immigrants, adding the new rules might prevent up to 80,000 children from attending public schools.</p>
<p>Giuliani, a Republican, was addressing Georgetown University's Law School in Washington.</p>
<p>&quot;The act creates dangers for our states and cities. If you have 400,000 undocumented immigrants who are cut off from hospitals, schools and police protection, it's going to create danger for us all.&quot;</p>
<p>Saying he believed the new welfare act &quot;does more harm than good,&quot; Giuliani focused on how he thinks it conflicts with the law. He only noted in passing that the new act fails to provide the funds needed to help welfare recipients find jobs, though he added the city sends the federal goverment $9 billion more than it receives back.</p>
<p>In early August, the mayor estimated that the dramatic new welfare rules, which require recipients to begin working after collecting benefits for two years, could cost the city as much as $600 million.</p>
<p>Under former Mayor Ed Koch, New York City enacted a law that protects undocumented and illegal aliens who want to use city health and safety services. The seven-year old law, which also was supported by former Mayor David Dinkins, protects all city residents, Giuliani said, explaining that immigrants who are ill might pose a danger to the public health.</p>
<p>He also said it was important not to discourge immigrants from reporting crimes. &quot;Muggers don't ask for a green card before commiting a crime.&quot;</p>
<p>Saying the federal government was targeting the weakest residents--children, crime victims and people who are ill--the mayor said it first should focus on the over 4,000 illegal, undocumented criminals who are jailed in the city every year.</p>
<p>While New York City has reported these criminals to the Immigration and Naturalization Service, he said only about 200 to 300 were deported.</p>
<p>The new welfare act also clashes with the city's police power, which tries to protect the confidentiality of undocumented or illegal aliens, Giuliani said.</p>
<p>He added part of the act would compel cities to put in place a Congressional reporting program, violating the 10th amendment in the U.S. constitution, which he said protects states and their subdivisions from being forced to serve federal regulators.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
