<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49804" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Immigrants occupy Paris police office.</title>
<headline>Immigrants occupy Paris police office.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of African and Asian immigrants occupied a Paris police office on Thursday to demand residence permits for 350 of them, witnesses said.</p>
<p>After several hours the protesters peacefully left the building, where police screen applications for residence permits, after receiving assurances that their demands would be considered.</p>
<p>Their spokesman said the 350 were nationals from 21 countries, and 150 of them were Asians.</p>
<p>Signalling a continuing hard line on illegal immigrants, the Interior Ministry said 57 Romanians were deported to Bucharest on a chartered flight on Thursday, and 14 Tunisians were sent home by ship this month.</p>
<p>The latest deportations took to more than 8,800 the number of foreigners expelled from France this year, an increase of 24 percent over the same period last year, the ministry said.</p>
<p>Thursday's protest took place in a heavily immigrant northern district, not far from the Saint Bernard church where some 300 Africans, 10 of them on a hunger strike, were holed up for two months to demand residence permits. Police evicted them in August.</p>
<p>The government has flown home eight of the Saint Bernard protesters and said the others had no legal right to stay in France but their cases would be reviewed individually on humanitarian grounds.</p>
<p>Many immigrants say they once enjoyed residence rights but were plunged into illegality when laws were stiffened in 1993 to curb immigration.</p>
<p>The Consultative National Human Rights Commission asked the government on Thursday to review implementation of the laws in order to grant residence permits to several categories of foreigners whose legal situation was unclear.</p>
<p>They included foreigners who have a French spouse, foreign spouses and children of legal foreign residents, parents of French-born children, illegal residents who have a job and have blended well in French society, students and ill persons.</p>
<p>It said the law also should be reviewed to allow residence permits for foreigners whose request for political asylum had been rejected but who would face serious danger if they were sent back to their home country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
