<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55197" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ANGOLA: ANGOLA FAILS TO DEPORT 18 S.AFRICANS.</title>
<headline>ANGOLA FAILS TO DEPORT 18 S.AFRICANS.</headline>
<byline>Lesley Wroughton</byline>
<dateline>LUANDA 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eighteen South Africans accused by police of illegally working in Angola's diamond areas were still being held by immigration authorities on Monday and did not board a flight to Johannesburg as scheduled, officials said.</p>
<p>The South African Embassy in Luanda said at the weekend that Angola's immigration authorities had agreed to deport the men on Monday. But Angolan police confirmed late on Monday they were still being held at a Luanda prison.</p>
<p>&quot;The South Africans are still with us...We are processing paperwork,&quot; a policeman who asked not to be named told Reuters. South Africa's Ambassador in Angola, Roger Ballard-Tremer, told reporters the men did not believe they were guilty of any customs infringements.</p>
<p>&quot;Indeed, none that we have spoken to can quite understand the problem that they are confronted with. One of the difficulties, of course, is that the charges -- if any -- still have to be formulated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ballard-Tremer said the men had however accepted they would be deported.</p>
<p>&quot;This morning the spirits were quite high, possibly because they might have heard from someone that they might be released. They certainly have now reconciled themselves to their plight, and are hoping to be released as soon as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>Angola launched a national campaign to root out foreigners operating illegally in the country and toughtened immigration laws last month. Until now the Cancer II operation has netted more than 1,000 foreigners, mostly from West Africa.</p>
<p>Three of the South Africans were arrested in Saurimo, the capital of Lunda Sul province, last week after being accused of entering the country on an illegal flight from Cape Town and failing to clear their equipment through customs.</p>
<p>The other 15 men were arrested during the week at N'Giva in Cunene province, for allegedly failing to pay import duties on equipment and entering the country on visitor permits instead of work visas.</p>
<p>Both groups had been contracted to work on diamond concessions in Lunda Norte province where most of Angola's diamonds are found.</p>
<p>Representatives of several South African mining companies who were meeting in Luanda at the weekend told Reuters they were in the country seeking help from South African and Angolan authorities to get back equipment worth millions of dollars.</p>
<p>They accused generals and businessmen who own concessions in Lunda Norte of cheating their South African partners by having them pay for equipment which was then &quot;hijacked&quot; once it arrived at the site.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ANGOLA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
