<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58611" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Congress meeting on U.S. immigration bill put off.</title>
<headline>Congress meeting on U.S. immigration bill put off.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A House-Senate conference to approve a major bill on illegal immigration was abruptly postponed Tuesday as it came under new attack by Democrats.</p>
<p>The Republican-drafted bill -- a compromise between bills passed by the House and Senate this year -- has been mired in controversy over a provision allowing states to deny public school education to children of illegal immigrants.</p>
<p>The provision, added in the House by Republican Elton Gallegly of California, is supported by presidential candidate Bob Dole and opposed by President Clinton, who has threatened a veto if it remains in the bill.</p>
<p>Republican officials said the conference was postponed because House members might not be able to attend, but Sen. Edward Kennedy said he had been told the delay was due to Republican &quot;disarray&quot; over the Gallegly amendment and that a new version was being &quot;cooked up.&quot; The Massachusetts Democrat said negotiations were taking place with the Dole campaign.</p>
<p>Published reports have said some Republicans want to keep Clinton from gaining politically by signing a widely popular bill with a flourish at a White House ceremony. Democrats complained that the measure was a partisan document aimed at improving Dole's election prospects.</p>
<p>Although attacks on the bill have focused on the Gallegly amendment, Democrats held a news conference to detail other objections under headings that ranged from treatment of asylum seekers to the environment. They complained that the bill:</p>
<p>-- Gutted provisions protecting Hispanics and others from discrimination by employers, eliminated protection for people fired or not hired because of incorrect information on their right to work and opened the way for possible discrimination by consular officials on the basis of sex or ethnic origin.</p>
<p>-- Exempted the construction of fences along the U.S.-Mexican border from two environmental laws, threatening several species of wildlife.</p>
<p>-- Eliminated the hiring of additional wage and hour inspectors by the Labour Department to clamp down on employers hiring illegal workers.</p>
<p>-- Restricted the ability of the average American to sponsor relatives wishing to move to the United States.</p>
<p>The Senate bill's leading architect, Republican Alan Simpson of Wyoming, said Monday that the Gallegly amendment, although modifified since it was adopted in the House, would lead to a filibuster in the Senate that would be supported by 10 or 12 Republicans.</p>
<p>The modified version would allow children of illegal immigrants currently in school to remain there. States would be able to charge fees if the children changed schools. The law would require a new vote by Congress to continue it beyond two and a half years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
