<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64275" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UAE: Foreign workers in UAE flock out ahead of new law.</title>
<headline>Foreign workers in UAE flock out ahead of new law.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The first boat hired to repatriate illegal foreign workers in the United Arab Emirates has set sail for India as an expatriate exodus continues ahead of a tough new immigration law, the Indian Association said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Embassies are flooded with applications for exit permits as tens of thousands of foreigners rush to leave the country by sea and air during a two-month amnesty period granted to illegal workers that expires on September 30.</p>
<p>The law, which comes into effect on October 1, imposes stiff penalties on illegal aliens or workers who violate labour laws.</p>
<p>&quot;The first launch left yesterday with 200 people on board,&quot; said K.V. Shankar, the secretary general of the privately funded association in Dubai.</p>
<p>Originally five small, open-decked cargo boats had been hired to make the four-day trip across the Arabian Sea. But after the first launch left on Wednesday, with a bucket as its toilet, the association pulled the plug.</p>
<p>&quot;For humanitarian reasons there will be no more launches, but a ship holding 2,000 people is due to leave on September 28,&quot; said Shankar, whose group organised Wednesday's sailing.</p>
<p>&quot;The boats were not in very good condition,&quot; said Shankar, adding: &quot;It is torture travelling with the open deck, the toilets, everything.&quot;</p>
<p>Many illegal expatriates have been leaving the UAE by air for weeks, but no figures on their numbers are available.</p>
<p>Diplomats expect up to 200,000 expatriates will have left by the end of the August-September amnesty period, in which violators can legalise their stay or leave the country.</p>
<p>The UAE has said foreigners who do not have permits to reside in the emirates or who work for employers other than their sponsors -- a widespread practice -- would be severely penalised and deported. The practice has always been illegal but the new law imposes harsher punishment.</p>
<p>From October 1, illegal workers and their employers face hefty fines and jail sentences if they are caught.</p>
<p>Foreigners, mostly from the Indian subcontinent but also from the Philippines and other southeast Asian states, make up 75 percent of the UAE's 2.4 million population.</p>
<p>UAE officials have said illegal aliens pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>But business executives and newspapers say the departure of large number of labourers could take its toll on businesses, which rely on low-paid foreign workers.</p>
<p>India's Ambassador, Murladhir Menon, said over 30,000 Indian nationals had applied for so-called &quot;out-visas&quot; and &quot;the stream of people applying for these permits to leave is continuing&quot;.</p>
<p>But he said that because many could not afford the 800 dirham ($220) airfare, he had asked the Shipping Corporation of India to send boats to help bring the workers home.</p>
<p>Joseph Angeles, charge d'affaires at the Philippines Embassy in Abu Dhabi, said some 3,500 people had sought help from the embassy since the amnesty began, but said it could just be the tip of the iceberg.</p>
<p>&quot;There might be a huge number of people who come in when the deadline draws nearer,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DUBAI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UAE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
