<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67400" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Bangladeshis return from UAE ahead of new law.</title>
<headline>Bangladeshis return from UAE ahead of new law.</headline>
<dateline>DHAKA 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than 450 Bangladeshi workers have returned to Dhaka from Abu Dhabi to avoid tough new immigration laws, the Independent newspaper said on Friday.</p>
<p>It said they were probably the first group of some 150,000 Bangladeshis expected to return to escape a crackdown on illegal workers in the United Arab Emirates (UAE).</p>
<p>The UAE had asked Bangladesh's diplomatic mission in Abu Dhabi to take back the illegal Bangladeshis by September 30, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>It quoted Dhaka airport officials as saying that most of the Bangladeshis usually go to UAE on short-term visas obtained through recruitment agencies.</p>
<p>&quot;After expiry of the visas, the workers destroy their passports and try to stay on illegally.&quot;</p>
<p>The UAE has given a two-month amnesty to illegal workers during which violaters can legalise their stay or leave the country.</p>
<p>The new immigration law, which comes into effect on October 1, imposes stiff penalties on illegal aliens or workers who violate labour laws.</p>
<p>Diplomats expect some 200,000 expatriates will have left by the end of the August-September amnesty period.</p>
<p>Government officials were not available for comment as Friday was a weekend in Moslem Bangladesh.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DHAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
