<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71186" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton would revive health care plan, Dole says.</title>
<headline>Clinton would revive health care plan, Dole says.</headline>
<byline>Michael Posner</byline>
<dateline>GRAYSLAKE, Ill 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republican presidential nominee Bob Dole searched for suburban votes on Sunday suggesting President Bill Clinton would try to revive a &quot;government takeover&quot; of health care if re-elected.</p>
<p>During a one-day trip to this Chicago area town, Dole tried to portray the president as a liberal who would use a second term to spend freely on government programs.</p>
<p>&quot;Now the election is just around the corner,&quot; Dole said in prepared remarks, &quot;so President Clinton will do everything he can to hide his liberal agenda.&quot;</p>
<p>Speaking at the College of Lake County rally, Dole said it was three years ago to the day that Clinton unveiled his health care insurance plan to cover most Americans, a plan that died in Congress after a fierce national debate.</p>
<p>The plan, Dole said, would have cost $1.5 trillion and &quot;created 50 brand new federal bureaucracies, countless new laws and federal penalties and put one-seventh of the U.S. economy under government control ...(and) imposed 17 new taxes.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There are hints that if re-elected, President Clinton might take another shot at a government takeover of health care,&quot; Dole added. &quot;Of course he says 'the era of big government is over.' As usual his actions tell a different story than his words.&quot;</p>
<p>Dole's press secretary Nelson Warfield said the purpose of his speech was to wish a &quot;happy anniversary to Bill Clinton's big government scheme and remind voters what's ahead if Bill Clinton never has to face voters again.&quot;</p>
<p>This will be a theme as the campaign enters the final six weeks of the campaign to the Nov. 5 election, Warfield said.</p>
<p>Clinton's press secretary Joe Lockhart fired back, saying Dole had passed no significant health care reform bills as majority leader of the first Republican Congress in 40 years.</p>
<p>&quot;Bob Dole's negative attacks can't hide his do-nothing record,&quot; he said in a statement.</p>
<p>Lockhart said it was only after Dole quit the Senate to concentrate on his presidential bid that Congress passed a Clinton-backed health-care bill allowing people to keep insurance if they change jobs or have a pre-existing illness.</p>
<p>Dole also hammered away at other familiar themes, including his proposed 15 percent income tax cut and an attack on Clinton's drug policies.</p>
<p>&quot;There are over a million more children using drugs today than the day Bill Clinton was elected,&quot; Dole said. &quot;That's enough to fill every football stadium in America.&quot;</p>
<p>In an attempt to lower expectations, Warfield said that Clinton is the favorite going into the presidential debates despite Dole's 35 years in Congress as a veteran of many debates before he resigned for full-time campaigning.</p>
<p>&quot;Clinton comes into the debates with a substantial advantage,&quot; Warfield told reporters. &quot;He's glib and agile, but I'm confident that Sen. Dole can hold his own.&quot;</p>
<p>Dole won a tactical victory on Saturday when negotiators decided to exclude Reform Party candidate Ross Perot from the two presidential debates, Oct. 6 in Hartford, Connecticut, and Oct. 16 in San Diego. That is what Dole wanted since his campaign believed Perot could cut into Dole's support.</p>
<p>Grayslake is part of a ring of suburban mostly Republican communities surrounding Chicago that Dole must carry if he wants to win Illinois.</p>
<p>A Reuters/Zogby poll last week showed Dole trailing Clinton by 16 percentage points in a state Clinton won over President George Bush four years ago.</p>
<p>A new CNN/USA Today/Gallup tracking poll conducted on Sept. 19-21 showed Dole trailing Clinton nationally by 19 percentage points, with the gap widening to 30 percentage points among likely women voters. Among men, Dole trailed by only six percentage points.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GRAYSLAKE, Ill"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
