<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72826" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Democrats unable to derail U.S. immigration bill.</title>
<headline>Democrats unable to derail U.S. immigration bill.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>A House-Senate committee on Tuesday cleared a major illegal-immigration bill for final Congressional action after stripping out a provision allowing states to bar illegal-alien children from public schools.</p>
<p>Angry Democrats blasted sections of the Republican-drafted bill and Senate Democratic Leader Tom Daschle threatened to use delaying tactics to force changes in it.</p>
<p>The bill, which aims to stem a flood of illegal aliens into the United States and has become tangled in election-year politics, was expected to clear the House of Representatives this week and then go to the Senate.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton had threatened to veto the bill if the school provision remained, even though Republicans had modified it so current students would not be expelled.</p>
<p>It was unclear whether removal of the provision would enable him to sign it in view of Democrats' vehement objections, although Republicans predicted he would do so.</p>
<p>Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole had urged retention of the school provision, attached to the House version of the bill by California Republican Elton Gallegly. Some Democrats said Dole wanted to force a veto and deny Clinton a political success.</p>
<p>But in a letter to Republican leaders in the House and Senate, Dole reversed his position, recommending that the school provision be removed and voted on separately.</p>
<p>Noting that California was being especially hard hit by the problem of illegal aliens in the school system, Dole said, &quot;President Clinton should sign both measures.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;However, if the liberal Democrats in Congress block consideration of the second measure, then the citizens of California will know whom to blame -- a liberal president who feels no compunction about inflicting a multi-billion dollar burden on California's taxpayers,&quot; Dole's letter said.</p>
<p>Clinton has ardently wooed vote-rich California in his quest for re-election. Polls show he is well ahead there.</p>
<p>In the Senate-House conference committee, normally used to iron out differences between bills passed by the two chambers, Democrats complained bitterly that they were being presented with a take-it-or-leave-it bill, with no amendments allowed.</p>
<p>But Daschle told reporters later that &quot;mean-spirited&quot; provisions in the measure had to be confronted. The bill would cut welfare benefits for legal aliens and set new financial standards for sponsors' support of legal immigrants.</p>
<p>With Congress nearing adjournment, Daschle noted that &quot;just the threat&quot; of an extended debate could doom the bill.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that it is either going to be done our way, in a way that we can work together, or it is not going to be done at all,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sen. Edward Kennedy, a Massachusetts Democrat, said the bill &quot;is weak on illegal immigration but harsh on American working families, legal immigrants and refugees.&quot;</p>
<p>Democrats charged the bill removed current safeguards for Americans such as Hispanics against discrimination from employers fearful of hiring aliens, and did not do enough to clamp down on employers hiring illegals.</p>
<p>They complained of &quot;harsh&quot; procedures for asylum-seekers and the elimination of a provision that would bar giving visas to wealthy people who renounce their citizenship to escape taxes.</p>
<p>The bill would:</p>
<p>- Double the size of the border patrol, adding 5,000 new agents and 1,500 support workers over five years and adding other investigators to trace people who overstay their visas.</p>
<p>- Authorise the building of new fences along the Mexican border near San Diego, California.</p>
<p>- Beef up penalties for alien smuggling and document fraud and speed removal of illegal aliens.</p>
<p>- Set up pilot projects for employers to verify their workers' immigration status and strengthen barriers against the granting of welfare benefits to illegal aliens.</p>
<p>- Revise provisions in anti-terrorism law relating to people entering the country without proper documents to give more protection to asylum claimants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
