<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72821" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Prudential in policyholder settlement.</title>
<headline>Prudential in policyholder settlement.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Vowinkel</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prudential Insurance Co. of America said it agreed to pay at least $410 million to settle lawsuits by policyholders claiming they were victims of deceptive sales practices.</p>
<p>Under the settlement, about 10.7 million policyholders who bought permanent life insurance policies between 1982 and 1995 would be eligible to apply for restitution.</p>
<p>The settlement improves the terms of an agreement Prudential reached with a multi-state task force of insurance regulators this summer, said Melvyn Weiss, one of the lead attorneys negotiating the settlement.</p>
<p>It provides policyholders with the potential for greater relief and makes it easier for them to qualify for it, he said. Weiss expects the policyholders to enter into a formal agreement with Prudential on Oct. 25 and a notice to class members to be sent out in November.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe the amounts paid out under our plan are more than what would have been paid out under the original plan,&quot; Weiss said.</p>
<p>A court hearing to determine whether or not the settlement is fair is likely to be held sometime in February or March.</p>
<p>&quot;This settlement allows Prudential to move forward in providing the best possible service to our clients and customers&quot; said Prudential Chairman Arthur Ryan</p>
<p>The settlement marks Prudential's latest effort to resolve allegations that it improperly pressured unsophisticated investors to replace their life insurance policies, a practice known as churning or twisting.</p>
<p>In July, insurance regulators from 43 states and Washington, D.C., recommended a $35 million fine and restitution programme for sales abuses by Prudential.</p>
<p>Prudential said it will request that the remediation programmes previously accepted by the states be modified to make them consistent with the class action settlement.</p>
<p>Prudential said discussions are being held with the remaining seven states to acquaint them with the terms of the class action settlement.</p>
<p>Those states had opposed the original multi-state agreement because of concern that it placed the burden of proof of wrongdoing on policyholders and not the company.</p>
<p>Complaints about abusive sales practices have plagued the life insurance industry over the past few years.</p>
<p>Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., New York Life Insurance Co. and Allianz Life Insurance Co. of North America all have been involved in similar actions in the last two years.</p>
<p>Metropolitan Life agreed in 1994 to pay $20 million in fines and up to $76 million in policyholder refunds to settle allegations it improperly marketed life insurance policies as retirement or savings plans.</p>
<p>New York Life last year agreed to a national class action settlement in a dispute over dividends on life insurance policies and Allianz Life in June agreed to pay $5.1 million, including $2.3 million in restitution to settle allegations it engaged in deceptive sales practices in California.</p>
<p>New York insurance regulators earlier this month moved to fight the industry's problems by proposing a tough new regulation to protect consumers from the inappropriate replacement of life insurance policies.</p>
<p>The Prudential class action settlement includes general relief as well as an alternative dispute resolution process.</p>
<p>The general relief, which includes enhanced life insurance, annuities and low-cost premium loans, is available to all policyholders who purchased permanent life insurance policies from 1982 to 1995.</p>
<p>Prudential said it did not have an estimate of the value of the general relief to policyholders.</p>
<p>Under the alternative dispute resolution process, policyholders could be eligible for restitution, as well as additional compensation, Prudential said.</p>
<p>The amount Prudential will pay under the alternative dispute resolution process is not capped, but the insurer is committed to paying at least $410 million.</p>
<p>If Prudential receives more than 110,000 legitimate claims, then it will pay out more than $410 million.</p>
<p>Under a formula worked out in the settlement, if Prudential receives 330,000 legitimate claims, it would pay $780 million in restitution and $300 million in additional compensation for a total payout of about $1.08 billion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
