<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72899" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Revised immigration bill cleared for final action.</title>
<headline>Revised immigration bill cleared for final action.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>A House-Senate committee on Tuesday cleared a major illegal immigration bill for final congressional action after stripping out a provision allowing states to bar illegal alien children from public schools.</p>
<p>The bill, which aims to stem a flood of illegal aliens into the United States and has become tangled in election-year politics, was expected to clear the House of Representatives this week and then win final approval from the Senate.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton had threatened to veto it if the schools provision remained, even though Republicans modified it to ensure that illegal alien children now in schoool would not be expelled.</p>
<p>Clinton's Republican election opponent, former Senate Majority Leader Bob Dole, had urged that the schools ban be retained -- a position some Democrats said was an attempt to force a veto and deny Clinton a political success.</p>
<p>But in a letter to Republican leaders in the House and Senate, Dole cleared the way for action on the long-delayed bill by a conference committee of the two houses, recommending that the schools provision be separated from the bill and voted on separately.</p>
<p>Noting that California was being especially hard-hit by the problem of illegal aliens in the school system, Dole said: &quot;President Clinton should sign both measures.</p>
<p>&quot;However, if the liberal Democrats in Congress block consideration of the second measure, then the citizens of California will know whom to blame -- a liberal president who feels no compunction about inflicting a multi-billion dollar burden on California's taxpayers,&quot; Dole's letter said.</p>
<p>California is America's most populous state and has by far the most votes in the Electoral College, which selects the president under the indirect U.S. voting system. Polls now rate Clinton a strong favourite to win California.</p>
<p>A House architect of the immigration bill, Republican Lamar Smith of Texas, said he expected a separate vote in the House on the school provision, added to the bill by California Republican Elton Gallegly last March.</p>
<p>However, prospects for this provision looked dim in the Senate where it faces strong opposition.</p>
<p>The whole bill could also be in danger in the Senate because of vehement Democratic opposition to some provisions.</p>
<p>Democratic Leader Tom Daswchle said that with adjournment looming &quot;just the threat of continued debate would make the immigration bill unlikely to be successfully completed.&quot;</p>
<p>At the House-Senate conference on the bill, called to resolve differences in versions pass by the two houses, Democrats complained they had been left out of negotiations and presented with a Republican &quot;take-it-or-leave-it&quot; measure.</p>
<p>The bill would:</p>
<p>- double the size of the border patrol, adding 5,000 new agents and 1,500 support personnel over five years and adding other investigators to trace people who overstay their visas;</p>
<p>- authorise the building of new fences along the Mexican border near San Diego, California;</p>
<p>- beef up penalties for alien smuggling and document fraud and speed removal of illegal aliens;</p>
<p>- set up pilot projects for employers to verify their workers' immigration status and stengthen barriers against illegal aliens getting welfare benefits;</p>
<p>- ensure that Americans who sponsor immigrants have the funds to provide for them so that they do not become a burden on the taxpayer;</p>
<p>- and revise provisions in anti-terrorism law relating to people entering the country without proper documents to give more protection to asylum claimants.</p>
<p>Democrats had a series of complaints about the bill.</p>
<p>They charged it removed current safeguards for Americans such as Hispanics who might suffer discrimination from employers fearful of hiring aliens, and did not do enough to clamp down on employers hiring illegals.</p>
<p>They said the bill damaged environmental laws by exempting the construction of fences along the U.S.-Mexican border from their application. And they also complained about &quot;harsh&quot; procedures for asylum-seekers and the elimination of a provision that would bar visas to wealthy people who renounce their citizenship to escape taxes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
