<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72895" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dole hits Clinton as liberal; economy steams on.</title>
<headline>Dole hits Clinton as liberal; economy steams on.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, Political Correspondent</p>
<p>Republican Bob Dole again branded U.S. President Bill Clinton an unrepentant liberal on Tuesday, but the president received more good economic news when the Federal Reserve decided not to raise interest rates.</p>
<p>The Fed's decision to leave rates unchanged means the economy will steam along unchecked at least until after the Nov. 5 presidential election. The Fed's next policy meeting is not until Nov. 13.</p>
<p>Speaking to reporters before the Fed announcement, Clinton took credit for the strong economy.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very pleased that we have strong growth and no sign of inflation,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Clinton leads Dole by 12-18 percentage points in recent polls and also leads in most &quot;battleground states&quot; where presidential elections are usually decided.</p>
<p>What is particularly striking is the fact that Dole has been unable to close Clinton's lead even a little this month. In 10 of the past 12 presidential elections, the front runner's lead has notably declined or evaporated between June and Election Day.</p>
<p>The only two exceptions were in 1972 and 1984, when incumbents Richard Nixon and Ronald Reagan extended their leads on the way to recording landslide victories.</p>
<p>With limited resources, Dole is already beginning to abandon some states he considers hopeless and he is being forced to spend valuable time and money in some traditionally Republican states like Arizona, Florida and Georgia.</p>
<p>Dole was in Michigan Tuesday, a must-win state where he trailed Clinton by 20 points in a Reuters poll last week.</p>
<p>In a speech before business people in Detroit, Dole attacked Clinton while promoting his proposal to cut income taxes by 15 percent while still balancing the budget.</p>
<p>&quot;The bottom line is under our plan, a family of four making $30,000 will save $1,261,&quot; Dole said. &quot;To some people that doesn't sound like a lot of money. But this is designed for Main Street, not Wall Street.&quot;</p>
<p>As he has for three days now, Dole portrayed Clinton as a liberal promoting conservative policies for the election but who would propose big spending programmes and taxes if elected.</p>
<p>Dole also suggested he may pick some cabinet members before the election.</p>
<p>Clinton played statesman, signing a landmark treaty that bans all nuclear testing and calling on the global community to get tougher on terrorists and drug traffickers.</p>
<p>Using the 51st session of the U.N. General Assembly to sketch out an election-year vision of international peace and prosperity, Clinton said the countries of the world needed to cooperate against terrorism and illegal drugs because no country was immune from these menaces.</p>
<p>Illustrating his determination to combat drugs, Clinton said he would provide &quot;more than $100 million worth of defence equipment, services and training&quot; to America's southern neighbours. This could help blunt Republican criticism of Clinton's anti-drug efforts.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in Washington, a congressional committee cleared a major illegal immigration bill for final congressional action after stripping out a provision backed by Dole that would have allowed states to bar illegal alien children from public schools.</p>
<p>It was another sign that congressional Republicans, anxious to present voters with a record of achievement, are beginning to abandon their presidential nominee to save their own electoral skins.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
