<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73037" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Juppe to crack down on illegal aliens.</title>
<headline>France's Juppe to crack down on illegal aliens.</headline>
<dateline>DEAUVILLE, France 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Prime Minister Alain Juppe, fresh from an acrimonious war of words with the far-right National Front, said on Tuesday he would next month put forward a bill cracking down on illegal immigration.</p>
<p>The conservative premier told a congress of parliamentarians of the UDF, junior partner in the ruling coalition, that the draft law would focus on clandestine workers, &quot;to dry up the source of clandestine immigration&quot;.</p>
<p>The bill would widen the definition of clandestine work, give authorities more powers and strengthen legal sanctions.</p>
<p>Juppe also said that next spring at the latest the government would put forward separate measures tightening already strict rules on French nationality.</p>
<p>&quot;Checks at borders and sending foreign nationals who have illegal status back to their country of origin is more than ever a priority,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The new measures will aim to simplify complex procedures for the expulsion of illegal immigrants and overhaul provisions for detention of suspects.</p>
<p>&quot;The law will take account of very special individual situations which this summer led to residence permits being granted on an exceptional basis,&quot; Juppe said in reference to a row over a long hunger-strike by illegal immigrants holed up in a Paris church until they were forced out by police.</p>
<p>While taking a tough line on illegal immigration, the government has also moved to appear sympathetic to immigrants in France accused by the far right of taking jobs from so-called native French people.</p>
<p>Juppe last week dubbed Jean-Marie Le Pen, leader of the anti-immigrant National Front, &quot;deeply, almost viscerally racist, antisemitic and xenophobic&quot;.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Jacques Toubon is preparing draft legislation for parliament after concluding that existing laws were too weak to prosecute Le Pen for stating this month that racial inequality was &quot;obvious&quot; and &quot;a fact&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEAUVILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
