<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75487" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mexico concerned at anti-immigrant mood in U.S..</title>
<headline>Mexico concerned at anti-immigrant mood in U.S..</headline>
<byline>Patrick Worsnip</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's foreign minister expressed concern on Wednesday over a &quot;new mood&quot; of hostility to foreign migrants in the United States but said he was relieved a draft immigration bill had been watered down.</p>
<p>Congressional negotiators on Tuesday approved details of a bill that deletes a Republican-backed provision allowing states to bar the children of illegal immigrants from public schools. Both houses of Congress now have to vote on the bill.</p>
<p>Speaking before talks with U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher, Mexico's secretary of foreign affairs, Jose Angel Gurria, said he was &quot;relieved that it's not going to have the chapter on education.&quot;</p>
<p>But he told reporters he was &quot;worried more generally about the context in which all this legislation is being proposed.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;That is something, by the way, which we feel will stay. It's not a question of, you know, disappearing after the November (U.S. presidential) election,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there is a new mood, and it's not good. We don't like what we see in terms of the attitudes of some members of the Congress and some regions in the United States, where the phenomenon of migration has given rise to attitudes which seem to be very hostile to migrants.&quot;</p>
<p>Gurria said that while Mexico did not want to encourage illegality, &quot;we're worried about the impact on human rights, labour rights.&quot; The country also feared that attitudes toward illegal migrants could spill over into attitudes toward legal migrants, he said.</p>
<p>State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said later that Gurria's remarks had struck a chord with Christopher.</p>
<p>&quot;Frankly, I can tell you that Secretary Christopher ... was in substantial agreement that the United States needed to remain an outward-focused country, a country that is open to foreigners, open certainly to immigration,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Both Gurria and Christopher played down differences over the U.S. Helms-Burton law, which punishes foreign companies that use property in Cuba that was seized by the Communist government in Havana from people who are now U.S. citizens. One Mexican and one Canadian firm have so far been targeted.</p>
<p>Gurria said the issue had &quot;got everybody worried&quot; but he had been working with Christopher and his aides &quot;in terms of how we can deal with the situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Christopher said Washington wanted to implement the law in a way that would hurt Cuba and minimise the impact on U.S. allies. The Clinton administration, clearly unenthusiastic about the law, has suspended a provision allowing Americans to sue foreign firms &quot;trafficking&quot; in their former property.</p>
<p>Gurria and Christopher hailed their countries' cooperation in the fight against the drug trade. Recent years have seen rising quantities of illicit drugs shipped through Mexico to the United States from producer countries in South America.</p>
<p>Burns said that as part of U.S. anti-drug aid to Latin America, the United States would supply Mexico with 20 helicopters for use along the two countries' common border and hoped to be able to provide 53 more later.</p>
<p>Out of $100 million promised on Tuesday by President Bill Clinton to help Latin American countries fight drug trafficking, $37 million will go to Mexico, Burns said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
