<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75593" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: House passes immigration bill; Democrats protest.</title>
<headline>House passes immigration bill; Democrats protest.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>The House of Representatives on Wednesday approved a bill aimed at stemming a tide of illegal immigration over Democratic protests against provisions they said unfairly targeted legal aliens.</p>
<p>The vote was 305-123, with 76 Democrats joining the Republican majority in favour of the Republican-drafted bill.</p>
<p>The measure now goes to the Senate where Democratic Leader Tom Daschle has been hinting at a possible filibuster.</p>
<p>Versions of the bill were approved overwhelmingly by the House and Senate earlier this year. But final congressional action was held up for months by a dispute over a provision allowing states to deny illegal immigrant children a public school education.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton said the provision would lead him to veto the bill. Republican presidential Bob Dole had supported it. Finally, with Dole's concurrence, the provision was stripped from the bill this week and was being voted on separately in the House following disposal of the main bill.</p>
<p>Clinton, meanwhile, was leaving his options open on whether he would sign the bill, a spokeswoman said, saying the president was talking to members of Congress about strengthening work-place enforcement of laws against hiring illegal aliens.</p>
<p>During the House debate, Democrats voiced anger at being left out of the drafting of the compromise measure, which they said was done in &quot;back rooms&quot; in concert with the Dole campaign.</p>
<p>They also complained the measure would require Americans who wanted to bring a close family member to the United States to meet financial standards that would be beyond low-income people.</p>
<p>Proponents of the bill said it would insure that sponsors of immigrants were held to their commitment to make sure their relatives were not a drain on taxpayers.</p>
<p>Critics also denounced provisions tightening up on admission of people arriving in the country without documents in search of asylum, saying it gave too much latitude to immigration inspectors.</p>
<p>Democrats charged that the bill removed safeguards for Americans such as Hispanics against discrimination by employers fearful of hiring aliens, and did not do enough to crack down on employers hiring illegals.</p>
<p>They criticised provisions they said would make legal immigrants liable for deportation if they used certain welfare programmes for more than a year, including tax-financed health care for AIDS victims.</p>
<p>They also complained that the building of new fences against illegal migration near San Diego was being exempted from some environmental laws.</p>
<p>The bill would:</p>
<p>- double the size of the border patrol, adding 5,000 new agents and 1,500 support personnel over five years and adding other investigators to trace people who overstay their visas;</p>
<p>- authorise the building of new fences along the Mexican border near San Diego;</p>
<p>- beef up penalties for alien smuggling and document fraud and speed removal of illegal aliens;</p>
<p>- set up pilot projects for employers to verify their workers' immigration status and stengthen barriers against illegal aliens getting welfare benefits.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
