<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78782" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton extols record with Congress leaders.</title>
<headline>Clinton extols record with Congress leaders.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton joined congressional Democrats in a pep rally Thursday and took credit with them for improvements in the nation's economy.</p>
<p>&quot;This country is on the right track,&quot; Clinton said after the closed-door meeting with members of the House and Senate. He appeared before cameras with Vice President Al Gore, Senate Democratic Leader Tom Daschle of South Dakota and House Democratic Leader Richard Gephardt of Missouri.</p>
<p>His trip to the Capitol came as Congress struggled toward pre-election adjournment, seeking to draft a catch-all bill to fund much of the government beginning Oct. 1 but still deadlocked over some other important measures.</p>
<p>Clinton said he and the Democratic leaders were determined not to allow the government to shut down for lack of a funding bill. If Congress is unable to work out a long-term measure for the full fiscal year, it is likely to approve one lasting a few days while negotiators continue to seek agreement.</p>
<p>Caught up in negotiations is a major illegal immigration bill that passed the House Wednesday but faces Democratic opposition in the Senate over provisions said to be &quot;mean-spirited&quot; toward legal immigrants.</p>
<p>The bill, aimed at stemming the tide of illegal aliens entering the country, is widely popular, especially in the key election state of California. In response to a reporter's question, Clinton declined to say if he would sign it.</p>
<p>He said he was gratified Republicans had removed from the bill a provision that would have allowed states to deny public education to illegal alien children. But he said he was withholding comment on the bill &quot;because it is the subject of intense negotiation.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I don't want to say anything that will complicate the work being done,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Clinton and Gore took the opportunity to brag about new census figures showing declining poverty and rising family income, with Gore reading 4-year-old newspaper headlines to point up the progress made during Clinton's term.</p>
<p>Clinton praised Congress's &quot;remarkable&quot; legislative record, declaring: &quot;I believe the American people want a Congress that will fight for the interests of the working families, expand education opportunities, balance the budget in the right way and never, ever shut the government down. And I am committed to that and I know they are.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
