<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81788" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Council of Europe urges better life for immigrants.</title>
<headline>Council of Europe urges better life for immigrants.</headline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG, France 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Council of Europe, which safeguards human rights and democracy, on Friday urged its 39 member states to step up the fight against racism and improve the legal situation of immigrants.</p>
<p>The Strasbourg-based Council's parliamentary assembly adopted a declaration calling for a more prominent role in society for immigrants and an improved standard of living for the poorest.</p>
<p>The vote, by a show of hands, was passed despite a move by French centrist and right-wing deputies to block it.</p>
<p>&quot;Immigrants are often concentrated in the suburbs and either don't want to or can't work, and they live with their many children with the help of a welfare state,&quot; said Charles Ehrmann, of the centrist UDF party, junior partner in France's ruling coalition.</p>
<p>The French deputies tried to block the declaration, saying it was not sufficiently hard on illegal aliens.</p>
<p>France's centre-right government has taken a tough stance on immigration and Prime Minister Alain Juppe announced last week that he was further stiffening laws on illegal immigration.</p>
<p>The declaration, which is not legally binding, called for a more vigorous fight against racism,</p>
<p>It also suggested that governments reach bilateral agreements with immigrant countries that would help contain illegal immigration and encourage foreigners to return home and asked for a study on how to reduce illegal immigration.</p>
<p>In August, riot police expelled 220 African immigrants, 10 of them on hunger strike, from a Paris church where they had camped out for two months to demand residence permits.</p>
<p>Human rights groups accuse the French government, which has expelled at least 8,800 foreigners so far this year, of being inhumane towards immigrants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
