<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82198" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: UAE's illegal immigrants fight time to get home.</title>
<headline>UAE's illegal immigrants fight time to get home.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tens of thousands of illegal immigrants are scrambling to get on planes and boats out of the United Arab Emirates, four days before a tough new labour law comes into force, diplomats said on Friday.</p>
<p>But thousands will likely be stranded in the Gulf state to face strict penalties when the law takes effect next Tuesday, as airlines and shipping companies struggle to cope with the mass exodus of illegal aliens.</p>
<p>Many expatriates without valid work papers have already left in a two-month amnesty period that expires on September 30.</p>
<p>But they are just the tip of the iceberg. Diplomats expect some 200,000 illegal aliens -- mostly from the subcontinent but also from Southeast Asian countries -- will try to go home before the law catches up with them. Embassies say they have issued only about 100,000 exit permits so far.</p>
<p>&quot;There are at least another 30,000 Indian nationals who still have to get out,&quot; Indian Consul-General in Dubai Prabhu Dayal told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If you divide that number by 250 for every aircraft needed to get them out, you'll need 120 airplanes. I don't know if that's possible in four days,&quot; he said, adding he expected a total of about 50,000 Indian nationals to leave.</p>
<p>Flights to destinations like New Delhi, Bombay and Manila have been booked solid until the deadline for over a week, travel agents said. Tickets for a 2,000-passenger ship due to leave the UAE on September 30 were sold out within hours.</p>
<p>An airport official in Dubai said the flood of foreigners leaving the country was so severe that sometimes travellers at the airport had to climb on each other's shoulders to move.</p>
<p>Immigrants make up 75 percent of the population in the Gulf oil state. Many came to the UAE legally, obtaining a work permit stipulating they have to work for their sponsor.</p>
<p>But large numbers break the law by overstaying their welcome, or absconding from their sponsors for what they say is better treatment or pay with other employers. The practices have always been illegal, but the new law imposes stricter punishment for offenders.</p>
<p>The UAE government says it is implementing the legislation to curb the spiralling number of illegal aliens, who it says pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>&quot;In the past there have been cases of embezzlement by employees who were not sponsored by their employer,&quot; said an Interior Ministry official quoted in the daily Gulf News on Friday. &quot;Others have stolen cash and fled.&quot;</p>
<p>The official said government studies had shown the new law was in the interest of all parties.</p>
<p>&quot;These studies showed there were many cases of sexual and physical abuse against housemaids working illegally for other employers that went unreported because the housemaids knew they had violated the law,&quot; the newspaper reported.</p>
<p>But many of the immigrants say they do not have enough time to prepare for their voyage home. Local newspapers report widespread complaints by the illegal aliens that employers are refusing to pay their due wages. Others say they do not have enough money to afford a flight or boat out.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very apparent that all these people cannot make an orderly exit in four days,&quot; Dayal said. &quot;Grace time is needed. What is so sacrosanct about the 30th of September? So many people have been harassed, there has been so much chaos. Extend the deadline.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
