<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82927" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: FEATURE - UAE's illegal Asian workers scramble to go home.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - UAE's illegal Asian workers scramble to go home.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Across the stream from the glitzy skyline of Dubai, Ram collapsed at the Indian consulate after hours in the blazing heat waiting for a permit to leave the country he had helped build.</p>
<p>Two storeys higher, Jeleel cowered in a corridor of the consulate, clutching her emergency travel papers with one hand as she wiped away tears with the other.</p>
<p>Ram and Jeleel are illegal guest workers in the United Arab Emirates, a Gulf oil state where immigrants make up 75 percent of the population.</p>
<p>But faced with a new law cracking down on illegal labour, they are now among an estimated 200,000 immigrants rushing to leave the country during a two-month amnesty period for illegal workers that expires on September 30.</p>
<p>The law, which takes effect on October 1, imposes stiff penalties on illegal aliens, foreigners without valid travel documents, and workers who violate labour laws.</p>
<p>The government vows it will rigorously enforce the law, and many immigrants -- mostly from the subcontinent but also from the Philippines and other Southeast Asian countries -- are scrambling to get out before it's too late.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of these people came to the country legally, but they absconded from their official employers for various reasons, primarily ill-treatment,&quot; said Prabhu Dayal, India's consul-general in Dubai.</p>
<p>&quot;Secondly, they absconded because their wages were not paid for some time. They were forced to abscond.&quot;</p>
<p>Many of the immigrants also obtain legal papers stipulating they have to work for their sponsor, but break the law by leaving to work for several employers on a part-time basis, which they say pays more than sticking to one job.</p>
<p>The UAE government says it is implementing the law to cope with a spiralling number of illegal immigrants, who it says pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>&quot;You don't know how, when and why the illegal immigrants came, so we have to clamp down on them to achieve safety for our own society,&quot; Mohammed Rashid al-Abdooli, director of the inspections department at the Labour and Social Affairs ministry, told the daily Emirates News.</p>
<p>The government also said the law would help combat the &quot;visa mafia&quot; which has made huge profits by illegally selling entry visas and work permits for up to $2,000.</p>
<p>Like many illegal workers, Ram and Jeleel came to the wealthy emirates from impoverished villages in India, filled with high hopes of big money.</p>
<p>They paid an Indian &quot;agent&quot; about 20,000 rupees ($550) to find them a job with a UAE sponsor -- a prerequisite for working in the country -- who would give them good pay, room and board.</p>
<p>&quot;But when I arrived, the horror started,&quot; said Jeleel, who left her husband and three young children behind in a town near Madras to work as a housemaid in Dubai.</p>
<p>&quot;They took my passport so I couldn't run away. I had to work days and nights cleaning, cooking, working but I never got paid. They told me 'later'. I still don't have a single dirham.&quot;</p>
<p>Allegations by Asian housemaids in the Gulf of abuse are hard to prove and are often discounted by governments as fabricated or exaggerated.</p>
<p>Ram, who worked as a construction labourer, stood in line outside the consulate with thousands of others, shielding himself from the scorching sun with a piece of cardboard. When he finally reached the counter to apply for his exit permit, he fainted.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a story of human suffering. It's not merely numbers,&quot; said an Indian diplomat.</p>
<p>When the workers return home, many will be deep in debt and face the same hardship they tried to escape by coming to the Gulf, diplomats say.</p>
<p>No figures for departures were available, but embassies said about 100,000 emergency papers had been issued. Many expect a rush for permits as the deadline nears.</p>
<p>The consul-general of Pakistan in Dubai, Sajjad Ashraf, said some families who applied to leave had come to the UAE over 30 years ago, before the seven emirates unified as one country and declared their independence from Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;They came when there were no border controls,&quot; Ashraf said. &quot;They just arrived on launches and started working.&quot;</p>
<p>Diplomats and travel agents say thousands of immigrants will be stranded in the UAE beyond the September 30 deadline because airlines cannot cope with the exodus.</p>
<p>Flights to destinations such as New Delhi, Bombay and Manila until the end of the amnesty have been booked for over a week. Tickets for a 2,000-passenger boat scheduled to leave Dubai on September 28 were sold out within hours.</p>
<p>Jeleel and many like her do not even have the money to pay for a flight or boat back to India. She huddled with other penniless immigrants in the consulate corridor, nervously waiting to hear if a donor could pay for her to go home.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DUBAI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
