<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83266" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: UAE extends illegal immigrant amnesty by a month.</title>
<headline>UAE extends illegal immigrant amnesty by a month.</headline>
<byline>Michael Georgy</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Arab Emirates on Saturday extended an amnesty for illegal immigrants, giving tens of thousands of people from the Indian subcontinent and southeast Asia another month to legalise their stay or leave.</p>
<p>Floods of illegal immigrant workers have been scrambling to get out of the oil-rich Gulf Arab state by plane and boat to avoid tough new penalties when the amnesty expires and a new law cracking down on illegal labour comes into force.</p>
<p>The previous amnesty was due to expire on October 1, and with airlines and shipping companies unable to cope with the mass exodus, diplomats feared thousands would be stranded in the UAE after the deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been decided that the amnesty period is extended one more month until October 31, 1996 to enable those remaining offenders to benefit from this temporary exemption,&quot; an Interior Ministry statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The ministry hopes that this matter will be taken very seriously without any delay in order not to find it necessary to take the strict legal procedures...,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>Jamal Sanad al-Suwaidi, the secretary-general of the committee for the demographic structure of the UAE which is in charge of the amnesty, said he expected some 140,000 illegal workers to leave the country.</p>
<p>&quot;By Monday I expect around 70,000 people will leave the country and for the following month I think it will be a similar number and most of those people are illegal in the UAE,&quot; he told Reuters Television in an interview.</p>
<p>He added that the move was prompted by political, economic and security factors.</p>
<p>&quot;With this huge number of illegal workers in fact what they are doing is they are creating an illegal labour market and creating at the same time economic hardships for themselves and for other workers in the country,&quot; al-Suwaidi said.</p>
<p>&quot;So I think it's an important decision and its about time that the decision was executed. It's a normal trend all over the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The UAE government says the new law will help curb the spiralling number of illegal aliens, who it says pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>But many of the immigrants complained the amnesty period was too short and did not give them enough time to prepare for the voyage, purchase tickets and collect outstanding wages.</p>
<p>Diplomats expect some 200,000 illegal aliens to try to leave the country before the new deadline expires at the end of October. But embassies said they had only issued about 100,000 exit permits thus far. Many diplomats feared a mad rush for the permits as the deadline approached.</p>
<p>The Indian consul-general in Dubai, Prabhu Dayal, said at least 30,000 Indians still had to leave the UAE, adding it would have been an impossible feat before the previous deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;There are 42,000 Indians who have taken out passes or emergency certificates... About 45,000 people altogether will be availing this opportunity,&quot; the Indian ambassador, Murlidhar Menon, told Reuters Television.</p>
<p>Speaking before the extended amnesty was announced, he said it would be a &quot;welcome development.&quot;</p>
<p>Foreigners make up 75 percent of the population in the UAE, where many work as labourers, housemaids or in the service sector. Diplomats say most come to the country legally with a work permit stipulating they have to work for their sponsor.</p>
<p>But large numbers break the law by overstaying their welcome or absconding from their sponsors for what they say is better treatment or pay with other employers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
