<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83428" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: UAE extends illegal immigrants' amnesty.</title>
<headline>UAE extends illegal immigrants' amnesty.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Arab Emirates on Saturday said it had extended for one month an amnesty for illegal immigrants to get their papers in order or leave the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The interior ministry has extended the amnesty for one month,&quot; a government spokesman said. The previous amnesty was due to expire on October 1.  </p>
<p>Tens of thousands of illegal immigrant workers -- mostly from the Indian subcontinent but also from southeast Asia -- have been scrambling to get out of the Gulf oil state by planes and boats in order to avoid tough new penalties when the amnesty expires.</p>
<p>The amnesty, which started at the beginning of August, preceeded a new law cracking down on illegal labour. The UAE says the law would help curb the spiralling number of illegal aliens, who it says pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>Diplomats expect some 200,000 illegal aliens to try to leave the country before the law catches up with them. Embassies say they have only issued about 100,000 exit permits thus far.</p>
<p>Foreigners make up 75 percent of the population in the UAE. Many come to the country legally. But large numbers break the law by overstaying their welcome or absconding from their sponsors for what they say is better treatment or pay with other employers. The practices have always been illegal, but the new law imposes stricter punishment for offenders.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
