<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83427" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: UAE extends illegal immigrant amnesty by a month.</title>
<headline>UAE extends illegal immigrant amnesty by a month.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Arab Emirates on Saturday extended an amnesty for illegal immigrants, giving tens of thousands of people from the Indian subcontinent and southeast Asia another month to legalise their stay or leave.</p>
<p>Floods of illegal immigrant workers have been scrambling to get out of the oil-rich Gulf Arab state by plane and boat to avoid tough new penalties when the amnesty expires and a new law cracking down on illegal labour comes into force.</p>
<p>The previous amnesty was due to expire on October 1, and with airlines and shipping companies unable to cope with the mass exodus, diplomats feared thousands would be stranded in the UAE after the deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;The interior ministry has extended the amnesty for one month,&quot; a government spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>The UAE government says the new law will help curb the spiralling number of illegal aliens, who it says pose a security threat to the country.</p>
<p>But many of the immigrants complained the amnesty period was too short and did not give them enough time to prepare for the voyage, purchase tickets and collect outstanding wages.</p>
<p>Diplomats expect some 200,000 illegal aliens to try to leave the country before the new deadline expires at the end of October. But embassies said they had only issued about 100,000 exit permits thus far. Many diplomats feared a mad rush for the permits as the deadline approached.</p>
<p>The Indian consul-general in Dubai, Prabhu Dayal, said at least 30,000 Indians still had to leave the UAE, adding it would have been an impossible feat before the previous deadline.</p>
<p>Foreigners make up 75 percent of the population in the UAE, where many work as labourers, housemaids or in the service sector. Diplomats say most come to the country legally with a work permit stipulating they have to work for their sponsor.</p>
<p>But large numbers break the law by overstaying their welcome or absconding from their sponsors for what they say is better treatment or pay with other employers.</p>
<p>The practices have always been illegal, but the new law imposes stricter punishment for offenders, including fines, jail terms and deportation.</p>
<p>For over a week, all flights to destinations such as New Delhi, Bombay and Manila have been booked solid past the previous deadline.</p>
<p>Amnesty-seekers crowded around travel agencies and the Indian consulate in Dubai where airlines built makeshift counters to process tickets. Thousands stood in line for hours in the scorching heat, only to discover there were no more seats available.</p>
<p>Tickets for a ship to India, which is due to leave on September 30 carrying 2,300 passengers, were sold out in hours. The Indian Association in Dubai, which organised the ship, said on Saturday it had arranged for a converted cargo ship to depart on the same day to take 2,000 other illegal workers home.</p>
<p>In addition, two launches were set to sail from Dubai for India on Saturday, despite widespread concern that the vessels were not safe enough for the four-day journey. Previous launches -- equipped with a bucket as the sole toilet facility -- were cancelled because they were deemed unsuitable for the trip.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no other cheap mode of transportation to go back,&quot; said Sunil Bhatia, who works at the privately-funded Indian Association. &quot;And even if someone can afford the 750 dirhams for a plane ticket, there just aren't enough places left.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
