<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83880" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: New UAE deadline eases pressure on illegal workers.</title>
<headline>New UAE deadline eases pressure on illegal workers.</headline>
<byline>Diana Abdallah</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1996-09-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pressure eased on Sunday at embassies and airlines in the United Arab Emirates following a decision to extend a deadline for an estimated 200,000 illegal immigrants to legalise their stay or leave, diplomats said.</p>
<p>Long queues still formed at embassies and airports of people trying to obtain exit permits or board congested flights mainly to India, Bangladesh, Sri Lanka, Pakistan and the Philippines.</p>
<p>The diplomats said Saturday's extension of a September 30 amnesty until October 31 for illegal immigrant workers would ensure that all illegal workers leave the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The amnesty eased the pressure. We really needed the extension due to the congestion on bookings. Now we think all those having to leave will do so by the end of October,&quot; said Joseph Angeles, the Philippines embassy charge d'affaires.</p>
<p>Thousands of workers have been scrambling to leave by plane and boat to avoid tough new penalties when the amnesty expires and a new law cracking down on illegal labour takes effect.</p>
<p>Airlines said they were unable to cope with the mass exodus despite introducing extra flights and diplomats had feared thousands would be stranded in the UAE after October 1.</p>
<p>Many of the immigrants complained the amnesty period was too short and did not give them enough time to prepare for the voyage, purchase tickets and collect outstanding wages.</p>
<p>The embassies said the Interior Ministry made it clear that the new deadline would not be extended further.</p>
<p>The government says the law will curb the growing number of illegal aliens, who it says are a security threat to the UAE.</p>
<p>&quot;People are less tense now and the extension will help them arrange transport and not be stranded here,&quot; said K.V. Shankar, secretary general of the privately-funded Indian Association.</p>
<p>He said the association has arranged for two ships to ferry 3,300 Indians to Bombay. One will leave on Monday with 1,200 people and another on Tuesday with 2,100 people.</p>
<p>Air India officials said the airline carried almost 19,000 Indian amnesty passengers home in the past week.</p>
<p>Jamal Sanad al-Suwaidi, secretary-general of the committee for the demographic structure of the UAE which is in charge of the amnesty, told Reuters Television on Saturday he expected some 140,000 illegal workers to leave the country.</p>
<p>Diplomats had expected some 200,000 illegal aliens to leave the country, but embassies said they had issued about 100,000 exit permits so far and thought the rush for permits was easing.</p>
<p>Now that the deadline has been extended, diplomats said some people might try to legalise their stay in the UAE.</p>
<p>&quot;But we think the majority want to leave,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>Foreigners make up 75 percent of the population in the UAE, where many work as labourers, housemaids or in the service sector. Diplomats say most come to the country legally with a work permit stipulating they have to work for their sponsor.</p>
<p>Many break the law by overstaying or absconding from their sponsors for better treatment or pay with other employers.</p>
<p>The new law has disrupted the day-to-day lives of residents, including working mothers who have lost their part-time maids, as well as small businesses who rely on part-time workers.</p>
<p>&quot;We advise the working women to either quit their work and look after their children or send them to daycare centres,&quot; the Khaleej Times newspaper on Sunday quoted a senior official at the federal immigration department as saying.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
