<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83913" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: House passes budget accord with Clinton's praise.</title>
<headline>House passes budget accord with Clinton's praise.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. House of Representatives late on Saturday easily passed a budget accord reached with the White House that President Bill Clinton hailed as bipartisan progress towards a balanced budget.</p>
<p>The compromise, reached early Saturday, grants the president the extra $6.5 billion he requested for domestic spending with $4 billion of that going to education.  The new fiscal year starts Tuesday, Oct. 1 and without passage of this bill, federal agencies would be forced to close.</p>
<p>The House voted 370-37 for the measure and sent it to the Senate where a vote is expected late on Monday, just hours before the start of the fiscal year.</p>
<p>In the Senate, Democrats said they were sceptical about what they said was the Republicans' &quot;midnight conversion&quot; to restored domestic spending. They wanted to comb the as-yet-unprinted bill carefully and could offer amendments during Monday's debate.</p>
<p>Speaking at a political rally in Providence, R.I., Clinton hailed the accord and praised Republicans for working in a bipartisan fashion and urged quick approval.</p>
<p>&quot;It is good for America because it continues to move us toward a balanced budget while protecting, not violating, our values,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Republican congressional leaders, who last year pushed the government to shut down twice rather than accept the administration's budget, stressed that the bipartisan accord ensured the government would stay open next week.</p>
<p>Senate Minority Leader Tom Dachle, D-South Dakota, said his party would not hold it up unnecessarily.</p>
<p>The massive spending bill provides $244 billion for defence and about $356 billion for domestic programmes. It also includes banking regulatory reform, bolsters savings and loan reserves, sells broadcast airwaves, clamps down on illegal immigration and expands anti-terrorism efforts.</p>
<p>The administration had wanted the defence department's budget cut by $3 billion and had asked for $10 billion in extra domestic spending.</p>
<p>Republicans were in a rush to adjourn so they could begin campaigning. Asked if that meant they gave in to Clinton, House Speaker Newt Gingrich said that was not the case but that compromises were made.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the lessons we learned is that you have got to find a way to work together to get things through the Senate. You have got to find a way to get the signature of the president if you want to get it done,&quot; Gingrich, R-Georgia, said of the compromises they made this year.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott, a Republican from Mississippi, added, &quot;If we had the White House, it (the budget) would be different.&quot;</p>
<p>A middle-of-night compromise on legislation to impose strict controls on immigration and crack down on illegal aliens cleared the way for agreement on the massive spending bill which funds the largest agencies in the government.</p>
<p>The extra $6.5 billion granted Clinton's request for $4 billion more for Head Start and other education programmes and raises college student Pell grants to the largest amount in history.</p>
<p>It allows $1.1 billion to fight terrorism, $650 million for fighting fires in Western states, $400 million to aid in recovery from Hurricane Fran, $123 million for troop redeployment in Saudi Arabia and $8.8 billion for the war on illegal drugs.</p>
<p>The extra spending will be paid for with $2.9 billion raised from the sale of cellular communications airwaves, $3.1 billion in higher bank reserves needed to clean-up the last of the savings and loan crisis, and $1 billion from defence.</p>
<p>The more than 2,000 page spending bill pays for the Pentagon, the national parks, education, jobs programmes, environmental protection, law enforcement including Clinton's plan to put 100,000 police on the street by 2000, the White House, foreign aid, health research and many other activities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
