<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83946" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Republican Congress mixes success and scandals.</title>
<headline>Republican Congress mixes success and scandals.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Admire it, revile it but most of all remember the first Republican Congress in 40 years for legislative landmarks, deep political division and government shutdowns.</p>
<p>As the 104th Congress fades into history, these may be the top dozen memories that will linger:</p>
<p>-- Americans, who always said they wanted less government, did not like it when they got it. Republicans orchestrated two government shutdowns that failed to produce a budget deal with President Clinton -- but did provoke public ire as &quot;closed&quot; signs went up at government offices and national parks.</p>
<p>-- Bob Dole surprised the country with an emotional decision to end a 36-year congressional career after he found he was unable to juggle his presidential campaign and Senate leadership amid guerrilla warfare by Democrats.</p>
<p>-- House Speaker Newt Gingrich showed extraordinary domination of the national political debate and mastery of the House Republican majority, but also struggled with ethical problems including a $4.5 million book deal and his demonisation by Democrats and the Clinton administration.</p>
<p>-- A year-long investigation of the Whitewater affair dogging President and Mrs. Clinton raised serious questions about the Clintons' conduct in 60 days of highly partisan hearings chaired by Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-New York.</p>
<p>-- A public perception that the United States was being overrun by immigrants, legal and illegal, led to legislation that sought to restrict both but wound up dealing mostly with illegal immigration.</p>
<p>-- Calling the war on poverty a failure, Republicans pushed through a historic bill ending a 61-year guarantee of federal aid to poor children, limiting benefits to five years and giving states new power to design their own welfare programmes.</p>
<p>-- Remember the health care crisis? Congress did, passing laws to help Americans keep insurance if they changed jobs or were ill. In a election-year nod to motherhood, lawmakers made insurers provide 48-hour hospital coverage for new moms.</p>
<p>-- Democrats posted a come-from-behind victory when Congress passed a bill raising the minimum wage from $4.25 to $5.15 an hour, something they did not do in the previous two years when they controlled Congress and the White House.</p>
<p>-- The graphic language of street debates came inside the Capitol as Congress passed, and Clinton vetoed, a bill to ban some late-term abortions. Congress voted more than 50 times on measures to restrict abortion.</p>
<p>-- Lawmakers sped onto the information superhighway, deregulating the telecommunications industry and paving the way for new technologies.</p>
<p>-- Farmers will have to produce for the market instead of the government under a landmark act phasing out Depression-era subsidies and planting restrictions.</p>
<p>-- Republicans tried to cut spending for toxic waste clean-up, sewage treatment and clean water only to face a rebellion in their ranks and attacks from Democrats.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
