<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83958" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. House passes immigration bill after changes.</title>
<headline>U.S. House passes immigration bill after changes.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. House of Representatives passed on Saturday a bill clamping down on illegal immigration after Republican leaders bowed to White House pressure and removed the most controversial measures from the bill.</p>
<p>A deal reached in negotiations that stretched through the night stripped out language that would make even legal immigrants liable for deportation if they used any of dozens of government relief programmes for one year out of their first seven in the country.</p>
<p>It also eased proposed income standards required of Americans seeking to sponsor entry of close family members.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton hailed the accord during a trip to Rhode Island, saying it fought illegal immigration &quot;without hurting innocent children or punishing legal immigrants.&quot;</p>
<p>The immigration measure was included in a huge bill funding much of the government for the 1997 fiscal year the House approved late on Saturday. The Senate was to vote on Monday.</p>
<p>Many Democrats had called the provisions in parts of a section called Title 5, targeting legal immigrants, &quot;mean-spirited&quot; and the White House refused to accept them.</p>
<p>Representative Howard Berman, a California Democrat and one of the bill's critics who has served on the congressional negotiating team, said: &quot;Basically all the worst provisions of Title 5 are out.&quot;</p>
<p>White House spokesman Mike McCurry said of the agreement: &quot;We're satisfied we have immigration measures that will continue to protect America's borders while setting the right kind of standards for legal immigration.&quot;</p>
<p>The agreement also removed a ban on government-paid treatment for AIDS for legal and illegal aliens.</p>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gingrich told a news conference Republicans had yielded to the White House on some issues &quot;in order to get everything done.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the administration had been adamant on allowing an illegal immigrant to have government-paid treatment for AIDS as well as emergency medical services.</p>
<p>&quot;We frankly receded to them on what most people would not think is a very good policy ... an illegal immigrant not only gets emergency medical services but can in fact be treated for AIDS at the cost of $119,000 to the taxpayer,&quot; Gingrich said.</p>
<p>The immigration bill approved by the House earlier this week would have required a sponsor of an immigrant to have an income of 140 percent of poverty level to sponsor immigration of a spouse or minor child or 200 percent to sponsor other close family members.</p>
<p>Under the accord a sponsor would need an income of 125 percent of poverty level and greater flexibility is allowed.</p>
<p>The idea is to make sure the immigrant does not become a public charge. But critics had said millions of Americans would have been denied the right to petition for family members to enter the Unites States.</p>
<p>But Gingrich said: &quot;I don't believe you can explain to most Americans where somebody who is already drawing food stamps ought to be a sponsor for somebody to come. But they (the White House) insisted on that.&quot;</p>
<p>The House author of the bill, Texas Republican Representative Lamar Smith, said all provisions aimed at stemming illegal immigration were retained. These included:</p>
<p>- Doubling the number of border control agents with 1,000 a year added for five years.</p>
<p>- Extra fences along the U.S.-Mexico border near San Diego.</p>
<p>- Increased criminal penalties for alien smuggling and document fraud and wiretap authority in such cases and a streamlined exclusion and deportation process.</p>
<p>- New rules for asylum procedures, including an entitlement to a judicial hearing within seven days.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
