<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16723" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dole has few friends among Democratic teachers.</title>
<headline>Dole has few friends among Democratic teachers.</headline>
<byline>Michael Conlon</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The teachers are mad at Bob Dole. In conduct unbecoming a classroom they hiss and boo the very mention of his name.</p>
<p>At least that is what happened on Tuesday when Vice President Al Gore addressed a group of teachers at the Democratic National Convention.</p>
<p>Two weeks ago, Dole picked the fight in his address accepting the Republican presidential nomination, telling the National Education Association and the American Federation of Teachers:</p>
<p>&quot;If education were a war, you would be losing it. If it were a business, you would be driving it into bankruptcy. If it were a patient, it would be dying.&quot;</p>
<p>In attacking union opposition to giving parents financial help to let them choose which schools their children attend and injecting what some see as capitalistic competition into the education system, Dole took on one of the most powerful forces in the Democratic party.</p>
<p>He also staked out an issue of interest to young parents and turned the school choice debate into a major campaign batleground.</p>
<p>About 550 of the delegates to this week's Democratic National Convention belong to one of the two unions, which together have more than 3 million members. The NEA says many of its members are Republicans, at least in name.</p>
<p>Gore told the teacher-delegates on Tuesday they were being made scapegoats by Dole who instead should be concentrating on making public schools &quot;the best in the world, bar none.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We oppose vouchers because we will not tolerate an assault on the financial structure of educational opportunity,&quot; Gore said.</p>
<p>He called the school choice idea a &quot;fradulent&quot; and &quot;misguided&quot; concept that would drain funds from the school system. The room sizzled with hisses and boos every time he mentioned Dole and running mate Jack Kemp. One delegate hoisted a hand-lettered sign reading &quot;mad and mobilized.&quot;</p>
<p>The teachers unions have traditionally backed Democratic candidates at most levels, and Dole might not have been able to count on much support from that quarter in the first place. But union members said the attack has triggered an anger that has resulted in a unified front for President Bill Clinton.</p>
<p>Mary Bergan, president of the California Federation of Teachers, said she was &quot;very surprised&quot; that Dole elected to single out the teachers unions for a special attack in his acceptance speech.</p>
<p>&quot;They had tried to make such a big deal of inclusion in that speech. They tried to make a distinction between teachers and their unions, which most people don't make and a lot of our members sure don't make,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of our members and a lot of NEA members happen to be Republicans, so he really solidified people, brought people over to Clinton in the education community for sure,&quot; said Bergan, who lives in Oakland, California.</p>
<p>A poll meanwhile released in Washington by Phi Delta Kappa International, an educational fraternity, and conducted by the Gallup organization found that 61 percent of those polled opposed the idea of allowing students to attend private schools at public expense while 36 percent supported it.</p>
<p>The group said a similar poll in 1995 showed 65 percent opposed and that the opposition stood at 74 percent in 1993.</p>
<p>Clinton on Tuesday proposed a $2.75 billion literacy campaign for children that would involve hiring spcialists to to help communities provide extra reading help before and after school for 3 million children at 20,000 schools.</p>
<p>The Dole camp fired back immediately, indicating it was not about to let the teachers unions off the hook.</p>
<p>&quot;Bill Clinton is admitting that our schools cannot accomplish the most basic task of literacy. But, instead of pursuing fundamental reform -- by confronting the teachers' unions and embracing school choice -- Bill Clinton announces a new government program and a new pot of money for the unions,&quot; the Dole campaign said.</p>
<p>&quot;By drawing education into the political discourse, Bill Clinton has drawn a clear distinction between Bob Dole and Bill Clinton. Bob Dole trusts the people. Bill Clinton trusts the NEA,&quot; it said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
