<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16841" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Support up for public spending on U.S. private schools.</title>
<headline>Support up for public spending on U.S. private schools.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Support has grown among Americans for public funding of private or church-related education but a majority still reject it, a poll released Tuesday said.</p>
<p>The poll commissioned by an education fraternity also showed respondents by more than two-to-one felt President Clinton has done more to improve public education than the Republican-led Congress.</p>
<p>The annual poll from Phi Delta Kappa International, conducted by the Gallup organization, said 61 percent rejected the idea of allowing students to attend private schools at public expense while 36 percent supported it.</p>
<p>The group said 65 percent opposed the proposal in 1995 and 74 percent in 1993.</p>
<p>Asked whether they would support letting parents choose public, private or church-related schools with government vouchers paying part or all of tuition, 54 percent opposed the idea.</p>
<p>&quot;The public believes they should support public schools, but support is growing for vouchers,&quot; Jack Jennings, director of the Center on National Education Policy, said at a briefing on the poll.</p>
<p>Results indicated the nation must move quickly to improve public schools to keep support from eroding, Jennings said.</p>
<p>Responding to an election year question, 44 percent said they felt Democrats were more interested in improving public schools, while 27 percent said Republicans were.</p>
<p>Forty-nine percent said Clinton had done more to improve public schools versus 23 percent for the Republican Congress.</p>
<p>At the briefing, Phi Delta Kappa officials said the timing of the poll's release, which coincided with the Democratic national convention in Chicago, was inadvertent.</p>
<p>While the poll showed modest support for the public school system, with only 21 percent giving it &quot;A&quot; or &quot;B&quot; grades, local public schools got more backing with 43 percent giving their community public schools an &quot;A&quot; or &quot;B.&quot;</p>
<p>If cost were not a factor, 63 percent of parents said they would keep their children in public schools, and 55 percent would send their child to the same public school.</p>
<p>The results from a telephone sample of 1,329 adults conducted in May had a margin of error of plus or minus 3 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
