<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="31281" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Many U.S. schools tardy on healthy meal rule- group.</title>
<headline>Many U.S. schools tardy on healthy meal rule- group.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many American schools will not comply this year with new rules requiring them to serve healthier meals, a consumer group said Wednesday, expressing fear it could be years before meals were upgraded nationwide.</p>
<p>A survey by the group, Public Voice for Food and Health Policy, indicated half of all school districts would apply for a waiver giving them another year or two to comply. Almost all school districts in Florida and California have requested waivers as have at least one-third in New York and Massachusetts, Public Voice said.</p>
<p>A 1994 law gave schools two years to modify lunch menus to comply with the Dietary Guidelines -- seven rules for healthful eating -- with the option of requesting waivers until 1997 or 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;We are raising a red flag here. We are not pointing fingers,&quot; Public Voice president Mark Epstein said.</p>
<p>The American School Food Service Association, which represents school food officials, said requests for waivers did not mean schools were dragging their feet. Some schools felt the new menu rules were too complex to digest easily or they needed more time and funding.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, said ASFSA nutrition director Tami Cline, schools have adopted many techniques to make meals healthier, such as baking instead of frying chicken, offering fruit daily or setting up salad bars. Cline said her group was confident schools would successfully meet the new rules.</p>
<p>About 25 million children in 94,000 schools eat hot meals each school day through the federal school lunch program, which costs the government about $5 billion a year.</p>
<p>The Dietary Guidelines recommend Americans limit fat to 30 percent of their calories, eat more fruits, vegetables and grains, and limit salt and sugar intake. A 1992 assessment by the Agriculture Department, which oversees school lunches, found the fat content of school lunches averaged 38 percent.</p>
<p>Epstein and other Public Voice officials said they feared school districts would use inexact methods, or even stick to their old meal plans, when writing menus under the new lunch rules. Compliance would be checked infrequently.</p>
<p>&quot;We could have the situation in which schools would not comply for several years,&quot; said Bob Hahn, who directed the survey.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
