<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41355" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: N.Y.C. council to probe school overcrowding.</title>
<headline>N.Y.C. council to probe school overcrowding.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>As New York City's schools struggled to find room for 91,000 more students than they have capacity for, the Council vowed to investigate the problem, while the mayor turned for help to the Roman Catholic Diocese.</p>
<p>&quot;We do have a crisis, it is an ongoing one, and it should be treated as such,&quot; City Council President Peter Vallone told reporters on Monday at a news conference at City Hall.</p>
<p>The leader of the council, who is a Democrat, called upon Gov. George Pataki, a Republican, to help solve the problem, noting that the city gives the state more revenue than it receives back as aid.</p>
<p>Vallone said sometime ago he warned Pataki and the legislature that the city's school system would add 20,000 new students each year until at least the turn of the century.</p>
<p>City officials, who asked not to be named, said that some of the measures New York state uses to distribute its aid for education discriminate against New York City.</p>
<p>For example, in school building aid, the state bases the amount cities and towns receive on average construction costs throughout the state, but such expenses typically are higher in New York City than upstate.</p>
<p>Mayor Rudolph Giuliani, a Republican, on Monday continued to press for the archdiosese's offer to enroll 1,000 of New York City's public schoolchildren, whose performance puts them in the bottom five percent, in Catholic schools.</p>
<p>&quot;We should fight for those kids instead of fighting bureaucracies, special interests and fighting out of fear,&quot; Giuliani told reporters at City Hall.</p>
<p>While the proposal, first made in 1991, would appear to violate the constitution that mandates the separation of church and state, there was speculation that this might be sidestepped. For example, New York City might make contributions to private Catholic foundations instead of paying the school children's tuition, who would have to volunteer for the program.</p>
<p>Speaker Vallone, who scheduled September 17 hearings into the overcrowding problem, said the question of sending public schoolchildren to parochial schools, where they would receive religous education, required study. &quot;We can't do it in violation of the law.&quot;</p>
<p>The Council increased the Board of Education's four-year capital plan by $1.4 billion in the city's 1997 fiscal budget, which totals about $33 billion.</p>
<p>However, at present additional funds for the city's schools do not appear to be available, although Vallone noted President Bill Clinton has proposed spending $5 billion to help local communities and states rebuild schools.</p>
<p>Clinton's plan would provide a subsidy of up to 50 percent of the interest for building new schools and renovating existing ones.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
