<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41521" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oral arguments set in Ohio school funding lawsuit.</title>
<headline>Oral arguments set in Ohio school funding lawsuit.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ohio and school districts will square off Tuesday before the state's supreme court on the issue of whether Ohio's system of funding schools is constitutional.</p>
<p>In oral arguments, the state will contend that the system, though not perfect, is constitutional, according to Jeffrey Sutton, state solicitor for Ohio Attorney General's office.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, attorneys for five Ohio school districts, as well as students, parents and teachers that filed the lawsuit in 1991, will argue that the state's funding system &quot;is neither fair nor is it adequate,&quot; according to Nicholas Pittner, a partner at Bricker &amp; Eckler, who is representing the plaintiffs.</p>
<p>So far, each side has scored a win in the courts, leading to the final round in the state's high court. In July 1994, a Perry County Common Pleas Court judge found Ohio's school funding system to be unconstitutional because it resulted in wide disparities between wealthy and poor districts.</p>
<p>That decision was overturned in August 1995 by a state appeals court.</p>
<p>Last January, the state's high court agreed to hear the case.</p>
<p>Sutton said the constitutionality of Ohio's school funding system has already been upheld by the state supreme court in a 1979 decision in another similar lawsuit.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been here before,&quot; he said, pointing out the state's funding formula is essentially the same now as it was in the 1970s.</p>
<p>Under that formula, the state makes up the difference between what a school district can raise with a minimum of 20 property tax mills and the state's per pupil foundation level of spending, which is around $3,500, Sutton said. He added that property tax collections in wealthier school districts can surpass the foundation level.</p>
<p>But funding needs have changed, according to Pittner. He contended that the funding system has not provided for districts' changing needs and has resulted in per pupil funding disparities that range from $12,000 to $3,000.</p>
<p>Pittner said Ohio's constitution mandates a &quot;thorough and efficient system of common schools.&quot;</p>
<p>Sutton said that since 1979, state funding of education has increased by 50 percent, while the state in recent years has taken steps to equalize funding to poorer school districts.</p>
<p>&quot;Our point is that no one is saying things are perfect, but that the system is constitutional,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A decision against the state in the case could cost billions of dollars, he added.</p>
<p>And billions of dollars are needed by school districts, according to William Phillis, executive director of the Ohio Coalition for Equity and Adequacy of School Funding, which represents 553 Ohio school districts that are supporting the lawsuit.</p>
<p>Phillis said $10 billion alone is needed to address school facilities problems. Gov. George Voinovich's proposed $1 billion, 10-year state bonding plan for school facilities failed to win support of lawmakers earlier this year. Last month, a new five-year, $2.5 billion bonding plan was proposed by a state lawmaker.</p>
<p>Phillis said he was optimistic the schools would prevail in their court challenge, adding that the plaintiffs have &quot;a catalogue of inadequacies to demonstrate to the court.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Our school system has suffered year after year of benign neglect, unconscionable neglect,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Both Pittner and Sutton said Ohio's high court could possibly decide the case by year-end.</p>
<p>--Karen Pierog, 312-408-8647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
