<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49731" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Takeover of Cleveland schools by city proposed.</title>
<headline>Takeover of Cleveland schools by city proposed.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>- The stage is being set in Ohio for a possible takeover of the beleaguered Cleveland school system by Mayor Michael White.</p>
<p>Late last week a bill was introduced in the legislature that would allow Cleveland's mayor to operate the schools in lieu of a board of education.</p>
<p>A legislative aide to State Rep. William Batchelder, R-Medina, one of the bill's sponsors, said lawmakers expect the measure to be refined with input from various interests.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, White reportedly said he would consider the proposal. A spokesman for White was not available to comment.</p>
<p>Cleveland Plain Dealer quoted White as saying the current school system was &quot;broken.&quot;</p>
<p>In fact, continued budget deficits led the Ohio Department of Education to take control of the schools in March 1995.</p>
<p>Last month, a U.S. District Court judge in Cleveland ordered that a 13.5 property tax mill operating levy be placed on the November ballot despite objections from Cleveland's school board.</p>
<p>According to state education officials, the $67.5 million the levy would raise a year is needed to pay off about $87 million of operating debt due to mature in December and in June 1997.</p>
<p>Under a new Ohio law set to take effect next week, Cleveland's schools would qualify for a fiscal emergency, according to the Ohio Auditor's Office. The law sets up a system for identifying districts in fiscal stress and overseeing districts that qualify for a fiscal emergency.</p>
<p>Batchelder's aide said the takeover bill is patterned after Chicago Mayor Richard Daley's takeover of the Chicago Public Schools. A 1995 state of Illinois law gave Daley the power to appoint the school board.</p>
<p>Since that time, Daley's appointees to the school board have been credited with streamlining operations, balancing the budget and launching a five-year, $806 million bond-funded capital improvement program.</p>
<p>--Karen Pierog, 312-408-8647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
