<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55891" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kemp gets grilling from black high school students.</title>
<headline>Kemp gets grilling from black high school students.</headline>
<dateline>NEWARK, N.J 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, U.S. Political Correspondent</p>
<p>Republican vice presidential candidate Jack Kemp on Monday was grilled on crime, immigration and racial issues by black students when he visited a high school in a tough city neighbourhood.</p>
<p>Kemp, who is trying to widen the appeal of presidential candidate Bob Dole, has been campaigning in areas seldom visited by Republicans. He received an enthusiastic welcome and a polite hearing at St. Benedict's Catholic Preparatory School from the mainly black and hispanic student body but his teenage interlocutors pulled no punches in their questions.</p>
<p>Several students asked Kemp about what one termed his &quot;flip-flop&quot; on affirmative action programmes that give women and minorities preferential treatment in education and employment.</p>
<p>&quot;I did not flip-flop. I have never supported affirmative action that led to quotas. I have always supported, continue to support affirmative efforts of government to open up equality of opportunity,&quot; Kemp said.</p>
<p>Polls show President Bill Clinton could receive upwards of 85 percent of the black vote in the Nov. 5 election. One analyst likened Kemp's efforts to eat into that vote as &quot;preaching to the unconvertible.&quot;</p>
<p>The size of the problem facing him was immediately clear in the well-prepared questions from students. One commented that Republicans seemed to focus more on punishing criminals than preventing crime and asked where Kemp stood. Both were important, the candidate replied.</p>
<p>When one student said the Republican Party platform advocated turning the children of illegal immigrants out of public schools, Kemp immediately interrupted: &quot;It didn't say that. It said that states should have the choice.&quot;</p>
<p>He added that neither he nor Dole wanted to see school teachers turned into agents of the border patrol but he saw no problem with requiring students to produce a birth certificate on entrance to the school system.</p>
<p>&quot;You don't want discrimination or national ID cards but if we're to keep this country from being turned into a police state, in my opinion, we have a responsibility to protect our borders,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Another black student alluded to Dole's ridiculing of an African proverb that became the title of a book on child rearing by first lady Hillary Rodham Clinton, &quot;It takes a whole village to raise a child.&quot;</p>
<p>Kemp said he meant no disrespect to African culture and acknowledged the proverb &quot;has truth to it or it would not have come down through the ages.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked why Republicans wanted to dismantle the federal Department of Education, Kemp said education was traditionally run by states and local governments and that responsibility had been usurped by the federal government.</p>
<p>Throughout his presentation, Kemp repeatedly referred to the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. and his vision of an America without racial divisisions. He argued that America needed moral leadership to bring about such equality of opportunity.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEWARK, N.J"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
