<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55974" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: N.Y.C watchdog offers solutions for jammed schools.</title>
<headline>N.Y.C watchdog offers solutions for jammed schools.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York City Comptroller Alan Hevesi Monday offered solutions for the city's overflowing schools, which have as many as 91,000 students trying to learn in crowded conditions.</p>
<p>Noting Los Angeles Unified School District has used a year-round schedule for 22 years, Hevesi, in prepared remarks, urged city officials to begin such an experiment as soon as possible, noting he had made a similar request of the Board of Education one year ago.</p>
<p>The comptroller's talks with the teachers' union showed that it is willing to cooperate, Hevesi said. &quot;They have reasonable conditions,&quot; such as requiring schools in a yeaer-round program to be air conditioned. He added this is not an obstacle to beginning a pilot program.</p>
<p>Noting that most existing capital funds are earmarked for repairing schools, Hevesi said that about 225 of the schools that are due to get new roofs or other repairs as part of a $150 million program should get an extra story added as well.</p>
<p>&quot;This would be significantly cheaper and faster than building a new school, because there would be no cost for land or foundations,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A preliminary analysis by the comptroller's staff showed that adding the additional story would cost $75 to $77 per square foot, much less than building a new school, estimated at about $98 a square foot. Hevesi added the expense of a new roof is is comparable to the cost of movable classrooms and other solutions the Board of Education is considering, which do not last as long.</p>
<p>Saying the comptroller's office issued reports on school overcrowding going back to 1986, Hevesi  also looked to the $125 million under the state's $1.75 billion environmental bond act for converting schools to natural gas from coal.</p>
<p>The conversions should help free up space that could be used for libraries, gyms, cafeterias, and other uses, he said.</p>
<p>New York voters on November 5 will have the chance to approve or reject the environmental bond act for which Gov. George Pataki has begun campaigning.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
