<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61487" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: N.Y. Comptroller finds fault with schools' audits.</title>
<headline>N.Y. Comptroller finds fault with schools' audits.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York state watchdog on Wednesday said taxpayers could not trust that the billions of dollars spent each year on public schools were going where they should as some schools' audits were faulty.</p>
<p>H. Carl McCall, in prepared remarks, also criticized the state Education Department for not helping the schools conduct their audits and providing more oversight.</p>
<p>&quot;Without vigilant oversight of school district operations, the public does not have adequate assurances that taxpayer dollars spent on education in their district or across New York state are being properly reported,&quot; said H. Carl McCall, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>The report by the comptroller's staff found that the state's lack of supervision, coupled with the school districts' failure to followup, led some districts to ignore deficiencies that turned up in their audits.</p>
<p>These included expenditures that were not appropriated by school boards and inadequate accounting for fixed assets even when these problems had been listed in previous audits.</p>
<p>Further, the Education Department's use of unaudited school financial and attendance data could let some districts receive less or more state aid than they were allowed. McCall noted the unaudited reports are used to distribute &quot;a significant portion&quot; of $10 billion in state aid.</p>
<p>The audit, which covered July 1991 to July 1995, involved 21 school districts, from Amsterdam City to New York City, where McCall said the scope and timeliness of its audits should be improved.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
