<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67135" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Fans of midget mascot threaten U.S. school board.</title>
<headline>Fans of midget mascot threaten U.S. school board.</headline>
<dateline>DICKINSON, N.D. 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Angry residents of a North Dakota community have threatened to remove school board members over efforts to eliminate a grimacing midget as the local high school's mascot, authorities said Friday.</p>
<p>Dickinson Schools Superintendent C. B. Haas said supporters of the midget character had threatened to call for new school board elections unless the board puts the proposed mascot change to a popular vote by Oct. 1.</p>
<p>&quot;The board members are not in a frame of mind to yield to that kind of ultimatum,&quot; Haas told Reuters. &quot;So it's like the two groups are on a collision course.&quot;</p>
<p>In July the board voted 4-1 to change the &quot;Midgets&quot; name of the high school's sports teams and the traditional logo after receiving complaints from a parents' advisory committee. But the move ran into opposition from what one board member described as &quot;die-hard fans&quot; of the 80-year-old mascot.</p>
<p>Haas said that under state law, the fans only need 40 signatures to validate a petition calling for new board elections. Dickinson has a population of about 16,000.</p>
<p>&quot;They're obsessed about this name. I'm calling it mob obsession,&quot; Haas said.</p>
<p>Last week more than 250 people attended a lively debate over the proposed change. At the time, School Board President Earl Abrahamson said the five-person board would consider all the opinions presented at the debate and would probably reach a decision at its October meeting.</p>
<p>But Haas said Friday that because of the threat, the board might have to arrange a special meeting before then to consider its options.</p>
<p>The word &quot;midget&quot; is seen by many as derogatory and politically incorrect. &quot;Little people&quot; is sometimes used as an alternative.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DICKINSON, N.D."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
