<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67169" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: N.Y.S. Regents urge $5 bln bond for public schools.</title>
<headline>N.Y.S. Regents urge $5 bln bond for public schools.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York State Board of Regents, the state's educational policy-makers, on Friday proposed an approximately $5 billion bond act to help pay for urgently needed repairs for public schools.</p>
<p>How the Pataki Administration will respond to the proposal is not yet clear, as a spokesman for the governor had no comment immediately available. The Regents are appointed by the state legislature, who in turn appoint the state Education Commissioner.</p>
<p>The Regents Chancellor, who estimated that public schools throughout the state need about $15 billion of repairs, with about half of these schools located in New York City and the rest upstate and on Long Island.</p>
<p>&quot;Many people believe this is a New York City problem. But in reality, it is a problem statewide,&quot; said Carl Hayden, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>As school districts, using local and state funding, have budgeted about $9.6 billion of the amount needed to pay for the repairs, the shortfall totals about $5.4 billion. But any bond act, which is not expected to go before the voters until November 1997 if the legislature approves the proposal, likely would be a bit less.</p>
<p>That is because the state education department said it might be able to cut costs by conserving energy, managing projects more effectively, sharing construction services, and bidding in groups. &quot;We want to discuss these approaches with the governor and legislature,&quot; said Education Commissioner Richard Mills, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>Other measures the Regents put forward would change state aid to allow schools to teach classes for 180 days during 12 months of the year, instead of the current 10 months.</p>
<p>Also, each school district would have to set up a maintenance reserve fund to keep buildings in good condition and there would be more oversight of their construction and maintenance programs. Another measure would aid New York City, whose construction costs typically run much higher than upstate, by adjusting state aid to take regional differences in construction costs into account.</p>
<p>--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
