<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68829" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Virginia Military Institute to allow in women.</title>
<headline>Virginia Military Institute to allow in women.</headline>
<byline>Lorrie Grant</byline>
<dateline>LEXINGTON, Virginia 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Virginia Military Institute, the country's last state-supported military academy to bar women, decided on Saturday to bow to a Supreme Court ruling and admit women after 157 years as an all-male school.</p>
<p>The decision was made in a 9-8 vote by the school's governing body following a June 26 U.S. Supreme Court ruling that the academy must open its doors to women or become a private school.</p>
<p>VMI, founded in 1839, was the only state-supported college in the country that had yet to admit women. The institute had said women would be unable to withstand its tough mental and physical training known as &quot;the Rat Line&quot;.</p>
<p>The Citadel, the only other state-supported U.S. military academy, admitted females in September after the high court's ruling in the VMI case.</p>
<p>&quot;The board made this decision with the full understanding that VMI will not change the military and academic features of its culture, which has distinguished the institute since its founding,&quot; William Berry, president of the Board of Visitors, told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;VMI will welcome women who come ready to meet the rigourous challenges they will find at VMI. I am resolute about VMI's future and its ability to meet this new test of its inherent greatness.&quot;</p>
<p>In Washington, the Justice Department said it was pleased by the decision.</p>
<p>&quot;We trust the school will now begin encouraging and accepting applications from women looking to enroll in next year's entering class,&quot; said Deval Patrick, a civil rights attorney in the Justice Department.</p>
<p>Gen. Josiah Bunting, the institute's superintendant and a graduate of the class of 1963, said changes to accomodate women would be minimal.</p>
<p>&quot;Female cadets will be treated exactly as male cadets are treated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said women will have to get the &quot;buzz&quot; hair cut required of cadets. They will live in barracks, and while they will have their own showers there will be no locks on the doors.</p>
<p>&quot;We teach what are called the vigorous virtues -- determination, self-reliance, self-control and courage. This is achieved through the application of mental stress, physical rigour, minute regulation of behaviour, pressures, hazards and physcological bonding,&quot; Bunting said.</p>
<p>Women will be admitted beginning in August 1997 to the academy, which currently has about 1,200 cadets. Spokesman Mike Strickler said that since the Supreme Court ruling about 80 women had enquired about admission.</p>
<p>The eight dissenters on the board wanted to privatise the school but faced funding difficulties.</p>
<p>The Supreme Court had ruled that VMI was unconstitutionally discriminating against women. Following the ruling, The Citadel, founded in 1842, admitted four women.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LEXINGTON, Virginia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
