<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70606" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Minnesota faces two school funding lawsuits.</title>
<headline>Minnesota faces two school funding lawsuits.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The state of Minnesota's funding of urban school districts is being challenged by two pending lawsuits.</p>
<p>The latest lawsuit was filed last week by the St. Paul Public School District. It follows another lawsuit filed last year by the Minneapolis branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the parents of several school children enrolled in Minneapolis public schools.</p>
<p>&quot;The common ground between our lawsuits would be both lawsuits are seeking to hold the state responsible under the constitutuion,&quot; said John Shulman, a Minneapolis attorney representing the NAACP.</p>
<p>In the St. Paul case, school officials claimed that the concentration of poverty in that city has put the district in a &quot;unique financial bind&quot; because of its inability to get funding referendums passed.</p>
<p>&quot;In allocating resources and other assistance for schools, the state has failed to take sufficient account of the substantially greater services needed to provide adequate educational opportunities for our students,&quot; said St. Paul Public School District Board of Education chair Mary Thornton Phillips in a news release.</p>
<p>According to a spokeswoman for the district, 64 percent of the district's $348 million annual budget comes from Minnesota. However, the lawsuit does not indicate how much more state money is needed by the school district to ensure students receive an adequate education, the spokeswoman added.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Minnesota Attorney General's Office said last week that the St. Paul school lawsuit was under review.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the NAACP's case charged that school children in Minneapolis are deprived of an adequate education because their schools are segregated and that the education offered in those schools in unequal to education provided in suburban Minneapolis school districts.</p>
<p>Shulman said the lawsuit seeks injunctive relief in the way the school district is set up and operated in addition to state funding.</p>
<p>He added that a Hennepin County District Court judge has ordered the plaintiffs and the state to explore the possibility of mediation. The judge has also forwarded certain questions pertaining to the case to the state supreme court in order to give the trial court guidance, Shulman said.</p>
<p>--Karen Pierog, 312-408-8647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
