<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70854" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: General Mills to fund schools in cereal promotion.</title>
<headline>General Mills to fund schools in cereal promotion.</headline>
<dateline>ENGLEWOOD, Colo 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>General Mills Inc. , whose stable of cereal brands includes Cheerios and Wheaties, Monday got a hand from Olympic gold medal winner Amy Van Dyken to announce a nationwide program to help elementary schools raise needed cash.</p>
<p>Under the program elementary schools will receive 15 cents for each special box top turned in, up to a $10,000 limit per school.</p>
<p>&quot;We all know that schools all over the country are struggling for funds to bring kids the best possible education,&quot; said General Mills spokesman David Dix. &quot;General Mills wants kids to have a good start with a good breakfast and a good education.&quot;</p>
<p>Van Dyken, the winner of four gold medals for swimming at this year's Olympics who recently appeared on a Wheaties cereal box, denied that the program brings corporate boosterism to the classroom.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it's (about) buying a product. I think that it's more getting a point across - that's it's for education,&quot; she said in a brief interview.</p>
<p>The Minneapols-based food giant, which holds a 24 percent share of the cereal market, is offering the program to any of the 85,000 elementary schools in the United States, including parochial and military schools.</p>
<p>The promotion, which will accept boxtops from any of General Mills' 37 cereal brands, is in force until March 31.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ENGLEWOOD, Colo"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
