<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46458" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: How do you rate?</title>
<headline>How do you rate?</headline>
<byline>Linda Stern</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
<text>
<p>It's a rare week indeed when an investor survey doesn't land on my desk.</p>
<p>These surveys are typically of the &quot;Baby boomers aren't saving enough for retirement! They better buy our mutual fund (or insurance policy) fast!&quot; genre.</p>
<p>Recently I've come across a new crop of findings that don't make all of us look like unprepared and ignorant idiots who had better hurry up and write those checks.</p>
<p>Here's a quick survey of recent surveys with some upbeat implications for the broader and smarter saving and investing public.</p>
<p>Taken together, this mixed bag of surveys reveals a saving and investing public that makes relatively sound decisions based on where they are in their work and life cycle. For the most part, we're putting away what we can, when we can, and muddling through as we always have.</p>
<p>-- The nation's young adults have a lot of money to spend. Roughly $100 billion a year, says Citibank. That's about $4,000 per person, much of it from summer and after school jobs and allowances.</p>
<p>The implications are that parents should invest some time in teaching their kids how to set aside money for necessities and long term goals, says Citibank. No wonder clothing and music markets are so youth-oriented!</p>
<p>-- Parents of high school students have typically saved only about a quarter of college costs, reports Sallie Mae. More than half have a pretty good idea of what college will cost, but have not been able to save it all. They place their children's college educations at a much higher priority than retirement savings.</p>
<p>This means that parents know what they are facing, and are doing what they can. They have figured out that paying for college is a patchwork of current income, savings, student jobs and loans, and have correctly gauged that they don't have to have four years in the bank before junior matriculates.</p>
<p>-- Baby busters don't intend to go bust. Two out of three of the 25-to-34 year olds are already saving for retirement privately and contributing to employer plans. Eighty percent are looking at stocks and stock mutual funds, says the American Stock Exchange, which concludes, &quot;new selling opportunities for Wall Street.&quot;</p>
<p>So, maybe the market won't go bust when the baby boomers start taking their money out.</p>
<p>-- Baby boomers aren't doing terribly on their retirement plans, either, and are learning their lessons. The median baby boomer household has $120,000 in home equity and another $180,000 in savings, reports Equitable, an insurance and financial services firm.</p>
<p>They feel more optimistic about their financial future and their ability to handle their investments. More than half said they had financial plans and three out of four participate in their company's retirement plan.</p>
<p>Boomers are showing themselves to be diversified among real estate (45 percent), stocks and stock-holding funds (26 percent) and bonds and other money market accounts. But most don't know the rates of return they are earning.</p>
<p>Implications: Perhaps all of these surveys are kicking in. Boomers are showing some tendency as they get older, to invest for retirement in the stock and real estate types of investments that tend to serve retirees well.</p>
<p>-- Most people who are invested in mutual funds held at least one fund before 1990, reports the Investment Company Institute, an industry trade group.</p>
<p>So don't assume all the money coming into funds is coming from inexperienced babes in the woods who will be shocked when a falling market cuts their kitty. Of course, they'll probably be shocked anyway!</p>
<p>-- Older Americans are in better shape than they used to be, and intend to do even better. While more than half of all retirees say Social Security provides their primary source of income, less than a third of workers over 50 expect that to be their case, and instead expect their own self-directed plans to provide sustenance.</p>
<p>Over-50 workers are feverishly feeding their 401(k) plans, setting up Keoghs and IRAs and lining up part time jobs for their early retirement years, reports the AARP Investment Programme from Scudder, the mutual funds group.</p>
<p>They have more money, too. A survey by Kemper Funds and Age Wave show that most &quot;empty nesters&quot; pick up at least an extra $5,000 a year as a &quot;parental bonus&quot; when their kids leave home. More than half direct at least some of this to retirement savings, and to fixing up their homes.</p>
<p>Implications: Despite the gloom and doom about baby boomers, there's evidence that people still use the decade-plus leading up to retirement to seriously sock away money for their post-work years.</p>
<p>Why? Because that's when they have money.</p>
<p>-- More than $4 out of very $10 going into defined contribution retirement plans are still going into employers' stock, reports the Institute of Management and Administration.</p>
<p>This despite warnings that retirement plans have not been diversified enough, and despite ample evidence (see all the surveys) that all Americans are depending more on their 401(k) plans than ever before.</p>
<p>Implications: If Americans are being encouraged at every stage of life to feed and depend on defined contributions plans, somebody ought to make sure these plans protect the saving public.</p>
<p>You can E-mail Linda Stern at 72160.1546(at)compuserve.com or write to her in care of Reuters, Suite 410, 1333 H St., NW, Washington, DC 20005.  She regrets that she cannot answer each letter individually, but will cover your questions in upcoming columns.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
