<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47530" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French government budget plans - summary.</title>
<headline>French government budget plans - summary.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The French government will present a budget for 1997 on September 18. The following gives details of tax reform plans already announced, along with likely changes in the 1997 budget.</p>
<p>TOTAL PUBLIC DEFICIT</p>
<p>This is to be cut to four percent of gross domestic product in 1996 and three percent in 1997 from five percent in 1995.</p>
<p>Government spokesman Alain Lamassoure said on Wednesday all public deficits next year, covering central government, local authority and welfare spending, would be contained within the three percent limit.</p>
<p>It comprises the following areas of spending:</p>
<p>-- CENTRAL GOVERNMENT BUDGET.</p>
<p>The government said earlier this year it planned to cut the deficit on this to around 248 billion francs next year, or three percent of GDP, from a forecast 288 billion this year. It has given no forecast recently for the 1997 budget deficit, which economists say may now be higher because of planned tax cuts.</p>
<p>Arthuis has said the government will announce a deficit total including tax cuts and a deficit total excluding tax cuts.</p>
<p>-- WELFARE SPENDING</p>
<p>This includes:</p>
<p>-- Social security accounts, covering healthcare, pensions and family benefit, financed through payroll taxes, expected to show a deficit this year of at least 50 billion francs.</p>
<p>The government has said it will not be able to meet its target of returning the welfare system to breakeven next year.</p>
<p>-- National unemployment fund UNEDIC. It said on September 10 it expected a surplus of 12 billion francs by the end of this year, against earlier estimates of a 10.5 to 10.9 billion surplus. It gave no new figure for 1997, but said in July it expected a surplus of 22.5 to 25.8 billion francs. These surpluses could offset part of the social security deficit.</p>
<p>A further seven billion francs in taxes will be raised next year to fund the welfare system.</p>
<p>-- LOCAL AUTHORITIES.</p>
<p>Economists expect these to show a small deficit in 1996. But they have been cutting costs and raising local taxes and may improve next year.</p>
<p>-- OTHER SOURCES OF REVENUE.</p>
<p>The government could find revenue to meet its deficit targets from a wide range of other government bodies, state-controlled banks and institutions, including state bank Caisse des Depots et Consignations.</p>
<p>A 37.5 billion franc contribution due from France Telecom is likely to be written into the state accounts as 1997 income, government sources say. The money is being transferred to cover pension liabilities which the state will assume ahead of the partial privatisation of the telecommunications company.</p>
<p>Welfare debt repayment fund CADES is expected to show an accounting surplus next year, since the national accounts will include all revenues raised by CADES but include only interest payments rather than capital repayments on the spending side. As a rough estimate this surplus could be around 10 billion francs.</p>
<p>			 ***************</p>
<p>CENTRAL GOVERNMENT BUDGET - SPENDING</p>
<p>This will be frozen at 1996's targetted 1,552 billion francs. But since spending on some areas will rise automatically by around 60 billion francs -- to cover inflation, debt service charges and pre-agreed civil service promotions, spending cuts of around 60 billion francs are expected elsewhere.</p>
<p>Spending cuts are expected to include:</p>
<p>-- A reduction in 6,500 to 7,000 civil service jobs, saving some one billion francs.</p>
<p>-- A cut in job subsidies, saving 15 to 20 billion francs.</p>
<p>-- A reduction in housing aid subsidies.</p>
<p>Defence, health, education, justice and labour spending are expected to increase next year.</p>
<p>			 ******************</p>
<p>REVENUES</p>
<p>GROWTH ASSUMPTIONS</p>
<p>Finance Minister Jean Arthuis said the 1997 budget will forecast growth of 2.3 percent, less than the 2.8 percent growth forecast made earlier this year.</p>
<p>INCOME TAX REDUCTION</p>
<p>The government says income taxes will be cut by 75 billion francs over five years, including 25 billion francs next year. However, given increases in other taxes the net income tax cut will be 18 billion (see below).</p>
<p>The top rate of tax will be reduced to 54 percent next year and 47 percent within five years from 56.8 percent now.</p>
<p>All income tax rates will be lowered and the threshhold before people have to start paying tax will be raised to help those on low incomes.</p>
<p>PAYROLL CHARGES AND THE CSG</p>
<p>Employee payroll contributions to cover healthcare will be reduced by 1.3 percentage points, which will be offset by an increase in the CSG (Generalised Social Contribution) to 3.4 percent from 2.4 percent. The CSG will be widened to cover virtually all income, including income from savings.</p>
<p>The additional one point increase in the CSG will be made tax deductible.</p>
<p>The increased tax burden to pay for the welfare system will total seven billion francs, reducing the net income tax cut next year to 18 billion francs.</p>
<p>LIFE-ASSURANCE</p>
<p>Tax benefits given for contributions to new life assurance policies will be scrapped from September 5, 1996. Benefits on proceeds from life policies will not be touched although these proceeds will in future pay the CSG tax.</p>
<p>Contributions previously agreed for existing life policies will continue to benefit from tax breaks.</p>
<p>PENSION FUNDS</p>
<p>Pension funds will be set up by employers or groups of employers, and managed by independent specialists.</p>
<p>Workers will contribute on a voluntary basis and it will be up to the companies themselves to decide whether to top up their employees' contributions.</p>
<p>A bill proposed by Finance Minister Jean Arthuis would set no limits on allocation of assets by the pension funds, which will thus be free to choose how much to invest in stocks and bonds. But prudential rules which currently tend to disfavour investment in shares will be changed.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe has opened a debate on pension funds, which may modify parts of the proposed bill. Notably he has suggested payouts could be in the form of annuities or a lump sum, whereas the proposed bill would limit payouts to annuities only.</p>
<p>ABOLITION OF SPECIAL TAX DEDUCTIONS</p>
<p>Special tax deductions given to some 100 professions, including journalists, will be phased out over five years, starting with 1997 income, payable in 1998.</p>
<p>A tax deduction for pensioners will be progressively cut, maternity benefits will be taxed, and tax deductions for people with children beyond primary school age will be reduced.</p>
<p>OTHER TAXES</p>
<p>Increases in Value Added Tax (sales tax) and wealth tax made in 1995 are expected to remain in place at least through 1997.</p>
<p>EXCISE DUTIES</p>
<p>The government is expected to raise excise duties on petrol, alcohol and tobacco, with the latter two hit hardest given their implications for public health.</p>
<p>Arthuis has said petrol duties, expressed in francs per unit, will be increased in line with inflation, while there would be higher taxes for alcohol and tobacco.</p>
<p>Alcohol duties, also expressed in francs, have not been ajdusted for inflation since 1993, giving the government room for a fairly hefty rise.</p>
<p>France raises some 200 billion francs a year in excise duties, so an increase even limited to the inflation rate just below two percent would raise some four billion francs.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +331 4221 5381 MEM CNN</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
