<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70556" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton to reveal plans for inflation-linked bonds.</title>
<headline>Clinton to reveal plans for inflation-linked bonds.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Seizing an arcane financial instrument as a tool for his re-election, President Clinton is expected to unveil plans to issue inflation-linked Treasury bonds this week, administration officials said Monday.</p>
<p>The officials, who asked not to be identified, said Clinton was to make the announcement Wednedsay while on the campaign trail in Pittsburgh and that he will emphasise using the bonds to save for college tuition and retirement.</p>
<p>They said Clinton chose to unveil the plan, outlined by the U.S. Treasury last May, while campaigning because it fits with his emphasis on education during this election year.</p>
<p>Asked about the announcement, White House spokesman Mike McCurry coyly encouraged reporters to accompany the president during his one-day trip to Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>&quot;The president is very interested in ways in which we can make savings for college educations more accessible to the American people,&quot; he said. &quot;If you're interested in that, it would be a good idea for you to go with the president.&quot;</p>
<p>How the complicated world of U.S. Treasury bond issues has entered the hurlyburly of a U.S. presidential election is a case study in the powers of incumbency. Knowing that the bonds were under study, Clinton is using them to enliven a campaign trip and stress saving for education, home ownership and retirement -- themes he has repeatedly evoked during this election year.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show Clinton now holds a lead of about 15 percentage points over Republican Bob Dole with six weeks left before the Nov. 5 election.</p>
<p>Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin announced on May 16 that the Treasury planned to issue the inflation-indexed bonds as a multi-year experiment and was studying precisely what form they might take. The securities are designed to strengthen national savings by offering people an investment that guarantees a return that exceeds inflation. The Treasury also expects them to cut its financing costs.</p>
<p>In announcing the idea, Rubin emphasised that the bonds can help people save for major expenses like college tutition. &quot;We think the kinds of investors who will be most interested in these securities will be individual Americans saving for their retirement or other long-term purposes, including their children's education,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the Treasury planned to make them available in denominatons as low as $1,000 to make them accessible to ordinary Americans.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
