<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75483" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Helping liberal arts majors become entrepreneurs.</title>
<headline>Helping liberal arts majors become entrepreneurs.</headline>
<byline>Daniel Grebler</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>Liberal arts undergraduate students often have no idea of where their interest in history, literature or psychology will lead them, but sooner or later, running their own business is likely to be an option.</p>
<p>&quot;All too often, it hits as the only option available to someone,&quot; said Sandy Weinberg, chairman of the department of entrepreneurship at Muhlenberg College, in Allentown, Pa.</p>
<p>&quot;If we look at current entrepreneurs, I don't think you'd find anyone who majored in entrepreneurship. It would be people who had an interest in a particular field and are applying it to make a living.&quot;</p>
<p>Weinberg says students need to ask, &quot;'How can I apply what I'm learning to make a living as an entrepreneur?' That's the kind of question we need to ask, and what we can help with.&quot;</p>
<p>The school's programme, one of the few such undergraduate departments in the nation, aims to combine liberal arts studies with teaching skills needed to run a small business.</p>
<p>&quot;The largest group of students in the programme are majoring in traditional liberal arts areas -- they really have no idea what their traditional liberal arts study may lead to,&quot; said Weinberg. &quot;The programme aims to combine entrepreneurship with liberal arts studies.&quot;</p>
<p>Some of the students come from family businesses and plan to return to them after graduating. Others think they will start a business sooner or later.</p>
<p>&quot;Those people need to understand the traps and opportunities that enterpreneurship presents,&quot; said Weinberg.</p>
<p>About 1,700 students attend Muhlenberg, a liberal arts college in northeastern Pennsylvania established in the 1840s. The entrepreneurship programme is now in its fourth year, with a total of about 30 students.</p>
<p>Of the program's first six graduates, who entered as sophomores, all were double majors -- one in english, one in biology, and the other four in marketing and finance. About half of them are now working in their own businesses, and half are in other people's businesses.</p>
<p>&quot;We suggest that if you want to start a business, it should be your second career move,&quot; said Weinberg. &quot;You should make your first mistakes using someone else's money.&quot;</p>
<p>The college encourages students to have a double major, focusing on a traditional liberal arts area as well as entrepreneurship.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not sure a student ought to spend the kind of money Muhlenberg costs -- $17,000 -- and get just a single major. We encourage a double major,&quot; said Weinberg.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't imagine a parent paying that kind of money if the student is going to end up opening a T-shirt store. If all you want to do is start a small business, you may be better off taking that tuition money and investing it in that small business,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But if you're studying to be a biologist or a physician and decide to apply this somewhere else, you should understand how a business pays off. This is not an end in itself, but a process.&quot;</p>
<p>Students in Muhlenberg's entrepreneurial programme take the school's basic business curriculum of five courses in general accounting, marketing, management, finance and macro-economics. They are also required to complete another 20 courses in liberal arts, human behaviour, foreign language, physical education and other areas.</p>
<p>The entrepreneurship courses include small business management; internship in a small business; consulting through the college's small business institute; and what Weinberg calls &quot;Capstone Strategies&quot; -- studying other startup efforts that have succeeded or failed.</p>
<p>In the small business management course, &quot;We take them from developing a business plan to starting a company, getting financing and as far as developing an exit strategy,&quot; Weinberg said.</p>
<p>As part of the internship programme, students work in a startup company for several hours a week. For example, one student is working with a local publishing company doing a marketing survey; another is doing marketing for a small restaurant that wants to expand.</p>
<p>In the college's Small Business Institute, students are assigned to a small company to work on solving a specific problem.</p>
<p>To offer students more hands-on experience, the school also has set up several on-campus ventures. One of them, an electronic publishing company, publishes books, student poetry, laboratory manuals and even a history board game on computer disks.</p>
<p>A student-run late-night convenience store and snack bar serves the local community, and a medical services venture modelled on a health maintenance organisation supplies prescription and non-prescription pharmaceuticals to supplement the college-run student health services.</p>
<p>Questions or comments on the Newbiz column can be addressed to DANIEL.GREBLER@REUTERS.COM@INTERNET</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
