<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24839" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Air bags do not reduce insurance claims -USA Today.</title>
<headline>Air bags do not reduce insurance claims -USA Today.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>A pair of reports show air bags do nothing to cut the overall injury rate in car crashes and do not save insurers money, USA Today reported on Friday.</p>
<p>A report to Congress by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration said air bags haD reduced fatal injuries in frontal collisions about 30 percent.</p>
<p>But air bags cause enough non-lethal injuries that their impact on overall injuries is nil.</p>
<p>&quot;The net effect is that it's a wash,&quot; Bill Hoehly, the agency's research chief, told the newspaper.</p>
<p>The overall effectiveness of air bags is undermined by an increase in arm and other injuries. When air bags deploy at speeds of up to 200 mph (320 kph) the force can break arms and cause other injuries.</p>
<p>In a report out next month, Virginia Commonwealth University researchers say insurers' injury and property damage claims go up when cars are equipped with air bags.</p>
<p>The arm injuries have contributed to spiraling insurance claims, said Virginia Commonwealth professor George Hoffer, a co-author of the study.</p>
<p>-- New York newsroom, (212) 859-1610</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
