<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="40292" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Nissan's '97 Infiniti Q45 price unchanged.</title>
<headline>Nissan's '97 Infiniti Q45 price unchanged.</headline>
<dateline>CARSON, Calif. 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nissan Motor Co Ltd's Infiniti luxury car division said its redesigned 1997 Q45 flagship sedan will carry a base U.S. price of $47,900, the same as the 1996 model it replaces.</p>
<p>Infiniti said the Q45t touring model, featuring a sport-tuned suspension and other features, will start at $49,900.  Optional heated front seats are available for $400 on the Q45 and are standard on the Q45t.</p>
<p>Destination and handling charges for both cars remain at $495.  </p>
<p>For 1997, the Q45 gets its first major redesign since the car was originally introduced in 1989.</p>
<p>Along with new exterior sheet-metal, the car features a new 4.1-liter, 32-valve V-8 engine.  Although horsepower in the new powerplant is decreased to 266 from 278 previously, Infiniti said the new engine offers better fuel economy and more low-speed torque than its predecessor.</p>
<p>The car features dual front air bags and front seat belts with pre-tensioning devices, but does not offer side air bags, which some European luxury car makers are now offering in the same class of vehicle.</p>
<p>An Infiniti spokeswoman said the new Q45s are now starting to arrive at U.S. dealerships, and an advertising launch for the new model is scheduled to begin September 22.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARSON, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
