<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49809" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Swedish shares hit record high, led by banks.</title>
<headline>Swedish shares hit record high, led by banks.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sweden's stockmarket closed at a record high on Thursday, buoyed by a strong bank sector sector, low Swedish inflation data and U.S. gains.</p>
<p>The Stockholm general index rose 0.79 percent to 2,032.20 after shares worth 4.8 billion crowns changed owners.</p>
<p>The bank sector was the strongest sector, rising 2.30 percent. Nordbanken was the star performer rising seven crowns to 156 crowns after announcing a five billion crown share buy back on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Handelsbanken rose 6.50 to 149 crowns and Swedbank closed 1.50 crowns higher at 88 crowns.  </p>
<p>Blue-chip Ericsson closed four crowns higher at 163, despite Motorola's heavy losses overnight in the wake of a warning about its third quarter earnings. &quot;Motorola's development differs from Ericsson's,&quot; said an analyst.</p>
<p>Another winner was car safety equipment maker Autoliv, which jumped nine crowns to 236.50 on news it was selling side air bags to Volkswagen.</p>
<p>&quot;It also shows the penetration of side airbags into the car market is greater than previously expected and could move onto other models,&quot; Swedbank analyst Mats Liss said.</p>
<p>-- Stockholm newsroom, +46-8-700 1017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
