<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50177" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Autoliv eyes front airbag sales to VW.</title>
<headline>Autoliv eyes front airbag sales to VW.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedish car safety equipment maker Autoliv said the groundwork was now laid to seek sales of front impact air bags for cars to Volkswagen.</p>
<p>Autoliv earlier Thursday announced that it had signed its first deal with Volkswagen, for the supply of side air bags, but it was hoping to expand on this arrangement.</p>
<p>&quot;Our problem has been that we have not had a steering wheel producer and Volkswagen wants to buy their anti-crash airbags already installed in steering wheels,&quot; Autoliv spokesman Mats Odman told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;But through the purchase of French Isodelta (the third largest manufacturer of steering wheels in Europe) this problem is solved.&quot;</p>
<p>Odman said currently Volkswagen buys anti-crash airbags from the fourth largest business in Europe, Magna.</p>
<p>Autoliv is the largest company in the market with a 40 percent market share.</p>
<p>Delivering side impact airbags to Volkswagen is strategically important for Autoliv.</p>
<p>&quot;Apart from the breakthrough at Volkswagen, this means the side impact airbag will soon become standard also in volume cars,&quot; Odman said.</p>
<p>&quot;So far side airbags have only been placed in extremely safety orientated cars, like Volvo and Mercedes.&quot;</p>
<p>Autoliv said side airbags are to become standard in Volkswagen's Golf and Passat models for the Scandinavian and German market. In other markets the side airbag will come extra.</p>
<p>&quot;The side impact airbag costs less than half of what a front imact airbag costs,&quot; Odman said.</p>
<p>-- Peter Fellman, Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1007</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
