<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58487" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NTSB urges states to tighten kids' car seat rules.</title>
<headline>NTSB urges states to tighten kids' car seat rules.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The National Transportation Safety Board urged U.S. governors and automakers on Tuesday to tighten regulations on children's car seats to ensure that youngsters up to 8 years old be strapped in properly.</p>
<p>The board noted that 1,203 children were killed in highway accidents in 1994, the most recent year that statistics were available, and children who were not properly restrained were killed at a rate double that of those who were restrained.</p>
<p>Among other recommendations, the board urged governors to emphasise the importance of putting children in the back seat, not the front seat, where passenger-side air bags might jeopardise their safety in case of a highway accident.</p>
<p>&quot;Passenger-side air bags as they are currently designed are not acceptable as a protective device for children positioned in front of them, and can kill or critically injure these children in accidents that would have been survivable had the air bag not deployed,&quot; the board concluded.</p>
<p>The board recommended that the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, which covers road travel, should require U.S. and foreign automakers to notify vehicle owners of the risks to children of passenger-side airbags.</p>
<p>NHTSA should also set up a timetable to implement so-called &quot;smart&quot; air bags that might be able to safeguard children who sit up front, the board said.</p>
<p>Children up to age 8 should be required by law to use child safety seats and booster seats, the board said, and children 8 and older should be required to wear seatbelts, whether they sit in the front seat or back seat of the vehicle.</p>
<p>Noting that adults often do not know how to properly install child safety seats, and that they are sometimes hampered by the design of a particular vehicle, the board urged foreign and domestic automakers to develop programmes to reduce the misuse of child carseats that would include training for workers at auto dealerships.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of the children in the Safety Board's study sample were not in the appropriate restraint for their age, height and weight; over half of the children who used child restraints were improperly restrained, and about one-quarter of the children who used seatbelts were improperly restrained,&quot; the board said in a report.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
