<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77429" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chrysler launches new ad campaigns to revamp image.</title>
<headline>Chrysler launches new ad campaigns to revamp image.</headline>
<byline>David Lawder</byline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chrysler Corp. has impressed Detroit and Wall Street with its remarkable turnaround over the last five years, but is worried that American consumers have not taken enough notice.</p>
<p>To help snuff out lingering perceptions of vehicle quality problems and portray itself as a designer of innovative cars and trucks, Detroit's No. 3 automaker said this week it is launching two all-new advertising campaigns, including its first new corporate image campaign since ex-chairman Lee Iacocca's last television spots in 1992.</p>
<p>The automaker also is trying to put a new luster into its premium Chrysler brand, which still suffers from an image as a seller of gussied-up &quot;K-cars,&quot; even though its entire product line has been replaced since 1992.</p>
<p>&quot;The perception of Chrysler lags reality,&quot; said Chrysler-Plymouth/Jeep-Eagle Division General Manager Martin Levine, who introduced the campaigns here this week to Chrysler-Plymouth dealers. &quot;We need to change the way people feel about the Chrysler brand and the way they think about Chrysler products.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts expect Chrysler to earn record profits in 1996, a far cry from the early 1990s, when its car and truck lines were severely outdated and recession left it short on cash for new products. But the lean years forced Chrysler to slash costs and develop better vehicles more quickly, allowing it to push its share of the U.S. car and truck market up to 16 percent.</p>
<p>The new campaigns will help lay the groundwork for $23 billion that Chrysler plans to spend to develop new products over the next five years, company executives said.</p>
<p>The Chrysler brand campaign makes an emotional appeal with television commercials featuring children asking philosophical questions like, &quot;Just because something hasn't been done before, does that mean it can't be done?&quot;</p>
<p>With the tag line, &quot;What's new in your world?&quot;, the ads aim to portraying Chrysler as new, young and innovative.</p>
<p>Longtime automotive consultant Christopher Cedergren said it may take a long time for Chrysler to make consumers forget about the vinyl tops on its now-extinct Imperial and Fifth Avenue models, but added that the division is headed in the right direction.</p>
<p>&quot;Five or six years ago, anything with a Chrysler badge on it was fuddy-duddy,&quot; Cedergren said. &quot;It was a fleet brand.&quot;</p>
<p>Cars like the sleek Sebring convertible, however, give the company an opportunity to attract new buyers, he said.</p>
<p>Still, Chrysler won't give up price promotion in the new campaign -- ads for the slow-selling LHS luxury sedan will emphasise a aggressive, $359-a-month lease payment.</p>
<p>Chrysler officials would not disclose spending on the new brand campaign, but the trade publication Advertising Age estimates it at about $147 million this year, about the same as the division spent in 1995.</p>
<p>John McDonald, Chrysler's new vice president of marketing, said the company and its dealers will spend a combined $2 billion on all advertising this year.</p>
<p>Advertising Age estimated that Chrysler is putting about $40 million behind its new corporate image campaign.</p>
<p>Chrysler's last corporate ad campaign in 1992 featured commercials with the soon-to-retire Iacocca presiding over the demolition of the automaker's ancient Jefferson Avenue assembly plant and watching its boxy old sedans &quot;morph&quot; into the sleek LH cars.</p>
<p>In the old campaign, Iacocca, who last year feuded with Chrysler's board over his involvement in billionaire investor Kirk Kerkorian's failed takeover bid, took much of the credit for Chrysler's rebound, saying, &quot;When it's your last time at bat, it sure is nice to hit a home run.&quot;</p>
<p>The new print campaign features anecdotes of Chrysler designers and engineers taking risks and getting inspiration from hot-rod model car kits, and uses the tag line, &quot;Great Cars. Great Trucks. Chrysler Corporation.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The last one was trying to communicate we were a changing company,&quot; said Chrysler spokeswoman Terri Houtman. &quot;This one is communicating the fact that we are a truly different company.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
