<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="18586" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: FOCUS-VW unveils new Passat, says sales well up.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-VW unveils new Passat, says sales well up.</headline>
<byline>John Gilardi</byline>
<dateline>DRESDEN, Germany 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's Volkswagen AG , unveiling a new Passat car aimed at boosting its share of the mid-size market, said on Wednesday its total sales for the first seven months of 1996 were up in Europe and the world.</p>
<p>The Wolfsburg-based carmaker said worldwide deliveries to customers from January to July were up 13.5 percent to 2.35 million vehicles, while deliveries in western Europe were up 11.3 percent to 1.451 million vehicles.</p>
<p>But the German market for Europe's largest carmaker was still anaemic, with growth at only 2.8 percent in the period.</p>
<p>VW management board chairman Ferdinand Piech said late on Tuesday at a news conference to unveil the new Passat, slated for release in October, that VW has &quot;witnessed a slight pick-up&quot; in the German market in the last few weeks.</p>
<p>He said the increase could stimulate German sales in the second half of 1996 and reaffirmed that VW expected full-year profits to top the 1995 level.</p>
<p>VW also said it wanted to double its 1995 third quarter group net profit of 72 million marks ($48.67 million) in 1996.</p>
<p>VW shares surged on the news, ending Frankfurt bourse trade up 14.50 marks at 551.50 marks, a gain of nearly three percent.</p>
<p>The higher sales come at a critical time for VW, which has been distracted by a battle with the European Commission over controversial subsidies to build vehicles -- including the new Passat -- at plants in former communist East Germany.</p>
<p>VW said on Wednesday it was considering filing its own complaint against the European Commission after the state Saxony filed a suit last Friday against the commission with the European Court of Justice in Luxembourg.</p>
<p>VW chief legal officer Jens Neumann told reporters the decision to take legal action, which must be reached by Sept 16, depends on progress in talks between Bonn and Brussels.</p>
<p>Both Bonn and Brussels have indicated they were preparing complaints but both said the focus for now was on discussions.</p>
<p>The choice of Saxony's capital of Dresden as a site to launch the new car, built on the same platform as the popular Audi A4 as part of a cost-cutting strategy, was no accident.</p>
<p>Piech again backed Saxony's decision to give the 90 million marks in questioned subsidies, saying the aid in question was a small amount to the carmaker but important to Saxony for creating jobs. He also denied allegations VW was blackmailing Saxony by threatening to leave if it did not get the funds.</p>
<p>Some 430 of the new Passats, which are styled after the A4 but will be about 3,000 marks cheaper than the similar Audi base model, will be made each working day in Saxony, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that the decision by the premier of Saxony to grant subsidies to Volkswagen is a decision for the people and for jobs in Saxony,&quot; Piech said.</p>
<p>Top VW executives have put enormous expectations on the new Passat, first introduced in 1973. VW plans to double its Passat production to about 300,000 for western Europe in 1997, with half as saloons and the other as estate wagons.</p>
<p>&quot;Our performance in the the middle-size class has so far been considerably below what we would like it to be,&quot; said VW management board member Robert Buechelhofer said.</p>
<p>VW has long drawn strength from the Golf, one of the top-selling compact models in Europe for the last decade.</p>
<p>But VW is limping in the mid-size class. During the first half of 1996, the Passat ranked a mere fifth in the mid-size west European market with only a 6.6 percent market share.</p>
<p>German automobile trade magazines have given high ratings to the Passat but have teased VW, which said at the weekend it had discovered a surveillance camera at its German test track, for &quot;spying&quot; on its Audi luxury carmaker unit for styling help.</p>
<p>Piech downplayed the similarities and concerns about fighting one another for sales.</p>
<p>&quot;We see no problem,&quot; Piech said. &quot;Our goal is to take sales more away from Mercedes and BMW, not one another.&quot; ($1=1.4791 Mark)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C313">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DRESDEN, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
