<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39496" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: VW chief wants to boost return on sales tenfold.</title>
<headline>VW chief wants to boost return on sales tenfold.</headline>
<byline>John Gilardi</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Volkswagen AG management board chairman Ferdinand Piech said in an interview on Sunday he intended to boost the German carmaker's meagre return on sales level more than tenfold by the turn of the century.</p>
<p>Piech said in the interview with Der Spiegel magazine that VW, Europe's largest carmaker, would keep up its cost-cutting measures and seek more favourable contracts from suppliers.</p>
<p>Piech, 56, said he viewed Chrysler Corp. as a model for Volkswagen since the U.S. carmaker had produced a similar number of vehicles -- about two million -- during the first six months of 1996.</p>
<p>He noted Chrysler had a return on sales of 6.6 percent compared to only 0.6 percent at VW during the 1996 first half.</p>
<p>Piech also said VW was &quot;about a quarter of the way&quot; on the road to reaching the goals he set out when he took over at the Wolfsburg-based carmaker in 1993.</p>
<p>When asked if VW could achieve its goal of a return on sales against pre-tax profits of at least 6.5 percent by 2000, Piech told the magazine, &quot;We have higher goals than just that. We want to become the most successful carmaker in Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We always show this to our employees. Our return on sales is represented by a golf ball, Chrysler's by a big medicine ball,&quot; Piech said in the interview.</p>
<p>He also expressed confidence that VW's struggling Spanish subsidiary SEAT would return to profitability. But Piech was vague in saying how long embattled SEAT chairman Juan Llorens would remain with the carmaker.</p>
<p>&quot;If Mr. Llorens reaches retirement age, then he will be replaced with a competent manager,&quot; Piech said. He noted that the average retirement age for top VW managers was 55 to 65.</p>
<p>German publications have speculated that VW would not extend the contrct of Llorens when it expires in November, saying Piech was unhappy with the Seat restructuring.</p>
<p>Piech said VW's new version of the Passat saloon marked the start of VW moving into the higher-price range for luxury cars.</p>
<p>Piech said VW, which owns luxury carmaker Audi AG, could envision offering a car for about 150,000 marks ($101,000) under the VW name that would cost about 200,000 marks at other carmakers.</p>
<p>&quot;Volkswagen is for the citizen what Mercedes is for the establishment,&quot; Piech said. But he added, &quot;We could push forward into higher price regions.&quot;</p>
<p>Piech said VW would not create a new brand such as Toyota did in creating Lexus but would instead expand on the Passat, which is designed like and built on the same platform as the popular Audi A4.</p>
<p>He dismissed criticism that the decision to use fewer production platforms led to fewer ways to distinguish between VW-made vehicles under the VW, Audi, Skoda and SEAT brands.</p>
<p>&quot;The differences will always be there but only when the customer also sees, hears and feels&quot; the vehicles, he said.</p>
<p>In the lower price range, Piech said VW was lining up its new Audi A3 compact, the VW Golf and the redesigned Beetle to compete against Mercedes' new A-class small vehicle.</p>
<p>&quot;Three against one, that should be sufficient,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Piech also reaffirmed his support for controversial VW management board member Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua, who is at the centre of a legal fight between VW and General Motors Corp over allegations Lopez stole secret GM documents.</p>
<p>Lopez was GM's purchasing czar at its German-based Opel division when he defected to VW in March 1993. GM has filed a U.S. lawsuit against VW, which also names Piech. VW has denied GM's claims and filed its own suit charging GM with defamation.</p>
<p>&quot;Volkswagen is not involved in industrial espionage,&quot; Piech said in the interview. &quot;I am fully convinced of his personal character... One must meet him before passing judgment.&quot;</p>
<p>($1=1.4854 Mark)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
