<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61780" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Red Cross rejects U.S. wartime &quot;spying&quot; charges.</title>
<headline>Red Cross rejects U.S. wartime &quot;spying&quot; charges.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC), defender of war victims and political prisoners around the globe, on Wednesday rejected U.S. charges that key officials had worked for Nazi Germany in World War Two.</p>
<p>The Swiss-run body, which holds the Nobel Peace Prize for its activities, said U.S. agents who made the claims in reports to Washington near the end of the war appeared to be ignorant of how it worked or what its mandated role was.</p>
<p>Initial investigation since the charges became public in the United States in August made it possible &quot;to refute the majority of the allegations of espionage and even of the infiltration of the ICRC by German agents&quot;, it declared.</p>
<p>But it said there had been one &quot;sordid affair&quot; in early 1945 involving an ICRC official in Turkey. He was found by police there to have gold coins he claimed to have been given by a Hungarian journalist a U.S. report said was a Nazi agent.</p>
<p>In another case, a Swiss national who had worked in the ICRC war prisoners' agency in Geneva for a year in 1941-42 but resigned and went to North Africa was arrested by the Free French authorities in 1943 and shot for spying a year later.</p>
<p>Documents containing the charges were recently discovered in the U.S. National Archives by researchers for the World Jewish Congress (WJC) trying to trace the assets of victims of the Holocaust, the Nazi drive to eliminate the Jews.</p>
<p>Their publication coincided with allegations by the New York-based WJC that Swiss banks were still secretly holding gold and other assets of Jews killed by the Nazis and wealth looted in occupied countries and sent to Switzerland from Germany.</p>
<p>The 130-year-old ICRC, which has no formal link with the Swiss government, said it had taken the charges against it and some of its wartime officials -- known as delegates -- seriously and had begun research in its own archives.</p>
<p>But initial findings showed that of 21 people identified as its representatives in reports from agents of the U.S. wartime intelligence agency, the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), released by the WJC, only 16 actually had worked for it.</p>
<p>&quot;The other individuals mentioned, indeed those against whom the most serious allegations have been made, did not work for the ICRC,&quot; a statement from the body said.</p>
<p>&quot;In several cases, ICRC delegates were labelled as 'enemy agents' and accused of espionage simply because the U.S. agent had no idea whatsoever of the ICRC's mandate,&quot; the humanitarian body, which acts as a neutral intermediary in wars, said.</p>
<p>&quot;As yet, the ICRC cannot certify that there were no Nazi (or other!) agents in its ranks during the Second World War,&quot; the statement declared.</p>
<p>But it said it was already clear that OSS agents &quot;misinterpreted activities carried out entirely openly and with the consent or at the request of the Allies, and qualified them wrongly as espionage&quot;.</p>
<p>In one document, an unnamed OSS operative reported what he regarded as the suspicious communication by an ICRC delegate in Algiers to the German authorities of technical details of a vessel, the SS Canada.</p>
<p>In fact, the statement said, the ICRC had been asked by the French government-in-exile in Algiers in 1943 to notify the German and Italian authorities that the vessel was being put into service as a hospital ship.</p>
<p>Another OSS agent, cited by the WJC researchers, reported that the ICRC in Tunis had communicated to Berlin the names of two representatives of German war prisoners in Allied camps in North Africa -- suggesting this was espionage.</p>
<p>&quot;Yet this was normal ICRC practice: the ICRC communicated information about millions of prisoners of war to their states of origin and their relatives,&quot; the statement declared. Many other charges in the OSS documents were based on rumour.</p>
<p>The body, which last year said it recognised it was guilty of &quot;moral failure&quot; for not publicly denouncing atrocities against Jews and others in Nazi concentration camps, said it would be pursuing its research.</p>
<p>It would also be sending a mission to the United States shortly to share the results so far with the WJC and New York Republican Senator Alfonse D'Amato, chairman of the Senate's Banking Committee, who is also investigating the matter.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
