<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82454" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German police detain 2 men in VW spy saga.</title>
<headline>German police detain 2 men in VW spy saga.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>German authorities said on Friday that two men have been detained on suspicion of industrial spying at German carmaker Volkswagen AG.</p>
<p>The two men were believed to have planted secret cameras at a test track operated by Volkswagen, Europe's largest carmaker. VW said the cameras, discovered last summer, had apparently sent out photographs of vehicles under development.  </p>
<p>The public prosecutor's office in Braunschweig, located near the Wolfsburg headquarters of VW, said the men did not work for Volkswagen or to competing car manufacturers.</p>
<p>&quot;These men did not work for Volkswagen or another car company,&quot; said prosecutor Eckehard Niestroj.</p>
<p>VW management board chairman Ferdinand Piech said in late August that the cameras had been sending out photographs from the track for some time, noting that he believed VW had been under surveillance for about eight years.</p>
<p>VW probed for cameras at the test track after four unauthorised photographs of prototypes appeared in car magazines in recent months. Pictures of new models and prototypes are highly valued by industry magazines.</p>
<p>--John Gilardi, Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
