<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13902" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Midcontinent Chicago unleaded gasoline firms.</title>
<headline>U.S. Midcontinent Chicago unleaded gasoline firms.</headline>
<dateline>HOUSTON 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Midcontinent spot unleaded gasoline prices firmed in Chicago on stronger differentials for late-August deliveries as trade wound down in the cash market on Monday, traders said.</p>
<p>In contrast, Group Three basis in Monday afternoon discussion eased as buyers were outnumbered by sellers motivated by strong prevailing prices in the market, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We were slightly weaker, with more sellers than buyers, especially for diesel fuel&quot; one trader active in the Group market said.  </p>
<p>Gasoline prices were under pressure from lower prices on the NYMEX, where bids in ACCESS after-hours trade had eased to 60.75 cents a gallon after the contract closed at 61.62 cents in the earlier floor session.</p>
<p>Group Three unleaded gasoline was bid 2.25 cents a gallon over the print for prompt deliveries and 1.50 cents over for later deliveries, easing 0.25 cent a gallon.</p>
<p>Chicago unleaded firmed 0.50 cent a gallon to bids 2.75 cents under the print for late-August deliveries.</p>
<p>Group Three low sulphur diesel remained bid 3.50 cents a gallon over the print for prompt and later deliveries, and Chicago low sulphur diesel firmed 0.25 cent to bids 1.75 cents a gallon over the print.</p>
<p>High sulphur diesel was talked 1.25 cents over the print in Group Three and 0.50 cent over in Chicago, traders said.</p>
<p>-- Houston Bureau 713 210-8508</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOUSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
