<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="35105" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. West Coast gasolines firm with higher NYMEX.</title>
<headline>U.S. West Coast gasolines firm with higher NYMEX.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prices for U.S. West Coast gasoline strengthened with a higher futures market midday but distillates fell, traders said.</p>
<p>NYMEX October gasoline rose as much as 1.54 cents gallon to 64.50 cents, as a second set of U.S. inventory data showed gasoline drawdowns nationwide.</p>
<p>Gasoline stocks fell by 3.4 million barrels last week to 193.2 million barrels.</p>
<p>Traders noted that despite a 3.2 million barrel rise in Western stocks last week, distillates nationwide remained a significant 18 million below year-ago, according to the API.  </p>
<p>But analysts early Thursday said distillate production in PADD 5 was up to last year's levels, despite trader fears of short supplies ahead of winter.</p>
<p>Locally, distillate inventories remained 715,000 barrels below year ago, at 10.9 million barrels, according to American Petroleum Institute data.</p>
<p>Traders said distillates were tight on lingering production problems at Arco and Mobil's Los Angeles refineries and Chevron's northern California plant.</p>
<p>They said a fluid catalytic cracker at the Mobil refinery was expected back late this week.</p>
<p>Traders reported that Chevron's Los Angeles refinery was due to shut a fcc later this week, but the company denied any maintenance was planned.</p>
<p>Los Angeles CARB diesel remained 76/77 cents a gallon, while &quot;EPA,&quot; or low sulphur diesel slipped a half cent to 71/72 cents.</p>
<p>Jet fuel was seen ample out west, and stayed 76/77 cents overnight.</p>
<p>Los Angeles conventional-grade gasoline added a cent to reach 69/70 cents a gallon, with premium seen 7 cents higher.</p>
<p>Bids for CARB-grade unleaded in L.A. rose a quarter cent to 71.25 cents, while offers edged up 0.50 cent.</p>
<p>-- David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau +1 213 380 2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
