<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36308" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. West Coast prods turn narrowly mixed late.</title>
<headline>U.S. West Coast prods turn narrowly mixed late.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prices for U.S. West Coast products turned narrowly mixed in thin late trade, as a softer futures market was offset by concerns about tight distillate stocks.</p>
<p>&quot;These are levels we moved to yesterday and it's still talked at those levels,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>West Coast traders noted that despite a 3.2 million barrel rise in stocks last week, distillates nationwide remained a significant 18 million below year-ago levels, according to data released from the American Petroleum Institute.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're going into the winter short,&quot; one California trader said, noting the state's diesel demand would increase in the next few weeks because of harvesting. Heating demand from the cooler Pacific Northwest would also increase consumption.</p>
<p>Locally, distillate inventories remained 715,000 barrels below year ago, at 10.9 million barrels.</p>
<p>Traders said distillates were tight on lingering production problems at Arco and Mobil's Los Angeles refineries and Chevron's northern California plant.</p>
<p>They said a fluid catalytic cracker at the Mobil refinery was expected back late this week.  </p>
<p>Los Angeles CARB diesel rose one cent late to 76/77 cents a gallon, while &quot;EPA,&quot; or low sulphur diesel also added a cent to reach 71.50/72.50 cents.</p>
<p>The spread between more expensive CARB-grade gasolines and conventional grades stayed unusually narrow Wednesday, with refinery problems making the cost of conventional to go up.</p>
<p>Bids for Los Angeles conventional-grade gasoline added a one cent loss to their earlier fall of 0.50 cent. The grade ranged between 68 and 69 cents a gallon as NYMEX October crude settled 16 cents lower on the day at $23.24 a barrel.</p>
<p>NYMEX October gasoline settled unchanged at 62.96 cents.</p>
<p>Offers for CARB-grade unleaded in L.A. dropped a half cent to 71.50 cents.</p>
<p>-- David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau +1 213 380 2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
