<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41275" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: MidEast firms to win Pakistan oil products tender.</title>
<headline>MidEast firms to win Pakistan oil products tender.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The lowest offers in Pakistan's tender to buy gas oil (diesel), fuel oil and gasoline for October-December delivery were made by two MidEast oil trading firms, traders said on Monday.</p>
<p>The tender sought two cargoes of 60,000 tonnes each of 1.0 percent sulphur gas oil for delivery each month.</p>
<p>Traders said Jeddah-based Bakri Bunkers' offer at a premium of $1.388 per barrel to  MidEast spot quotes on a cost-and-freight (c-and-f) basis to Keamari was most competitive.  </p>
<p>Bakri Bunkers also made the lowest offer for the 100,000 tonnes of 3.5-percent sulphur, 180-cst fuel oil sought by the tender.</p>
<p>The offer was at a premium of $8.88 per tonne to MidEast quote, c-and-f Fotco.</p>
<p>Bakri offered 3.5-percent sulphur, 125-centistoke grade fuel oil delivered in Noveber and December, c-and-f Fotco, based on a formula of 95 percent for the 180-centistoke grade and five percent for the gas oil formula.</p>
<p>The price was $8.88 per tonne over MidEast fuel oil quotes and 99 cents per barrel over MidEast gas oil quotes.  </p>
<p>Pakistan sought 100,000 tonnes of 125-grade fuel oil for delivery in November and December. This grade is normally used by power stations during winter.</p>
<p>Star Energy offered the lowest price for 80-octane leaded gasoline at $17.45 per tonne above MidEast naphtha quotes, c-and-f Keamari.</p>
<p>The tender sought one 25,000-tonne cargo each month, but the November cargo was optional.</p>
<p>--Singapore Newsroom (+65-8703084)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
