<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="51488" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan refiners step up efforts to restructure.</title>
<headline>Japan refiners step up efforts to restructure.</headline>
<byline>Junko Oshima</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The failure of plunging gasoline prices to rebound has forced Japanese oil refiners to step up efforts to slim down, industry sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners increasingly need to cut costs as gasoline retail prices are not recovering,&quot; said Takashi Kawai, an analyst with the private Nikko Research Center.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners are very puzzled,&quot; Kawai said.</p>
<p>Showa Shell Sekiyu KK, an oil refiner and distributor owned 50 percent by the Royal Dutch/Shell Group, said it would hasten plans to slash distribution costs.</p>
<p>It said it would aim to trim its distribution costs by 13 billion yen ($118 million) by 2000, moving forward an earlier target date by four years.</p>
<p>The efforts to cut distribution costs are part of a plan Showa Shell unveiled earlier this year aimed at improving profits by 40 billion yen ($363 million) by the year 2000.</p>
<p>&quot;We will take all possible measures to cut costs,&quot; a spokesman for Showa Shell said.</p>
<p>Refiners have been struggling to cut costs as revenue from gasoline sales, previously a pillar of their income, has tumbled together with plunging retail prices.</p>
<p>In the past two years, in the run up to deregulation in oil product imports this April, gasoline retail prices nose-dived as gasoline stations raced to cut prices fearing floods of cheap imports.</p>
<p>Refiners lost their monopoly on imports of items such as gasoline, kerosene and gas oil after the deregulation.</p>
<p>In order to combat imports, major refiners introduced a new wholesale pricing system this year which reflects international oil product prices as well as crude prices and currency rates.</p>
<p>With the implentation of the new system, refiners had expected gasoline retail prices to pick up in regions where they had fallen too far.</p>
<p>However, since April, retail prices have weakened despite rising wholesale prices.</p>
<p>During the period from April to August, refiners raised their wholesale prices by about 1.5 yen per litre reflecting higher crude prices and a weaker yen against the dollar.</p>
<p>But during the same period retail prices dropped by about 2 yen to a national average of 105 yen ($0.95) per litre.</p>
<p>Tax, which is fully passed on to the consumer, accounts for more than half of the retail price.</p>
<p>In September 1995, the average national gasoline retail price was 112 yen (about $1), down 8 yen from a year earlier, according to Japan's Oil Information Service Centre.</p>
<p>The weak market environment has forced the refiners to forge cooperation agreements with each other.</p>
<p>The industry was stunned last year when arch-rivals Nippon Oil Co Ltd and Idemitsu Kosan Co Ltd, Japan's top two oil firms, announced plans to cooperate.</p>
<p>On Friday, Nippon Oil and Idemitsu Kosan said they had started supplying fuel oil to each other.</p>
<p>The agreement should save Nippon Oil about 1 billion yen ($9 million) in the year to next March, Nippon Oil said.</p>
<p>Persistent rumours that stronger ties between Nippon Oil and Idemitsu would eventually lead to a merger, have been denied by both companies.</p>
<p>Analysts said rather than a complete merger, Nippon Oil and Idemitsu may eventually jointly manage distribution. ($1=110)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
