<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="63311" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX gasoline ends lower on oversupply concerns.</title>
<headline>NYMEX gasoline ends lower on oversupply concerns.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX gasoline prices ended sharply lower Thursday as talk of imports from Europe arriving on top of ample U.S. stocks fueled concerns of oversupply, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a combination of imports when we have ample supply, and the gasoline season being now over,&quot; said Gerald Samuels, managing director of ARB Oil.</p>
<p>October gasoline settled down 1.74 cent at 61.32 cents a gallon after falling as low as 60.40 cents during the day. Support was pegged at 60.40 and after that at $59.70.  </p>
<p>&quot;Sell stops were triggered at around 61.25,&quot; said a trader explaining gasoline's drop Thursday to 60.40.</p>
<p>Gasoline demand traditionally peaks during the summer, but inventory draws this summer were considered lackluster by traders.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, shipping sources have noticed a sharp increase in charters for gasoline shipments from Europe to the United States in September.</p>
<p>October crude oil settled off 35 cents to $23.54 a barrel and October heating oil settled 1.10 cent lower to 66.77 cents a gallon on profit-taking.</p>
<p>Crude and heating oil rallied strongly Wednesday after inventory data from the American Petroleum Institute showed a much smaller-than-expected build in heating oil stocks. Heating oil stocks are at historical lows as winter approaches.</p>
<p>Traders said the demand for heating oil and the demand for crude to produce it contained Thursday's selling in both.</p>
<p>The strength of crude prices, energized recently by U.S.- Iraqi tensions, has deteriorated the gasoline-to-crude crack spread. The gasoline crack closed at $2.21 a barrel, the lowest level since mid-October of 1994.</p>
<p>The weaker fundamentals in gasoline has made it a laggard on the NYMEX for months, though traders said gasoline prices could go higher during the winter as refiners produce less gasoline in favor of heating oil.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a great deal of pressure on gasoline for some time, but things will change later in the season, and then one can make a strong case for it,&quot; said Thomas Blakeslee of Cargill Investor Services.</p>
<p>Traders said market forces are also creating a disincentive for refiners to make gasoline due to the deteriorating premium of gasoline over crude oil, which hurts profitability.</p>
<p>-- Harry Milling, New York Energy Desk, 212-859-1761</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
