<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65019" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US West Coast prods flatten late on sparse buying.</title>
<headline>US West Coast prods flatten late on sparse buying.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. West Coast product prices were mostly unchanged late as buyers continued to avoid a market propped up by NYMEX energy futures, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a little confused with a very strong NYMEX as backdrop,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>West Coast fundamentals remained mixed, with meager supply offset by even weaker demand.</p>
<p>&quot;Low inventories don't help you unless you have something to drive it up,&quot; the broker said.</p>
<p>West Coast stocks fell last week by 709,000 barrels to hit 26.9 million, the American Petroleum Institute (API) said.  </p>
<p>Traders called those volumes extremely low.</p>
<p>But demand has eased for gasoline, brokers said, curbing tight supply and the sharp rises in Wednesday's futures market -- which saw October heating oil up 2.28 cents a gallon to 67.87 cents.</p>
<p>Futures prices received a lift after Tuesday's API report indicated meager builds in U.S. distillate stocks, already at historic lows.</p>
<p>In the West, falling gasoline supplies and below-average refinery output come right before a period of heavy refinery maintenance, poising products for possible upswings should unplanned outages occur.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Ultramar denied rumours on Wednesday that the hydrotreater shut at its 100,000 barrel-per-day refinery in Wilmington, California</p>
<p>A company spokeswoman said the plant was running short of hydrogen this week because an outside supplier had cut shipments due to production problems.</p>
<p>One trader said a lack of hydrogen could eventually hamper production from the plant's fluid catalytic cracker, which needs the gas.</p>
<p>Conventional or &quot;clear&quot; grade gasoline in Los Angeles remained 67/68 cents after falling 2.50 cents a gallon early.</p>
<p>Premium conventional in L.A. was nine cents over regular. The grade remained strong following a fire in early September at Mobil's Torrance, California, reformer -- a unit which turns low grade into high-grade gasoline.</p>
<p>Ultra-clean CARB gasoline in L.A. gave back early gains by slipping a cent to 72.50/73 cents a gallon.</p>
<p>Deals for October and September cost nearly the same, as business shifted to the later month.</p>
<p>Bids for low-sulphur diesel in L.A. paused after their morning downturn, staying 71 cents, while offers remained 72.50 cents. CARB grade also flattened out at 76/77.50 cents.</p>
<p>But traders say distillates might still soften, with cargoes expected soon.</p>
<p>Jet fuel prices slipped when a deal got done at 74.50 cents a gallon, 2.50 cents below Wednesday's early levels.</p>
<p>--David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau +1 213 380 2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
