<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65942" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan oil firms seen battered by poor petrol price.</title>
<headline>Japan oil firms seen battered by poor petrol price.</headline>
<byline>Junko Oshima</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Floundering gasoline retail prices are expected to eat away at Japanese oil companies' profits for the third consecutive year, industry analysts say.</p>
<p>&quot;The oil industry's profits have slumped from a peak to their worst ever in a matter of years,&quot; Toshinori Itoh, a senior analyst with private think-tank Daiwa Institute of Research (DIR) said.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only are gasoline retail prices still weakening, but margins for kerosene and gas oil are also falling,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Itoh expects combined current profits at seven Japanese refiners -- Nippon Oil Co Ltd, Mitsubishi Oil Co Ltd, 5004 T Koa Oil Co Ltd, Cosmo Oil Co Ltd, Fuji Kosan Co Ltd, General Sekiyu KK and Japan Energy Corp -- to plunge an average 52.23 percent in fiscal 1996/97 ending March 31 compared to a year earlier, to 34.4 billion yen ($315 million).</p>
<p>This compares with the seven firms' combined current profits of 175.96 billion yen ($1.61 billion) in fiscal 1993/94.</p>
<p>Current profit is pre-tax profit including losses or gains on investments. Most refiners are due to announce their mid-term company results in October.</p>
<p>In 1993/94, leading refiner Nippon Oil Co posted current profits of 42.3 billion yen ($388 million). Itoh forecasts Nippon Oil's current profits for 1996/97 at four billion yen ($36.6 million).</p>
<p>Refiners have been battling in vain to boost oil product retail prices, partly by keeping refinery operations low and oil product stockpiles tight.</p>
<p>A new wholesale price system introduced by leading refiners this April, which brings kerosene and gas oil prices higher, is also meeting stiff opposition from retailers and consumers.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners had been counting on gasoline retail prices to recover this year, but prices have weakened further,&quot; Takashi Kawai, an analyst with the Nikko Research Center Ltd said.</p>
<p>The retail price of gasoline, formally the pillar of refiners' income, has been falling since mid-1994, when the industry grew certain that deregulation of the oil product imports was inevitable.</p>
<p>Anticipating a flood of cheap imports, refiners rushed to build gasoline stations and encourage dealers to slash retail prices in a desperate attempt to secure market share.</p>
<p>Last April, oil product imports were liberalised and refiners lost their monopoly on imports of oil products, such as gasoline, kerosene and gas oil.</p>
<p>In addition to the poor oil product retail market, rising crude oil prices have also dealt a crippling blow to the industry, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners have not been able to pass on higher costs deriving from strong crude prices and a weaker yen against the dollar, to the retail stage,&quot; Nikko's Kawai said.</p>
<p>During the period from April to August, leading refiners raised their wholesale prices by about 1.5 yen ($0.013) per litre reflecting higher crude prices and a weaker yen against the dollar. But during the same period, retail prices dropped by about two yen ($0.018) to a national average of 105 yen ($0.96) per litre.</p>
<p>In August 1995, the national average gasoline retail price was 113 yen ($1.04) per litre, and 120 yen ($1.10) in August 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners will be in a very serious situation if high crude prices prevail and retail prices do not recover,&quot; Itoh said.</p>
<p>Unlike western major oil companies which develop a large quantity of their own crude and profit from higher crude prices, Japanese oil firms do not benefit from strong crude prices, especially when retail prices are easing.</p>
<p>Crude oil developed by Japanese oil firms overseas accounts for only an estimated 15 percent of Japan's total crude imports, Kawai said. Japan imported 266.83 million kilolitres of crude oil in calendar 1995, official statistics show. ($1=109 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I65200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
