<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67199" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Retail gasoline continues to fall in N. California.</title>
<headline>Retail gasoline continues to fall in N. California.</headline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Against the national trend, gasoline prices at the pump in northern California continue to fall from springtime highs, according to a price survey conducted by the state's motorist association.</p>
<p>California State Automobile Association (CSAA) reported the average cost of self-serve unleaded gasoline has fallen two cents since last month to $1.47 a gallon.</p>
<p>Some cities, like San Francisco, saw average declines of nine cents to $1.45 a gallon. Prices at state capital Sacramento dipped three cents to $1.45.</p>
<p>Prices have gradually fallen from late April, when a rash of refinery shutdowns helped jack up self-serve unleaded to $1.54 a gallon, an 11-cent rise in one week.</p>
<p>&quot;Northern California was really high with all the refinery problems. It had a long way to go (down),&quot; one gasoline broker said.</p>
<p>The national average for self-serve unleaded fuel is up two cents from last month to $1.25 and eight cents higher than September, 1995.</p>
<p>Prices have eased with a seasonal decline in motorist demand following the U.S. Labor Day weekend.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, ample inventories and reports of higher European imports have forced down the value of NYMEX gasoline futures, which help determine the value of retail prices.</p>
<p>Unleaded gasoline for October delivery fell a sharp 1.74 cents Thursday to 61.32 cents a gallon.</p>
<p>But dealers in the California gasoline market doubted the price declines would continue, with regional stocks low at 26.9 million barrels and scheduled maintenance starting up at refineries.</p>
<p>&quot;I doubt it will go much lower,&quot; a California broker said.</p>
<p>--David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau 213-380-2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I65200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
