<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68177" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan refiners face strong opposition on prices.</title>
<headline>Japan refiners face strong opposition on prices.</headline>
<byline>Junko Oshima</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japanese refiners are facing strident demands from gasoline station owners to change their oil product wholesale pricing system so it better reflects domestic market conditions, oil industry sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;Under the new system, refiners are making profits while retailers are losing money,&quot; said Hiroshi Kawane, vice-chairman of the National Federation of Petroleum Commercial Associations, an oil product retailers' group.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices set under the new system do not reflect the domestic retail market,&quot; Kawane told Reuters.</p>
<p>Leading Japanese refiners introduced a new wholesale pricing system in April when restrictions on oil product imports were lifted because they believed liberalisation would lead to a flood of cheap imports.</p>
<p>Liberalisation caused Japanese refiners to lose their virtually exclusive right to import oil products.</p>
<p>Although most Japanese refiners have stuck to the new system, General Sekiyu KK said it had stopped using the system because it was not functioning.</p>
<p>&quot;After four months of implementation, we realised the wholesale pricing system was unrealistic,&quot; a General Sekiyu spokesman said. &quot;We could not allow the retailers to suffer.&quot;</p>
<p>Traditionally, Japanese oil companies kept gasoline prices high while keeping the price of kerosene and gas oil at low levels.</p>
<p>The new system -- designed to reflect international oil product and crude prices as well as currency fluctuations -- lowers the price of gasoline while raising those of kerosene and gas oil to better reflect global markets.</p>
<p>Also in April, refiners announced they would drop the practice of guaranteeing retailers a rebate if prices fell below a certain level as a result of market competition.</p>
<p>Industry sources expect this move will eventually force many of Japan's 60,000 gasoline stations, which together sell 50 million kilolitres of the fuel a year, out of business.</p>
<p>In the past two years, during the run up to market deregulation, gasoline retail prices in regions where stations are close together, plummeted on expectations of cheap imports.</p>
<p>The average national gasoline retail price has dropped 17 yen (15 cents) per litre since early 1994 to 105 yen (95 cents).</p>
<p>Tax accounts for about 56 to 57 yen (51 to 52 cents) of the retail price.</p>
<p>Gasoline retail prices have fallen since April under the new system, contrary to expectations they would recover in regions where they had fallen too sharply.</p>
<p>Kawane said the new pricing system has failed to stop the price cutting war, partly because refiners affiliated to foreign oil firms, such as Esso Sekiyu K.K, and Mobil Sekiyu K.K., have not adopted the system and keep their prices below those of major Japanese refiners.</p>
<p>Esso Sekiyu, an affiliate of Exxon Corp, for example, sets its gasoline wholesale price about four to five yen (cents) below major Japanese refiners, he said.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for Esso Sekiyu said the company made it a policy not to reveal its wholesale price.</p>
<p>Nippon Oil Co and Idemitsu Kosan, the top two domestic refiners, have repeatedly made clear their determination to continue the pricing system.</p>
<p>Industry analysts, however, said refiners would most likely review the system. &quot;Refiners are expected to have no choice but to review the system soon,&quot; said Toshinori Itoh, senior analyst with private think-tank Daiwa Institute of Research.</p>
<p>&quot;Refiners should also take into consideration price differences according to regions,&quot; Itoh said.</p>
<p>A Ministry of International Trade and Industry official said: &quot;We give the new system high marks, and we think it should be kept.&quot; ($1 = 110 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
