<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82059" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US West Coast products ease more, buyers sidelined.</title>
<headline>US West Coast products ease more, buyers sidelined.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. West Coast product prices drifted lower late on Thursday, with recent fluctuations in futures markets sidelining local trade, while some distillates benefitted from tightened supplies.</p>
<p>&quot;No one was anxious to do anything,&quot; one Arizona-based trader said.</p>
<p>He was surprised that prices for low sulphur diesel, which is used outside California, failed to make gains with supplies supposedly lean in Las Vegas, Nevada.</p>
<p>Low sulphur, or &quot;EPA&quot; diesel, slipped 1.0 to 1.50 cents a gallon to 71/72.00 cents.  </p>
<p>But CARB diesel, used in California, bucked the bearish trend in products by gaining one cent late to end 78/79 cents a gallon. Rumours that a products ship was &quot;drydocked&quot; in San Francisco made L.A. supply leaner.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, heating oil for October delivery retreated from new highs to end the day down 0.87 cent at 70.90 cents.</p>
<p>Profit-taking and fading interest in expiring October products contracts pressured the market.</p>
<p>November crude oil and front-month gasoline also dropped in line with heating oil  </p>
<p>Wholesale prices for conventional regular gasoline in Los Angeles erased Wednesday's gain by falling a penny early, then staying flat at 66/67 cents in the afternoon. San Francisco grades were 2.75 cents lower than L.A. material.</p>
<p>Consumption of conventional gasoline will drop in coming weeks as interior Western states add more oxygenates to car fuels and cut back on straight gasoline use.</p>
<p>&quot;It will lower the demand for gasoline by 10 percent,&quot; in the Phoenix, Arizona-area, one trader said.</p>
<p>CARB gasoline in L.A. eased 0.50 cent to 71.50/72.00 cents a gallon. -- David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau +1 213 380 2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
