<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="18405" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: China's environmental needs seen overtaking U.S.</title>
<headline>China's environmental needs seen overtaking U.S.</headline>
<byline>Eddie Evans</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's booming economy and growing population will soon put more demands on the earth's resources than the United States does, a Washington-based study group said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>And if China, with its much larger population, tries to replicate a consumer economy, it will quickly become clear that it is unsustainable, the Worldwatch Institute said.</p>
<p>&quot;In recent decades, many observers noted that the United States, with less than five percent of the world's population, was consuming a third or more of its resources,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is no longer true. In several areas, China has overtaken the United States,&quot; the group said in the September/October 1996 issue of its World Watch magazine.</p>
<p>China already consumes more grain and red meat, uses more fertilizer, produces more steel and burns more coal than the United States, the article by Worldwatch President Lester Brown and Vice President Christopher Flavin said.</p>
<p>In its use of oil and carbon dioxide emissions, it is fast catching up. Its emissions of carbon dioxide, the leading greenhouse gas, are currently a tenth of the world total, Worldwatch said.</p>
<p>China's economy has grown by 10 to 14 percent a year for the last four years, and would overtake the United States as the world's largest by 2010 if the growth rate continued.</p>
<p>Since China's population is nearly five times that of the United States, its per capita demands are still far less -- for example the average American consumes 25 times as much oil as the average Chinese citizen.</p>
<p>But even on a per capita basis, China is closing the gap on the United States in some products, consuming 66 pounds (30 kgs) of pork per person a year, compared with 68.3 pounds (31 kgs) in the United States.</p>
<p>If Chinese people were to consume as much beef as the 99 pounds (45 kgs) per year eaten by Americans, it would take 343 million tonnes of grain -- the entire U.S. harvest -- to feed the cattle to make up the difference, Worldwatch said.</p>
<p>&quot;As its population of 1.2 billion people moves into modern houses, buys cars, refrigerators and televisions, and shifts to a meat-based diet, the entire world will feel the effects,&quot; Worldwatch said.</p>
<p>If China were to consume as much grain and oil per person as the United States, prices of both would go off the top of the charts and carbon dioxide emissions would soar, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;The bottom line is that China, with its vast population, simply will not be able to follow for long any of the development paths blazed to date,&quot; it added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
