<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25303" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - World coal use to grow despite eco fears.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - World coal use to grow despite eco fears.</headline>
<byline>Nicholas Shaxson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Efforts by rich countries to curb the use of coal, seen as the worst culprit among the main fossil fuels in contributing to global warming, will be overwhelmed as economic growth surges in the giants of the developing world.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no way out of it,&quot; said David Brezovec of London-based Coal Week International.</p>
<p>&quot;It is my opinion that the environmental lobby will not be able to stop the increase in coal-fired construction.&quot;</p>
<p>Surging demand for electricity in the rapidly growing economies of southeast Asia, backed by vast world reserves, will spearhead the ballooning global appetite for coal.</p>
<p>International trade in coal will soar too, Brezovec said, due partly to European countries scaling down subsidies to local producers and looking further afield for their coal.</p>
<p>Australian and U.S. exports are set to roughly double by 2010, according to the International Energy Agency (IEA), while imports into China, south Asia and east Asia will grow almost by a factor of four.</p>
<p>Many scientists believe the carbon dioxide emitted when coal, oil and natural gas are burned traps heat in the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Coal is the most carbon-intensive fossil fuel and increased use of it means more greenhouse emissions, and a warmer planet.</p>
<p>The IEA said 1995 was the warmest global year on record since 1856.</p>
<p>CHINA LARGEST SINGLE SOURCE OF CARBON DIOXIDE EMISSIONS</p>
<p>Among developing countries, the IEA said in its World Energy Outlook 1996, &quot;China will remain the single largest source of emissions and is projected to more than double its emissions by 2010.&quot;</p>
<p>Coal accounts for about three quarters of all electricity generated in China and this share was unlikely to change, it added.</p>
<p>The increase in China's emissions over the next 15 years will roughly equal that of the combined total of Europe, North America and the wealthy countries of the Pacific region.</p>
<p>One implication is that national initiatives by rich countries to reduce carbon dioxide emissions &quot;will have only a limited effect on global emissions, and even less on atmospheric concentrations of all greenhouse gases by 2010.&quot;</p>
<p>Industrial nations pledged at the latest round of the U.N. Conference on Climate change in Geneva last month to seek specific, legally binding objectives to curb global emissions.</p>
<p>Even initiatives like this are meeting fierce opposition.</p>
<p>Various energy trade groupings argue the proposals would be so costly that a global economic slump would result.</p>
<p>Australia, the world's largest coal exporter, dissociated itself in Geneva from a key clause on emissions targets.</p>
<p>But insurance company representatives argued that the economic costs of failing to act, such as rising sea levels, would be far greater.</p>
<p>The World Health Organisation pitched in, too, with gloomy forecasts that steadily rising world temperatures would provoke outbreaks of new epidemics.</p>
<p>While sulphur and nitrogen oxide pollution can be cut back by installing expensive equipment in industrial plants and power stations, carbon dioxide is much harder to eliminate.</p>
<p>One way to cut back is to raise efficiency at power plants.</p>
<p>New coal-fired plants which further recycle waste heat may increase net thermal efficiency from around 40 percent currently to 50 percent in the next few years, according to the World Coal Institute.</p>
<p>ANTI-POLLUTION TECHNOLOGY SEEN AS A LUXURY BY SOME COUNTRIES</p>
<p>But such technology costs money, and is often seen as a luxury by many developing countries.</p>
<p>&quot;China and eastern Europe, for example, have environmental legislation in place but it is rarely enforced,&quot; said a U.K.-based coal industry official, who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>&quot;We must convince them that more efficient coal technology will save them money in the end.&quot;</p>
<p>Fledgling efforts are being made to this effect.</p>
<p>Companies like the U.K.-based CRE Group Ltd are trying to foster the use of clean coal technology appropriate for poor countries, such as efficient coal-burning domestic stoves.</p>
<p>Another avenue being explored by members of the IEA's Greenhouse Gases Research and Development Programme is to freeze carbon dioxide into blocks and dump it deep in the Atlantic, where it will diffuse into the surrounding sea.</p>
<p>But analysts say options like this are still too expensive to be workable.</p>
<p>Countries wishing to move away from burning coal have little room for manoeuvre.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite the fast growth of many novel forms of energy,&quot; the IEA said, &quot;fossil fuels will still account for nearly 90 percent of global energy consumption by 2010.&quot;</p>
<p>Governments are wary of over-dependence on oil, after the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting countries (OPEC) sent its price soaring in the oil shock of the 1970s.</p>
<p>Many wealthy countries are switching from burning coal to natural gas, which produces less carbon dioxide per energy unit.</p>
<p>But Europe has only enough gas reserves to last 21 years at current production rates, British Petroleum said in its 1996 Statistical Review of World Energy.</p>
<p>More is expected to be discovered, but coal reserves are in a different league. At current production rates, the world's proven coal reserves would last for well over 200 years.</p>
<p>&quot;Many developing countries will quite quickly be up to speed with coal technology,&quot; said the coal industry official.</p>
<p>&quot;If the gas runs out in the U.K. in 30 years' time, we will probably find ourselves buying clean coal technology from the Chinese.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
