<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="28014" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Airline business faces anti-pollution tax threat.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Airline business faces anti-pollution tax threat.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Neil Winton, Science and Technology Correspondent</p>
<p>Air travel could be the prerogative of the rich if environmentalists' plans to protect the skies from pollution are successful.</p>
<p>The Green lobby says aircraft are a serious threat to the atmosphere and the pollution they cause is increasing. The industry must be curbed and ending the tax free status of fuel used for international air travel is the way to do it.</p>
<p>&quot;If the airline industry was a country it would rank about eighth in the world in terms of emissions, equivalent to a large Euorpean Union country, with the growth rate of an Asian Pacific tiger economy,&quot; said the Climate Action Network at a meeting in July of a United Nations commission on global warming.</p>
<p>The tax free status for international aviation jet fuel, set by the 1944 Chicago Convention on Civil Aviation, should be ended, Climate Action Network added.</p>
<p>The aerospace industry, gathering this week for the biennial air show in Farnborough, southern England, wants none of this.</p>
<p>The industry insists it is not a major polluter, just an easy target compared with cars, lorries and power stations.</p>
<p>Any increase in taxes would be unlikely to curb air travel. Taxes would simply raise the cost to ordinary people, slap down the growing air freight business, bring windfall gains to national treasuries, and ruin the hard-won efficiency of the world's airline industry.</p>
<p>Because air travel is so crucial to modern life, it would be curbed only by huge tax increases, the industry says.</p>
<p>The environmentalists will not be deflected.</p>
<p>&quot;An aviation fuel tax or some variation is coming and the industry should take appropriate action. We are the blinking warning light to the manufacturers and the airlines on global warming and aviation emissions,&quot; said Annie Petsonk, international counsel with the U.S. lobby group, the Environmental Defence Fund in Washington.</p>
<p>Petsonk said although the aviation industry had made itself more efficient, overall emissions would continue to increase as demand for aviation rises.</p>
<p>There was a possibility that an aviation tax would make serious inroads into the mass market for travel, she said, adding that this depended on the strength of the public's appetite for flight.</p>
<p>&quot;Leisure and business are all different. It may be that the tax would increase load factors,&quot; Petsonk said.</p>
<p>The increasing level of pollution from planes had to be tackled urgently, she continued.</p>
<p>&quot;Aviation emissions are projected to increase from roughly three percent (of the world's total) today to as much as 10 percent in the midterm time frame. The altitude of the emissions means it is most active as a greenhouse gas and possible ozone layer depletion,&quot; Petsonk said.</p>
<p>Greenpeace International's Bill Hare also sees this as a growing problem, but has a more conciliatory proposal.</p>
<p>&quot;The airline business is growing at about seven percent a year and current global emissions are between two and three percent. But because of the altitude the effect is more like five to six percent,&quot; said Hare, Greenpeace's climate policy director in Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Hare says the best solution would be to include emissions from planes in each country's official pollution count, something which is not done currently. Emissions could then be subject to a national carbon tax and governments could decide on aviation's share.</p>
<p>The independent World Energy Council (WEC) said those clamouring for action against airline pollution in the name of curbing global warming were aiming at the wrong target.</p>
<p>&quot;These proposals are misdirected. You should be phasing out huge energy subsididies, then tackle the biggest examples of inefficiency and waste,&quot; said Michael Jefferson, the WEC's deputy secretary general.</p>
<p>Jefferson said air travel growth was in fact declining, from over 13 percent a year in the 1960s, to about nine percent in the 1970s, and less than six percent a year since then.</p>
<p>Jefferson said the first losers from an aviation fuel tax would be the poor, and air freight which has been growing at about 12 percent a year since the 1960s.</p>
<p>&quot;All this to tackle about three percent of carbon dioxide emissions, about one twentieth of road vehicles, at least in the U.K. This shouldn't be the number one priority,&quot; Jefferson said.</p>
<p>The International Air Transport Association (IATA) is understandably nervous about the tax possibility, especially after watching world airlines turn huge losses from 1990 to 1993 into expected profits this year of $6 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;We think that aviation has done a superb job of cleaning up its act and becoming more efficient, more so than most tranpsort industries,&quot; said IATA spokesman Tim Goodyear.</p>
<p>&quot;We would resist any attempts to introduce fuel taxes on international aviation,&quot; he said from his office in Geneva.</p>
<p>But environmentalists believe the change is inevitable.</p>
<p>&quot;The pressure is building,&quot; said Dr Dan Lashof, senior scientist with the Natural Resources Defence Council in Washington.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to believe that the current situation where the average motorist has to pay in the U.K, for example, 50 pence (75 cents) a litre in tax every time he drives up to a filling station, while an aircraft can do the same and pay nothing cannot go on and pressure is clearly building to change it,&quot; Lashof said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
