<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38330" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Global warming generates hope for nuclear power.</title>
<headline>Global warming generates hope for nuclear power.</headline>
<byline>Tom Ashby</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Faced with a ballooning world population and growing concerns about global warming, the nuclear power industry is selling its environmental benefits to snatch a slice of a predicted huge growth in electricity demand.</p>
<p>The problem is that the industry is still trying to shake off its bad image, and private financiers are reluctant to fund its expansion, a Uranium Institute conference heard.</p>
<p>World electricity demand is set to double in the next 50 years, even after efficiency and conservation measures, and John Taylor, chief executive of British Nuclear Fuels Ltd, sees a supply deficit growing to 8,000 terrawatt hours by 2050, equivalent to a third of current world oil production.</p>
<p>&quot;I would argue that this gap can only be filled by either additional fossil-fired generation or by nuclear,&quot; he told the conference.</p>
<p>Delegates at the conference which ends on Friday heard that the choice of which fuel source to use would not be determined by resource availability, but by other factors such as environmental impact and convenience.</p>
<p>Nuclear power lost much public support in the West after accidents at Three Mile Island in 1977 and Chernobyl in 1987, Taylor said, but this image was changing because of growing concerns about climate change.</p>
<p>While the fear of another Chernobyl still dominates many people's view of nuclear power, its supporters prefer to point to its low waste output and zero sulphur and carbon emissions.</p>
<p>&quot;Global warming is now becoming the world's number one environmental issue, and that is an opportunity for the nuclear industry,&quot; Taylor said.</p>
<p>There are currently 450 nuclear reactors worldwide delivering seven percent of the world's primary energy needs, but this is expected to fall to six percent in 15 years. Primary energy sources embrace electricity, oil products and coal, as well as alternatives like wind and solar power.</p>
<p>If nuclear does have a continuing large part to play in the world's energy future, a crucial factor will be finding the cash to do it, experts say.</p>
<p>Because of high up-front capital costs and large decommissioning costs, private financiers are reluctant to commit to nuclear energy while cheaper alternatives, such as gas, exist.</p>
<p>Only in Asia, where government support for nuclear power is strongest, are private companies actively investing new plant.</p>
<p>But as the cost of waste disposal and decommissioning are written in to the price of nuclear power, so fossil fuels should increasingly incorporate the cost of acid rain and climate change.</p>
<p>&quot;If global warming is a reality, it will most definitely appear on the bill of tomorrow's consumer,&quot; Taylor said.</p>
<p>But perhaps the biggest limitation to nuclear power's growth is its lack of research and development funds, delegates heard.</p>
<p>Without more research, nuclear power could become a victim of its own success because supply of uranium is limited and the next generation of fast-breeder reactors, which run on plutonium, has not achieved commercial viability.</p>
<p>Ivan Vera, administrator of the OECD's Nuclear Energy Agency, said if the world gets serious about reducing the gases responsible for global warming, like carbon dioxide, nuclear power could be extended to supply 45 percent of world electricity demand, from 17 percent currently.</p>
<p>This was the finding of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which examined how nuclear power could contribute to a massive reduction in carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
<p>&quot;In order to support the projected nuclear capacity growth up to the end of the 21st century, the nuclear fuel resource would need to be extended,&quot; Vera said.</p>
<p>&quot;Several alternatives may be considered for this purpose, including a deployment of breeder reactors (which would have to be initiated by 2025), enhanced uranium expoloration and recovery efforts, and, in the long-term (by 2050 or so), the introduction of other types of nuclear power plants such as thorium fuelled reactors, hybrid systems and even fusion reactors.&quot;</p>
<p>Delegates said that the most ambitious forecasts were unlikely, but that a major nuclear expansion in east Asia was possible.</p>
<p>&quot;Given the timescales inherent in the industry it is necessary to start with a somewhat visionary approach,&quot; BNFL's Taylor said.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 8145</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
