<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58634" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. to press for agreement on curbing emissions.</title>
<headline>U.S. to press for agreement on curbing emissions.</headline>
<byline>Robert Green</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States will press for a binding international agreement to curb emissions that could cause global warming, Under Secretary of State for Global Affairs Timothy Wirth said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;All countries must work together to do more to guard against harmful climate changes,&quot; Wirth, a former Democratic senator from Colorado, said at a hearing of the Senate Energy Committee. He was speaking for the Clinton administration.</p>
<p>&quot;The United States recommended in Geneva that future negotiations focus on an agreement that sets a realistic, verifiable and binding medium-term emissions target,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the latest round of the United Nations Conference on Climate Change, held in Geneva in July, the United States switched its position to back mandatory targets for pollution cuts. The move opened the way for a binding pact at a follow-up meeting of government ministers in December 1997 in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
<p>Wirth said that although the scientific community did not agree on how much or at what rate the Earth's climate would change because of increases in emissions from vehicles, factories and other power sources, there was general agreement on the finding of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change that current trends would lead to warmer temperatures.</p>
<p>This will cause flooding of some coastal areas and threaten food supplies in some areas of the world, he said.</p>
<p>Wirth's conclusions were challenged by Chairman Frank Murkowski, an Alaska Republican, who said, &quot;But thus far, the scientific jury is still out over the question of whether or not human activities such as the burning of fossil fuels will result in dangerous, significant, adverse climate change.&quot;</p>
<p>Murkowski said he was concerned by the possibility of a treaty setting legally binding emission limits because that could cripple the U.S. economy and allow other nations such as China to bring the United States before the World Court if U.S. targets were not met.</p>
<p>Wirth said developing nations would also have to be part of any international agreement. He said no conclusions had been made about specific emission targets or timetables, but any targets that were set would have to be flexible.</p>
<p>&quot;The cost of action in the medium term is less than the cost of inaction in the long term,&quot; Wirth said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not talking about extreme action,&quot; he said. Asked if any U.S. energy taxes were being considered to curb energy use, Wirth replied, &quot;We're not at that point yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Sen. J. Bennett Johnston, a Louisiana Democrat, said Americans would resist any new energy taxes or laws that would dramatically affect their lives, such as limits on the size or horsepower of cars and trucks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
