<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14838" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Old heart drug from flower is still useful - doctors.</title>
<headline>Old heart drug from flower is still useful - doctors.</headline>
<dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Digitalis, a popular heart drug derived from a common garden flower, still stands up pretty well against sophisticated modern pharmaceuticals, doctors said on Monday.</p>
<p>Heart specialists attending the European Congress of Cardiology in Birmingham debated just what aspects of heart disease digitalis was good for -- but they agreed the old-fashioned treatment still had its uses.</p>
<p>The artist Vincent van Gogh was prescribed digitalis and painted his doctor holding the foxglove plant from which it is extracted. But the drug has been subjected to few clinical trials, perhaps because of its venerable reputation.</p>
<p>Richard Gorlin of the Mount Sinai Medical Centre in New York headed a study of 8,000 patients given a drug derived from digitalis, called digoxin, for congestive heart failure -- when the heart does not pump effectively and blood backs up in the system.</p>
<p>He said digoxin had little effect on deaths. &quot;There was no impact on mortality,&quot; he told a news conference.</p>
<p>But, he said, 25 to 30 percent fewer patients had to be hospitalised for congestive heart failure -- indicating that the drug was doing some good. Patients were, however, hospitalised for other problems at the same rate as heart patients not given digoxin.</p>
<p>William Littler, chief of cardiology at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital in Birmingham, said digoxin made patients feel better even if it did not lengthen their lives.</p>
<p>&quot;Digoxin clearly improves symptoms,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the nature of heart disease had changed in the 200 years since digitalis was first prescribed by an English doctor intrigued by the success of an old woman herbalist.</p>
<p>There were fewer cases of rheumatic heart disease arising from fevers and more cases of coronary heart disease, which is often related to a high-fat diet.</p>
<p>He said digoxin was still one of the best drugs for heart arrhythmias, or irregular heart-beat rhythms, which affect 15 percent of westerners over the age of 70.</p>
<p>Thomas Smith from Brigham and Women's Hospital at Harvard University in Massachusetts said multiple drugs were now used to treat heart disease, including angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, beta-blockers and even aspirin and diuretics. Their effects on one another were not yet clear.</p>
<p>He said those same drugs allowed doctors to prescribe digoxin in lower, less toxic doses, making it more useful.</p>
<p>Smith said doctors were still not sure how digitalis works. It was clear, he said, that it strengthened heart contractions and it might affect hormones important to heart function.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIRMINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
