<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52263" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Health experts warn of world epidemic of obesity.</title>
<headline>Health experts warn of world epidemic of obesity.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Reaney</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Health experts said on Friday an epidemic of obesity was threatening the world, posing one of its fastest developing and most serious public health problems.</p>
<p>Since 1980 the proportion of adults in Britain who are obese has doubled. In the United States, which has the highest prevalence of obesity, 100 percent of the population will be obese by 2230 if current trends continued, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a fantastic epidemic, a tidal wave of obesity is coming at us,&quot; Professor Philip James, director of the Rowett Research Institute in Aberdeen, Scotland, said at the launch of the Obesity Resource Centre (ORIC) in London.</p>
<p>Set up by the Association for the Study of Obesity, a British professional group of 300 scientists, clinicians and therapists, ORIC hopes to increase awareness of obesity and its increased risk of chronic and potentially fatal diseases.</p>
<p>Even in developing countries where malnutrition continues to be a big problem childhood obesity is already becoming apparent in some sections of the population, James said.</p>
<p>A fall in physical activity, dietary changes, environmental factors and in some cases genetics are responsible for the world's population getting fat, very fat.</p>
<p>Along with the increase in pounds (kilos) are a myriad of medical problems including strokes, heart problems, infertility, gout, certain types of cancer, osteoarthritis and diabetes.</p>
<p>&quot;Obesity must be considered as an important medical issue,&quot; Nick Finer, a physician and endocrinologist, told reporters. &quot;A catalogue of diseases are caused and exacerbated by obesity.&quot;</p>
<p>Obesity develops when the amount of energy (calories) consumed as food and drink exceeds the energy which is used for exercise and other metablic processes.</p>
<p>It is measured by estimating the correct body weight for height and is also classified according to body shape, showing where the excess fat is stored. The &quot;beer belly&quot; is one example.</p>
<p>Extremely obese people face a 400 percent greater risk of osteoarthiritis, 480 percent greater risk of death from heart disease and 5,300 percent greater risk of non-insulin treated diabetes.</p>
<p>&quot;These figures are quite terrifying,&quot; said Finer, adding there would be 70 percent fewer cases of diabetes without obesity. &quot;We need to consider treatment and prevention of obesity in its own right,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>James called for more governmental involvement in the problem of obesity, which represents nearly 10 percent of the total sick care costs in western countries.</p>
<p>An international Obesity Task Force under the auspices of the United States and the World Health Organisation are trying to increase public awareness of the problem and urging governments and health professionals to recognise the condition as a serious medical condition and a major health problem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="WORLD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
