<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52301" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Diet craze hits nine-year-olds, experts say.</title>
<headline>Diet craze hits nine-year-olds, experts say.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The idea that thin means beautiful has filtered down to primary schools, with girls as young as nine starting diets, psychologists said on Friday.</p>
<p>But supermodels were not the role models for the dieting pre-adolescents. Instead, the girls were influenced by thin classmates, mothers who diet or even dolls, said Andrew Hill, a behavioural psychologist at the University of Leeds.</p>
<p>&quot;Even by the age of nine there were girls who reported they were dieting,&quot; Hill told delegates at the British Association for the Advancement of Science's annual festival in Birmingham.</p>
<p>Hill, who has studied hundreds of young girls in his research, said this had nothing to do with actual weight.</p>
<p>&quot;As has been found in adolescents, it was their perception of body shape rather than their actual weight that was at the root of their motivation to diet,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Thin people are seen not only as more attractive but more intelligent and popular as well, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Fat is a modern, three-letter 'f' word,&quot; Hill told reporters. &quot;It's something we are all disgusted at.&quot;</p>
<p>But Hill said the young girls were not getting their ideas from the emaciated catwalk beauties.</p>
<p>&quot;She wants to be like the thinnest girl in her class,&quot; he said. Children whose mothers dieted were more aware of what dieting meant and toys also played a role. &quot;Children's toys also reflect their changing experience of the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hill said Sindy dolls, originally made in the 1960s for young teenage girls, are now targeted at six to eight year olds.</p>
<p>&quot;Sindy has lot her brunette bob, plain clothes and doll-like shape. She is now unashamedly blonde, pointedy thin (and) dressed immaculately to match,&quot; Hill said.</p>
<p>Boys also want different bodies, but only girls want to be thinner. In Hill's study of 400 nine-year-olds, boys preferred a body shape 12 percent heavier than their own average weight, while girls wished they weighed 11 percent less.</p>
<p>Such preferences can lead to eating disorders such as anorexia, when victims stave themselves, sometimes to death, in a vain attempt to control their lives.</p>
<p>Glen Waller of London's Royal Holloway College estimated anorexia affects up to one percent of young women and bulimia -- suffered by Princess Diana -- is seen in two to three percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIRMINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
