<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="57755" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. action on abortion drug likely this week.</title>
<headline>U.S. action on abortion drug likely this week.</headline>
<byline>Joanne Kenen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal health officials were expected to take a huge step in the next few days toward making the controversial RU 486 French &quot;abortion drug&quot; available to American women.</p>
<p>The drug, for use in the first few weeks of pregnancy, would give women an alternative to surgical abortion. By moving early abortion out of the clinic and into a doctor's office, activists expect it to transform the emotionally laden, politically divisive nature of the abortion debate in the United States.</p>
<p>In July a Food and Drug Administration (FDA) advisory panel recommended approving RU 486, known in the United States as mifepristone, although it expressed concern about labeling and making sure doctors were trained to administer the two-step, two-drug procedure.</p>
<p>The FDA by law has a goal, although not an outright requirement, to act on &quot;priority&quot; drug applications within six months. In this case, that meant mid-September and FDA Commissioner David Kessler has said mid-September was likely.</p>
<p>FDA officials would not comment on the approval process on Tuesday, and the drug's U.S. sponsor, the nonprofit Population Council, said it had not heard from the drug approval agency.</p>
<p>The FDA is not bound by advisory panel recommendations, although it usually follows them, sometimes with conditions or modifications.</p>
<p>Kessler has said in the past that if there was a &quot;safe and effective medical alternative to any surgical procedure,&quot; women should have the option. The drug is already in use in France, Sweden and Britain.</p>
<p>The drug could be administered in a doctor's office early in pregnancy, usually between the fifth and seventh weeks, allowing patients and doctors to avoid the pickets, protests and occasional violence that surround many abortion clinics.</p>
<p>&quot;It will increase access to abortion dramatically,&quot; Ellie Smeal, president of the Feminist Majority, said.</p>
<p>Noting that more than four out of five U.S. counties have no abortion provider, she added, &quot;We already know that many more doctors will be willing to administer mifepristone than surgical abortion.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;And I believe it will help reduce clinic violence. They (protesters) won't even know where the sites are,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The FDA could grant outright approval to the drug, in which case the FDA would make the announcement in Washington. It could also deem the drug &quot;approvable&quot; pending certain steps, in which case the Population Council would choose how and when to publicise the decision.</p>
<p>Council spokeswoman Sandra Waldman said the group had not heard from the FDA and did not have any updated information about the timetable, despite the word circulating among abortion groups -- pro and con -- that approval was imminent, perhaps in a day or two.</p>
<p>Although an announcement shortly before a presidential election might inflame emotions, the Clinton administration has strongly advocated abortion rights. Donna Shalala, secretary of health and human services, played a central role in setting up the nontraditional sponsorship of clinical trials by the Population Council in 1994.</p>
<p>Normally, the company that developed a drug would sponsor its trials, but Roussell Uclaf, a French subsidiary of the German company Hoechst AG, faced boycotts or the threat of reprisals.</p>
<p>Anti-abortion groups campaigned hard against the abortion pill, saying that by definition no drug that ends a foetus's chance of being born is &quot;safe&quot; and that the long-term effect on women's health had not been adequately studied.</p>
<p>If approved, the drug would be distributed by the non-profit Advances in Health Technology. Its U.S. manufacturer may remain anonymous.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
