<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81929" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: DAX hit by profit-taking, but new records seen.</title>
<headline>DAX hit by profit-taking, but new records seen.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>German shares ended lower on on Friday as a mild bout of profit-taking set in following recent moves up towards record-highs, but dealers said the underlying market was buoyed by the dollar's strength.</p>
<p>The DAX index of Germany's 30 leading shares closed 7.51 points or 0.28 percent lower at 2,659.04 on modest volumes, while December DAX futures traded 6.5 points down 2,677.0 points.</p>
<p>The IBIS index of all-day electronic trade later closed at 2,659.04, 7.51 points or 0.28 percent down on the day.</p>
<p>A firmer dollar, trading above 1.5200 marks, and a modest recovery in German debt prices helped underpin the market as traders debated whether the DAX would make another bid to reach the record high of 2,672.48 points reached on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;There's going to be some consolidation but at least volumes are starting to pick up again,&quot; said one dealer, adding there was little danger of the market losing recent gains.</p>
<p>Others forecast that the market would seek to establish further record-highs towards the end of next week.</p>
<p>Among specific shares, the banking sector had another largely weak day after Moody's Investors Service said its outlook on Dresdner Bank AG for its long-term and financial strength ratings were negative.</p>
<p>Shares in Dresdner, which the credit rating agency said it still saw as a &quot;very strong and financially stable banking group&quot; fell 23 pfennigs to 40.42.</p>
<p>Deutsche Bank, whose shares suffered earlier this week after Moody's said it planned to review the bank's rating, traded a further 15 pfennigs lower at 71.98.</p>
<p>BASF was a top volume stock, falling 80 pfennigs to 48.10 marks after a U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory board withheld ruling on an application for a weight-loss drug.</p>
<p>BASF has high hopes for the drug, called Meridia, which BASF management board member Dieter Stein last April predicted would have annual sales of $200 million to $400 million.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said the one-a-day anti-obesity capsules appeared effective but said they had questions about safety.</p>
<p>Other chemical stocks were also lower. Bayer AG slipped 42 pfennigs to 56.35 marks while rival Hoechst AG was down two pfennigs at 55.97 marks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
