<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85265" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Formerly obese woman sues for surgery cost.</title>
<headline>Formerly obese woman sues for surgery cost.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>A woman who lost 150 pounds (68 kilograms) through dieting and hard work sued her health insurance company on Monday for not paying for surgery to remove excess flaps of skin that remained on her thighs.</p>
<p>The 37-year-old woman was suing her insurance company for the $25,000 surgery performed in 1994 to remove the excess skin, and $300,000 in punitive damages.</p>
<p>She filed the suit against Chubbhealth and Chubb Life Insurance Co, units of Chubb Corp.. The suit was moved to federal court on Monday.</p>
<p>The upstate New York woman had weighed about 300 pounds (136 kg) for most of her adult life but took off about half of it through hard work and dieting -- but no surgery -- her lawyer, Mark Stratton, said.</p>
<p>She did not resort to surgery until she had kept the weight off for five years, when the excess skin proved inelastic and &quot;made her life hell,&quot; Stratton said. She was not able to exercise, maintain proper hygiene, go to the bathroom normally or have sex normally, he said.</p>
<p>Four surgeons said the surgery was medically necessary to alleviate pain and bacterial skin inflamation, according to the suit. The surgery &quot;changed her life,&quot; Stratton said, adding that she started exercising and eventually married.</p>
<p>But Chubb classified the surgery as cosmetic and refused to pay for it, the suit said. Before the surgery, Chubb declined to render a decision on whether the procedure would be covered, Stratton said.</p>
<p>A Chubb lawyer declined comment.</p>
<p>&quot;The insurance companies try to scare people away from seeking coverable procedures.&quot; Stratton said. &quot;The irony is her medical costs will now be a fraction of what they would've been&quot; because she is no longer much overweight, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
