<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="12858" id="root" date="1996-08-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Thirty said killed in flood-hit Pakistan province.</title>
<headline>Thirty said killed in flood-hit Pakistan province.</headline>
<byline>Aurang Zeb</byline>
<dateline>LAHORE, Pakistan 1996-08-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Floods killed at least 30 people and injured 100 in the Pakistani city of Lahore and other parts of Punjab province, newspapers reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>Officials in Lahore said seven people had been killed and four injured there on Friday and many houses had collapsed. They had no details of the other reported casualties.</p>
<p>They said 461 mm (18 inches) of rain had drenched the Punjab provincial capital in 36 hours, turning streets to rivers, knocking out power, water and telephone services, disrupting air and rail traffic and sweeping away houses and cars.</p>
<p>Pakistan usually receives an average of 140 mm (5-1/2 inches) during the whole July-September monsoon season.</p>
<p>&quot;There's still four feet (1.3 metres) of water on the roads, so there's no transport,&quot; said newspaper worker Muhammad Bilal on Saturday. &quot;There's no electricity or water at my house.&quot;</p>
<p>He said skies had cleared and water was receding, but ground floors and basements of many buildings were still flooded.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been trapped upstairs since 10 a.m. yesterday when water rushed into the ground floor,&quot; said resident Mahmoud Sandhu. &quot;We didn't even have time to rescue our things.&quot;</p>
<p>They said thousands of people had been made homeless after a breach opened in the city canal, inundating residential areas. Many were given temporary accommodation in school buildings.</p>
<p>Local authorities declared a state of emergency on Friday, calling on troops to help evacuate residents of low-lying areas.</p>
<p>An official at the Flood Warning Centre in Lahore said the Ravi and Chenab rivers, which both flow through Punjab, were exceptionally high. Rising water could pose a threat to the Jhang, Muzaffargarh and Rajanpur areas, he said.</p>
<p>The Urdu-language Nawa-i-Waqt newspaper said a girl drowned when water flooded a ward in Lahore General Hospital, where 10 other patients died for lack of treatment.</p>
<p>It said floods had also hit the cities of Sialkot, where a student died in a house collapse, and Wazirabad and Gujrat, north of Lahore. Eight people died in flood-related accidents in the town of Sheikhupura, 50 km (30 miles) west of Lahore.</p>
<p>Three people, including two children, died when a house collapsed in Kahna, a village near Lahore. A man was electrocuted in the same village when a power line fell on him.</p>
<p>A mother and daughter were killed in Gujranwala, 70 km (45 miles) north of Lahore, it said. A child drowned in a water channel in Korang, near the Pakistani capital, Islamabad.</p>
<p>Several newspapers said two members of the religious Jamaat-i-Islami party had drowned while trying to remove books from a basement library at the party headquarters in Lahore. One newspaper said five members of the party had died.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAHORE, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
