<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78125" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FEATURE - All aboard for the wild, wild east.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - All aboard for the wild, wild east.</headline>
<byline>Rodney Pinder</byline>
<dateline>ABOARD THE TRANS-SIBERIAN EXPRESS 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>As the mighty Trans-Siberian express lurches out of Moscow for Beijing, a smiling attendant dishes out the spittoons.</p>
<p>A hairy blanket, creased sheet and lumpy pillow complete the Chinese Railways travel kit for passengers who will spend the next six days and 7,865 km (4,915 miles) on the fabled train.</p>
<p>The dimpled tin basin is a rude reminder that the trek to China across Siberia and Mongolia is not for the faint-hearted. In the day of neatly-packaged and sanitised luxury travel, it remains among the world's last great adventures.</p>
<p>From the hubbub of Moscow's Yaroslavskii Station through the empty stillness of the Mongolian plains, the journey on train T4 is long, hard, crude -- and endlessly interesting.</p>
<p>Running on tracks begun in the last decade of last century, the train follows lines etched across Siberia in blood and tears by millions of political exiles from the Tsars to the Soviet communists. Slave labour laid many of the rails.</p>
<p>It shakes, rattles and rolls across five time zones, through vast forests and treeless grasslands, past brightly-painted log cabins and dull grey concrete cities, over mountains and rivers from the Russian steppes to the Great Wall of China.</p>
<p>Several trains follow the routes along the length of the world's biggest country. The green, snaking T4 is one of the busiest -- a moving marketplace of Chinese traders, Russian travellers and foreign tourists.</p>
<p>The T4 leaves Yaroslavskii station in scenes of mild chaos at 7.50 p.m. very Tuesday. Female station attendants harass luggage-laden passengers with cries of &quot;minutes, minutes&quot; half an hour before departure.</p>
<p>Second, or Hard Class, sleeper accommodation is literal -- a bunk like a board, a pillow which could double as a sandbag and a bathroom used by dozens of others and never cleaned.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the no-smoking signs throughout the train are entirely theoretical. Led by the chain-smoking staff and a large woman who grimly presided over the restaurant car, passengers filled most of the train with an acrid fug.</p>
<p>As an appetite repressant, smoking probably was encouraged by the awfulness of the restaurant. Most items on the eight-page menu were unavailable -- even the beef stroganoff was more off than on. The rest was reminiscent of the chow which movies show being slopped up on wagon trains in America's Wild West.</p>
<p>Prewarned travellers in the wagons of Russia's Wild East train tucked into rations carried from home. Tinned caviar, amazingly cheap in Moscow, makes a tasty mid-Siberian snack.</p>
<p>Many passengers simply filled up, for breakfast, lunch and dinner, with the cheap vodka that was in ample supply.</p>
<p>Life aboard quickly settles into an easy routine of sleeping and window-gazing. Each morning the carriages awake to a dawn chorus of expectoration as travellers clear their head passages into the spittoons.</p>
<p>The train whistles through Perm, once closed to foreigners; Yekaterinburg, where the last Tsar and his family were murdered; Omsk, where Dostoyevsky did four years hard labour from 1849; Krasnoyarsk, Irkutsk, Novosibirsk. Under royalty and communism much of the area was forbidden.</p>
<p>At 2,078 km (1,300 miles), it passes a four metre (12-ft) high pillar marking the beginning of Siberia -- the place where multitudes of exiles said their last farewells.</p>
<p>Many of these once-fearful places have become profit centres for Chinese traders who hang out of the train windows at stations day and night, swapping piles of clothing for fistfuls of roubles. As we turn towards Mongolia, the traders disembark with their remaining wares and head back again.</p>
<p>There are as yet few visible signs of capitalist development in Siberia. Peasant families, bent double in the fields, still gather potatoes by hand as the birch trees blaze gold in a watery autumn sun. Many timbered villages, without roads of any kind, can have changed little in centuries.</p>
<p>The train pulls slowly through smoggy smokestack cities past crumbling factories, festering buildings and rusty rolling stock which give an overwhelming sense of widespread dilapidation.</p>
<p>The scene is strikingly different along the line in booming China, where modernistic smoked-glass offices are rising in several bustling cities.</p>
<p>In Mongolia, the virginal Gobi desert has been marked for intensive strip mining.</p>
<p>For now, the empty vastness sees only the occasional yurt, or tent, of a nomadic family, herds of wild horses and a few camels. From airliners leaving vapour trails high above, our train must look like a caterpillar on a great big cabbage leaf.</p>
<p>After crossing the Great Wall, the train ends its journey of 139 hours 45 minutes precisely on time at 3.35 p.m. on Monday.</p>
<p>As it nears Beijing, attendants vacuum the carpets for the first time and many weary travellers, as in hotels around the world, cast around their rooms for an appropriate souvenir of an unforgettable trip.</p>
<p>But there are no bathroom sachets, no slippers or robes to be had. And the attendants have secured the spittoons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ABOARD THE TRANS-SIBERIAN EXPRESS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
