<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46228" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>Japan: Japan PM, coalition heads to mull election date.</title>
<headline>Japan PM, coalition heads to mull election date.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leaders of the three parties in Japan's ruling coalition agreed to meet on Thursday to discuss the timing of long-anticipated general elections.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto, president of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), will meet the heads of the Social Democratic Party and New Party Sakigake president Shoichi Ide to hammer out an election schedule.</p>
<p>Social Democratic Party head Tomiichi Murayama and Sakigake chief Shoichi Ide had earlier expressed anger at a flurry of newspaper reports attributed to LDP sources that said a general election was likely to be held on October 20.</p>
<p>Many in the LDP want to hold elections as soon as possible, but the two smaller parties, embroiled in a dispute over how to contest the polls, needed more time, a senior Social Democratic Party official told reporters.</p>
<p>Hashimoto on Wednesday reiterated earlier statements that he would set an election date after confirming that Japan's economy was in full recovery and settling a dispute with the southern island of Okinawa over U.S. military bases.</p>
<p>&quot;I will make a decision on a specific date after confirming that the Okinawa issue will be solved and that a full economic recovery is under way,&quot; Hashimoto said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to first see Japan's gross domestic product (GDP) to make sure the economy is heading for full recovery,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Polls for the 500-seat lower house of parliament are not mandated until July 1997.</p>
<p>The April-June GDP data is to be released on Friday, government officials announced on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Okinawa hurdle appeared partially cleared after a meeting on Tuesday between Hashimoto and Masahide Ota, the governor of the southern Japanese prefecture, who channeled outrage at the rape of a local schoolgirl by U.S. servicemen last year into a fiery campaign for removal of the U.S. bases.</p>
<p>Hashimoto pledged renewed efforts to shrink the bases and set up a five billion yen ($45.8 million) fund for the economic development of Okinawa if Ota would ease calls for a total pullout of U.S. forces, which are seen by Tokyo as a bulwark of regional security.</p>
<p>Analysts have said the main focus of what appears to be a mostly issue-free election will be the effect of drastic electoral reforms introduced in 1994 to balance a system in which thinly-populated rural districts enjoyed vastly more clout than urban areas.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
