<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46485" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ostrich firm to pay $15.2 million in fraud case.</title>
<headline>Ostrich firm to pay $15.2 million in fraud case.</headline>
<byline>Gene Ramos</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>A California-based company that promoted what it billed as a billion-dollar, ostrich-raising business was ordered to pay $15.2 million to settle fraud charges, the Securities and Exchange Commission said Wednesday.</p>
<p>The order against Trans-American Ostrich Traders Inc., was issued as a default judgment by federal Judge Robert Takasugi in Los Angeles, the SEC said.</p>
<p>Takasugi also barred Larry Earp, a founder of the Thousand Palms, Calif.-based company and its president and chief executive, from acting as an officer or director of any public company.</p>
<p>Separately, the SEC issued an administrative order barring Earp from the securities industry for life. Earp consented to the court and SEC orders without admitting or denying guilt, the SEC said.</p>
<p>The case against a third defendant, David Silver, national marketing director of the company, is pending, the SEC said.</p>
<p>Of the penalties against the company, $7.17 million represents forfeitures of illegal profits, a civil penalty of the same amount, and $863,342 in prejudgment interest.</p>
<p>SEC lawyer James Coffman said Trans-American Ostrich was inactive, and the SEC will have to find out if the firm has assets that could be used to satisfy the court judgment.</p>
<p>Takasugi's order stemmed from a civil complaint by the SEC filed in March against the company and two of its executives.</p>
<p>The SEC said the defendants collected $7.45 million from about 350 investors in 40 states to operate an ostrich ranch to raise and later slaughter and sell its meat for food.</p>
<p>The defendants allegedly used high-pressure, boiler-room telemarketing tactics and a TV commercial to sell between November 1993 and December 1994 unregistered securities in 17 partnerships at a price of from $7,500 to $20,000 a unit.</p>
<p>Trans-American Ostrich was a general partner of the partnerships, the SEC said.</p>
<p>The SEC alleged the investors were made to believe that the price of ostriches would double when the defendants knew that as of July 1994, its market price had slumped.</p>
<p>The defendants also allegedly promised investors fantastic profits ranging from 45 percent in the first two years, 1,147 percent in five years, 5,003 percent in eight years and up to 9,355 percent in 10 years.</p>
<p>But about half of the investors' money went to sales commissions and marketing expenses, the SEC alleged, contrary to the defendants' claim they would use 80 percent of those funds to buy ostriches and for operating capital.</p>
<p>After the market for ostrich collapsed, the partnerships filed for bankruptcy, the SEC said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100121">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
