<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47049" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK consumers demand direct links with companies.</title>
<headline>UK consumers demand direct links with companies.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Growing numbers of British consumers would rather speak directly to the companies with whom they do business than deal with intermediaries, Britain's main direct marketing body said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>New ways of banking or buying car insurance over the phone underscore the trend for firms to provide direct links with their own and rivals' customers via 'hotline' phone numbers, Colin Lloyd, chief executive of the Direct Marketing Association (DMA) said.</p>
<p>Direct marketing, a growth sector within the 10 billion pound advertising industry, encompasses investments in direct mail, telemarketing, door-to-door promotions and magazine inserts.</p>
<p>&quot;The enablers for these changes are a combination of advances in technology, telephony, database and profiling combined with a high degree of consumer acceptance of tele-ordering,&quot; Lloyd said in the industry body's annual report.</p>
<p>Major retailers like Tesco, Safeway and more recently Sainsbury, who act as intermediaries between wholesalers and consumers, had reacted to these changes, he said.</p>
<p>The big supermarkets have started this year to create their own 'media' to allow them to speak directly with customers.</p>
<p>Customer information, including precise profiles of individuals and their shopping tastes -- obtained from direct contact with them -- could give a retailer a crucial edge over its rivals in &quot;tomorrow's retail battleground&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Consumers, many with access to home-shopping facilities via cable and satellite television or via the Internet's World Wide Web, are also becoming more demanding.</p>
<p>&quot;We now have a more literate, demanding and transient consumer. They know what they want, they demand choices of access to products that are compatible with their needs and lifestyles...&quot; Lloyd said.</p>
<p>Direct marketing in Britain turned over 5.5 billion pounds in 1995, up from 4.5 billion pounds a year earlier.</p>
<p>The DMA forecasts that by 2000 some 40 percent of British companies' marketing budgets will go on direct marketing.</p>
<p>-- London Advertising Newsroom +44 171 542 2792</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
