<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49650" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FCC eases way for utilities to offer phone service.</title>
<headline>FCC eases way for utilities to offer phone service.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Federal Communications Commission Thursday simplified its procedures for allowing utilities to offer phone and other telecommunications services.</p>
<p>The rules implement the landmark telecommunications law enacted earlier this year. That law permits registered public utility holding companies to enter the telecommunications business -- without prior approval from the Securities and Exchange Commission -- by acquiring or maintaining an interest in a so-called &quot;exempt telecommunications company,&quot; or ETC.</p>
<p>The FCC has the power to determine whether a company warrants ETC status.</p>
<p>The agency's new rules require applicants seeking that status to file with the agency a brief description of their planned activities together with a sworn statement attesting to any facts or representations presented to demonstrate ETC status as defined in the 1996 law.</p>
<p>Since the new law was enacted in February, the FCC has received 15 applications seeking ETC status and has approved 13 of those bids.  Two are still pending.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
