<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52020" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INTERVIEW - Cincinnati Bell CEO.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - Cincinnati Bell CEO.</headline>
<byline>Susan Zimmerman</byline>
<dateline>CLEVELAND 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Despite uncertainties facing its local telephone service, Cincinnati Bell Inc said strong growth in its billing services and telemarketing units will help it reach its targeted 15 percent annual earnings growth.</p>
<p>But significant challenges face the local telephone business, including a previously reported renegotiation of a major contract with AT&amp;T Corp, still under discussion.</p>
<p>&quot;It could have a significant impact on 1997's results if (that contract) went away or scaled back dramatically,&quot; John LaMacchia, president, said in an interview late Thursday.  </p>
<p>He said regulatory and competitive issues also exist but the company continues to target 15 percent earnings growth.</p>
<p>The local telephone unit, Cincinnati Bell Telephone Co, bundles AT&amp;T long-distance in local phone bills.  AT&amp;T accounts for five to seven percent of revenues at that unit, which in turn represents under half of overall revenues and operating profits.</p>
<p>In 1995, the parent company earned $114.2 million or $1.72 a share excluding special charges on revenues of $1.34 billion.  </p>
<p>LaMacchia said the MATRIXX telemarketing unit and CBIS billing and customer service unit are both growing revenue at 20 percent a year with operating profits rising &quot;even faster.&quot;</p>
<p>With new contracts announced earlier, CBIS is in a strong position to maintain those rates, he said.  MATRIXX &quot;had a good first half (and) we expect an even stronger second half.&quot;</p>
<p>To bolster its local telephone unit, he said Cincinnati Bell plans significant, but as yet unspecified, investments.</p>
<p>Like other phone companies, Cincinnati Bell Telephone will offer a range of products and services, he said.  </p>
<p>It is exploring long-distance options including competing against AT&amp;T.  Separately, the company has said it will appeal a Delaware court ruling that kept intact a 12-year partnership for cellular communications with Ameritech Corp. Cincinnati Bell seeks to dissolve that partnership and is studying alternatives for cellular services as well, he said.</p>
<p>In addition, the local phone unit introduced Internet and digital satellite television access services, LaMacchia said.</p>
<p>The parent is not at present considering splitting or spinning off any units because CBIS and MATRIXX derive much expertise from the local phone unit, he said.  </p>
<p>He said the company is on the lookout for small, strategic acquisitions.</p>
<p>Competitive and regulatory uncertainties and the contract renegotiation with AT&amp;T, have contributed to stock volatility, he said, adding the price has ranged from 26 to more than 57 in the last year. It was up 7/8 to 50-1/8.</p>
<p>AT&amp;T is also a significant customer of CBIS and MATRIXX but the current negotiations are unrelated to those units.</p>
<p>--Cleveland Newsdesk 216-579-0077</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CLEVELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
