<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54771" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: John Major's wife urges tougher privacy laws.</title>
<headline>John Major's wife urges tougher privacy laws.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister John Major's wife Norma called on Sunday for tougher privacy laws in Britain.</p>
<p>Adopting a much higher profile in the leadup to next year's general election, she said: &quot;I don't think the public has a right to know everything and be everywhere.&quot;</p>
<p>Several newspapers carried pictures taken with telephoto lenses of the Major family enjoying its summer holiday on a luxury yacht in the south of France,</p>
<p>&quot;Well, taken from about quarter of a mile away and you don't know they're there, it's...it's not comfortable,&quot; Norma Major said in an interview with Sir David Frost on BBC Television.</p>
<p>&quot;Your house and your garden, that should be sacrosanct...or if you're doing something which is obviously private and I think holiday obviously is private,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>She said everyone from politicians to pop stars was entitled to privacy.</p>
<p>She has accompanied her husband on the campaign trail around Britain in the past two weeks. The Conservative prime minister, trailing opposition Labour Party leader Tony Blair in opinion polls, has to call an election by next May.</p>
<p>Norma Major played down claims that she has been given a new role as her husband's &quot;secret weapon&quot; as campaigning intensifies.</p>
<p>She flatly rejected the notion that she may be tempted to copy Elizabeth Dole, wife of U.S. Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole, who took to the stage at the recent San Diego party convention.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't think of anything that would make me want to do that...however much I might love him,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
