<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58009" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: Slovak NAFTA shares a sell - ING report.</title>
<headline>Slovak NAFTA shares a sell - ING report.</headline>
<dateline>BRATISLAVA 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares of Slovakia's largest oil and gas storage company Nafta a.s. are rated a sell after revising downward the 1996 earnings estimate for the firm, ING Barings said on Tuesday in an investor report.</p>
<p>&quot;We have downgraded our 1996 earnings forecast and are recommending investors to sell their holdings (in Nafta) at the current price,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>The recommemdation came when Nafta's price was 1,980 crowns. Nafta shares closed at 2,030 crowns on Monday, down 30 crowns from Friday's close.</p>
<p>ING representatives were not immediately available for comment on whether the recommendation remained the same given the issue's current price.</p>
<p>Nafta reported disappointing results in the first half of 1996, as rising costs clashed with an inflexible revenue structure, the report said.</p>
<p>Nafta posted a pre-tax profit of 409.104 million crowns for the January-June period.</p>
<p>&quot;The key problem was sharply rising maintanence and repair costs in Nafta drilling and gas storage operations, which the company was unable to pass on to customers who enjoy long-term negotiated gas storage rates,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>The report said this was the basis a cut in its 1996 full year profit forecast by 200 million crowns to around 510 million.</p>
<p>Another reason for the negative recommendation was the recent sale of the state's 45.9 percent in Nafta to a company unknown in the investment community.</p>
<p>In August the state privatisation agency, the National Property Fund, sold its entire holdings in Nafta to Druha Obchodna a.s., for a price far below the market value.</p>
<p>The new owner had to pay 500 million crowns, while on the Bratislava Stock Exchange the stake was worth around 3.2 billion crowns.</p>
<p>&quot;Until more is known and understood about the buyer of the stake, we believe that the stock will be kept off most foreign investors' buy lists,&quot; ING said.</p>
<p>-- Peter Laca, Bratislava Newsroom, 42-7-210-3687</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRATISLAVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
