<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60154" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: July trade gap highest in eight years.</title>
<headline>July trade gap highest in eight years.</headline>
<byline>Glenn Somerville</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. trade deficit soared in July to its highest level in more than eight years as imports surged and foreign sales shrank for a second straight month, the Commerce Department said Wednesday.</p>
<p>The surprisingly steep 42.6 percent jump in the July deficit to $11.68 billion from $8.19 billion in June was caused partly by weaker sales of American-made commercial aircraft, as well as brisk demand for Japanese cars and costlier oil.</p>
<p>&quot;The primary culprit is our strong appetite for imports and that's a reflection of the strong U.S. economy,&quot; said economist Sung Won Sohn of Norwest Corp. in Minneapolis.</p>
<p>He added that weaker net exports might trim third-quarter economic growth moderately but said gross domestic product still was likely to grow at around a 3 percent annual rate.</p>
<p>&quot;That would still exceed (Federal Reserve) Chairman (Alan) Greenspan's safe economic speed limit,&quot; Sohn said.</p>
<p>During July, the value of imports climbed 1.2 percent to $78.87 billion while exports to foreign markets dropped 3.6 percent to $67.19 billion.</p>
<p>Commerce Department officials said the overall July trade deficit was the highest since late 1987, when shortfalls during the fourth quarter averaged $12.9 billion.</p>
<p>White House spokesman Mike McCurry, commenting to reporters aboard President Clinton's airplane enroute to a campaign appearance in Arizona, said the U.S. export performance has outpaced most of its major industrial trade partners.</p>
<p>&quot;But obviously the strength of the U.S. economy, the rising incomes of American workers, have made it more possible for them to buy goods from abroad so imports have gone up,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The trade report was one of the final pieces of broad-based economic evidence before next Tuesday's meeting of the policy-setting Federal Open Market Committee to review interest-rate strategy.</p>
<p>Though not as significant as last week's reports showing restrained wholesale and consumer price rises in August, as well as a slim 0.2 percent rise in August retail sales, the trade figures raised questions about the economy's vigour and the need for interest-rate hikes to control inflation.</p>
<p>&quot;The third quarter is beginning to look weak with a growth rate that could be below 2 percent,&quot; said Joel Naroff, a Philadelphia-based economist with First Union Corp. The Fed considers a 2-to-2-1/2 percent growth rate a safe pace for the economy to grow without generating big wage and price rises.</p>
<p>The trade report depressed the dollar in foreign exchange trading, dropping it to 109.20 Japanese yen from 110.28 yen late Tuesday, and to 1.5090 German marks from 1.5142 marks.</p>
<p>A bigger-than-expected trade deficit lowers the dollar's value because when the economy imports more than it exports, a surplus of dollars flows abroad to pay for those imports.</p>
<p>During July, the politically sensitive trade gap with Japan widened sharply, by 32.9 percent to $4.31 billion as it once again became the country with which the United States has the largest monthly deficit.</p>
<p>New-car imports from Japan were nearly $300 million higher in July than in June, Commerce Department officials said, while exports to Japan fell.</p>
<p>The deficit with China, which temporarily overtook Japan in June as the largest single contributor to the U.S. trade deficit, grew again in July, by 14.7 percent to $3.82 billion. Imports from China were a record $4.8 billion in July.</p>
<p>Lawrence Chimerine, chief economist for the Economic Strategy Institute in Washington, said the China deficit was a warning that the United States must get tougher with countries that run persistently rising trade shortfalls.</p>
<p>&quot;One-way free trade is not in our national interest, but that unfortunately is what we seem to have,&quot; Chimerine said.</p>
<p>At a news conference, Commerce Secretary Mickey Kantor cited &quot;deep concern about the deficit with China because it is the result of sanctuary markets.&quot; He insisted the long-term trend for the U.S. deficit was favourable, but said the economies of key trading partners like Japan and Canada were growing more slowly than expected.</p>
<p>The United States typically runs a surplus on its trade with other countries in services like travel and tourism that partly offsets big merchandise trade deficits.</p>
<p>In July, the merchandise deficit widened sharply to $17.52 billion from $14.62 billion in June. The surplus on services contracted to $5.84 billion from $6.43 billion in June.</p>
<p>There were a few areas of bilateral trade improvement in July. The deficit with Mexico was down 7 percent to $1.38 billion, while the shortfall with Canada dropped in July by 19.3 percent to $2.1 billion.</p>
<p>At the same time, the monthly gap with Western Europe more than quadrupled to $4.25 billion from $761 million in June. Exports to Europe fell $2 billion in July, partly because of a $566 million plunge in aircraft exports and a $200 million drop in computer sales.</p>
<p>Overall foreign sales of civilian aircraft plummeted $686 million in July to $856 million, while foreign sales of U.S.-made cars and parts fell $345 million to $5.18 billion.</p>
<p>The cost of imported crude oil rose 10 percent to $4.7 billion in July -- the highest for any month since October 1990, when $4.8 billion of petroleum was imported.</p>
<p>The price per barrel of imported crude oil was up to $18.24 from $18.02 in June. growing more slowly than expected.</p>
<p>The United States typically runs a surplus on its trade with other countries in services like travel and tourism that partly offsets big merchandise trade deficits.</p>
<p>In July, the merchandise deficit widened sharply to $17.52 billion from $14.62 billion in June. The surplus on services contracted to $5.84 billion from $6.43 billion in June.</p>
<p>There were a few areas of bilateral trade improvement in July. The deficit with Mexico was down 7 percent to $1.38 billion, while the shortfall with Canada dropped in July by 19.3 percent to $2.1 billion.</p>
<p>At the same time, the monthly gap with Western Europe more than quadrupled to $4.25 billion from $761 million in June. Exports to Europe fell $2 billion in July, partly because of a $566 million plunge in aircraft exports and a $200 million drop in computer sales.</p>
<p>Overall foreign sales of civilian aircraft plummeted $686 million in July to $856 million, while foreign sales of U.S.-made cars and parts fell $345 million to $5.18 billion.</p>
<p>The cost of imported crude oil rose 10 percent to $4.7 billion in July -- the highest for any month since October 1990, when $4.8 billion of petroleum was imported.</p>
<p>The price per barrel of imported crude oil was up to $18.24 from $18.02 in June.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
