<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61165" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico's  IUSA says to buy  Reading Tube Corp.</title>
<headline>Mexico's  IUSA says to buy  Reading Tube Corp.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's  Industrias Unidas SA (IUSA), the holding company of cellphone firm Grupo Iusacell, said on Wednesday that its U.S. unit  Cambridge-Lee Industries Inc signed a final agreement to buy the assets of U.S. copper tubing firm  Reading Tube Corp.</p>
<p>&quot;This operation, subject to normal closing conditions, should be consolidated around the 25th of this month,&quot; IUSA said in a statement.  </p>
<p>IUSA did not say how much the deal was worth, but said the transaction &quot;can be considered one of the most significant acquisitions by a Mexican company of a U.S. company since the approval of the North American Free Trade Agreement.&quot;</p>
<p>NAFTA came into force on January 1, 1994.</p>
<p>Reading Tube is based in Reading, Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>IUSA is one of Mexico's biggest makers of copper tubing products.</p>
<p>&quot;This transaction gives our operations in Mexico and the United States a great strategic position which will give us the ability to put together in North America a copper business with sales, as a group, of more than $500 million,&quot; IUSA Vice President Carlos Peralta said, according to the statement.</p>
<p>The acqusition &quot;will create one of the biggest groups in the world in production and distribution of copper tubing and related products,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Martin Langfield, Mexico City newsroom 525 7289558</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
