<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36421" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Pope, his health in spotlight, visits Hungary.</title>
<headline>Pope, his health in spotlight, visits Hungary.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>With his health yet again in the spotlight, Pope John Paul resumes foreign travel on Friday with a two-day visit to Hungary intended to highlight his drive for Christian unity in the approach to the year 2000.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pontiff, who hopes to lead the Roman Catholic Church into the third millennium, travels to the former communist country to mark the 1,000th anniversary on Friday of a Benedictine monastery at Pannonhalma in western Hungary.</p>
<p>He will also celebrate mass in the nearby city of Gyor, on the River Danube, and meet Hungarian bishops before returning to Rome on Saturday evening.</p>
<p>The trip, the Pope's 73rd abroad, follows a fresh scare about his health in mid-August when he entered hospital briefly for a battery of sophisticated medical tests.</p>
<p>The Vatican said the tests, part of a regular series since surgery for a colon tumour in 1992, showed nothing noteworthy.</p>
<p>They were brought forward after the Pope complained of an abdominal problem. The ailment followed two other bouts of stomach illness since Christmas, none of which Vatican officials have fully explained.</p>
<p>Pannonhalma, a Catholic outpost on the edge of a huge Orthodox Christian community to the east, was founded before the Great Schism of 1054 split Christendom.</p>
<p>Hopes at the Vatican that the monastery would be the venue for an historic meeting between the Polish-born Pope and Patriarch Alexiy II of the Russian Orthodox Church were dashed in July when the latter made it known he would not attend.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a disappointment not only to the Pope but also to Hungarian Catholics. But it would be a mistake to think that this is a tragic disappointment,&quot; Csaba Ternyak, secretary of the Hungarian Bishops' Conference, told Reuters in Budapest.</p>
<p>&quot;...The links between the two heads of the Churches have not been broken off and we truly hope that the meeting of those two will be realised in due time at a suitable location,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope has made the quest for greater unity among Christians of different dominations the ambition of his pontificate in the build-up to the start of the new millennium.</p>
<p>He will pray for unity at Pannonhalma and said last month that Catholics and Orthodox Christians, whose relations have been strained since the collapse of communism and by the wars in former Yugoslavia, should look more at what linked them.</p>
<p>&quot;Differences may persist on one issue or another but we must not forget that what unites us is much more than what divides us,&quot; the Pope said on August 11.</p>
<p>This weekend's visit, the Pope's second to Hungary, will be followed in late September by a more gruelling and far more controversial four-day visit to France.</p>
<p>The September 19-22 visit has stirred opposition both from secularists and from liberal Roman Catholics opposed to the Pope's conservative teachings on birth control and AIDS.</p>
<p>Police this week defused a crude bomb in a church the Pope is due to visit in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre, western France. The unidentified attackers had scrawled &quot;Pope-Pope-BOOM&quot; on a wall.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
