<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36985" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Pope, in Hungary, leads prayers for unity.</title>
<headline>Pope, in Hungary, leads prayers for unity.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>GYOR, Hungary 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul used a visit to Hungary to press his quest for Christian unity but an historic ecumenical meeting failed to take place, highlighting obstacles to overcoming divisions within the Christian faith.</p>
<p>The Polish-born Pope, who hopes to lead Roman Catholics into the year 2000, presided over prayers for unity on Friday night in the small basilica of a 1,000-year-old monastery at Pannonhalma in western Hungary.</p>
<p>The Benedictine archabbey, celebrating its millennium with the 76-year-old Pontiff, was founded before the Great Schism of 1054 split Christendom over a host of theological disputes.</p>
<p>&quot;The beginnings of your history bring us back to the time when the Christian East and West were still undivided,&quot; a tired-looking Pope said in a homily in Hungarian to about 300 worshippers.</p>
<p>&quot;In your daily ministry, work for Christian unity, engaging in dialogue with everyone,&quot; he said in an address delivered by a monk in his stead with the exception of brief passages in which the Pope struggled with the difficulties of the language.</p>
<p>The Vatican had hoped that Patriarch Alexiy II of the Russian Orthodox Church would join the Pontiff in Pannonhalma for the first such meeting of its kind.</p>
<p>But Alexiy made it known in July that he would not travel to Pannonhalma, a decision Catholic sources said they believed reflected resistance among Russian Orthodox bishops.</p>
<p>Relations between Rome and the Russian Orthodox Church have been strained since the collapse of Soviet communism by disputes over property and the alleged poaching of followers.</p>
<p>Such tensions have been aggravated by the conflicts that devastated former Yugoslavia. The fighting in both Croatia and Bosnia was fired by strong undercurrents of religious as well as ethnic rivalry.</p>
<p>Hungary's President Arpad Goncz referred to the problems in a speech welcoming the Pope at Budapest airport for a two-day visit rendered low key by Patriarch Alexiy's absence.</p>
<p>&quot;I say together with Your Holiness that on the threshold of the year 2000, Christians should continue to make every effort to promote mutual understanding and fight the manifestations of short-sighted and excessive nationalism,&quot; Goncz said.</p>
<p>&quot;Both the churches and the individual nations, and particularly the neighbouring peoples, badly need mutual reconciliation and brotherly cooperation.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope, who will hold an open-air mass in the western city of Gyor on Saturday, has made the search for unity an overriding theme of his papacy in the approach to Christianity's third millennium.</p>
<p>He announced at the Friday vesper service that he planned to visit Prague early next year to mark the 1,000th anniversary of the death of a pre-Schism saint, Adalbert.</p>
<p>Illness and advancing years have slowed the Pope's pace in recent years, but a Vatican spokesman said he would also travel to Poland, France and Brazil in 1997.</p>
<p>The Pope gave an insight into his approach to old age and infirmity at a meeting with sick and elderly residents of a hospice at the Pannonhalma monastery, telling them illness made a man realise his limits but also brought him close to God.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GYOR, Hungary"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
