<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36992" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Pope gives insight into views on infirmity.</title>
<headline>Pope gives insight into views on infirmity.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>PANNONHALMA, Hungary 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul gave an insight into his approach to old age and infirmity on Friday, saying sickness confronted men with their own limits but also put them in touch with God.</p>
<p>&quot;Illness is a paradoxical state,&quot; the 76-year-old Pope, troubled by recurrent health problems in recent years, told a group of elderly and infirm monks and nuns during a visit to a hospice at Pannonhalma Abbey in western Hungary.</p>
<p>&quot;On the one hand it is an impediment to the person, leading to first-hand experience of one's own limits and fragility.</p>
<p>&quot;On the other hand it puts us in direct contact with the Cross of Christ, and opens new doors to us. By the offering up of their sufferings to Christ, those who are sick can make a personal contribution to his redemptive work...,&quot; the Pope said.</p>
<p>He called the elderly &quot;precious for the family and society&quot; as &quot;guardians of a rich patrimony of values and experiences&quot; which they could share with younger generations.</p>
<p>The remarks were addressed specifically to the 70 or so residents of the hospice at the hilltop Benedictine abbey, which the Pope was visiting to celebrate its 1,000th anniversary on the first day of a two-day visit, his second to Hungary.</p>
<p>But they were also likely to be seen as a reflection of his own experience, marked in the past four years by the removal of a colon tumour, decreased mobility following hip replacement surgery and unspecified abdominal ailments since last Christmas.</p>
<p>Fresh concern among Roman Catholics for the Polish-born Pope's condition and renewed media speculation about his health was fired last month when he entered hospital briefly for a battery of sophisticated tests.</p>
<p>The Vatican, which has in the past denied media reports of serious illness, said the tests were part of a series since the colon tumour was removed in 1992 and showed nothing noteworthy.</p>
<p>It confirmed then that the visit to Hungary and a four-day trip to France in late September would go ahead.</p>
<p>The Pope appeared in reasonable health on his latest trip, the 73rd abroad by history's most travelled pontiff, and walked slowly but steadily without the aid of the cane he sometimes used following the surgery after he broke his leg in 1994.</p>
<p>The pace of his visits since then, however, has slowed markedly from that of the whirlwind international tours he would previously conduct.</p>
<p>For long an avid mountaineer and skier, the Pope bounced back from near death when he was shot in an assassination attempt in 1981, returning to foreign travel with trips that took in 11 countries the following year.</p>
<p>Despite his evident fraility, aides say the Pope is determined to continue travelling in the run-up to the year 2000, when he hopes to lead the Roman Catholic Church into Christianity's third millennium.</p>
<p>No additional trips have been scheduled for 1996 after the September 19-22 visit to France.</p>
<p>Chief Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro-Valls said four visits were planned for next year -- to Prague in April, Poland in June, Paris in August and Brazil next October.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls also indicated that the Pope also still hoped to visit Sarajevo and Beirut, where trips were cancelled in 1994 for security reasons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PANNONHALMA, Hungary"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
