<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38244" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SmithKline offers hope on Parkinson's.</title>
<headline>SmithKline offers hope on Parkinson's.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sufferers of Parkinson's Disease were offered fresh hope on Friday when SmithKline Beecham Plc launched a new drug to combat the incurable condition.</p>
<p>Studies show Ropinirole, marketed under the brand name Requip, is effective in the early stages of Parkinson's disease, which affects around 100,000 people in Britain.</p>
<p>The disease took centre-stage at the Olympic Games in Atlanta in July when former boxing champion Mohammed Ali, who suffers from Parkinson's, lit the Olympic flame.</p>
<p>SmithKline said on Friday it hopes Requip will be of particular benefit to younger sufferers of the disease.  </p>
<p>It said the drug, which is being launched in Britain first, may allow doctors to delay use of the current &quot;gold standard&quot; drug Levodopa, marketed by Merck &amp; Co under the name Sinemet CR.</p>
<p>Levodopa, which was a major advance in treating Parkinson's, has the disadvantage of inducing severe involuntary twisting and writhing movements as a side effect in long-term use.</p>
<p>Parkinson's is a progressive illness which attacks the nervous system, often disabling sufferers for more than a decade before it proves fatal.  </p>
<p>Early symptoms include trembling, muscular stiffness and slowing of body movement which gradually develop into loss of control affecting facial muscles, the throat, feet, limbs and neck.</p>
<p>Speaking at the launch of Requip, doctors said the new drug increases the treatment options open to them.</p>
<p>Consultant geriatrician Douglas MacMahon of the Camborne Redruth Community Hospital in Cornwall quoted one of his patients as saying &quot;the diagnosis of Parkinson's disease is like getting a death sentence.&quot;</p>
<p>MacMahon said Requip &quot;is offering something new, a reprieve from that death sentence.&quot;</p>
<p>Andrew Lees of the National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery stressed &quot;it is not a cure, but we think it may be useful for a significant proportiion of patients.&quot;</p>
<p>Long-term assessment of the full impact of the drug, which is costed at 3.31 stg per day, will continue for another decade.</p>
<p>SmithKline Beecham said Requip, which was developed at its Harlow research base in England, is its first ever neurological drug. A spokesman said France and the USA are likely to be the next target markets after the U.K.</p>
<p>-- Jonathan Birt, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
