<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39110" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: POPE LEAVES HUNGARY AFTER DEMANDING TWO-DAY VISIT.</title>
<headline>POPE LEAVES HUNGARY AFTER DEMANDING TWO-DAY VISIT.</headline>
<byline>Duncan Shiels</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul flew out of Budapest's Ferihegy airport on Saturday after a punishing two-day visit to Hungary during which his health came under close public scrutiny.</p>
<p>His trip, to mark the 1,000th anniversary of a monastery at Pannonhalma, near Gyor, in western Hungary, was the first since hospital tests following an abdominal infection in mid-August raised renewed concern for his health.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pontiff made the last leg of his visit from Gyor to Ferihegy by helicopter in driving rain and was escorted by the arm to his waiting plane by Hungarian president Arpad Goncz, the Pope's white papal gown and white umbrella contrasting sharply with Goncz's and other Hungarian officials' black rain-soaked overcoats.</p>
<p>The Pope fulfilled all his engagements during the trip although a farewell speech from the airport tarmac was cancelled because of the weather conditons. &quot;We didn't want to risk the Pope's health,&quot; a Hungarian government official said.</p>
<p>Pope John Paul appeared fatigued during his visit and earlier had to brave a bitingly cold wind at an open-air mass for an estimated 130,000 people on Saturday.</p>
<p>Joaquin Navarro-Valls, the Pope's chief spokesman and a doctor himself, told reporters the Pope &quot;basically...remains a healthy man&quot; and had no plans to stop the foreign travel that has been the hallmark of his papacy. A four-day trip to France is scheduled for later this month.</p>
<p>&quot;The tests in August didn't find out the source of the infections,&quot; he said. &quot;As a personal opinion, a hypothesis that could explain what is going on in the field of the infection is that it could be some intestinal weakness left from the first operation in 1981.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope survived a 1981 assassination attempt when he was shot in the abdomen in St Peter's Square.</p>
<p>Earlier the Pope met all 20 members of the Hungarian Bishops Conference, who said afterwards that the Pontiff had appeared to be in good health.</p>
<p>&quot;He seemed to be in pretty good health and full of energy,&quot; said Istvan Seregely, Archbishop of Eger.</p>
<p>During his two-day visit the Pontiff sought to promote a post-communist spiritual revival in eastern Europe.</p>
<p>He told the Hungarian bishops that many younger people saw no need for religion and urged the Church to combat &quot;consumerist and hedonistic society&quot;, preserve the family and fight the &quot;culture of death&quot; of abortion. He urged the bishops &quot;above all (to) be defenders of human life&quot;.</p>
<p>During the last engagement before his departure -- a meeting in Gyor Cathedral with 1,000 clergy from the Gyor diocese -- Pope John Paul said the end of communism had not been a cureall for society.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been no lack of disillusionment,&quot; he said. &quot;The return to religious practice has been slow. Difficulties have been placed in the way of the Church regaining the schools and institutes which belonged to her.</p>
<p>&quot;Do not let the ideals of solidarity and the sense of responsibility for others be eclipsed by individualism and selfishness,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
