<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39153" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Pope says mass in Hungary, health in spotlight.</title>
<headline>Pope says mass in Hungary, health in spotlight.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>GYOR, Hungary 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul called in Hungary on Saturday for a post-communist spiritual drive as the Vatican sought to dispel fresh speculation about his health.</p>
<p>Returning to a theme that has run through his recent visits to Eastern Europe, the Polish-born Pope urged worshippers at an open-air mass to spread the Christian message to fellow Hungarians who had known only communism.</p>
<p>&quot;Do not be discouraged by economic and social difficulties, by unemployment, by widespread poverty, by the decline of moral values in the generation which grew up without religion,&quot; the 76-year-old Pope said.</p>
<p>The mass in the western city of Gyor was the largest public event of his two-day visit to Hungary.</p>
<p>His trip, to mark the 1,000th anniversary of a monastery at Pannonhalma, near Gyor, was the first since hospital tests following an abdominal infection in mid-August raised renewed concern for his health.</p>
<p>The Pope has appeared fatigued during the trip and had to brave a bitingly cold wind at Saturday's mass, which he spoke of at the end of the service in unprepared remarks in Italian.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no interest in demonstrating that the Pope is a superman,&quot; his chief spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, told reporters at a briefing after the mass dominated by questions about the Roman Catholic leader's health.</p>
<p>But he said the Pope &quot;basically...remains a healthy man&quot; and had no plans to stop the foreign travel that has been the hallmark of his papacy. A four-day trip to France is scheduled for later this month.</p>
<p>Poor health in recent years, including surgery to remove a colon tumour in 1992, has fired constant speculation about the Pope's condition and unconfirmed reports of serious illness.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls had to issue a statement on Saturday after one news story erroneously said that the Pope had stopped reading a text in Hungarian and left a local monk to deliver it at a Friday evening service because he felt faint.</p>
<p>The spokesman acknowledged that the Pope had looked very tired at the service but he said the Pontiff often had someone else read his remarks when he found the language difficult.</p>
<p>&quot;He looked fine to me. Of course, his age and the fatigue of travel shows,&quot; said one woman who was close to the Pope when he toured Saturday's mass site in his glass-roofed &quot;Popemobile&quot;.</p>
<p>The Pope used a hydraulic lift to reach the specially built wooden mass platform without climbing steps, a feature of many of his masses on foreign trips since hip replacement surgery in 1994 reduced his mobility.</p>
<p>Police estimated the crowd, which included Roman Catholics from neighbouring countries, at 130,000 though reporters present said the size appeared substantially less.</p>
<p>&quot;At the end of the 20th century, how great is the need to know Christ,&quot; the Pope said in his homily.</p>
<p>&quot;There are numerous ideologies and cultural trends which promote themselves. They promise happiness, success and freedom but they cannot explain the real purpose of life.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope is widely credited with a major role in helping to bring down communism in Poland and throughout Eastern Europe.</p>
<p>Jan Mosinski, a Solidarity Union official among a group of some 150 people who had travelled from Poland for the mass, said: &quot;The Holy Father liberated not only Poland but the whole world. He has liberated the whole world from communism&quot;.</p>
<p>The Pope, however, has argued that in many cases communism has given way to moral amd material decadence as societies rush towards capitalist economies.</p>
<p>He told Hungarian bishops at a meeting after the mass that many younger people saw no need for religion and urged the Church to combat &quot;consumerist and hedonistic society&quot;, preserve the family and fight the &quot;culture of death&quot; of abortion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GYOR, Hungary"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
