<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39150" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Pope's health at centre stage in Hungary trip.</title>
<headline>Pope's health at centre stage in Hungary trip.</headline>
<byline>Michael Roddy</byline>
<dateline>GYOR, Hungary 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul's health was the focus of attention on Saturday during a visit to Hungary in which he sought to promote a post-communist spiritual revival in eastern Europe.</p>
<p>His trip, to mark the 1,000th anniversary of a monastery at Pannonhalma, near Gyor, was the first since hospital tests following an abdominal infection in mid-August raised renewed concern for his health.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pope has appeared fatigued during the trip and had to brave a bitingly cold wind at an open-air mass for an estimated 130,000 people on Saturday, final day of his two-day visit.</p>
<p>&quot;The tests in August didn't find out the source of the infections or whether they were the same infection or whether they will recur,&quot; Joaquin Navarro-Valls, the Pope's chief spokesman, told reporters after the mass at a briefing dominated by questions about the Roman Catholic leader's health.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no interest in demonstrating that the Pope is a superman,&quot; said Navarro-Valls, who is a doctor himself.</p>
<p>He said, however, that the Pope &quot;basically...remains a healthy man&quot; and had no plans to stop the foreign travel that has been the hallmark of his papacy. A four-day trip to France is scheduled for later this month.</p>
<p>Following the briefing, Navarro-Valls amplified on his remarks, telling reporters, &quot;As a personal opinion, a hypothesis that could explain what is going on in the field of the infection is that it could be some intestinal weakness left from the first operation in 1981.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope survived a 1981 assassination attempt when he was shot in the abdomen in St Peter's Square.</p>
<p>Poor health in recent years, including surgery to remove a colon tumour in 1992, has fired speculation about the Pope's condition and unconfirmed reports of serious illness.</p>
<p>Following the mass, the Pope met all 20 members of the Hungarian Bishops' Conference, who said afterwards that the Pontiff had appeared to be in good health.</p>
<p>&quot;He seemed to be in pretty good health and full of energy,&quot; said Istvan Seregely, Archbishop of Eger and chairman of the bishops' conference, which held its meeting with the Pope in the 16th century bishop's palace of this western Hungarian city.</p>
<p>Bishop Asztrik Varszegi, Arch Abbot of the Pannonhalma Monastery where the Pope presided at vespers on Friday, said he wanted to dispel &quot;rumours&quot; that the Pope had felt faint and was too tired to read his homily, and a monk had to read it for him.</p>
<p>&quot;The Holy Father started the address in Hungarian but as originally conducted there was a Hungarian reader and sometimes the Holy Father read some sections in Hungarian,&quot; Varszegi said.</p>
<p>The Pope in his mass and later remarks pressed Hungarian and East European Catholics to undertake a post-communist spiritual revival.</p>
<p>&quot;Do not be discouraged by economic and social difficulties, by unemployment, by widespread poverty, by the decline of moral values in the generation which grew up without religion,&quot; the Pope said at the mass where people wore heavy winter coats and wrapped themselves in blankets to stay warm.</p>
<p>The Pope later urged the bishops &quot;above all (to) be defenders of human life&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Nowadays a consumerist and hedonistic society especially threatens life which is not yet born and that which is reaching its end,&quot; the Pope said. &quot;It is the duty of believers to promote the values of life and to defend life in word and action.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GYOR, Hungary"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
