<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39922" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Vatican sheds some light after pope health worries.</title>
<headline>Vatican sheds some light after pope health worries.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An unusually frank discussion by Pope John Paul's chief spokesman about his health may signal a cautious start to an era of openness at the Vatican about what ails the leader of the world's 960 million Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>The Pontiff, currently in the 18th year of a history-making papacy, clearly is not a man who is at death's door.</p>
<p>On Sunday he spoke for 20 minutes while standing at his summer residence and plans a Vatican audience on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But more often than not, the 76-year-old Pope appears fatigued and sometimes clearly in discomfort during appearances.</p>
<p>His left hand shakes, at times uncontrollably, and he frequently seems to have lost much of the vigour that made him famous. On Sunday, even a cheering crowd failed to draw a smile from him.</p>
<p>What exactly is wrong with the Pope?</p>
<p>The Vatican has always been tight on details of his health. The Pope's personal doctor, Renato Buzzonetti, has never held a news conference, even after the Pontiff underwent surgery in 1981, 1992 and 1994.</p>
<p>But on Saturday in Hungary, after a fatigued Pope sparked fresh concern among journalists, chief spokesman Joaquin Navarro-Valls became uncharacteristically forthcoming.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no interest in demonstrating that the Pope is a superman,&quot; said Navarro-Valls, adding that the Pope &quot;basically...remains a healthy man&quot;.</p>
<p>But the conversation by the man sometimes called the &quot;Papal spin doctor&quot; indicated that the Vatican may have decided on a new tack now that it has become painfully obvious that the Pope is no longer the vigorous man who once left aides breathless.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls, himself a trained doctor, said the Pope had suffered from an intestinal infection that caused a fever twice this year and which tests had so far failed failed to pinpoint.</p>
<p>He said the while the problem might recur, it was not degenerative and that there were no signs of a return of a tumour removed in 1992.</p>
<p>&quot;We still don't know the origin of this infection. Is it the same or a different one? Probably it is the same one because it has already surfaced several times,&quot; Navarro-Valls said in a briefing on Saturday before the Pope returned to Rome.</p>
<p>He added that antibiotics the Pope has taken for the infection &quot;tend to make him feel dejected&quot;.</p>
<p>Aides say old age and loss of some mobility following leg surgery in 1994 have taken their psychological toll on a man accustomed to being so active.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said one explanation for the infection was that it may be caused by adhesions in the intestine.</p>
<p>Adhesion, or the joining of normally separate tissues, occurs between loops of intestine in people who have undergone abdominal surgery.</p>
<p>The Pope had major abdominal surgery in 1981 after an assassination attempt and in 1992 to remove a colon tumour. In both cases surgeons removed tracts of his intestine.</p>
<p>Intestinal adhesions can cause obstructions of the alimentary canal and sometimes sharp pain during digestion, which could shed light on some of his unexplained grimaces.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said there was a possibility that the Pope could eventually undergo a laparoscopy, an examination of the abdominal structure in which an illuminated viewing tube is inserted through a small incision.</p>
<p>The Vatican has never fully explained the sometimes violent trembling in the Pope's left hand and a sometimes drooping right eyelid. In the past, the Vatican has said this was probably caused by nerve damage suffered in the 1981 shooting.</p>
<p>Now, some Vatican officials say privately this may be caused by some other neurological disorder. Doctors who have observed the Pope from a distance say the symtoms are similar to those at the initial stages of Parkinson's disease.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said the Pope had no plans to stop the foreign travel that has been the hallmark of his papacy. A visit to France later this month is still on and four trips are planned for next year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
