<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44789" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Leftist groups denounce Pope ahead of French trip.</title>
<headline>Leftist groups denounce Pope ahead of French trip.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dozens of mostly leftist groups, planning a protest when Pope John Paul visits France this month, accused the Pontiff on Tuesday of moral intolerance and of trampling French laws separating church and state.</p>
<p>The 67 organisations, ranging from feminists to anarchists, aim to stage a rally against the Pope and the centre-right government in Paris on September 22, when the Pontiff will be in Reims in eastern France on the final day of a four-day trip.</p>
<p>&quot;We're united under three causes -- respect for separation of church and state, refusal of public funding for pastoral aspects of the papal trip and rejection of a return to a moral order,&quot; Thierry Meyssan, a spokesman for the groups, told a news conference at the French Senate.</p>
<p>The Paris rally is the main protest planned against the Pope amid unprecedented controversy about the visit in France, long a faithful follower of Rome.</p>
<p>The rally, a secular alternative to the Pope sponsored by groups including anti-racism campaigners, feminists, masons and a police union, will mark the anniversary of the proclamation of the First Republic in September 1792.</p>
<p>The same day, the Pope will be in Reims to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in Western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism and seen by some Roman Catholic traditionalists as the father of France.</p>
<p>The organisations accuse conservative President Jacques Chirac of being in league with the Pope to reassert the primacy of Catholicism, France's religion before the Revolution, in violation of a 1905 law separating church and state.</p>
<p>Mouloud Aounit, of the anti-racism group MRAP, said the government was trying to pander to radical Catholics and voters from the anti-immigrant National Front, which has adopted Clovis as a symbol.</p>
<p>The groups say that an estimated 30 million francs ($6.0 million) spent by the state on the visit would be better invested on jobs.</p>
<p>The Roman Catholic Church says France also paid for non-religious aspects of the Pope's previous four visits.</p>
<p>Leaders of a dozen or so of the 67 groups took turns to berate the Pope for his moral teachings against birth control, abortion and homosexuality.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope is on a crusade against the rights of women,&quot; said Maya Surduts, a spokeswoman for women's groups favouring abortion and contraception. &quot;This Pope has blood on his hands.&quot;</p>
<p>Bechir Chemla of the Gemini group for homosexuals said: &quot;there's no sacrilege in two people loving each other if they are of the same sex.&quot;</p>
<p>An 18-year-old Ivorian student, identified as &quot;Clovis&quot; and who is seeking French residence papers, will be appearing on anti-racist posters in France as part of the anti-Pope campaign.</p>
<p>&quot;My name's Clovis. I'm 18 years old. French history is also mine,&quot; the caption says under a photograph of Clovis Achi, who has lived for 12 years in France.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
