<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44818" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Vatican denies tired Pope set to enter hospital.</title>
<headline>Vatican denies tired Pope set to enter hospital.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Vatican denied on Tuesday that Pope John Paul was about to enter hospital but did not comment on a French newspaper report suggesting he has Parkinson's disease, a disabling nervous disorder.</p>
<p>The Pope has a trembling left hand which has fuelled speculation that he may have developed the chronic illness.</p>
<p>Now 76, he looked extremely fatigued during his trip to Hungary last weekend, sparking fresh concern for the health of the leader of the world's Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no plans for the Pope to enter hospital,&quot; chief Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro-Valls said, responding to an Italian report that the Polish-born Pope would have hosspital checks in Rome after a September 19-22 visit to France.</p>
<p>The report was followed by a flood of rumours that the Pope would enter hospital on Tuesday or Wednesday. The rumours also said the Pope would not hold his weekly general audience.</p>
<p>The Vatican said the audience would go ahead as scheduled on Wednesday and workmen were preparing St Peter's Square for the event, which usually attracts tens of thousands of people.</p>
<p>The Pope also received 10 Indonesian bishops at his summer residence south of Rome on Tuesday, the Vatican said.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls, himself a trained doctor, told reporters in Hungary on Saturday that the Pope had suffered from an intestinal infection that caused a fever twice this year and which tests so far had failed to pinpoint.</p>
<p>The Pope had major abdominal surgery in 1981 after an assassination attempt and in 1992 to remove a colon tumour. In both cases surgeons removed tracts of his intestine.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said in Hungary there was a possibility that the Pope could eventually undergo a laparoscopy, an examination of the abdominal structure in which an illuminated viewing tube is inserted through a small incision.</p>
<p>The spokesman's unusually frank discussion in Hungary may have signalled a cautious start to an era of openness at the Vatican about what ails the Pontiff.</p>
<p>More often than not, the history-making Pope appears fatigued and sometimes clearly in discomfort during appearances.</p>
<p>The Vatican has never fully explained the violent trembling in the Pope's left hand and a sometimes drooping right eyelid.</p>
<p>In the past, the Vatican has said this was probably caused by nerve damage suffered in the 1981 shooting.</p>
<p>But recently Navarro-Valls has begun suggesting to reporters that one possible explanation of the of Pope's trembling left hand was an &quot;extrapyramidal&quot; disorder.</p>
<p>Extrapyramidal refers to that part of the human central nervous system situated outside the pyramidal tract in the brain stem. The pyramidal tract is a a bundle of motor nerve fibres.</p>
<p>Doctors says Parkinson's disease -- manifested by trembling and muscle rigidity and which can affect speech and facial expressions -- is one type of an extrapyramidal illness.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said in Hungary that while the intestinal problem might recur, it was not degenerative and there were no signs of a return of the intestinal tumour removed in 1992.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
