<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45278" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FEATURE - Pope stirs unprecedented opposition in France.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Pope stirs unprecedented opposition in France.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul's planned visit to France this month is triggering unprecedented opposition in a country once proud of its Roman Catholic piety.</p>
<p>A crude bomb was defused early this month in a church in northwest France where the Pontiff is due to pray on the first day of his September 19-22 visit. Unknown attackers had daubed &quot;In nomine-Pope-BOOM!&quot; on a wall of the crypt.</p>
<p>Up to 600 people have written to their bishops to ask that their names be struck off baptism registers to protest at the Pope's unflinching opposition to birth control, abortion and homosexuality.</p>
<p>His fifth trip to a country that long called itself &quot;the eldest daughter of the Church&quot; has stirred anti-clerical currents stretching back to before the 1789 French Revolution.</p>
<p>More than 50 anti-Pope groups, from Trotskyites to birth control advocates, have called a rally in Paris on September 22 &quot;for the separation of church and state, against the return of the moral order&quot;.</p>
<p>Local councils and the centre-right government have come under fire for spending public funds on the visit to Tours, Vendee, Brittany and Reims. Critics accuse them of violating a 1905 law separating church and state.</p>
<p>The Archbishop of Paris, Cardinal Jean-Marie Lustiger, blasted opponents of the Pontiff's visit as &quot;fanatical and intolerant. I am outraged as a Frenchman and as a democrat.&quot;</p>
<p>Pierre Lagoutte, secretary-general of the French Bishops' Conference, lamented: &quot;There was less criticism of the Pope on previous visits.&quot;</p>
<p>But the Bishops' Conference says the attacks are causing a backlash among the dwindling ranks of the faithful, raising interest as well as donations.</p>
<p>&quot;Controversy has helped us,&quot; Lagoutte said. &quot;We've had to revise upwards our estimates of how many people are coming to Reims to 120,000-130,000 people from 80,000-100,000.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope's visit follows a long crisis of Catholicism in France and a slide from papal standards that mirrors that of many other Western societies. &quot;We have a great number of internal problems to tackle,&quot; Lagoutte said.</p>
<p>About 45 million of France's 58 million inhabitants are nominally Catholics, but the Bishops' Conference says about six million go to church on Sundays. Only 120 to 130 priests are ordained each year, a tenth of the number just 20 years ago.</p>
<p>Hardline secularists were shocked when President Jacques Chirac, an occasional churchgoer, paid a state visit to the Vatican last year and many deplored a requiem mass at Notre Dame cathedral for his Socialist predecessor Francois Mitterrand.</p>
<p>But the Chirac family also symbolises French non-conformism towards Catholic morality. The president proudly poses with his unmarried daughter, her boyfriend and their six-month-old baby.</p>
<p>Reims, in the champagne-growing region, is a lightning rod for controversy about the visit since the Pope is to commemorate there the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, a pagan king who converted to Christianity around 496 A.D. -- purists say it was probably later.</p>
<p>Lionised by the far-right National Front party, Clovis was the first king in Western Europe to convert to Catholicism and became a symbol of a supposed divine link between God and French monarchs. That dogma was overthrown by the French Revolution.</p>
<p>In his 1994 bestseller &quot;Crossing the Threshold of Hope&quot;, Pope John Paul wrote that &quot;the French Revolution overturned Christ's altars, it threw crucifixes into the street and replaced them with the Goddess of Reason&quot;.</p>
<p>In a challenge to secular traditions, he said France needed to rediscover its Catholic roots.</p>
<p>Yet the Pope's teachings have become less palatable to the French since his last visit in 1988, the year before elections brought democracy to John Paul II's native Poland.</p>
<p>&quot;Since the fall of the Berlin Wall, the Pope's fight against communism and for human rights has receded in peoples' minds,&quot; said Jean Bauberot, head of a state-funded think-tank on the sociology of religions and secularism.</p>
<p>&quot;Now people just hear his ideas on abortion and contraception. To many French people they sound so unrealistic as to go against free choice,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Vatican's sacking last year of &quot;Red Cleric&quot; Jacques Gaillot as Bishop of Evreux for espousing liberal views such as the use of condoms to help prevent AIDS underscored the extent of French alienation from the Pontiff.</p>
<p>Polls showed more French identify with Gaillot's ideas than with the Pope's. &quot;Transferred&quot; to a non-existent ancient diocese in the Sahara desert, Gaillot uses the Internet computer network as an alternative pulpit to preach on behalf of the unemployed and homeless.</p>
<p>Politically, the Church often seems trapped between conflicting extremes.</p>
<p>It has distanced itself from an ultra-traditionalist Catholic movement, close to the far-right, anti-immigrant National Front, which wants to turn the Clovis anniversary into a chauvinist celebration of France as a &quot;Christian nation&quot;.</p>
<p>But it has also tried to shed an uneasy alliance with the Left after giving shelter in a Paris church to about 300 African immigrants for 50 days until a police raid ordered by the centre-right government last month.</p>
<p>And there has been trouble on other fronts.</p>
<p>Abbe Pierre, an elderly priest and anti-poverty campaigner long voted France's most popular man, drew fierce criticism this year by endorsing an author who cast doubt on the Nazi Holocaust and blaming the furore on a world Jewish conspiracy.</p>
<p>He retracted in July, asking the forgiveness of all he had hurt.</p>
<p>Many French people were shocked at the disclosure that right-wing priests had hidden the late Paul Touvier, convicted in 1994 of crimes against humanity for killing Jews in World War Two, for almost 50 years. He was arrested in a Nice monastery.</p>
<p>Lagoutte said criticism of public funding of the papal visit was misguided. Chirac's predecessors had done the same or more.</p>
<p>The Church will pay up to seven million francs ($1.4 million) for religious events. The state will pay for security, an airliner and helicopters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
