<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53720" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: FEATURE - Papal health in spotlight amid talk of Parkinson's.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Papal health in spotlight amid talk of Parkinson's.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>What exactly is wrong with the Pope?</p>
<p>Sometimes, he appears so tired and short of breath that it seems he might not be able to finish reading a speech.</p>
<p>Often in recent months, Pope John Paul II has been in obvious discomfort, leading Italian newspapers to call him &quot;the suffering Pope&quot;.</p>
<p>The vigour that made him famous appears faded. More often than not, even a cheering crowd can't draw a smile from the former actor.</p>
<p>His left hand shakes, sometimes so violently that he has to put it under his thigh or brace the arm of his throne in order to keep it steady.</p>
<p>At other times he seems tranquil -- showing signs of his age and past medical operations but no extraordinary difficulties.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old pontiff, currently in the 18th year of a history-making papacy, clearly is not a man who is at death's door.</p>
<p>But it is equally -- and painfully -- obvious that something is not right with his health.</p>
<p>Recent health scares have led to fresh media speculation that he is suffering from Parkinson's disease and might consider resigning if debilitated by a drawn-out illness.</p>
<p>The Vatican has always been extremely reluctant to disclose details of his health, citing traditional reserve and personal privacy.</p>
<p>The Pope's personal doctor, Renato Buzzonetti, has never held a news conference, even after the Pope underwent surgery in 1981, 1992 and 1994.</p>
<p>The Vatican instead issued terse statements and left it to its spokesman to explain the Pope's condition to the world.</p>
<p>Now, an uncharacteristically forthcoming discussion by the spokesman may have signalled a cautious start to an era of openness at the Vatican about what ails the leader of the world's 960 million Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no interest in demonstrating that the Pope is a superman,&quot; said Joaquin Navarro-Valls, talking to reporters alarmed by the Pope's marked fatigue during a trip to Hungary.</p>
<p>In what appeared to be a change of policy, Navarro-Valls -- the man sometimes called the &quot;Papal spin doctor&quot; -- has been telling reporters over the past month that the Pope may be suffering from some kind of &quot;extrapyramidal&quot; neurological disorder.</p>
<p>This would explain the uncontrollable shaking of the left hand, a malady that had previously been explained as being caused by nerve damage suffered in a 1981 assassination attempt.</p>
<p>Extrapyramidal refers to that part of the human central nervous system situated outside the pyramidal tract in the brain stem. The pyramidal tract is a bundle of motor nerve fibres.</p>
<p>Doctors say Parkinson's disease -- manifested by trembling and muscle rigidity and which can affect speech and facial expressions -- is one type of an extrapyramidal illness.</p>
<p>The Vatican did not deny a report in the French newspaper Le Monde that interpreted Navarro-Valls remarks about extrapyramidal disorder to mean that the Pope has Parkinson's.</p>
<p>The recent health concerns have led to reports of a power play in the Vatican and speculation that the Pope might prefer to resign if a protracted illness made him unable to carry out his duties at the head of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>Popes are elected for life. The last Pope to resign was Celestine V in 1296, who stepped down in turbulent historical circumstances.</p>
<p>In May 1995, when the Pope marked his 75th birthday, he publicly dismissed suggestions by dissident Catholics that he should resign. He declared he wanted to serve the Church until his dying day and that only God could end his reign.</p>
<p>All bishops of the Roman Catholic Church except the Pope -- who is Bishop of Rome -- are required to hand in their resignations when they turn 75.</p>
<p>At the time the Pope said: &quot;I renew before Christ my willingness to serve the Church as long as he wants, abandoning myself completely to His holy will. I leave to Him to decide when and how He wants to relieve me of this service.&quot;</p>
<p>Reporters speculated at the time that the word &quot;how&quot; may have been his way of leaving an opening for a resignation. The Vatican has repeatedly denied suggestions of resignation.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls also told reporters in Hungary that the Pope had suffered from an intestinal infection that caused a fever twice this year and which tests had failed to pinpoint.</p>
<p>Antibiotics the Pope has taken for the infection &quot;tend to make him feel dejected&quot;. Aides say old age and the loss of some mobility following leg surgery in 1994 have taken their psychological toll on a man accustomed to being so active.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said one explanation for the infection was that it may be caused by adhesions in the intestine.</p>
<p>Adhesion, or the joining of normally separate tissues, occurs between loops of intestine after abdominal surgery.</p>
<p>The Pope had major abdominal surgery in 1981 after the assassination attempt and in 1992 to remove the tumour. In both cases surgeons removed tracts of his intestine.</p>
<p>Intestinal adhesions can cause obstructions of the alimentary canal and sometimes sharp pain during digestion, which could shed light on some of his unexplained grimaces.</p>
<p>Navarro-Valls said there was a possibility that the Pope could eventually undergo a laparoscopy, an examination of the abdominal structure in which an illuminated viewing tube is inserted through a small incision.</p>
<p>But the Vatican has denied a Rome newspaper report that there were plans for the Pope to go into hospital for tests after a September 18-22 trip to France.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
