<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54157" id="root" date="1996-09-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton re-election could bring departure of Reno.</title>
<headline>Clinton re-election could bring departure of Reno.</headline>
<byline>James Vicini</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton's re-election could lead to major Justice Department personnel changes, including the possible departure of Attorney General Janet Reno, administration officials said.</p>
<p>Although White House and Justice Department officials said it was too early to know for sure what moves would be made, they increasingly questioned whether Reno, who suffers from Parkinson's disease, would stay on for a second term.</p>
<p>Commerce Secretary Mickey Kantor and Deputy Attorney General Jamie Gorelick have emerged as the leading candidates to replace Reno as the nation's top law enforcement officer, the officials said.</p>
<p>Clinton, who enjoys a 15 to 20 percentage point lead in the polls over Republican rival Bob Dole, has ordered his aides not to talk about the cabinet members who will stay and who will go if he wins the November election.</p>
<p>Justice Department spokesman Bert Brandenburg dismissed as &quot;Washington parlor games&quot; widespread speculation that the 58-year-old Reno would leave.</p>
<p>&quot;If Clinton asks her, she is ready to stay four more years,&quot; he said, adding that Reno's illness, a degenerative disease that causes trembling and muscular rigidity, has not affected her ability to do her job.</p>
<p>&quot;She is as strong and vigorous as ever,&quot; he said of Reno, who has been widely viewed as improving her performance in office after a rocky start and initial strained relations with the White House.</p>
<p>White House sources said Kantor would be a likely replacement for Reno in a potential Clinton cabinet reshuffle, with former White House chief of staff Thomas &quot;Mack&quot; McLarty replacing Kantor.</p>
<p>Kantor, a longtime Clinton associate, was the president's chief negotiator for the debates with Dole. &quot;If Mickey wants the job (of attorney general), then he can have it,&quot; one source said, describing him as unhappy at the Commerce Department.</p>
<p>But they said Kantor may end up becoming White House chief of staff during a second Clinton term.</p>
<p>Within the Justice Department, the top candidate to succeed Reno would be her deputy, Gorelick, who has been in charge of the day-to-day activities for much of the agency's sprawling operations.</p>
<p>&quot;Jamie makes the trains run on time,&quot; a Justice Department official said. &quot;She does the job very well.&quot;</p>
<p>But Gorelick, who previously served as Pentagon general counsel, may be more interested in top positions at the Defense Department or the Central Intelligence Agency if they become available, Justice Department officials said.</p>
<p>Gorelick deflected questions about her future at the weekly Justice Department news briefing on Thursday, saying, &quot;I really love my job ... I am just going to keep on doing it as long as I can.&quot;</p>
<p>The officials said Associate Attorney General John Schmidt, a politically-connected Chicago lawyer, has been campaigning hard to replace Reno. He briefly was considered for attorney general after the 1992 election.</p>
<p>They said FBI chief Louis Freeh no longer was in the running due to the controversy over the disclosures that the Clinton White House improperly obtained hundreds of FBI files in 1993 and 1994 on prominent Republicans and others.</p>
<p>In a second term, Clinton also must find a replacement for Assistant Attorney General Anne Bingaman, who has aggressively enforced the antitrust laws. She plans to leave after the November election.</p>
<p>He also must decide who will permanently become assistant attorney general in charge of the Justice Department's Criminal Division and solicitor general, the government's top lawyer at the Supreme Court. These posts are filled now on an acting basis.</p>
<p>With all the expected changes, a Justice Department official said, &quot;The bottom line is that everything is up in the air.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
