<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54175" id="root" date="1996-09-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Pope to have appendix out later this year.</title>
<headline>Pope to have appendix out later this year.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul is suffering from recurring inflammation of the appendix and will go into hospital before the end of the year for surgery to remove it, the Vatican said on Saturday.</p>
<p>In a statement that finally disclosed what has been ailing the 76-year-old Pope recently, the Vatican said there were no signs of a recurrence of an intestinal tumour removed in 1992.</p>
<p>The Vatican's chief spokesman ruled out cancer but the statement made no mention of another problem -- the Pope's sometimes violently trembling left hand which has sparked media speculation that he is suffering from Parkinson's disease and might consider resigning if debilitated by a drawn-out illness.</p>
<p>Joaquin Navarro-Valls stressed that the 76-year-old Polish Pope, who has looked fatigued and in discomfort recently and caused concern during a trip last weekend to Hungary, would go ahead with a September 19-22 trip to France and an October 6 beatification ceremony at the Vatican.</p>
<p>The spokesman told Reuters Television the inflammation had been &quot;in a mild form&quot; and that the Pope was tranquil about undergoing surgery again.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a recurring thing and so it's better to intervene from the surgical point of view and remove the risk but there is no special concern,&quot; said Navarro-Valls, himself a doctor.</p>
<p>&quot;Any possibility of cancer has been excluded,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Pope's sixth operation since his election in 1978 would take place sometime between October 6 and the end of the year.</p>
<p>A statement by the Pope's personal doctor, Renato Buzzonetti, said a series of abdominal problems and fevers the Pope has suffered since Christmas were caused by &quot;recurring episodes of inflamation of the appendix&quot;.</p>
<p>It was treated thus far only with antibiotics because of the Pope's many commitments, and each time was resolved, it said.</p>
<p>Buzzonetti consulted four other doctors on September 12 who unanimously agreed that surgery was ultimately necessary. The Pope consented.</p>
<p>The doctor's statement said &quot;all other aspects of the Pope's health do not give rise for particular concern&quot; and that the Pope had been receiving regular check-ups by specialists.</p>
<p>Appendicitis is an inflammatory disease which chiefly causes abdominal pain. Vomiting, diarrhoea and slight fever occur.</p>
<p>Relapsing appendicitis causes repeated slight attacks of pain and discomfort. In some such cases, the slightly inflamed appendix may undergo spasmodic, painful contractions, known as appendicular colic.</p>
<p>This would explain some of the Pope's recent grimaces.</p>
<p>Acute appendicitis must be treated quickly or it can lead to peritonitis or an abcess.</p>
<p>The fact that the Pope was not taken to hospital immediately indicates he has not suffered an attack of acute appendicitis.</p>
<p>The Pope has suffered from slight fevers at least three times this year. Last Christmas he had to cancel Christmas mass and later was unable to finish his &quot;Urbi et Orbi&quot; address to the city and the world.</p>
<p>In March he had to cancel several engagements because of fever and suffered another bout in mid-August.</p>
<p>The Pope underwent abdominal surgery twice in 1981 after an assassination attempt and again in 1992 to remove the tumour.</p>
<p>The Pope also had surgery to fix a dislocated shoulder in 1993 and to repair a broken leg bone in 1994.</p>
<p>Regarding the Pope's trembling left hand, Navarro-Valls has told reporters in past weeks that the Pope may be suffering from a &quot;extrapyramidal&quot; neurological disorder.</p>
<p>He declined to make any comment on that ailment on Saturday.</p>
<p>Extrapyramidal refers to that part of the human central nervous system situated outside the pyramidal tract in the brain stem. The pyramidal tract is a bundle of motor nerve fibres.</p>
<p>Doctors say Parkinson's disease -- manifested by trembling and muscle rigidity and which can affect speech and facial expressions -- is one type of an extrapyramidal illness.</p>
<p>The Vatican did not deny a report in the French newspaper Le Monde that interpreted Navarro-Valls remarks about extrapyramidal disorder to mean that the Pope has Parkinson's.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
