<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54747" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Sceptics question Vatican version of Pope's health.</title>
<headline>Sceptics question Vatican version of Pope's health.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Vatican has announced that Pope John Paul will undergo surgery to remove his appendix but commentators said on Sunday the Holy See is not disclosing all about the shaky health of the 76-year-old Pontiff.</p>
<p>In a statement that finally disclosed at least part of what has been ailing the Pope, the Vatican said on Saturday that he is suffering from inflammation of the appendix.</p>
<p>A statement by the Pope's personal doctor, Renato Buzzonetti, also insisted there were no signs of a recurrence of an intestinal tumour removed in 1992.</p>
<p>But Buzzonetti made no mention of another problem -- the Pope's sometimes violently trembling left hand which has sparked media speculation he is suffering from Parkinson's disease and might consider resigning if debilitated by a drawn-out illness.</p>
<p>The announcement of the operation, which will take place later this year, drew scepticism over whether the Pope's frailty could be explained by such a banal problem.</p>
<p>&quot;If the intention was to reassure public opinion, it missed the mark,&quot; said Francesco Margiotta Broglio, an Italian jurist who has negotiated international treaties with the Vatican.</p>
<p>&quot;The type of illness declared is certainly not proportionate with the image of the Pope's progressive frailty and suffering that is there for everyone to see,&quot; he wrote in Corriere della Sera newspaper.</p>
<p>La Repubblica and L'Unita newspapers ran interviews with Italian doctors who raised doubts about the diagnosis.</p>
<p>La Repubblica quoted Carlo Caruso, a surgeon at one of Rome's best-known hospitals, as saying he believed the statement had been issued &quot;to hide something much more serious.&quot;</p>
<p>Marco Politi, co-author of a new book on the Pope with Carl Bernstein, of Watergate fame, wrote in La Repubblica that the statement had shattered what he called the &quot;long lie that the Pope is in substantially good health, only tired, only old&quot;.</p>
<p>While the Vatican stressed that there was no sign the Pope had cancer, Italian newspapers speculated that the operation would give doctors a chance to carry out an overall check-up on modern history's most famous Pope.</p>
<p>La Stampa said three small unexplained marks in the intestinal tract were observed when the Pope underwent a CAT scan in August after complaining of abdominal pains.</p>
<p>Saturday's statement said a series of abdominal problems and fevers the Pope has suffered since Christmas were caused by &quot;recurring episodes of inflammation of the appendix&quot;.</p>
<p>But at the time of the illnesses, at Christmas and in March, the Vatican explained the fevers as being caused by either an influenza or a &quot;digestive problem&quot;.</p>
<p>The Vatican said the inflammation had been treated so far only with antibiotics because of the Pope's many commitments.</p>
<p>Commentators have questioned why such a simple operation was not carried out sooner if the problem has existed for at least nine months, laying the Pope low several times.</p>
<p>The statement by his doctor said &quot;all other aspects of the Pope's health do not give rise for particular concern&quot; and that he had been receiving regular specialist check-ups.</p>
<p>Regarding the Pope's trembling left hand, chief Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro-Valls has told reporters in past weeks that the Pope may be suffering from an &quot;extrapyramidal&quot; neurological disorder.</p>
<p>Doctors say Parkinson's disease -- manifested by trembling and muscle rigidity and which can affect speech and facial expressions -- is one type of an extrapyramidal illness.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
