<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55832" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pope worked with CIA against Soviet Union - book.</title>
<headline>Pope worked with CIA against Soviet Union - book.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul II and former U.S. President Ronald Reagan established an informal &quot;secret alliance&quot; to bring about the fall of Communism, according to a new book co-authored by Watergate investigative reporter Carl Bernstein.</p>
<p>The book, &quot;His Holiness: John Paul II and the Hidden History of Our Time,&quot; by Bernstein and Italian journalist Marco Politi, claims that Reagan and his Central Intelligence Agency chief William Casey traded sensitive intelligence information with the Polish-born pontiff because they viewed the 20 block-long Vatican as a &quot;spiritual superpower.&quot;</p>
<p>The book, which will be published this week by Doubleday, also says that the Reagan administration secretly spent $50 million to keep Solidarity, Poland's independent trade union organisation, alive from 1982 to 1989.</p>
<p>The pope was kept informed, although he was careful not to learn too many of the details, the book said.</p>
<p>Bernstein and Politi did not draw a conclusion as to whether the Soviet Union or Communist Bulgaria was behind the assassination attempt on the pope's life in 1981, but the book said Casey and the pope's closest aides were convinced that Bulgaria was involved -- an idea rejected by the pontiff.</p>
<p>The authors said the pope did not want to see investigations pursued out of fear that if the Soviet Union was involved it would throw international relations into a hopeless crisis.</p>
<p>They quote the pope as telling a close friend, &quot;Whoever was responsible was literally doing the work of the devil. It doesn't interest me because it was the devil who did this thing and the devil can conspire in 1,000 ways ... &quot;</p>
<p>But the authors said they obtained top secret Soviet documents that detailed increased Soviet preoccupation with the pope and the frustration of Soviet leaders with Poland for not cracking down on the Catholic church in the weeks preceding the assassination attempt by Turkish gunman Mehmet Ali Agca.</p>
<p>After the attempt, the pope ordered the statue of the Fatima virgin brought to the Vatican where he prayed before it, asking for the liberation of the Soviet Union from atheism.</p>
<p>The book said: &quot;Beginning in the spring of 1981, the Reagan administration maintained an intelligence shuttle at the highest level between the White House and the pope, who was regularly briefed by Casey and Vernon Walters, a former CIA deputy director. Between them Walters and Casey secretly visited the pope about 15 times over a six-year period to discuss matters of mutual importance.&quot;</p>
<p>It added that the pope received &quot;some of America's most carefully guarded secrets and sophisticated political analysis: information from satellites, from intelligence agents, from electronic evesdropping, from political discussions at the White House, State Department and CIA. And the United States received information from the pope.&quot;</p>
<p>The book also said that during this period of Vatican-U.S. collaboration, the Reagan administration reinforced the pope's opposition to abortion by blocking funds for family planning programmes around the world.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
