<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59532" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Feuding France awaits ailing Pope.</title>
<headline>Feuding France awaits ailing Pope.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Amid unprecedented controversy over secularism, history and Church dogma, Pope John Paul begins a four-day visit to France on Thursday with a gruelling schedule that will test his shaky health.</p>
<p>Unlike the 76-year-old Pontiff's four previous pastoral visits, this trip has been clouded by rows over the separation of Church and state, the historical significance of the baptism of Clovis 1,500 years ago and papal teaching on sexual morality.</p>
<p>Despite the disputes, opinion polls show 79 percent of French people are indifferent to the visit. The crowds expected to greet the Pope in Tours, Brittany and Reims will be paltry compared to the huge throngs he draws in the Third World.</p>
<p>Some 45 million of France's nearly 60 million citizens are nominally Roman Catholics, but only six million regularly attend church. Even among that minority, many say they feel the Pope's dogged rejection of birth control, abortion and homosexuality are out of date.</p>
<p>Militant secularists plan a colourful counter-rally on Sunday in the Place de la Republique in central Paris. Security will be tight at the Pope's 21 public appearances following discovery of a crude bomb two weeks ago at a church in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre, where he is to pray at a saint's tomb.</p>
<p>&quot;These polemics which have sullied the Pope's visit and impugned the Church's motives have caused a real mobilisation of the faithful,&quot; Bernard Lagoutte, general secretary of the French Bishops' Conference, told Reuters.</p>
<p>All eyes will be on the health of the Polish-born Pontiff, who looked tired and frail during a trip to Hungary this month, prompting the Vatican to disclose on Saturday that he would undergo surgery to remove his appendix next month.</p>
<p>Vatican-watchers questioned the official diagnosis of an inflammation of the appendix, saying it did not explain the sometimes uncontrollable trembling of his left hand.</p>
<p>French police officers said arrangements had been made to treat the Pope at three hospitals on his route in an emergency.</p>
<p>President Jacques Chirac, an occasional churchgoer who made a state visit to the Vatican in February, is to greet Pope John Paul at an air base outside Tours, in western France, on Thursday morning and the two will hold private talks.</p>
<p>In deference to France's secular constitution, however, the president is not to attend any of the religious ceremonies, including the celebration on Sunday of the anniversary of Clovis's baptism in Reims -- the climax of the papal visit.</p>
<p>Clovis's conversion to Catholicism around 496 A.D. -- modern historians say it was probably later -- is seen by many as one of the founding acts of France, although his kingdom then covered more of western Germany, the Netherlands and Belgium.</p>
<p>At issue in fierce public debate is whether the baptism of Clovis makes France a &quot;Christian nation&quot;, as the extreme-right National Front asserts, and whether the warrior king was really a Catholic hero or a Dark Ages war criminal -- or both.</p>
<p>Anti-immigration National Front leader Jean-Marie Le Pen has said he plans to attend the Reims mass, although the Church says he was not invited and will not be admitted to a VIP enclosure.</p>
<p>The Bishops' Conference on Tuesday joined a chorus of condemnation of Le Pen's espousal of racial inequality. &quot;Such statements are unacceptable to a Christian,&quot; it said in a statement, adding that they endangered the whole of society.</p>
<p>Secularists have also latched on to the public subsidies for some of the Pope's public events -- estimated by the French bishops' conference to cost five to six million francs (around $1 million).</p>
<p>For security reasons, the government has provided air bases, aircraft and helicopters for the Pontiff's travels, as well as mobilising some 6,000 police and paramilitary gendarmes, elite snipers and bodyguards to protect him and control the crowds.</p>
<p>But the left-wing opposition in Reims won a court order banning the city from paying for a 1.5-million-franc ($300,000) podium, and other courts have banned several million francs in subsidies under a 1905 law strictly separating Church and state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
