<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61734" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French hospitals on alert for Pope's visit.</title>
<headline>French hospitals on alert for Pope's visit.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Jarry</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hospitals in the French city of Tours will be on alert from Thursday when Pope John Paul arrives on a four-day trip, in frail health and drawing vast crowds, officials said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The medical alert is aimed both at safeguarding the 76-year-old Pontiff, who will spend three nights in Tours, as well as up to 150,000 people expected to pour into the western city during his trip, doubling the normal population.</p>
<p>&quot;We're on a pre-emergency alert from today and until Sunday,&quot; said Patrick Faugerolas, spokesman for Tours University Hospital. &quot;We've organised it so that we should have several hundred beds free.&quot;</p>
<p>The Vatican said at the weekend the Pope will enter hospital in Rome for surgery to remove his appendix, probably in the second week of October. But it has not commented on a sometimes violent trembling of the Pope's left hand, a potential sign of Parkinson's Disease.</p>
<p>Hospital operating theatres and special rooms would be kept free in case the Pope or President Jacques Chirac, who will greet the Pontiff on arrival in Tours on Thursday, needs treatment. Such hospital measures were routine for such visits.</p>
<p>The Pontiff's visit to France, his fifth, has stirred up unprecedented controversy about the separation of church and state in a country where 80 percent of the population are nominal Catholics.</p>
<p>Police have not ruled out violent attacks, even though the main anti-Pope rally will be in Paris when he is in the north-eastern city of Reims on Sunday.</p>
<p>Unknown attackers planted a crude bomb that failed to explode early this month in a church where the Pontiff is due to pray. A group of anarchists threw cream pies at priests in Nantes cathedral last week.</p>
<p>Six thousand police, paramilitary gendarmes, bodyguards and elite sharpshooters will be on duty to protect the Pope and control crowds.</p>
<p>An ambulance will accompany the Pope wherever he travels on the trip. He is scheduled to make 21 public appearances. A helicopter ambulance in Tours will be ready to take off within minutes if needed.</p>
<p>The Defence Ministry also said that a Falcon 900 jet with medical facilities will be on stand-by at the Villacoublay military airbase near Paris.</p>
<p>There will also be emergency medical posts in the towns the Pope will visit -- Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre, Sainte-Anne-d'Auray and Reims.</p>
<p>Faugerolas said that hospitals were making beds available by delaying routine hospital stays for people from the region.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
