<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62470" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Pope's health will figure large on trip to France.</title>
<headline>Pope's health will figure large on trip to France.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scepticism about the Vatican's pronouncements on the shaky health of Pope John Paul will accompany the 76-year-old Pontiff on Thursday when he begins a gruelling and controversial four-day trip to France.</p>
<p>The visit is the Pope's final foreign trip of the year before he enters hospital in Rome for surgery to remove his appendix, probably in the second week of October.</p>
<p>The operation was announced by the Vatican last weekend when it finally revealed that an inflammation of the appendix was the cause of three fevers which have struck the Polish-born Pope since last Christmas.</p>
<p>The statement, issued by the Pope's personal physician Renato Buzzonetti, said there were no signs of a recurrence of an intestinal tumour removed in 1992 and that other aspects of his health were not cause &quot;for particular attention&quot;.</p>
<p>But the lack of explanation in the statement of a sometimes violent trembling of the Pope's left hand, a potential sign of Parkinson's Disease, only fuelled speculation that the Vatican is continuing to hold back on his true state of health.</p>
<p>The trembling was evident on Wednesday when the Pope, who coughed several times and appeared in slight discomfort, addressed pilgrims gathered at the Vatican for his weekly two-hour general audience.</p>
<p>Speaking from his throne in slow French, he said he would use his visit to France to appeal for solidarity with the weakest members of society.</p>
<p>&quot;I intend to launch a new appeal for solidarity with all those who suffer in their bodies and in their heart, those for whom life is precarious and threatened, both in France and beyond its borders,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>His remarks followed an attack by the French Bishops' Conference on Tuesday on anti-immigration National Front leader Jean-Marie Le Pen for espousing racial inequality.</p>
<p>The hard-right leader has said he hopes to attend Pope John Paul's mass in Reims next Sunday celebrating the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of king Clovis, although the Church said on Monday he had not been invited.</p>
<p>Clovis's conversion to Catholicism around 496 A.D. -- modern historians say it was probably later -- is seen by many as one of the founding acts of France, although his kingdom then covered more of western Germany, the Netherlands and Belgium.</p>
<p>The visit will be the Pope's fifth to France since 1980 and will take him to Tours, Brittany and Reims.</p>
<p>One of his most demanding this year, it will involve nine flights by plane and helicopter, a dozen speeches and 21 public appearances including three open-air masses.</p>
<p>The visit will take place amid unprecedented controversy over the separation of Church and state, the significance of the Clovis conversion and the Pope's contested rejection of birth control, abortion and homosexuality.</p>
<p>Militant secularists plan a colourful counter-rally on Sunday in central Paris. Security will be intense following discovery of a crude bomb two weeks ago at a church in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre, where he is to pray at a saint's tomb.</p>
<p>French police said arrangements had been made to treat the Pope at three hospitals on his route in an emergency.</p>
<p>The Pope, who appeared fatigued and frail on a 36-hour trip to Hungary in early September, has undergone surgery five times during his 18-year papacy, including twice after an assassination attempt in 1981.</p>
<p>His spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, said in Hungary that four foreign trips are planned for next year.</p>
<p>He has told reporters in past weeks that the trembling in the Pope's left hand may be the result of an &quot;extrapyramidal&quot; neurological disorder. The shaking has until now been linked by the Vatican to the 1981 shooting.</p>
<p>Doctors say Parkinson's Disease, manifested by trembling and muscle rigidity which can affect speech and facial expressions, is one type of extrapyramidal illness.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
