<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64629" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope skirts religious controversy in France.</title>
<headline>Pope skirts religious controversy in France.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, on the first day of a gruelling four-day trip to France, skirted controversy over the role of the Church and his moral teachings on Thursday to stress solidarity with the poor and the sick.</p>
<p>On his last foreign trip before entering hospital for an operation to remove his appendix next month, the 76-year-old Pontiff looked on relatively robust form -- he walked unaided, waved to crowds and joked about the rainy weather.</p>
<p>The Pope and French President Jacques Chirac, who met the Polish Pope on his arrival in Tours, both dodged French feuding over the separation of Church and State and criticisms of the conservative papal teachings such as against birth control.</p>
<p>After private talks with Chirac in Tours, he said: &quot;I am mindful of the fact that French society faces many problems as, for example, an economic crisis which is also the case for many countries throughout the world.</p>
<p>&quot;My thoughts go first to all those who are suffering trials of all sorts, particularly those who must bear with poverty, to those who are victims of prejudice, or bias, those who lack security and those who are ill,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On his sixth visit to France, including a trip to the Indian Ocean island of La Reunion, the Pope praised French aid to developing countries in a &quot;long tradition of solidarity and fraternity for their fellow men&quot;.</p>
<p>He also hailed French Catholics' dialogue with the country's large Moslem and Jewish communities. Moslem leaders welcomed the Pope and wished him well in a mission to foster dialogue between all faiths.</p>
<p>Neither the Pope nor Chirac, accused of violating a 1905 law separating Church and State by helping fund the visit, used France's traditional Catholic title of &quot;eldest daughter of the Church&quot;. The Pope used the title on his first visit in 1980.</p>
<p>Chirac said France was &quot;proud of its roots&quot; as a nation that blended secular traditions of the 1789 Revolution, respectful of religious freedom, with a history of spirituality. Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics.</p>
<p>Chirac said the Holy See and France stood together to promote &quot;tolerance, dignity, justice and peace&quot;, and praised the Pope as a &quot;tireless pilgrim of the absolute&quot;.</p>
<p>After visiting Tours, the Pope made a helicopter pilgrimage to a shrine in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre where a crude bomb was defused two weeks ago. Unknown attackers had scrawled &quot;In nomine-Pope-BOOM!&quot; on the wall of the crypt.</p>
<p>In Saint-Laurent, he prayed at the tomb of Saint Louis-Marie Grignion de Montfort, an 18th-century missionary whose Latin motto &quot;Totus Tuus&quot; (All Yours) he has adopted as a symbol of devotion to the Virgin Mary.</p>
<p>He earlier praised Catholic &quot;martyrs&quot; from the Vendee region around Saint-Laurent killed in an uprising they launched against the 1789 French Revolution. But he balanced the remarks by saying there had been sin on both sides.</p>
<p>&quot;You are the heirs of men and women who were courageous enough to remain faithful to the Church of Jesus Christ at a time when its freedom and independence were threatened,&quot; the Pontiff told a crowd of about 3,000 mostly young people.</p>
<p>An estimated 100,000 people died when Paris's revolutionary government stamped out the Vendee uprising from 1793-95.</p>
<p>During the visit to Saint-Laurent, the Pope briefly shook hands and joked about a break in the rain. &quot;The earth needs rain but sometimes we'd like it to be a bit lighter. This has happened right here, thanks to you,&quot; he said to applause.</p>
<p>Some 6,000 police, paramilitary gendarmes, bodyguards and marksmen are on duty to guard the Pontiff during the trip, which will also take him to Brittany and the eastern city of Reims. He will spend three nights in Tours.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including anarchists, freemasons and a police trade union are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday, when the Pope will be in Reims, to protest at the Pope and back the secular ideals of the Revolution.</p>
<p>The Pope will be in Reims for the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism.</p>
<p>But he avoided suggesting the traditional Catholic view that Clovis's conversion was the baptism of France as a nation.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show many French citizens are indifferent to the visit, and to arcane disputes about Clovis.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
