<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64651" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope visits western France religious stronghold.</title>
<headline>Pope visits western France religious stronghold.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Jarry</byline>
<dateline>SAINTE-ANNE D'AURAY, France 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul flies to Brittany on Friday on the first visit by a head of the Roman Catholic Church to this western region, a stronghold of religion and resistance to secularism in France.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pontiff, who looked relatively robust and walked unaided on the first day of his four-day trip, faces another gruelling schedule as he flies from Tours to Sainte-Anne d'Auray, 130 km (80 miles) northwest of Nantes.</p>
<p>He is to hold an open-air mass with 70 French bishops before some 150,000 faithful and address 3,000 young couples with their children. He is expected to urge the faithful to spread the message of Christ and extoll family values before returning to Tours.</p>
<p>According to tradition, Sainte-Anne, the Virgin Mary's mother, appeared to farmer Yves Nicolazic in Auray in 1624, ordering him to rebuild a ruined chapel.</p>
<p>Wrecked again during the 1789 revolution, the chapel was later rebuilt into a basilica which became a focus of resistance to a 1905 Republican law to separate the state and the Church.</p>
<p>Thousands of Bretons gathered at the basilica in March 1906 to foil the official inventory of church property ordered under the law. The government had to send in troops to Sainte-Anne to carry out the inventory later that year.</p>
<p>On his visit to Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre on Thursday, Pope John Paul hailed those who fought in the brutally suppressed 1793-95 Vendee uprising against the French Revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;You are the heirs of men and women who were courageous enough to remain faithful to the Church of Jesus Christ at a time when its freedom and independence were threatened,&quot; he said. But he added there was sin on both sides.</p>
<p>The Pontiff appeared keen to skirt controversy over the role of the Church which marked preparations for his visit, stressing solidarity with the poor and sick rather than moral teachings.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including leftists, anarchists and freemasons are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday to back the secular ideals of the Revolution and protest against the Pope's ban on condoms, birth control and abortion.</p>
<p>The Pope and French President Jacques Chirac, who has been accused of violating the 1905 law by helping fund the sixth papal visit to France, both dodged feuding over the separation of Church and State and criticism of the Pope's conservative teachings when they met in Tours.</p>
<p>The Pope spoke for those suffering from poverty, prejudice, insecurity and illness. He praised French aid to developing countries and French Catholics' dialogue with the country's large Moslem and Jewish communities.</p>
<p>Conservative Chirac said France was &quot;proud of its roots&quot; as a nation that blended secular traditions of the 1789 Revolution, respectful of religious freedom, with a history of spirituality.</p>
<p>Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics, but only six million attend mass, and many of these believe Pope John Paul's conservative teachings are out of date. Opinion polls show most French people are indifferent to his visit.</p>
<p>Security was stringent after a crude bomb was defused two weeks ago at Saint-Laurent's basilica. Unknown attackers had scrawled &quot;In nomine-Pope-BOOM!&quot; on the wall of the crypt.</p>
<p>The Pope will be in Reims on Sunday for the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism.</p>
<p>But he avoided evoking the traditional Catholic view that Clovis's conversion was the baptism of France as a nation, and using the country's traditional Catholic title as &quot;the Church's eldest daughter&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAINTE-ANNE D'AURAY, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
