<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65315" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Frail Pope starting controversial visit to France.</title>
<headline>Frail Pope starting controversial visit to France.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Jarry</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul arrives in France on Thursday in frail health for a four-day trip to a once staunchly Roman Catholic nation torn by controversy about the role of the Church and the Pontiff's moral teachings.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac will greet the 76-year-old Pope when he lands at Tours airport in western France, the first stop of a gruelling trip that will take him to Brittany, Vendee and the eastern city of Reims.</p>
<p>On his first day, the Pope will travel with his Popemobile into a rainswept Tours, have talks with Chirac and make a helicopter pilgrimage amid tight security to a shrine where a crude anti-Pope bomb was defused two weeks ago.</p>
<p>Unknown attackers had scrawled &quot;In nomine-Pope-BOOM!&quot; on the wall of the church in Saint-Laurent-Sur-Sevre.</p>
<p>About 6,000 police, paramilitary gendarmes, bodyguards and marksmen will be on duty to guard the Pontiff during his last trip abroad before he enters hospital in October for an operation to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>&quot;I intend to launch a new appeal for solidarity with all those who suffer in their bodies and in their heart, those for whom life is precarious and threatened, both in France and beyond its borders,&quot; the Pontiff said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Even though the Pontiff has avoided controversy in talking about his fifth visit to France, he has awoken unprecedented protests in a country that long vaunted its fidelity to Rome.</p>
<p>Apart from the homemade bomb, the most dramatic opposition was a group of custard-pie-throwing demonstrators who disrupted a service in Nantes cathedral last week.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including anarchists, free-masons and a police trade union are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday, when the Pope will be in Reims, to protest at the Pope and back the secular ideals of the 1789 French Revolution.</p>
<p>They accuse Chirac of violating laws separating Church and State by partly funding the visit and celebrations of the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in Western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism in Reims.</p>
<p>&quot;The Unwieldy Visitor&quot;, headlined the leftist daily Liberation. Some moderate bishops felt concerned at the visit, and Chirac would meet the Pontiff for only 20 minutes so as to signal the state-Church divide, it said.</p>
<p>Paris Archbishop Jean-Marie Lustiger dismissed the controversy, telling RTL radio that it was &quot;preposterous&quot; to suggest the French republic was in any danger.</p>
<p>&quot;France has always remained faithful to the Holy See, despite the revolution and the separation of Church and state,&quot; echoed the Vatican's &quot;culture minister&quot; Paul Poupard in an interview with the daily Le Parisien.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show many French citizens are indifferent to the visit, and to arcane disputes about Clovis.</p>
<p>A CSA poll published in Le Parisien showed that support for the Pope has waned since his last visit in 1988, reflecting French disaffection with the Pontiff's teachings against birth control, abortion or homosexuality.</p>
<p>Fifty-one percent had reserves or strongly disapproved of his actions during his papacy, up from 26 percent in 1988. And only 22 percent of the 1,004 people quizzed from September 16-17 saw him as being &quot;open to the world&quot; against 46 percent in 1988.</p>
<p>The Pope's trip on Thursday afternoon to Saint-Laurent-Sur-Sevre is to enable him to pray at the tomb of Saint Louis-Marie Grignion de Montfort, an 18th century missionary whose writings the Pope has admired for decades.</p>
<p>The Pope, who personally asked to visit the tomb, adopted the saint's Latin motto &quot;Totus Tuus&quot; (I am all yours) as a symbol of devotion to the Virgin Mary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
