<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65439" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope visits France, dodges controversy.</title>
<headline>Pope visits France, dodges controversy.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, starting a four-day visit to France on Thursday that will test his shaky health, dodged controversies about his trip and said his thoughts were with the suffering and the poor.</p>
<p>On his last foreign trip before entering hospital for an operation to remove his appendix next month, the Pontiff walked unaided down the steps of his airliner after it landed at Tours, western France, to be greeted by President Jacques Chirac.</p>
<p>Amid heavy security, he left the airport in a bullet-proof car but switched to his Popemobile in central Tours to wave to sparse lines of wellwishers who braved rain to cheer him.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pontiff looked alert and more robust than on a visit to Hungary two weeks ago. Tours is the first stop of a gruelling trip that will take him to Brittany, Vendee and the eastern city of Reims.</p>
<p>In his first speech on a trip including 21 public appearances, the Pope skirted controversies in France over the role of the Church in a modern secular state and opposition to his strict moral teachings on issues such as birth control.</p>
<p>&quot;I am mindful of the fact that French society faces many problems as, for example, an economic crisis which is also the case for many countries throughout the world,&quot; the Pope said after meeting Chirac in Tours in the Prefecture building.</p>
<p>&quot;My thoughts go first to all those who are suffering trials of all sorts, particularly those who must bear with poverty, to those who are victims of prejudice, or bias, those who lack security and those who are ill,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On his sixth visit to France, including a trip to the Indian Ocean island of La Reunion, the Pope praised French aid to developing countries in a &quot;long tradition of solidarity and fraternity for their fellow men&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;These gestures of friendship must be accompanied on the part of the Western world by a new attitude, refusing to take advantage of these poor nations simply for the goods they produce,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>He also hailed French Catholics' dialogue with the country's large Moslem and Jewish communities.</p>
<p>Neither the Pope nor Chirac, accused of violating a 1905 law separating Church and State by helping fund the visit, used France's traditional Catholic title of &quot;eldest daughter of the Church&quot;. The Pope used the title on his first visit in 1980.</p>
<p>Chirac said France was &quot;proud of its roots&quot; as a nation that blended secular traditions of the 1789 Revolution, respectful of religious freedom, with a history of spirituality. Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics.</p>
<p>Chirac said the Holy See and France stood together to promote &quot;tolerance, dignity, justice and peace&quot;, and praised the Pope as a &quot;tireless pilgrim of the absolute&quot;.</p>
<p>In the afternoon, the Pope will make a helicopter pilgrimage amid tight security to a shrine where a crude bomb was defused two weeks ago. Unknown attackers had scrawled &quot;In nomine-Pope- BOOM!&quot; on the wall of the church in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre.</p>
<p>Some 6,000 police, paramilitary gendarmes, bodyguards and marksmen were on duty to guard the Pontiff during the trip.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including anarchists, freemasons and a police trade union are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday, when the Pope will be in Reims, to protest at the Pope and back the secular ideals of the 1789 French Revolution.</p>
<p>The Pope will be in Reims for the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Christianity.</p>
<p>The Pontiff avoided the traditional Catholic view that Clovis's conversion amounted to the baptism of France. &quot;By joining the Catholic faith, (Clovis) was able to guide different people towards the construction of a single nation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show many French citizens are indifferent to the visit, and to arcane disputes about Clovis.</p>
<p>A CSA poll published in Le Parisien showed that support for the Pope has waned since his last visit in 1988, reflecting French disaffection with the Pontiff's teachings against birth control, abortion or homosexuality.</p>
<p>Fifty-one percent had reserves or strongly disapproved of his actions during his papacy, up from 26 percent in 1988. And only 22 percent of the 1,004 people quizzed on September 16 and just 17 percent saw him as being &quot;open to the world&quot; against 46 percent in 1988.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
