<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66005" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac welcomes ailing Pope to France.</title>
<headline>Chirac welcomes ailing Pope to France.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Jarry</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Amid fears for his health, Pope John Paul arrived in France on Thursday for a four-day visit that will test his stamina and his ability to rally the Roman Catholic faithful amid controversy over the Church's role.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pontiff, due to undergo surgery to remove his appendix next month, landed at the Saint-Symphorien air base near the western city of Tours aboard a special Alitalia flight, bearing the papal crest and the Vatican and French flags.</p>
<p>He looked much fitter and less exhausted than on a visit to Hungary earlier this month as he walked slowly but firmly down the gangway beneath a white umbrella and shook hands with President Jacques Chirac and his wife Bernadette.</p>
<p>Despite steady rain, the Pope reviewed a Republican Guard honour guard and shook hands with a long line of dignitaries before driving to a private meeting with Chirac in Tours.</p>
<p>The visit, packed with 21 public appearances, is the Pope's final foreign trip of the year before he enters hospital in Rome, probably in the second week of October.</p>
<p>French media highlighted controversy over his visit. The left-of-centre Liberation called him &quot;The Cumbersome Visitor&quot; in its front-page headline, while the tabloid Le Parisien stresed disaffection between the French people and a Pontiff they increasingly see as out of touch with his times.</p>
<p>Tours is the first stop of a trip that will take him to Brittany, Vendee and the eastern city of Reims.</p>
<p>For security reasons and to enable the Pope to sit, a bullet-proof car replaced his Popemobile on the drive into a rainswept Tours. He was to make a helicopter pilgrimage later to a shrine where a crude anti-Pope bomb was defused two weeks ago.</p>
<p>Unknown attackers had scrawled &quot;In nomine-Pope-BOOM!&quot; on the wall of the church in Saint-Laurent-sur-Sevre.</p>
<p>About 6,000 police, paramilitary gendarmes, bodyguards and marksmen were on duty to guard the Pontiff during the visit.</p>
<p>&quot;I intend to launch a new appeal for solidarity with all those who suffer in their bodies and in their heart, those for whom life is precarious and threatened, both in France and beyond its borders,&quot; the Pontiff said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Even though he has avoided controversy in talking about his fifth visit to France, the Pope has awoken unprecedented protests in a country that long vaunted its fidelity to Rome.</p>
<p>Apart from the bomb attempt, the most dramatic opposition was when a group of anarchists disrupted a service in Nantes cathedral last week throwing cream pies.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including anarchists, freemasons and a police trade union are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday, when the Pope will be in Reims, to protest at the Pope and back the secular ideals of the 1789 French Revolution.</p>
<p>They accuse Chirac of violating laws separating Church and State by partly funding the visit and celebrations of the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in Western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism in Reims.</p>
<p>The president, an occasional churchgoer, was to have only a 20-minute meeting with the Pope and attend none of the religious ceremonies, underlining the state-Church divide.</p>
<p>But Paris Archbishop Jean-Marie Lustiger dismissed the controversy, telling RTL radio that it was &quot;preposterous&quot; to suggest the French Republic was in any danger.</p>
<p>&quot;France has always remained faithful to the Holy See, despite the revolution and the separation of Church and state,&quot; echoed the Vatican's &quot;culture minister&quot;, Paul Poupard, in an interview with the daily Le Parisien.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show many French citizens are indifferent to the visit, and to arcane disputes about Clovis.</p>
<p>A CSA poll published in Le Parisien showed that support for the Pope has waned since his last visit in 1988, reflecting French disaffection with the Pontiff's teachings against birth control, abortion or homosexuality.</p>
<p>Fifty-one percent had reservations or strongly disapproved of his actions during his papacy, up from 26 percent in 1988. And only 22 percent of the 1,004 people quizzed on September 16 and 17 saw him as being &quot;open to the world&quot; against 46 percent in 1988.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
