<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66820" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Chronology of Yeltsin's heart problems.</title>
<headline>Chronology of Yeltsin's heart problems.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>A top Russian doctor, announcing the extension of President Boris Yeltsin's hospital stay, said on Friday that the president faced a &quot;big and serious&quot; operation on his heart.</p>
<p>Following is a chronology of Yeltsin's heart problems, both real and rumoured.</p>
<p>October 1991 - Yeltsin is ordered to take two weeks' rest after aides said he had suffered minor heart problems.</p>
<p>February 1992 - Yeltsin tells French television: &quot;I have never had any heart trouble. Every day I have a cold shower -- I am in very good shape.&quot;</p>
<p>July 1995 - Yeltsin goes into hospital with an ischaemic heart condition -- a blood supply problem. He spends two weeks in hospital followed by two weeks in a sanatorium.</p>
<p>October 26, 1995 -  Yeltsin is taken to hospital and doctors say it is again an ischaemic heart condition. He moves to the sanatorium a month later and leaves on New Year's Eve.</p>
<p>June 28, 1996 - Yeltsin misses a meeting with farmers between the two rounds of the Russian presidential election. Aides say he has a sore throat.</p>
<p>August 2, 1996 - A Yeltsin aide says the president is suffering from &quot;colossal weariness&quot; after his election campaign and needs two months of peace and quiet.</p>
<p>August 9, 1996 - In his first public appearance since June 26, Yeltsin takes his oath of office. He appears for just 16 minutes and speaks for only 45 seconds.</p>
<p>August 19, 1996 - Yeltsin's spokesman denies a report in U.S. magazine Time, which said that Yeltsin would go to a Swiss clinic for a heart bypass operation after suffering further heart problems in the second half of July.</p>
<p>August 23, 1996 - The Kremlin press office denies a press report that Yeltsin will have treatment at a special clinic.</p>
<p>Sept 5, 1996 - Yeltsin, in a shock announcement breaking with secretive Kremlin tradition, says he has agreed to have heart surgery, later announced to be a heart bypass operation, probably to take place at the end of the month in Moscow.</p>
<p>Sept 12, 1996 - NTV commercial television says foreign doctors will participate in Yeltsin's surgery.</p>
<p>Sept 13, 1996 - Yeltsin goes into Moscow's Central Clinical Hospital for a weekend of pre-surgery tests.</p>
<p>Sept 16-17, 1996 - The Kremlin twice says Yeltsin's hospital visit will be extended, initially for two days, then for the rest of the week.</p>
<p>Sept 19, 1996, Kremlin spokesman Sergei Yastrzhembsky says doctors will meet on September 25 to set the date for Yeltsin's operation.</p>
<p>Sept 20, 1996 - Top Kremlin doctor Sergei Mironov says Yeltsin's surgery will be &quot;big and serious&quot;. He extends the president's pre-surgery hospital stay for a third time.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
