<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67267" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope honours Saint Martin, who helped clothe poor.</title>
<headline>Pope honours Saint Martin, who helped clothe poor.</headline>
<byline>Christian Curtenelle</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, on the third day of a four-day trip to France, was to celebrate a mass on Saturday honouring the memory of Saint Martin of Tours, who tore his cloak to share it with a poor man who was cold.</p>
<p>The mass, marking the 1,600th anniversary of the holy man's death, was expected to give the Pontiff an opportunity to address the continuing need for charity in modern times.</p>
<p>Saint Martin, at the time a Roman officer, shared his cloak during the fourth century at the gates to the northern city of Amiens. He later was bishop of Tours and ultimately became the first non-martyred saint, church officials said.</p>
<p>Organisers of the Pope's trip, his last before he enters hospital next month to have his appendix removed, thought Saint Martin an appropriate symbol for the occasion.</p>
<p>&quot;One cannot remember the man who shared his cloak without thinking of those who are today's poor,&quot; Jean Honore, Tours' current archbishop, wrote recently.</p>
<p>In the hamlet of Saint-Anne d'Auray in Brittany, western France, on Friday, couples cheered and applauded when the Pope told them to respect life from the moment of conception.</p>
<p>His remarks defending traditional Christian marriage and the family were his first mention of sexual morality during his visit to France, where opinion polls have shown a majority of people in a once fervent Roman Catholic nation either opposes or ignores his strict bans on abortion and birth control.</p>
<p>&quot;Every human being that is conceived has the right to exist,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope, 76, also praised marital fidelity and said the family, in France as elsewhere, faced not only economic and social difficulties but also moral challenges.</p>
<p>But he appeared to steer clear of many of the controversies surrounding his visit.</p>
<p>His address to families did not use the word &quot;abortion&quot; and it contained a reminder that separated and divorced couples &quot;remain members of the Christian community&quot;.</p>
<p>The trip has been billed as a test of his ability to rally his flock in the face of controversy over the separation of Church and state in France and the Pontiff's own strict opposition to contraception, abortion and homosexuality.</p>
<p>Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics, but only six million attend mass and many of these believe the Pope's conservative teachings are outdated.</p>
<p>The trip has also generated interest due to persistent rumours about the Pope's fragile health, though he has so far appeared relatively robust.</p>
<p>While some object to the Pope's conservative moral views, others criticise his visit as violating the strict separation of church and state since the government is helping to pay for logistics and security.</p>
<p>Still others fault the Pope's plan to travel to the eastern city of Reims on Sunday to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Catholicism.</p>
<p>They charge that the Pope's presence in Reims would seem to sanction the extreme nationalistic view -- embraced by France's far-right National Front -- that the baptism marked the creation of a Catholic France. Clovis's kingdom stretched from what is now Germany and the Netherlands into France.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including leftists, anarchists and freemasons are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday to back the secular ideals of the French Revolution and protest against the Pope's teachings on sexual morality.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
