<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67794" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope begs French Catholics to answer indifference.</title>
<headline>Pope begs French Catholics to answer indifference.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>SAINTE-ANNE D'AURAY, France 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul said on Friday that a &quot;climate of indifference&quot; threatened religious faith in France and urged Roman Catholics to respond by spreading the Christian message.</p>
<p>He chose the western region of Brittany, for long a religious bastion opposed to the secular traditions of the 1789 Revolution, to confront the issue of falling congregations and diminishing adherence to Church teachings in modern France.</p>
<p>&quot;This faith, which is your common heritage, is met with numerous problems,&quot; the 76-year-old Pope told worshippers gathered in bright sunshine at this Catholic shrine for his first outdoor mass of a four-day visit to France.</p>
<p>&quot;For sure, the causes to worry are numerous. Thus we see develop a climate of indifference and individualism,&quot; he said in a sermon from a huge grey and blue wooden altar platform erected in front of a crowd estimated by police at 120,000.</p>
<p>&quot;Too often the Christian faith grows weak, noticeably in the younger generation, which really struggles to acquire their religious heritage.&quot;</p>
<p>But, referring to what he called &quot;numerous signs of vitality&quot; in the Church, he urged the faithful to spread a message of Christian hope. &quot;Like your forefathers, be the builders of the Church in the new generations,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope, on the second day of his final foreign visit before surgery to remove his appendix next month, appeared relatively robust at the service, the biggest event so far on a gruelling schedule that will test his fragile health.</p>
<p>&quot;Let us thank God for the sun,&quot; he remarked to the crowd after constant rain had fallen on the first day of his trip. &quot;Thank you for coming in such large numbers...I must say that I have found a lot of hope here,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope's tour has been billed as a test of his ability to rally his flock in France in the face of controversy over the separation of Church and state and the Pontiff's own strict opposition to contraception, abortion and homosexuality.</p>
<p>He was likely to use a meeting with some 3,000 young couples and their children later on Friday in the hamlet of Saint-Anne d'Auray, for centuries a shrine to the mother of the Virgin Mary, to extol Christian marriage and the family.</p>
<p>Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics, but only six million regularly attend mass, and many of these believe the Pope's conservative teachings are out of date.</p>
<p>Opinion polls have shown that most French people are indifferent to his visit, his fifth to mainland France.</p>
<p>A French bishop sacked by the Vatican for his liberal views predicted on Friday that the papacy would rapidly lose its role in setting moral standards for Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>Modern society rejected &quot;this type of authority...This function of the authority of the Church will quickly collapse,&quot; &quot;Red Cleric' Jacques Gaillot told France Inter radio.</p>
<p>Gaillot was ousted from his diocese in Normandy in 1995 and transferred to a non-existent ancient seat in the Sahara for his liberal views on issues ranging from condom use to abortion.</p>
<p>He also faulted the Pope's plan to honour a fifth century king in France who converted to Christianity, saying it would help the far right and Roman Catholic traditionalists.</p>
<p>The Pontiff is to travel to the eastern city of Reims on Sunday to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to embrace Catholicism. Traditionalists see him as a father of France.</p>
<p>Seventy groups including leftists, anarchists and freemasons are planning a rally in Paris on the same day to back the secular ideals of the French Revolution and protest against the Pope's teachings on sexual morality.</p>
<p>The Vatican's chief spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, played down opposition to the visit, which has been blanketed in tight security after a crude bomb was left two weeks ago at a basilica which the Pope visited on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Up until now we haven't seen any protests,&quot; Navarro-Valls told reporters. &quot;The French press has talked about demonstrations but it seems to be fizzling out.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAINTE-ANNE D'AURAY, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
