<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68856" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope calls for new solidarity with the weak.</title>
<headline>Pope calls for new solidarity with the weak.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul struck out at the exclusion of society's weakest members on Saturday, telling a church filled with the sick and marginalised that they were a living image of God.</p>
<p>Launching a strong appeal for solidarity at the emotional meeting, held in the basilica of Tours on the third day of a visit to France, the Pope attacked selfishness in society and called for a fairer distribution of resources.</p>
<p>&quot;Every person wounded in body or in spirit, every person deprived of their most elementary rights, is a living image of Christ,&quot; the 76-year-old Roman Catholic Pontiff told an audience that included AIDS sufferers, immigrants, homeless people, gypsies and the mentally and physically handicapped, one of them on a stretcher.</p>
<p>&quot;Whatever their origin, whatever the weight of their problems, refusing to see them is to condemn oneself to understand nothing about life,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope waded through the small crowd, blessing a boy in a wheelchair, stroking heads and accepting gifts of a compact disc from an AIDS sufferer and a small statue of the Virgin Mary.</p>
<p>French Church officials said prostitutes had also been invited to the meeting as well as a young non-Christian rape victim who wanted to meet the Pope to restore her dignity.</p>
<p>The Pope's speech was his strongest so far on a visit that has stirred controversy over the separation of Church and state and the Pontiff's conservative injunctions on sexual issues, including opposition to use of condoms to guard against AIDS.</p>
<p>He delivered it in a turn-of-the-century basilica that holds the relics of Saint Martin, a fourth-century bishop of Tours whose charity the Pope hailed at an outdoor mass earlier on Saturday to mark the 1,600th anniversary of his death.</p>
<p>As a Roman officer, according to legend, Martin ripped his cloak at the gates to the French city of Amiens and shared it with a poor man dying of cold whom other passers-by had ignored.</p>
<p>&quot;A society is judged on how it treats those afflicted by life and the attitude towards them,&quot; the Pope said.</p>
<p>He launched an &quot;appeal for real solidarity among all people&quot; and suggested that rich countries like France must share resources more equitably among their people and with others elsewhere, and find new ways of ensuring employment for all.</p>
<p>&quot;When will all the rights of people be truly respected -- to work, to a home, to one's culture, to health, to an existence worthy of this name?&quot; he asked. A stagnating economy has brought France record unemployment and a growing number of homeless.</p>
<p>&quot;The Church would gravely lack its mission if She did not remind everyone of this urgent obligation to do everything possible in the rich societies of the West as in every society, to root out the scourges which are rampant on the surface of our planet,&quot; the Pope said.</p>
<p>His four-day visit is his fifth to mainland France and his last trip abroad before expected surgery to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>Despite frailty, he has appeared relatively robust and at ease during the trip, billed as a test of his ability to rally his flock in a once fervent Roman Catholic nation that is now largely indifferent to his moral teachings.</p>
<p>The main event of the visit will be an open-air mass in the eastern city of Reims on Sunday to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Catholicism.</p>
<p>Critics charge that the Pope's presence in Reims would seem to sanction the extreme nationalistic view -- embraced by the far-right National Front -- that the baptism marked the creation of a Catholic France. Clovis's kingdom stretched from what is now Germany and the Netherlands into France.</p>
<p>Protesters, including leftists, anarchists and freemasons are to rally in Paris on Sunday against his visit.</p>
<p>Alain Peyrefitte, a former minister of the late president Charles de Gaulle, praised the Pontiff's courage for sticking to his visit despite poor health and sometimes mocking criticism.</p>
<p>&quot;People sharing the same society...should refrain from wounding each other. Some practices of mockery are no longer acceptable,&quot; he wrote in the conservative newspaper Le Figaro.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
