<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68865" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French to protest as Pope says mass for ancient king.</title>
<headline>French to protest as Pope says mass for ancient king.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>REIMS, France 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Demonstrators will march in the French capital on Sunday to protest against Pope John Paul's strict views on birth control, abortion and homsexuality and to contest the symbolism of a long-dead French king.</p>
<p>The Pope, meanwhile, will say mass near Reims to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first west European king to convert to Catholicism and source of a bitter modern row about the separation of Church and State.</p>
<p>About 150,000 people were expected to attend the mass at an air base near the capital of France's eastern champagne region, on the last and most controversial day of the Pontiff's visit.</p>
<p>He seemed likely to seek to appease opponents by avoiding a traditional Catholic view that the conversion of Clovis marked the birth of France, instead using a sermon to stress the importance of baptism to Catholics.</p>
<p>In Paris, 70 anti-papal groups will stage a rally to accuse the Church, President Jacques Chirac and the far right of trying to use Clovis -- whom they say was a brutal warlord -- to revive belief that France is rightfully Catholic.</p>
<p>The groups, including anarchists, Greens, Freemasons and police trade unions, will instead celebrate the traditions of the 1789 Revolution and criticise the 76-year-old Pope for his opposition to birth control, abortion or homosexuality.</p>
<p>&quot;For the separation of Church and State, against the return of moral order,&quot; their posters say.</p>
<p>Clovis, born in what is now Belgium and who ruled an area stretching from eastern France to Germany, was baptised in Reims around 496. He extended his kingdom in battles against tribes like the Visigoths to cover most of France.</p>
<p>The Pontiff, on a visit that has taken him to Tours, Brittany and Vendee, has so far played down his controversial moral views -- which few French people follow -- and has stressed solidarity with the poor and the suffering.</p>
<p>In Tours on Saturday, the Pope embraced AIDS victims, prostitutes and an unmarried woman about to give birth.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope is not coming for a historical commemoration,&quot; said Bernard Lagoutte, secretary-general of the French Bishops' Conference. &quot;He's coming to remind Catholics of the importance of their individual baptism.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope upset France's other religious groups -- mainly Moslems, Jews and Protestants -- on his first visit in 1980 when he spoke of France's 1,500-year history as a nation.</p>
<p>&quot;France, eldest daughter of the Church, what have you done with the promises of your baptism?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>Chirac has been accused of violating a 1905 law separating Church and State by helping fund the visit. Early this year, a Reims court overturned a 1.5 million franc ($300,000) subsidy by the local council to build the podium for the Reims mass.</p>
<p>In Reims, the Pope will also hold a meeting with France's bishops on Sunday -- including &quot;Red Cleric&quot; Jacques Gaillot, sacked last year by the Vatican for his liberal views, such as favouring condoms to prevent the spread of AIDS.</p>
<p>The Pope will also visit Reims cathedral, almost wrecked by during World War One and where Catholics say Clovis was baptised -- and where French monarchs were crowned.</p>
<p>After brief talks with Prime Minister Alain Juppe, he will fly home to Rome, ending his last trip abroad before an operation next month to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>Among those missing the Pope's mass will be the pretender to the French throne -- 86-year-old Henri d'Orleans told a French newspaper he was suffering from 'flu.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="REIMS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
