<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68862" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope calls for new spirit of charity.</title>
<headline>Pope calls for new spirit of charity.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>TOURS, France 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, on the third day of a visit to France, put the focus on the need to help the weak, honouring a fourth century saint who shared his cloak with a poor man dying of cold.</p>
<p>His praise of Saint Martin at an outdoor mass on Saturday to mark the 1,600th anniversary of his death set the tone for a day on which the Pontiff was expected to launch a strong appeal for solidarity with the weakest members of society.</p>
<p>&quot;Here in France the Church has been singing the hymn to charity for 16 centuries,&quot; the 76-year-old Pope, on his last visit abroad before surgery to remove his appendix, told worshippers gathered in sunshine at Tours military airport.</p>
<p>&quot;Saint Martin was an admirable apostle, but it is not sufficient just to remember. In the various situations of today, be in your turn living members of the living Church,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Saint Martin, born in 336 in what is now Hungary, helped spread Christianity through much of western Europe.</p>
<p>He was a young Roman officer when, according to legend, he tore his cloak to share it with a poor man freezing to death at the gates to the northern city of Amiens. Martin was later bishop of Tours, were he died in 397 aged 61.</p>
<p>His relics are held in the central city's basilica, where the Pope was due later on Saturday to meet 190 &quot;casualties of life&quot; -- people living in poverty or distress, including a prostitute, an AIDS victim, homosexuals, tramps and immigrants.</p>
<p>The Pope said at the Vatican this week that he would launch a &quot;new appeal for solidarity with all those who suffer in their bodies and in their heart, those for whom life is precarious and threatened&quot;.</p>
<p>Saturday's mass, which police said drew 80,000 people, was also attended by French Protestant and Orthodox leaders whom the Pope met before the service for a brief exchange of remarks on the search for Christian unity.</p>
<p>The Pope also recorded a personal message on the Internet to inaugurate a new computer web site which the Catholic Church in France has set up to help spread its message.</p>
<p>The Pope's four-day visit to France, in which he has looked in reasonable health, has been billed as a test of his ability to rally his flock in the face of opposition and indifference to the Church's role and teachings in modern society.</p>
<p>Most of France's 58 million people are nominal Catholics, but only six million attend mass and many of these believe the Pope's conservative teachings opposed to abortion, birth control and homosexuality are outdated.</p>
<p>The main event of the Pope's visit will be an open-air mass in the eastern city of Reims on Sunday to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first pagan king in western Europe to convert to Catholicism.</p>
<p>Critics charge that the Pope's presence in Reims would seem to sanction the extreme nationalistic view -- embraced by France's far-right National Front -- that the baptism marked the creation of a Catholic France. Clovis's kingdom stretched from what is now Germany and the Netherlands into France.</p>
<p>Sixty-seven groups including leftists, anarchists and freemasons are planning a rally in Paris on Sunday to back the separation of Church and state and protest against the Pope's teachings on sexual morality.</p>
<p>Alain Peyrefitte, a former minister of the late president Charles de Gaulle, praised the Pontiff's courage for sticking to his visit despite poor health and sometimes mocking criticism.</p>
<p>&quot;People sharing the same society...should refrain from wounding each other. Catholics, a new minority, are entitled to respect. Some practices of mockery are no longer acceptable,&quot; he wrote in the conservative newspaper Le Figaro.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOURS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
