<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69428" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Pope honours long-dead king, triggering protests.</title>
<headline>Pope honours long-dead king, triggering protests.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>REIMS, France 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul ended a four-day visit to France on Sunday with a tribute to a long-dead king, triggering protests by opponents who say the papal praise trampled on the ideals of the 1789 Revolution.</p>
<p>The Pontiff said mass for 200,000 people at a military air base near Reims, heart of the Champagne wine region, to celebrate the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of Clovis, the first west European king to convert to Roman Catholicism.</p>
<p>A few thousand people -- 15,000 according to the organisers -- including anarchists and human rights activists, marched in Paris to denounce the Pope's strict moral teachings and blast the Clovis celebrations as violating France's secular, republican traditions.</p>
<p>The Church dismissed the protesters as a tiny minority.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the French people have better sense than those who claim to speak in their name,&quot; Paris Archbishop Jean-Marie Lustiger told a news conference. Opinion polls say most French people were indifferent to the visit.</p>
<p>The Pope used the motto of the French Republic in a farewell speech, when he urged France to remain faithful to its &quot;ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity&quot;.</p>
<p>The ailing 76-year-old Pope looked fairly robust on his last trip abroad before an operation to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>French cardinals said he talked openly and without fear of the day he would die and of his plans to lead the Roman Catholic Church for the rest of his life. &quot;There is no fear in the face of the void,&quot; Lustiger said.</p>
<p>The Pope said the baptism of Clovis was a &quot;signal event in the history of your country&quot; and spoke of the &quot;soul of France&quot; in a homily urging modern Catholics to cherish their baptism.</p>
<p>But he avoided the traditional Catholic and far right-wing view that the baptism of Clovis marked the birth of France. The far-right National Front said it welcomed the Pope &quot;on the French nation's 1,500th birthday.&quot;</p>
<p>Opponents at the Paris rally, and at two smaller protests in the Reims area, said Clovis was a brutal warlord hijacked by the Church and conservative President Jacques Chirac as a symbol of France's supposed Catholic roots despite a 1905 law separating Church and State.</p>
<p>Clovis was a central figure in French history before the 1789 Revolution abolished the monarchy. Born in what is now Belgium, he was baptised in Reims around 496 -- most modern historians say it was probably later.</p>
<p>He ruled from eastern France to the Netherlands and Germany and extended his kingdom in battles against tribes such as the Visigoths to cover most of modern France.</p>
<p>The Paris marchers, who included homosexuals, freemasons and members of a police trade union, also protested against the spending of public funds on facilities for the Pope' visit and his opposition to birth control, abortion and condoms.</p>
<p>Some sported blown-up condoms tied to their hair, others brandished caricatures of the Pontiff.</p>
<p>The Pope, on a visit that also included Tours, Brittany and Vendee, generally played down his controversial moral views -- which few French people follow -- and stressed solidarity with the poor and the suffering.</p>
<p>In a meeting with French bishops, he urged the Church to &quot;clarify misunderstandings&quot; and overcome sometimes &quot;loud resistance&quot; about publicising its teachings.</p>
<p>&quot;To express one's convictions does not mean to impose them but to exercise an inalienable right,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Olivier de la Brosse, spokesman for the French Bishops' Conference, clashed with Lustiger by saying the Pope's speeches reflected a desire not to stir up controversy.</p>
<p>Lustiger retorted the outlines of the trip were set two years ago. &quot;The tone was not one of appeasement. It was what the Pope wanted to say,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe bid the Pope farewell an an airbase near Reims. The Pontiff is scheduled to visit France again next August for World Youth Day.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="REIMS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
