<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71255" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Frail Pope defuses French clashes, wins praise.</title>
<headline>Frail Pope defuses French clashes, wins praise.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, bearing up well despite frail health, won praise in France on Monday for defusing controversy on a four-day visit when huge crowds at his masses dwarfed scattered protests.</p>
<p>&quot;The visit surpassed our most optimistic hopes,&quot; said Bernard Lagoutte, secretary-general of the French Bishops' Conference.</p>
<p>French media said the 76-year-old Pope skilfully avoided confronting opponents of his strict moral teachings on contentious issues like birth control and abortion, and skirted clashes over France's religious and secular traditions.</p>
<p>On his final trip abroad before entering hospital next month to have his appendix removed, he preached solidarity with the needy and Christian family values.</p>
<p>&quot;John Paul II leaves saintly and sound,&quot; the left-leaning Liberation said in a front-page headline.</p>
<p>&quot;By attacking the Holy Father, opponents of the trip rallied the faithful around him,&quot; the conservative Le Figaro commented in an editorial.</p>
<p>Lagoutte told Reuters the visit had confounded views that religious fervour was a thing of the past in France, where only about six million people regularly go to mass. About 45 million of France's 58 million people call themselves Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>The Pope's mass on Sunday drew a crowd of 200,000, more than double the original prediction by the Church in June.</p>
<p>The biggest anti-papal protest, called by an alliance of 70 mostly leftist groups ranging from anarchists to a police trade union, attracted only a few thousand people in Paris to denounce the Pope's moral teachings.</p>
<p>They also accused him of violating a 1905 law separating church and state by holding the mass in Reims to honour the 1,500th anniversary of the baptism of king Clovis, the first monarch in western Europe to convert to Roman Catholicism.</p>
<p>The Church and President Jacques Chirac had been accused of trying to transform the occasion into a nationalist celebration of France's birth.</p>
<p>Before boarding his plane, the Pontiff sought to reconcile religious and secular traditions by speaking of France's &quot;soul&quot; while urging it to continue spreading liberty, equality and fraternity -- the ideals of the 1789 revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;Pope disarms Clovis,&quot; the daily France-Soir said in a banner headline.</p>
<p>The Pontiff looked drained by the end of his visit but was in more robust form than on a brief trip to Hungary this month.</p>
<p>Before his arrival, an unpredecented rash of anti-papal protests had worried both the church hierarchy and French security services mindful that in Berlin in June he had received his worst reception for years from protesters.</p>
<p>Hundreds of German anarchists yelled &quot;Go to Hell&quot; and two bags of paint splattered on to the &quot;popemobile&quot; as he drove past.</p>
<p>Two weeks before the Pope arrived in France, a crude bomb was defused in a church on his scheduled route. In another incident, a gang of custard-pie throwers broke into Nantes Cathedral and knocked a priest to the ground.</p>
<p>The Pontiff did not call France &quot;eldest daughter of the Church&quot; -- a title favoured by Catholic traditionalists but denounced by critics who say it implies France is rightfully Catholic. The Pope used the title on a first visit in 1980.</p>
<p>Lagoutte denied that the Church had toned down the Pope's speeches to tailor them to a country where few obey his moral teachings on issues like birth control. But Lagoutte admitted: &quot;It's true we were careful not to use explosive words.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
