<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80435" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Oxford BioMedica aims gene work at market.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Oxford BioMedica aims gene work at market.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Birt</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A tiny biotech company which has grown out of the laboratories of Oxford University said on Friday it is hoping a revolution in gene therapy would carry it all the way to the stock market.</p>
<p>Oxford BioMedica believes it may hold the key to transforming the treatment of a whole range of conditions, including cancer, HIV and Parkinson's Disease.</p>
<p>Its ambitions will be put up for scrutiny by the markets over the next few weeks as it prepares to raise at least 5.0 million pounds ($7.8 million) to fund its work through a flotation on the Alternative Investment Market (AIM).</p>
<p>The company, set up by the directors of Oxford University's retrovirus molecular biology group, Alan and Sue Kingsman, plans to seek a listing in mid-November as long as market conditions are favorable.</p>
<p>In a telephone interview, Alan Kingsman said gene therapy is fixed in many people's minds as something to correct defective genes, which are behind diseases like multiple sclerosis and cystic fibrosis.</p>
<p>Oxford BioMedica's goal is to exploit the much greater potential of genes to conquer a wide range of poorly-treated conditions.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going back to looking at effective gene delivery technology and revamping the way we deliver genes for therapy,&quot; Kingsman said. &quot;There is a whole range of applications. There is not a sector of disease I would exclude from gene therapy.&quot;</p>
<p>To begin with Oxford BioMedica will focus on HIV and cancer.</p>
<p>Kingsman said it may be possible to deliver a therapeutic gene to the healthy cells of an individual who is HIV positive which would protect those cells from infection with the HIV virus, effectively stopping HIV in its tracks.</p>
<p>In cancer, Oxford BioMedica scientists are working on &quot;a product to make cancer cells very visible to the immune system, which then destroys them.&quot;</p>
<p>And further ahead, he said scientists &quot;are making very exciting progress&quot; in the field of neurobiology.</p>
<p>Oxford BioMedica is looking at putting genes into brain cells to tackle fatal diseases like Alzheimer's, which causes dementia, and Parkinson's Disease, which attacks the nervous system.</p>
<p>If its flotation succeeds, Oxford BioMedica will use the funds to recruit a staff of 30 for its new headquarters in Oxford. Kingsman said it also hopes to take any new drugs through early and intermediate stage human trials itself before finding major drug company partners.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope to raise enough money to take the technology forward and and take them into Phase I and Phase II ourselves, and from that point look for corporate partners to carry out more extensive trials,&quot; Kingsman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to go out for corporate alliances from a position of real strength.&quot;</p>
<p>Oxford Biomedica is coming to the market at a difficult time, with investors' cash already stretched by the plethora of flotations and rights issues in the sector this year. Australian group Peptide Technology Ltd was forced to pull the plug on its plans for a London listing on Thursday.</p>
<p>But Percy Lomax of stockbrokers Tether &amp; Greenwood, who is advising Oxford BioMedica, said the group had already raised 750,000 pounds from private investors without difficulty.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't think we will have much difficulty in exciting people about the company and making them realise they do have a superior product,&quot; Lomax said. ($1=.6405 Pound)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
