<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82415" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: African faith healer says he prays for Pope.</title>
<headline>African faith healer says he prays for Pope.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Archbishop Emmanuel Milingo, the controversial African Roman Catholic faith healer, said on Friday he regularly prays that Pope John Paul will overcome his health problems.</p>
<p>&quot;He (the Pope) continues to suffer and this has worried all of us,&quot; Milingo told a news conference where a new book about the archbishop was presented.</p>
<p>&quot;We never cease to ask God to prolong the life of Pope John Paul as much as possible because he really is an apostle who has given all to the the world,&quot; Milingo said.</p>
<p>Some Italian bishops have banned Milingo, the former archbishop of Lusaka, Zambia, from saying public Masses in their dioceses.</p>
<p>Some Church officials say Milingo, who also practices exorcisms, has gone too far in blending traditional African faith-healing practices with Catholic liturgy.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Pope, who has had a spate of health problems in the past few years, is expected to go into hospital early next month for an operation to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>The Vatican said a recurring inflamed appendix was the cause of at least part of the discomfort, pain and fevers the Pope has been suffering.</p>
<p>The Vatican has said he would go into Rome's Gemelli hospital on or after October 6, when he is due to preside at a beatification ceremony at the Vatican.</p>
<p>In an indication that the Pope expects to be back on his feet a few weeks after the operation, Rome's Cardinal Camillo Ruini on Friday invited the pastors of all parishes in the capital to attend a mass celebrated by the Pope on November 1.</p>
<p>The mass will be part of celebrations marking the 50th anniversary of the Pope's ordination as a priest.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
