<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86296" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Pope to enter hospital next week for appendix op.</title>
<headline>Pope to enter hospital next week for appendix op.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul will enter Rome's Gemelli hospital next week for surgery to remove his appendix, the Vatican announced on Monday.</p>
<p>It said all papal audiences would be suspended from October 7 &quot;as a result of the Holy Father's hospitalisation&quot;.</p>
<p>The statement did not specify which day the Pope, 76, would be admitted to hospital nor when the operation would take place.</p>
<p>Vatican sources said they expected the Polish-born Pontiff to go to the Gemelli on the evening of October 6 after leading a beatification ceremony at St Peter's.</p>
<p>&quot;The Prefect of the Pontifical Household, His Excellency Monsignor Dino Monduzzi, announces that all audiences will be temporarily suspended as from October 7 as a result of the Holy Father's hospitalisation,&quot; the brief statement said.</p>
<p>The Rome newspaper Il Messaggero reported on Monday that the Pope would undergo surgery on the morning of October 7 and remain in hospital until October 10, when he would return to the Vatican to convalesce.</p>
<p>The Vatican announced on September 14 that the Pope would shortly undergo surgery to remove his appendix.</p>
<p>It said then that periodic inflammation of the appendix was the cause of three bouts of &quot;intestinal fever&quot; which have ailed the leader of the world's Roman Catholics since Christmas.</p>
<p>The statement was issued by the Pope's personal physician Renato Buzzonetti following a flurry of speculation in the media about the health of the Pontiff, who has appeared increasingly fatigued and at times in discomfort in the past year.</p>
<p>It said other aspects of the Pope's health did not give cause for &quot;particular concern&quot; but made no mention of a violent trembling of the Pontiff's left hand.</p>
<p>Such trembling can often be a sign of Parkinson's Disease, according to medical experts.</p>
<p>The Pope had major abdominal surgery twice in 1981 after he was shot by Turkish gunman Mehmet Ali Agca in St Peter's Square and again in July 1992 to remove a colon tumour.</p>
<p>He also had hip replacement surgery in 1994 after breaking his leg in a bathroom fall and he dislocated a shoulder in 1993.</p>
<p>The appendix operation will be the sixth time the Pope has been taken into the Gemelli hospital since his election in 1978.</p>
<p>He will be admitted to a special, heavily guarded suite with its own chapel and kitchen on the 10th floor of the hospital.</p>
<p>Il Messaggero said the suite was protected by two armour-plated doors and bulletproof windows.</p>
<p>Vatican officials say the Pope is eager to be back on his feet in time to celebrate the 50th anniversary of his ordination as a priest in November.</p>
<p>He is due to lead a special mass to mark the occasion on November 1, the Roman Catholic feast of All Saints, and further ceremonies are scheduled later the same month.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
