<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13345" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Grief unites, anger divides Belgium in sex scandal.</title>
<headline>Grief unites, anger divides Belgium in sex scandal.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>The deaths by starvation of eight-year-old girls Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo while in the hands of a paedophile gang have united Belgium in grief but threaten to divide it again in anger.</p>
<p>Belgian police have arrested six people, including one woman, and seized some 400 paedophile porn video tapes and quantities of magazines in the inquiry so far.</p>
<p>The tender age of the victims, graphic pictures of the makeshift dungeon in which they were kept and the probability that the affair was linked to an international paedophile ring have raised emotions to boiling point.</p>
<p>The manner in which the two youngsters died -- starved to death nine months after being abducted in June last year -- has served to throw new light on a problem that knows no borders and has been around for a long time.</p>
<p>Sexual abuse of children is a global issue. More than a million children around the world have been forced by economics or coersion into prostitution, according to child rights lawyer Michele Hirsch.</p>
<p>Counting is difficult, solving the problem is much harder.</p>
<p>At least three petitions are doing the rounds in Belgium following the discovery last weekend of the two dead girls, the rescue of two others and the admission by the key witness, Marc Dutroux, that he had kidnapped two more.</p>
<p>One petition demands the reintroduction of the death penalty, another urged that there should be no parole for convicted child rapists, and there was also a blanket call for tougher penalties all round.</p>
<p>Even people who would normally count themselves as liberal are now seriously considering demanding the death penalty for child abusers and killers.</p>
<p>Many are not even aware that Belgium finally erased the death penalty -- by the guillotine -- from the statute books in June after it had lain dormant for many years.</p>
<p>&quot;These people should be killed,&quot; said 14-year-old Marie-Char as she waited with thousands of others of all ages and walks of life to pay homage at the funeral of Julie and Melissa in Liege last Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;They deserve the death penalty,&quot; said mother-of-two Claudine.</p>
<p>Most aree with the sentiment but not necessarily with the solution.</p>
<p>&quot;The death penalty has gone, but we still have to punish these people,&quot; said another woman at the memorial service for the two girls.</p>
<p>Gino Russo, Melissa's father, who has acted as a spokesman for the two girls' parents, has also distanced them from the death penalty calls in a show of moderation that has been widely praised.</p>
<p>Herman de Croo, leader of the main opposition party in Belgium, told Reuters the death penalty was gone for good but there would definitely be changes in the law to control the early release of child sex offenders.</p>
<p>Dutroux, 39, was released for good behaviour in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
<p>But as far as Hirsch is concerned, simply locking up abusers and throwing away the key is no answer.</p>
<p>&quot;If you don't deal with the demand there is no solution,&quot; she told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;You have to treat the victims because every time you treat an abuser you find that the abuser was abused. It will take a long time -- 20 years at least -- but it is the only way of treating what is a global problem,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
