<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13342" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Belgian case spotlights sex abuse conference.</title>
<headline>Belgian case spotlights sex abuse conference.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>An international conference on the commercial sexual exploitation of children begins in Sweden this week in a glare of attention raised by a horrific child-sex case unfolding in Belgium.</p>
<p>United Nations Children Fund spokeswoman June Kane said the Belgian case, in which children were abducted and sexually abused and two were left to starve to death, emphasised the need for firm action to stop sexual exploitation of children globally -- not just in the Third World.</p>
<p>&quot;This horrific case just shows that this is happening worldwide, not just in Thailand, Sri Lanka and the Philippines where child sex tourism is rife,&quot; Kane told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;This has hit everyone with a bang.&quot;</p>
<p>The conference will focus on child prostitution, pornography and the sale of children for sexual purposes.</p>
<p>UNICEF estimates that more than one million children a year are forced into child prostitution, trafficked, or used in child pornography but most studies have centred on Asia.</p>
<p>Organisers of the five-day conference, starting August 27, said the Belgian case has sparked more interest in the congress after triggering a Europe-wide alert for paedophile gangs.</p>
<p>Over 1,000 government, inter-governmental and non-government delegates and over 200 journalists from 130 countries will attend the conference to discuss the scope of the problems, legal reform, and raising public awareness.</p>
<p>Delegates include actor Roger Moore, a goodwill ambassador for UNICEF, about 50 ministers from different countries, and a youth panel with some teenagers who were victims themselves.</p>
<p>Interest had already been high in the conference that was first mooted two years ago by the Swedish branch of the Save the Children Fund and supported by the Swedish government.</p>
<p>&quot;But we have had more people wanting to come since the Belgian affair,&quot; said head of the press centre, Lars Lonnback.</p>
<p>UNICEF, End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT) and the Non-Government Organisation Group on the Rights of the Child have helped to organise the congress which is being treated as a one-off event at present.</p>
<p>The conference will be opened by Swedish Prime Minister Goran Persson and closed by Sweden's Queen Silvia, who in a rare outburst last month attacked Swedish politicians for not yet making the possession of child pornography illegal.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a shame that Sweden, as host country to the conference, has still not criminalised possession of child pornography,&quot; Madeleine Leijonhuvud, criminal law professor and congress committee member told Reuters.</p>
<p>A 15-strong delegation from Belgium, including Foreign Affairs Minister Erik Derycke, will attend the conference.</p>
<p>Belgium's ambassador to Sweden, Carlos De Wever, told Reuters the minister would speak to the congress about the recent case in his home country and the action being taken.</p>
<p>The case that has shocked the world came to light this month when two kidnapped girls were rescued from a makeshift dungeon at the home of a convicted child rapist.</p>
<p>Police then found the bodies of two other kidnapped girls who had died of starvation and are searching for two other missing girls.</p>
<p>&quot;Our population is in shock over this horrific case,&quot; De Wever told Reuters. &quot;This is obviously a worldwide problem but that it has arisen in Belgium has stunned everybody.</p>
<p>&quot;The public is now so much more involved in this issue that we are glad there is a conference like this one to air this dreadful problem and formulate some action.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
