<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16922" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Chronology of events in Belgian child sex scandal.</title>
<headline>Chronology of events in Belgian child sex scandal.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a chronology of the main events in an unfolding child sex scandal which came to light when the bodies of two young girls were discovered in the garden of a convicted sex offender.</p>
<p>June 1995: Eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo disappear while on a short walk near their home in Grace-Hollogne, eastern Belgium. They were last seen by a motorway bridge, waving at passing cars.</p>
<p>August 1995: An Marchal, 19, and Eefje Lambrecks 17, disappear in the Belgian port town of Ostend while on holiday, after attending a hypnotist's show. The teenagers were last seen getting off a tram.</p>
<p>December 1995: Marc Dutroux is arrested on charges of car theft and related crimes, and spends almost four months in prison. Dutroux had been released for good behaviour from jail in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
<p>February/March 1996: Around this time Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune, held captive in one of Dutroux' houses in southern Belgium, die of starvation while he is in jail.</p>
<p>August 13, 1996: Dutroux, 39, arrested, charged along with accomplice Michel Lelievre with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children. Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin, a key witness in the case, is arrested and charged with being an accomplice.</p>
<p>August 15: Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, discovered alive in a makeshift dungeon at Dutroux' house in Marcinelle. Both girls had been sexually abused. Delhez had been missing for a week, Dardenne had disappeared nearly three months previously.</p>
<p>August 17: Dutroux leads police to bodies of Julie and Melissa, buried in the garden of another of his houses, in Sars-La-Bussiere along with body of his accomplice Bernard Weinstein. Dutroux admits killing Weinstein, saying he had given him money to keep the girls fed in his absence. Police start programme of searches at Dutroux' five other houses.</p>
<p>August 20: Brussels businessman Jean-Michel Nihoul, a contact of Dutroux, is charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>August 22: Michael Diakostavrianos, of Greek origin, arrested, charged with criminal associaton. Two of his houses are searched.</p>
<p>August 23: Claude Thirault, a friend of Dutroux, arrested and charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>August 25: Detectives looking at the sex scandal arrest Chief Detective Georges Zicot - specialist in tackling vehicle theft - for truck theft, insurance fraud and document forgery. Two others, Gerard Pinon and Thierry Dehaan also arrested in connection with the vehicle theft ring.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
