<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17619" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Global child sex conference convenes in Stockholm.</title>
<headline>Global child sex conference convenes in Stockholm.</headline>
<byline>Trevor Datson</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>An international conference on the commercial sexual exploitation of children opened in Sweden on Tuesday with calls for tougher action to combat sex tourism and child pornography.</p>
<p>The conference, being held as a child-sex scandal in Belgium triggered a Europe-wide alert for paedophile gangs, ends on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope this will have effects that will last for years to come. You can't hold a conference on this scale, meet for a few days, raise the issues and then just drop them,&quot; congress host chairman Lisbet Palme told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>More than 1,000 government, inter-governmental and non-government delegates will discuss the scope of the problems, legal reform, and raising public awareness.</p>
<p>Opening proceedings, Swedish Prime Minister Goran Persson highlighted the scale of the problem.</p>
<p>&quot;The plague of child prostitution, pornography and trafficking in chidren has increased dramatically over the past few years. Millions of children around the world are being sexually abused,&quot; he said in his opening address.</p>
<p>The conference is jointly organised by the Swedish government, the United Nations Childrens Fund (UNICEF), pressure group ECPAT (End Child Prostitution in Asia Tourism) and the NGO group on the rights of the child.</p>
<p>The five-day programme will include plenary sessions, workshops and keynote speeches by politicians and celebrities such as actor Roger Moore and Queen Silvia of Sweden.</p>
<p>Palme, chairman of the Swedish UNICEF committee and widow of assassinated Prime Minister Olof Palme, said the horrific disclosures in Belgium had proved the importance of openness in combatting child sex abuse.</p>
<p>&quot;The most important thing is to be able to talk about the problem. Take a look at the recent tragedy in Belgium, we saw grown men crying in rage and frustration,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Belgan police investigating Marc Dutroux, suspected of running a paedophile ring, said on Monday they had arrested a 10th suspect. In the rapidly-widening child sex scandal, two kidnapped eight-year-old girls have been found dead, two other girls rescued and police are hunting at least two more girls who have been missing for a year.</p>
<p>A 15-strong delegation from Belgium, including Foreign Affairs Minister Erik Derycke, will attend the conference.</p>
<p>Palme, a trained child psychologist, said social taboos on talking about child pornography and paedophile sex were some of the strongest in existence.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course no-one wants to talk about it. You talk to children who have been involved and they deny it right up until they're shown the pictures, and sometimes beyond. So it's not surprising the subject is hidden to us.&quot;</p>
<p>Delegates were greeted at the Stockholm City Conference Centre by children's choirs, orchestras and a 30-strong demonstration from German anti-sex tourism campaign group Terre des Hommes in scarves painted with scenes of child abuse.</p>
<p>Group spokeswoman Barbara Hebbing told Reuters of her hopes for the congress.</p>
<p>&quot;Sex tourism is a big problem, we're to tell the politicians that it's very important for them to talk about it openly. We need international meetings like this because it's an international problem,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Persson said: &quot;At this congress we must shed light on the abuse and commercial exploitation taking place in almost every country in the world. And then we must go from words to deeds by developing strategies to fight these intolerable acts.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
