<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19599" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police have files on 13 missing children.</title>
<headline>Belgian police have files on 13 missing children.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police investigating Belgium's scandal of child kidnapping, porn and killing that has stunned Europe have files on 13 children who have gone missing over the past 10 years, a senior official said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Our first mission is looking for bodies. We don't know how many there could be,&quot; Gendarmerie Commander Johan Dewinne told reporters after police spent a fruitless day digging at a house owned by Marc Dutroux, the man at the centre of the inquiry.</p>
<p>&quot;We are working on 13 dossiers on missing children from the past 10 years,&quot; Dewinne, head of Belgium's disaster investigation team and leading the hunt for corpses, said.</p>
<p>Belgium was plunged into shock on August 17 as Dutroux led police to the bodies of eight-year-old friends Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune in the garden of another house he owns. With them lay accomplice Bernard Weinstein, whom he admitted killing.</p>
<p>Gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin said digging would resume on Thursday, and Dewinne said he hoped to wrap up excavations at the house in Jumet, a suburb of the southern city of Charleroi, by Friday evening.</p>
<p>He said in all 11 sites would be systematically searched.</p>
<p>As the scandal reverberated around the country, the lawyer of convicted child rapist Dutroux refused to defend him.</p>
<p>&quot;I have a little girl of Julie and Melissa's age, who has been really disturbed by these events, and I don't think she could have understood that her father was defending this man,&quot; lawyer Didier de Quevy told Belgian radio.</p>
<p>Dutroux and associate Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued on August 15 from a makeshift dungeon in another of the six houses Dutroux owns in and around Charleroi.</p>
<p>Dutroux has also confessed to kidnapping teenagers An Marchal and Eefje Lambrechts who disappeared from the port of Ostend a year ago. Their fate remains unknown.</p>
<p>Battling against heavy rain on Wednesday, investigators dug in several places in the yard of the Jumet house and are due on Thursday to begin investigating the rubble-filled basement.</p>
<p>Britain's Superintendent John Bennett who supervised excavations in the Fred and Rosemary West &quot;House of Horrors&quot; murder case in England two years ago, was present on Wednesday.</p>
<p>There were also fresh searches at other sites including the house in Sars-La-Buissiere where Melissa and Julie were hidden.</p>
<p>Dutroux said the girls, who disappeared in June 1995, starved to death early this year, He denies killing them but admits paying accomplices 40,000 francs ($1,300) to kidnap them.</p>
<p>They were buried in the eastern city of Liege on Thursday after what amounted to a state funeral amid outpourings of grief and anger.</p>
<p>As the searches continued in Belgium, Dutroux was named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman. The Slovak office of Interpol said he was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one other Slovak woman.</p>
<p>So far 10 people have been arrested in what has now become known as the &quot;Dutroux Affair&quot;, including Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin who has been charged as an accomplice.</p>
<p>Martin and Lelievre were interrogated again on Wednesday.</p>
<p>There has been widespread anger over revelations of police bungling, and the Justice Ministry has ordered an inquiry. A chief police detective has also been arrested on fraud charges, fuelling questions about a possible high-level cover-up.</p>
<p>There is also widespread disbelief that no one appeared to question how Dutroux, an unemployed father of three with no visible means of support, managed to own six houses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
