<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19634" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Grim timetable in Belgian child sex-abuse scandal.</title>
<headline>Grim timetable in Belgian child sex-abuse scandal.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian police have been searching 11 days for more bodies, clues and survivors in a scandal of child-murder, sex-abuse, kidnapping and pornography blamed on a deadly network of paedophiles.</p>
<p>So far police have arrested 10 people -- nine men and one woman.</p>
<p>Here is the grim timetable of events that sent shockwaves of revulsion across Europe.</p>
<p>- Aug 13, 1996: Police hunting for Laetitia Delhez, 14, detain chief suspect Marc Dutroux, Michel Lelievre and Michelle Martin after eyewitness recalls part of licence plate of van seen near scene of her abduction five days earlier.</p>
<p>- Aug 15: Dutroux leads police to house he owns in Rue de Philippeville in Charleroi suburb of Marcinelle. They find Laetitia and Sabine Dardenne, 12, who was abducted in May, in a secret prison in the cellar.</p>
<p>- Aug 16: Dutroux and Lelievre charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>- Aug 17: Dutroux takes police to house he owns in Rue de Rubignies in village of Sars-La-Buissiere, south west of Charleroi. Excavations uncover bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo kidnapped in June 1995. Dutroux says they starved to death in February or March this year. Police also find body of Dutroux accomplice Bernard Weinstein who Dutroux admits killing. Dutroux also admits abducting two girls still missing, An Marchal, 17, and Eefje Lambrecks, 19, in Aug 1995.</p>
<p>- Aug 18: Excavations go on at Sars-La-Buissiere, start at another house he owns in Rue des Hayettes in Charleroi suburb of Mont-sur-Marchienne which is occupied by Michael Diakostavrianos, and fresh searches at Marcinelle house. Police confiscate quantities of video tapes and magazines from Mont-sur-Marchienne house.</p>
<p>- Aug 19: Michelle Martin charged as accomplice to Dutroux and Lelievre. Searches spread to Dutroux' three other houses -- Rue Leopold le Noble in Charleroi suburb of Jemeppe-sue-Sambre, Rue Daubresse in Charleroi suburb of Jumet and formerly occupied by Weinstein, and Rue Jules Destree in Charleroi suburb of Marchienne-au-Pont and home of Lelievre.</p>
<p>Marchienne-au-Pont house reveals trench-like cells for holding children in the basement. Jumet house reveals children's clothing, more pornographic material and a gun.</p>
<p>In all searches police use dogs specially trained to find bodies. They also bring in British police Superintendent John Bennett and special radar imaging equipment he used to unmask Fred and Rosemary West in Britain's &quot;House of Horrors&quot; sexual-murder investigation.</p>
<p>- Aug 20: Belgian police contact Interpol for help. Brussels businessman Jean-Michel Nihoul, a contact of Dutroux, is charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>- Aug 22: Julie and Melissa buried in virtual state funeral in Liege. Thousands throng streets to pay last respects. Michael Diakostavrianos arrested and charged with criminal associaton. Dutchman, 74, held near Amsterdam in connection with investigations. House searched but nothing found. He released a few days later.</p>
<p>- Aug 23: Claude Thirault, associate of Dutroux, arrested and charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>- Aug 24/25: Dutroux and Diakostavrianos questioned through the night.</p>
<p>- Aug 25: Police in sex-scandal investigation arrest Chief Detective Georges Zicot - specialist in tackling vehicle theft - for alleged truck theft, insurance fraud and document forgery. Two others, Gerard Pinon and Thierry Dehaan also arrested in connection with the vehicle theft ring. Police start excavating at property of German-born scrap merchant. They find nothing.</p>
<p>- Aug 26: Pierre Rochow, the scrap metal dealer's son, arrested on charges related to theft and receiving stolen goods.</p>
<p>- Aug 27/28: Police intensify digging in and around the house in Jumet.</p>
<p>- Aug 28: Slovakian office of interpol announces that Dutroux suspected of murdering a young Slovak woman and planning kidnap of at least one more.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
