<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="20133" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgians fear bodies of five children at dig-site.</title>
<headline>Belgians fear bodies of five children at dig-site.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgians fear police may find the remains of five youngsters in a search for bodies at a house owned by Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in a child sex, killing and kidnapping scandal.</p>
<p>Police again ransacked the property on Wednesday as a traumatised nation awaited the outcome of a probe that has sent shock-waves of revulsion across Europe.</p>
<p>The high-tech excavation went ahead as Dutroux was named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman.</p>
<p>The Slovak office of Interpol said Dutroux was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one Slovak woman.</p>
<p>Speculation grew in the Belgian media about a prospect of five bodies hidden at the site here, including those of teenagers An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks.</p>
<p>Dutroux says he kidnapped the two a year ago from the port of Ostend. Their fate remains unknown.</p>
<p>&quot;Digging works have resumed in the shed and in the yard,&quot; gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin told reporters at the scene. &quot;We're looking for all possible indications, but of course primarily bodies. We will dig as deep as is needed.&quot;</p>
<p>Battling against heavy rain investigators began using an excavator in the yard - which has been cleared of debris - and were also digging beneath a concrete floor at three spots located on Tuesday by sniffer dogs in a shed at the site.</p>
<p>Nearly 20 people were involved with the search.</p>
<p>Darkness forced police to suspend their search late on Tuesday after they had excavated to a depth of two metres (6-1/2 feet) at one of four locations indicated by the dogs in the shed, and six metres at one spot in the garden.</p>
<p>&quot;The unbearable wait,&quot; wrote popular daily La Derniere Heure across its front page above pictures of Marchal's parents, looking strained, and of searches at the house in Jumet, southern Belgium, on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted child rapist and unemployed father of three, led police 11 days ago to the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of another of the six houses he owns around the southern city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>The body of Weinstein, whom Dutroux admits to killing, was found next to the girls.</p>
<p>A chief police detective has also been arrested on fraud charges, prompting allegations of police bungling or a possible high-level cover-up.</p>
<p>Dutroux said the two girls starved to death early this year, nine months after being abducted in June 1995. He denies killing them but admits paying two accomplices 40,000 francs ($1,300) to kidnap the two friends.</p>
<p>They were buried on Thursday amid an outpouring of grief across Europe and calls for reinstatement of the death penalty.</p>
<p>Foreign experts assisted in the excavations on Tuesday after Dutroux, 39, had suggested sites to dig. Prosecutor Michel Bourlet said Dutroux was calculating and highly manipulative.</p>
<p>Superintendent John Bennett, the British police officer who supervised excavations in the Fred and Rosemary West &quot;House of Horrors&quot; murder case in England two years ago, was brought in last week to help.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued on August 15 from a makeshift dungeon in another of Dutroux' houses. So far 10 people have been arrested in what has now become known as the &quot;Dutroux Affair&quot;.</p>
<p>Dutroux and associate Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice. Seven others face charges ranging from fraud to criminal association.</p>
<p>At least 15 children have gone missing in Belgium in the past six years. To date seven have been found dead, two have been rescued and six are still officially listed as missing.</p>
<p>A Brussels police official told Reuters police were looking for at least three other Belgian girls who have disappeared in the last five years. It was not known if Dutroux was involved.</p>
<p>On Tuesday Slovak police said they were cooperating with Belgian collegues in the search for An and Eefje. They said Dutroux visited Slovakia a number of times and that about 10 young Slovak women went to Belgium at his invitation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
