<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24490" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Hots spots in Belgian body hunt, sex rules changed.</title>
<headline>Hots spots in Belgian body hunt, sex rules changed.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police searching for the bodies of missing girls in Belgium's child sex scandal found &quot;hot spots&quot; on Friday in two houses owned by the chief suspect, convicted paedophile rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>A senior police detective arrested last Sunday in connection with the investigations was formally charged on Friday.</p>
<p>The Belgian cabinet, in its first meeting since the summer break, agreed on tougher controls on the early release from jail of sex offenders.</p>
<p>Dutroux, an unemployed electrician who owns six houses, was released 10 years early in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for raping five children.</p>
<p>Gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin told reporters in the Charleroi suburb of Jumet that investigators using British radar-imaging equipment had found two &quot;hot spots&quot; in one house and one in another.</p>
<p>Both houses are owned by father of three Dutroux, the key suspect in the case of paedophile abduction, porn and death that has horrified Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;Now we are using only the British apparatus in the cellar of the Jumet house,&quot; Boudin told reporters. &quot;Up to now this apparatus has indicated two places of interest in the cellar.&quot;</p>
<p>He added that the equipment had also found an &quot;anomaly&quot; in a house in the Charleroi suburb of Marcinelle.</p>
<p>The British radar-imaging equipment is triggered by cavities underground. In Britain's &quot;House of Horrors&quot; case it was set off by underground holes which were found to contain bodies.</p>
<p>On Friday evening exhausted police suspended their searches until Monday.</p>
<p>In two weeks of hunting police have discovered the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of another of Dutroux's houses in Sars-La-Buissiere near Charleroi.</p>
<p>They have rescued two other sexually abused girls -- Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne -- from a dungeon in the Marcinelle house and are searching for at least two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks -- whom Dutroux admits kidnapping.</p>
<p>The Jumet house was formerly occupied by Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice who Dutroux admits murdering. His body was found next to those of Julie and Melissa.</p>
<p>South of Charleroi in the town of Neufchateau, the nerve centre of the investigations, magistrates confirmed the charges of vehicle theft, insurance fraud and forgery against chief police detective Georges Zicot.</p>
<p>Charges were also confirmed against two other men arrested with Zicot on Sunday in connection with the car theft ring uncovered by police investigating Dutroux' paedophile sex gang. A fourth man, Pierre Rochow, was released.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been linked to organised vehicle theft and police are investigating the child sex and theft ring together.</p>
<p>Belgian radio said police would travel to Bratislava and Prague to search for missing Belgian children.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman. Interpol's Slovak office has said he was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one other Slovak woman.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Belgian gendarmerie's special disappearances squad said they were also likely to contact colleagues in Austria investigating what seemed to be a &quot;child-for-hire&quot; network spread across central Europe.</p>
<p>Dutroux has said Julie and Melissa, who he admits paying Weinstein and associate Michel Lelievre 40,000 francs ($1,300) to abduct in June 1995, starved to death early this year while he was in jail for car theft.</p>
<p>Belgian newspapers said Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin -- also under arrest -- had admitted that she failed to feed the children out of fear of facing them in their cell.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the affair including Martin who has been charged as an accomplice. Dutroux and Lelievre are charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
