<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26603" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Austrian rightist wants life jail for sex abusers.</title>
<headline>Austrian rightist wants life jail for sex abusers.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian far-right leader Joerg Haider said on Sunday convicted child sex offenders should be sent behind bars for life, days after Austrian police detained five men for suspected sexual abuse of children.</p>
<p>&quot;There must be no mitigation for child abusers,&quot; the leader of the Freedom Party said in a statement released by his office. Producers of and dealers in child pornography should serve life in prison.</p>
<p>Under Austrian law, sexual abuse of children carries a maximum of ten years in prison. Producers of child pornography can be sentenced to up to one year, while customers of such materials risk up to six months imprisonment.</p>
<p>Austrian police on Friday arrested two men for suspected sexual abuse of children aged between four and 15 living in a refugee shelter in the city of Linz. Two days earlier, Vienna police detained three men on charges of child sex abuse and producing child pornography in a suspected &quot;child-for-hire&quot; network spread across central Europe.</p>
<p>Austrian police declined to say whether the arrests were connected to the Belgian case of Marc Dutroux, alleged to be the leader of a peadophile pornography ring.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been named by police in the Slovak capital Bratislava, about one hour's drive from Vienna, as a suspect in the murder of one Slovak woman and the kidnapping of another.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
