<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29894" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian sex abuse bodies identified - official.</title>
<headline>Belgian sex abuse bodies identified - official.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>The two bodies found on Tuesday by police investigating the Belgian paedophile kidnapping, sex abuse and murder scandal that has alarmed all Europe are those of teenage girls abducted a year ago, a public prosector said.</p>
<p>&quot;The human remains discovered on Tuesday afternoon at Jumet have been identified as those of An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, Public Prosecutor Michel Bourlet announced officially on Tuesday evening,&quot; Belga news agency reported.</p>
<p>The cause and date of death were not immediately known.</p>
<p>&quot;All I can say is that they have been dead for a long time,&quot; An's father Paul Marchal told VTM television standing next to his wife Betty outside their home in Hasselt.</p>
<p>Convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, the key suspect in a scandal that has shocked Europe, admitted kidnapping An, then 19, and Eefje, 17, on August 22 last year in the port of Ostend.</p>
<p>Police found the badly decomposed bodies 2.5 metres (yards) under a shed in the garden of a house owned by Dutroux in the Jumet suburb of the southern city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>It was formerly occupied by Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice who Dutroux admits murdering and who he blames for killing the two teenagers.</p>
<p>The governor of Arlon jail where Dutroux is being held said on Tuesday he was being monitored every seven and a half minutes, day and night, to stop him committing suicide.</p>
<p>British serial killer Fred West hung himself in jail before he could be tried.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene sent his condolences to the families of the two girls, and Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck expressed his &quot;profound sadness&quot;.</p>
<p>RTBF Radio said Eefje had been identified by a wristwatch she was wearing.</p>
<p>Several other Belgian girls have gone missing in recent years. Their files are all now pooled in Neufchateau, nerve centre of an international paedophile hunt.</p>
<p>Police have been digging around the Jumet house, one of six owned by Dutroux, a convicted multiple child rapist, in or near Charleroi, for the past week.</p>
<p>The find follows discovery of the bodies of two eight-year-old children and that of Weinstein on August 17 at a house owned by Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere, south of Charleroi.</p>
<p>Dutroux said the two girls, Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, abducted in June 1995, starved to death earlier this year.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne, were rescued from another of Dutroux's houses 12 days ago. Both had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>The discovery of the paedophile web has horrified the country, prompted the government to tighten rules on early release of sex offenders and triggered calls for a global war against the child sex trade.</p>
<p>The fact that Dutroux was released early from a 13-year sentence for child rape, and that he has fathered three children by his two wives, has bewildered adults and children alike.</p>
<p>There have also been allegations of police bungling or worse. One of the people held is chief detective Georges Zicot.</p>
<p>The hunt for missing girls has taken on international dimensions. Belgian police have visited Slovakia and the Czech Republic and have contacted colleagues in Austria and Germany.</p>
<p>Authorities in Bratislava suspect Dutroux of the murder of a Slovak woman and the planned kidnapping of at least one other.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the Belgian affair, including Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin.</p>
<p>Police have found trench-like cells allegedly for holding kidnapped children in one of Dutroux's houses and seized more than 300 paedophile porn video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux himself -- plus magazines, childrens clothing and a gun.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
