<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29911" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Body count mounts in Belgian child sex scandal.</title>
<headline>Body count mounts in Belgian child sex scandal.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a chronology of the main events in an unfolding child sex abuse scandal which came to light when the bodies of two young girls were discovered in the garden of a convicted sex offender.</p>
<p>June 1995: Eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo disappear while on a short walk near their home in Grace-Hollogne, eastern Belgium. They were last seen by a motorway bridge, waving at passing cars.</p>
<p>August 22, 1995: An Marchal, 19, and Eefje Lambrecks 17, disappear in the Belgian port town of Ostend while on holiday, after attending a hypnotist's show. The teenagers were last seen getting off a tram. Police visit convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux at house where it later discovered that the girls are being held.</p>
<p>December 1995: Police investigating theft visit Dutroux at home again, hear childrens' voices but find nothing. Dutroux is later arrested on charges of car theft and related crimes, and spends almost four months in prison. Dutroux had been released for good behaviour from jail in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
<p>February/March 1996: Around this time Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune, held captive in one of Dutroux' houses in southern Belgium, die of starvation while he is in jail.</p>
<p>May: Sabine Dardenne, 12, disappears.</p>
<p>August 9: Laetitia Delhez, 14, disappears.</p>
<p>August 13: Dutroux, 39, detained along with accomplice Michel Lelievre and Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin as police search for Laetitia.</p>
<p>August 15: Dutroux leads police to makeshift dungeon in a terraced house he owns in Marcinelles, a suburb of Charleroi and one of the six houses he owns in and around the city where they find both Laetitia and Sabine. Both girls have been heavily drugged and sexually abused.</p>
<p>August 16: Dutroux and Lelievre charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>August 17: Dutroux takes police to bodies of Julie and Melissa, buried in the garden of another of his houses, in Sars-La-Buissiere along with body of his accomplice Bernard Weinstein. Dutroux admits killing Weinstein and kidnapping An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks. Police start programme of searches at Dutroux' five other houses. They find more than 300 child porn video tapes, magazines, childrens' clothing, a gun and quantities of soporific drugs.</p>
<p>August 19: Michelle Martin charged as an accomplice in the kidnappings and imprisonments.</p>
<p>August 20: Police find more cells in a Dutroux house in Charleroi suburb Marchienne-au-Pont formerly occupied by Lelievre. Brussels businessman Jean-Michel Nihoul, a contact of Dutroux, is charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>August 22: Julie and Melissa buried in what is virtually a state funeral in Liege. Thousands throng streets to pay last respects. Michael Diakostavrianos, of Greek origin, arrested, charged with criminal associaton. Two of his houses are searched.</p>
<p>August 23: Claude Thirault, associate of Dutroux, arrested and charged with criminal association.</p>
<p>August 25: Detectives looking at the sex scandal arrest Chief Detective Georges Zicot - specialist in tackling vehicle theft - for truck theft, insurance fraud and document forgery. Two others, Gerard Pinon and Thierry Dehaan also arrested in connection with the vehicle theft ring.</p>
<p>August 26: Pierre Rochow, son of a scrap metal dealer, arrested on charges related to theft and receiving stolen goods He was released on August 30 when charges dropped.</p>
<p>September 3: Police find human remains under shed in garden of house in Charleroi suburb of Jumet owned by Dutroux and formerly occupied by Weinstein. Bodies are identified as those of An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
