<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36447" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Dead Belgian sex victim girls to be buried apart.</title>
<headline>Dead Belgian sex victim girls to be buried apart.</headline>
<dateline>HASSELT, Belgium 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>The bodies of two young girl victims of a Belgian kidnapping and sexual abuse gang, found under a shed on a property belonging to the chief suspect, will be buried separately here in their home town on Saturday.</p>
<p>Eefje Lambrecks will be buried after a service at 1030 local (0830 GMT) in Banneux Church in Hasselt, eastern Belgium. Her friend An Marchal will be buried after a service at 1400 local (1200 GMT) in Hasselt Cathedral, a city official told Reuters.</p>
<p>The bodies of the girls were found on Tuesday in a metal container 2.5 metres (yards) beneath a shed on the grounds of a house in the city of Charleroi belonging to convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, who admits kidnapping them in August 1995.</p>
<p>The house was formerly occupied by frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing and who he accuses of murdering An and Eefje.</p>
<p>The parents of the two girls fell out some while ago over the decision of one to sell postcard-sized pictures of them with requests for leads in order to raise money to hire a private detective to pick up where the police had evidently left off.</p>
<p>Belgium has been in shock and mourning since August 15 when two girls were rescued from a makeshift dungeon in another house owned by Dutroux in Charleroi, and two more were found dead from starvation two days later in a Dutroux house south west of the city.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HASSELT, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
