<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41541" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German sentenced to jail on &quot;sex tourist&quot; crimes.</title>
<headline>German sentenced to jail on &quot;sex tourist&quot; crimes.</headline>
<byline>John Gilardi</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German man was sentenced on Monday to two years in prison for sexual offences against young girls during a holiday in Thailand.</p>
<p>A Frankfurt judge said in sentencing the 52-year-old man that the prison term was increased because the man was involved in distributing child pornography and had returned to Thailand despite the German criminal investigation.</p>
<p>German customs in February 1994 had confiscated a pornographic tape from the man which was turned over to Frankfurt prosecutors. He was accused, among other things, of having sex with a 10-year-old girl and having the act filmed.</p>
<p>The man said in court he has been attracted for some time to young Asian women but not to children.</p>
<p>The case was only one of a handful in which German authorities have managed to track down suspects under a law which lets them pursue Germans who commit sex offences abroad.</p>
<p>The 1993 law allows Germany to impose prison sentences of up to 10 years to its citizens convicted of having sex with minors abroad.</p>
<p>But prosecutions have been rare since evidence is hard to gather and German officials have said foreign officials often turn a blind eye to the problem.</p>
<p>An estimated 200,000 German men travel abroad each year in search of sex, many seeking girls under 14, according to German child welfare experts.</p>
<p>In a similar sex tourism case, Berlin prosecutors in late August filed charges against two German men for sexually abusing children in Thailand and distributing pornographic films and pictures of their acts.</p>
<p>The two men, aged 43 and 33, are alleged to have carried out indecent acts with children as young as 10 years old between 1994 and 1995.</p>
<p>Like the Frankfurt case, Berlin prosecutors were alerted to the two men by customs officials who intercepted packages containing pornographic photographs and order forms.</p>
<p>Another German man accused of committing sex offences with young children in Asia also goes on trial later this month in the Philippines.</p>
<p>Engineer, Konrad Heinrich Jecht, 63, of Munich, faces three counts of child abuse for his alleged fondling of the private parts of two boys aged 16 and 15.</p>
<p>Jecht, who pleaded not guilty last week to the charges in a Manila courtroom, is one of the latest to be prosecuted as part of a crackdown in the Philippines to eradicate the country's image as a haven for paedophiles.</p>
<p>Philippine courts recently sentenced a Briton and an Australian to up to 17 years each for sexually molesting children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
