<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41594" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium - conspiracy hotbed or bunglers' paradise?.</title>
<headline>Belgium - conspiracy hotbed or bunglers' paradise?.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraqi superguns, shadowy NATO anti-Communist vigilante groups, political assassinations and charges of high-level protection for paedophiles -- Belgium has it all and more.</p>
<p>The arrest of five people, including a former government minister, at the weekend on charges of murdering Andre Cools, patriarch of the Socialist party of Belgium's francophone community, five years ago is the latest in a litany of intrigue, incompetence and in-fighting.</p>
<p>The murder in March 1990 of ace gun designer Gerald Bull who had been making a super-long range weapon for the Iraqis may have been an isolated incident, but it helped illustrate the position the Capital of Europe played in the world of international conspiracies.</p>
<p>The unveiling eight months later of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation's secret GLADIO network of deep-cover agents spread across Europe to fight an invasion from the East only served to underline that position.</p>
<p>NATO's civilian headquarters are in Brussels and its military headquarters 60 km (40 miles) south in Mons.</p>
<p>But if those scandals exposed Belgium as a centre of international conspiracy, they had nothing on the intricate web of national political plotting and police rivalry exposed by the killing of Cools in July 1991.</p>
<p>The investigations that ensued uncovered links to the Mafia, theft, bribery, a political slush fund, toppled three federal government ministers and one former minister, prompted an Air Force general to commit suicide and forced NATO Secretary General Willy Claes to resign.</p>
<p>It also exposed deep rivalry between investigators, police and the gendarmerie in different regions of the country as the case -- originally being investigated in both Liege and Neufchateau -- has centralised on Liege.</p>
<p>But after more than five years of investigations, police were still at a loss to define either the true motive or find the killers, prompting allegations of a cover up.</p>
<p>That remained the case until the Neufchateau investigators thrown off the original case began sniffing around again in their hunt for more victims and clues of a murderous child sex and car theft gang seemingly led by Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>In the Dutroux case 10 people have so far been charged -- including a chief detective -- two child victims have been rescued, four girls found dead, one accomplice found murdered and the body of an associate exhumed and found to have been poisoned.</p>
<p>Here too there have been allegations of police bungling and possible protection of Dutroux and his gang -- at least passive if not active.</p>
<p>Officially there are no links between the Cools and Dutroux investigations other than that at one stage the same public prosecutors and investigating magistrates were involved -- Prosecutor Anne Thily and magistrate Veronique Ancia in Liege and Prosecutor Michel Bourlet and magistrate Jean Connerotte in Neufchateau.</p>
<p>But Belgian newspapers have made tentative connections, particularly between Jean-Michel Nihoul and former companion and disbarred lawyer Annie Bouty both of whom have been charged with criminal association in the Dutroux affair.</p>
<p>Newspapers said they also had links to a medical fund set up by Cools in the late 1980s and run by a close associate.</p>
<p>There is also scepticism at the coincidence of the timing of the weekend announcements that Alain Van der Biest, his private secretary Richard Taxquet and three others had been charged with the murder of Cools and attempted murder of his girlfriend.</p>
<p>Taxquet, a former policeman, and one of the others were arrested in 1992 in connection with 500,000 francs ($16,280) of stolen bearer bonds in a theft that magistrate Connerotte for one has insisted all along was directly linked to the Cools killing. Van der Biest's name also came up at the time.</p>
<p>Nothing ever came of it as the case was removed from Connerotte's hands and put under the exclusive care of Liege.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
