<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44758" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police raid homes in child sex probe.</title>
<headline>Belgian police raid homes in child sex probe.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police probing Belgium's scandal of child sex abuse, murder and car theft raided homes and offices around Charleroi on Tuesday and questioned 23 people, several of them police.</p>
<p>Assistant Public Prosecutor Jean-Paul Pavanello told Reuters that the 15 premises searched included an office occupied by the city's judicial police.</p>
<p>A total of 23 people questioned included eight members of the judicial police, three gendarmes and 12 people who were close to chief detective Georges Zicot, he said.</p>
<p>Zicot was arrested two weeks ago during investigations into a paedophile porn and car theft gang led by Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>In a case that has stunned Belgium, police last month rescued two young girls abducted by Dutroux and his accomplice Michel Lelievre and unearthed the bodies of four more as well as that of Frenchman Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>Pavanello said the questioning of the 23 was over the car thefts and the murder of Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing.</p>
<p>He said police were finding increasing links between the child sex case and the car thefts.</p>
<p>He added that no arrest warrants had been issued for any of the 23, and he did not expect any.</p>
<p>Zicot appeared in court in Liege on Tuesday morning to make a formal appeal against charges of car theft, insurance fraud and forgery.</p>
<p>Insurance fraud investigator Thierry Dehaan, who has also been charged with fraud and forgery, was in court alongside Zicot. Gerrard Pinon, charged with handling stolen goods, has not appealed and was not in court, Pavanello said.</p>
<p>In Neufchateau, nerve centre of the international paedophile pornography hunt, Annie Bouty was to appear in court on charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>Bouty, a disbarred lawyer, is the former companion of Jean-Michel Nihoul a Brussels businessman who has been charged with criminal association relating to the sex abuse and pornorgaphy side of the investigations.</p>
<p>Dutroux, Lelievre and Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin -- charged as an accomplice -- are due to appear in court on September 13 to have the charges against them renewed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
