<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49815" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: New charge in Belgian paedophile scandal.</title>
<headline>New charge in Belgian paedophile scandal.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jean-Michel Nihoul, previously charged only with criminal association in the Belgian scandal of child abduction, sexual abuse and murder, had the charge of kidnapping added on Thursday, Belga news agency said.</p>
<p>Belga said Public Prosecutor Michel Bourlet had informed it that Nihoul was now officially linked to the abduction on August 9 of 14-year-old Laetitia Delhez.</p>
<p>Laetitia was rescued six days later along with Sabine Dardenne, 12, from a makeshift concrete dungeon in the basement of a house in the Charleroi suburb of Marcinelle owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Sabine had been abducted on May 28. Both children had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>Belgium has been racked with grief and anger for nearly a month as first the two youngsters were rescued and then the bodies of four more were found in two different locations -- both connected with Dutroux.</p>
<p>Police have stepped up the hunt for seven other missing children.</p>
<p>Nine people are currently under arrest in connection with the linked cases of child abduction and car theft.</p>
<p>Dutroux and associate Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment and Michelle Martin, Dutroux' second wife, has been charged as an accomplice.</p>
<p>Nihoul's former companion Annie Bouty -- seemingly the link to Belgium's other scandal of political assassination -- is charged with criminal association, as are two other men.</p>
<p>Chief detective Georges Zicot and businessman Gerrard Pinon have been charged in the related case of car theft.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
