<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53523" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Lawyer for Belgium child rapist gets death threats.</title>
<headline>Lawyer for Belgium child rapist gets death threats.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>He has had death threats and accepts there could be a fall-off in his legal practice, but the Belgian lawyer for child molester Marc Dutroux says he will not back down from the challenge of defending his client.</p>
<p>&quot;It was undoubtedly...the most difficult decision I ever had to take in my life,&quot; Julien Pierre, a 43-year-old with piercing eyes, told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>The case of Dutroux, accused of leading a padeophile gang which kidnapped, abused and murdered young girls, has shocked an entire nation.</p>
<p>A convicted child rapist, Dutroux has admitted kidnapping at least six girls, four of whom have been found dead, and killing an accomplice.</p>
<p>Authorities in Bratislava suspect him of the murder of a Slovak woman and the planned kidnapping of at least one other.</p>
<p>He is known to most ordinary Belgians simply as &quot;the monster.&quot;</p>
<p>Pierre, speaking to Reuters in an interview, said he could understand people's anger and anguish. But he said Dutroux, more than anyone else, needed a lawyer.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a number of principles which have to be respected, including the democratic, natural right for each accused to be defended,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's precisely because people were moving away from a number of principles that we ended up in a society where children were bought and sold, that we ended up in a society which made extraordinary cases like these possible,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Pierre gave no details of his conversations with Dutroux, who has been described by psychotherapists as a psychopath playing a subtle game of power with investigators.</p>
<p>&quot;He talks, he talks, he talks. He is alone and only talks to investigators, the chaplain. When he sees me, he tends to talk a lot,&quot; Pierre said.</p>
<p>&quot;Is he a monster?, I don't know what that is, a monster,&quot; Pierre said. &quot;What is certain...is that he has elements which remind me of people you meet in every street every day.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked whether Dutroux was sick, he said: &quot;I'm not a psychiatrist...but it seems to me through certain features of his personality that perhaps indeed he merits an examination&quot;.</p>
<p>Dutroux's own lawyer refused to take on the defence because his daughter -- eight years old like two of the dead girls -- would not comprehend.</p>
<p>Another leading lawyer declined, fearing for his safety.</p>
<p>Pierre, who has taken on tough defence cases before, said he had first talked to his 16-year-old son and 11-year-old daughter before accepting the Dutroux dossier.</p>
<p>So far there has been little impact on his personal life.</p>
<p>He has received some death threats but shrugs them off. He admits some of his clients were considering dropping him but he said most had remained loyal.</p>
<p>Pierre declined to give details of his line of defence for Dutroux, whose sister says he scares her to death and whose parents had begged the authorities not to release their son early after an earlier conviction.</p>
<p>Pierre, who expects the trial to start in two years time, said he has had offers of help from leading French and Italian lawyers. he said he preferred to work alone on the case for the moment but left open accepting help later on.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
