<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54762" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: PM kidnap gang member on trial as Belgium reels.</title>
<headline>PM kidnap gang member on trial as Belgium reels.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dubbed the Houdini of Belgian crime because of the number of times he has escaped from prison or custody, the last member at large of what was once the country's most wanted gang goes to trial on Monday.</p>
<p>It could not have come at a worse time for a country already reeling from the twin scandals of paedophile kidnapping, rape and murder and political assassination that have brought Belgium's already shaky political system under attack.</p>
<p>Basri Bajrami, who broke out of a Belgian prison in 1993 in a televised escape that would have movie directors drooling, goes on trial at Brussels' central criminal court on charges related to his membership of the Haemers Gang, which wrought havoc across the country in the 1980s.</p>
<p>It culminated in the kidnapping in January 1989 for one month of former Belgian prime minister Paul Vanden Boeynants. He was released for a ransom reputed to have been more than $1.5 million.</p>
<p>The leader of the gang, Patrick Haemers, was caught in Brazil in May 1989 and extradited to Belgium. He hanged himself in prison in 1993.</p>
<p>Two years after his Brussels jailbreak with a hostage spreadeagled across the windshield of the escape car, his head through the sunroof and a pistol jammed in his mouth, Bajrami was extradited to Belgium from his native Macedonia.</p>
<p>Although the Haemers gang has ceased to exist, its spectre continues to haunt Belgium.</p>
<p>A central suspect in the so-called Dutroux Affair of child kidnapping, sexual abuse, pornography and murder -- named after the key suspect Marc Dutroux -- is Jean-Michel Nihoul.</p>
<p>Nihoul, who had prevously been charged only with criminal association, was charged on Thursday with abduction after police rejected the alibi for the night in question that had been provided by a former associate of Patrick Haemers.</p>
<p>Nihoul, who has admitted only passing acquaintance with Dutroux -- who has confessed to abducting or involvement in the abduction of six young girls -- was identified as being in the vicinity when Laetitia Delhez, 14, was kidnapped on August 9.</p>
<p>Laetitia was rescued six days later, along with Sabine Dardenne, 12, who had been missing for nearly three months, from a makeshift dungeon in the basement of a house owned by Dutroux in the southern city of Charleroi. Both girls had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>The discovery two days later of the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in another Dutroux house and two weeks later of the corpses of teenagers Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal -- who Dutroux admits kidnapping -- sent the country into shock.</p>
<p>The arrest one week later of six people, including a former government minister, on charges of having murdered another former Socialist minister, turned shock into disgust at the Belgian judicial and political system.</p>
<p>Bajrami's trial will be an uncomfortable and for some, unwanted reminder of Belgium's darker, criminal side.</p>
<p>The canker of cheating the system goes all the way to the top -- including the judiciary, according to at least one witness whose first professional acquaintance with the country was a lecture by two judges on how to avoid paying tax.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
