<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58476" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: California governor signs &quot;chemical castration&quot; law.</title>
<headline>California governor signs &quot;chemical castration&quot; law.</headline>
<dateline>VAN NUYS, Calif. 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gov. Pete Wilson signed a controversial law on Tuesday making California the first state to force repeat child molesters to undergo &quot;chemical castration.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the new law, repeat child molesters when released from prison on parole, will be given weekly injections of a testosterone-inhibiting drug to reduce their sex drive.</p>
<p>Wilson said this would take away the urge &quot;to attack and attack again.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Child molesters can't stop because they have a compulsion to do what they do,&quot; Wilson said. &quot;And as long as they have that urge, they'll keep on victimising children -- unless we do something about it.</p>
<p>&quot;That's why we're taking a common sense step to eliminate that sick impulse among our sickest criminals,&quot; Wilson, a Republican, said.</p>
<p>The &quot;chemical castration&quot; measure has drawn opposition from civil rights advocates who say it raises serious constitutional questions about the right to privacy and the right to procreate, and from some medical experts who question whether the treatment will work in all cases.</p>
<p>The law is the latest tough anti-crime measure adopted by California, which two years ago passed a &quot;three strikes, and you're out&quot; law mandating long sentences for career criminals.</p>
<p>The &quot;chemical castration&quot; bill, authored by Republican Assemblyman Bill Hoge of Pasadena, passed both houses of the state legislature by large margins last month.</p>
<p>Under the new state law, an offender convicted twice of molesting a child would, after release on parole, receive weekly injections of a drug such as Upjohn Co.'s Depo-Provera to reduce his sex drive. Courts have discretion to order the treatment for first-time offenders. Convicts may opt for surgical castration instead.</p>
<p>Wilson's office said studies had shown that &quot;chemical castration&quot; was an effective treatment for sex offenders, who have a high recurrance rate.</p>
<p>According to the California Department of Corrections, over half of all paroled sex offenders commit a new sex offence or parole violation less than one year after release from prison and three out of four commit a new offence or parole violation within two years.</p>
<p>The term &quot;chemical castration&quot; is not strictly accurate since the drug stops working after the patient stops taking it. Hoge has said offenders would be treated only while on parole, which lasts three years in child molestation cases.</p>
<p>Ann Bradley, spokeswoman for the American Civil Liberties Union of southern California, said the ACLU opposed the measure as &quot;a serious violation of basic civil rights.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;You are taking away the decision of the individual about their own body,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>She said the law gave a false sense of having solved the problem of child molestation when the medical and psychiatric communities said the injections did not work unless the pedophile was willing to stop molesting and was involved in a counselling programme.</p>
<p>Bradley said many child molesters were motivated by aggression rather than by sexual urges. She questioned how a drug to reduce sex drive would stop such offenders.</p>
<p>The Department of Corrections estimates it will cost about $2,380 a year for each parolee given the weekly injections. There were 244 inmates admitted to state prison in 1995 that could have qualified for the treatment, officials said.</p>
<p>Sweden, Germany and Denmark offer chemical castration to convicted sex offenders but none forces it as a condition of parole.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VAN NUYS, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
