<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65394" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EP demands EU action on child sex.</title>
<headline>EP demands EU action on child sex.</headline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Parliament pressed the European Union on Thursday to act to curb child sex and trafficking rings, saying the fight against sexual abuse of children must be an &quot;absolute priority&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The scourge of paedophilia, trade in children and sexual exploitation is constantly increasing, not only in isolated cases but also through transnational networks and sex tourism, which involve extreme violence,&quot; the parliament said in a resolution.</p>
<p>&quot;Combatting the sexual exploitation of children must be an absolute priority for all EU member states, and the European Union must support their efforts,&quot; deputies said.</p>
<p>The text urged EU governments to create the legal frameworks for police and justice departments to pool efforts to break up child prostitution networks and to pursue those EU nationals involved in child &quot;sex tourism&quot; outside the 15-country bloc.</p>
<p>Other suggested measures included the establishment of a central register of abducted children, more money for Europol -- the bloc's embryonic police force -- to fight such crimes and special training for magistrates and police officers pursuing sex criminals.</p>
<p>But a last-minute amendment which would have backed the creation of an EU register of convicted paedophiles was defeated.</p>
<p>Parliament's call to action follows Belgium's unfolding horror story of child kidnapping, sexual abuse and murder in which four girls have been found dead since August and another two have been rescued alive from captors' hands.</p>
<p>Belgian police have arrested nine people on a series of charges since finding the girls alive, including convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>The affair has revolted the country and raised questions of police bungling and political cover-up.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G159">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
