<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65414" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Excerpts from Belgian govt statement on scandals.</title>
<headline>Excerpts from Belgian govt statement on scandals.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are key excerpts from Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene's statement to parliament on Thursday on the paedophilia and political murder scandals which have rocked the country:</p>
<p>The child sex and murder cases, which exposed &quot;networks of extreme criminality&quot;, were &quot;so revolting that words were hard to find&quot;. They had caused &quot;sadness and amazement&quot; in the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The dramatic events of the past weeks have touched us all profoundly...</p>
<p>&quot;Together we must ask ourselves what has gone wrong. We must also wonder what we have done wrong ourselves, each of us, in politics, in the judiciary, the police, in the media, and the population in general so as to prevent a repeat of these events...</p>
<p>&quot;Now there must be clarity first. The investigation into the murder raised many questions and led to a general feeling of mistrust of our institutions. The judiciary now must go to the heart of the matter...&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It must not be hindered in any way.&quot;</p>
<p>Dehaene pledged an extra 500 million francs ($16 million) for the Justice Ministry budget and 200 additional staff.</p>
<p>Reports on investigations into bungling by police and the judiciary &quot;should not be allowed to affect the progress of the investigations&quot; into the murder of socialist politcian Andre Cools and the paedophile case.</p>
<p>Any serious errors in the investigation of the child sex case would be punished. &quot;If it appears that during earlier phases of the investigation serious errors have been made, there will be sanctions.&quot;</p>
<p>Any cases of bungling that might be found should not be seen as evidence the whole system was corrupt or incompetent.</p>
<p>Belgium was reviewing its parole rules for sexual offenders, had begun a drive for international cooperation in the fight against paedophilia and would change rules on help for the victims of crime.</p>
<p>Services monitoring paroled sex delinquents would be reinforced.</p>
<p>Those engaging in or possessing child pornography or paedophilia abroad would now also be punishable at home.</p>
<p>A central body would be created to improve coordination among investigators. ($1=31.14 Belgian Franc)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
