<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66107" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian parliament meets on child abuse, murder.</title>
<headline>Belgian parliament meets on child abuse, murder.</headline>
<byline>Nieck Ammerlaan</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium's parliament meets in early session on Thursday to consider urgent steps for rebuilding public confidence shattered by a shocking child sex abuse case and a political murder scandal.</p>
<p>Political parties were expected to back the setting-up of a committee of inquiry into judicial bungling in investigation of the 1991 mafia-style murder of a leading politician and the activities of a paedophile ring.</p>
<p>The scandals have shocked this mainly Roman Catholic country of 9.9 million people at the hub of western Europe and sullied its image as an untroubled backwater famed for good food and beers.</p>
<p>High-level corruption has emerged in both cases.</p>
<p>In the child sex case -- in which at least four young girls died after being abducted -- police officers are suspected of having been involved in a car theft racket led by paedophile gang leader and convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>In the case of the killing of former Socialist minister Andre Cools, party-appointed investigators have attempted to divert inquiries leading to party members, judicial sources say.</p>
<p>Faction leaders in parliament brought the start of the parliamentary year forward by almost three weeks to discuss urgent measures needed to restore people's shattered confidence in the judicial and political system.</p>
<p>Four ministers have lost their jobs so far in the five-year probe into the slaying of Cools. But until recently investigators had failed to find any murder suspects.</p>
<p>The case came to life again a week and a half ago when four men were arrested in the wake of information from an anonymous witness.</p>
<p>They include former regional and federal minister Alain van der Biest and his former private secretary Richard Taxquet.</p>
<p>A francophone socialist, Van der Biest has been charged with Cools's murder. He denies any involvement in the case.</p>
<p>Two more arrests have been made but many details are still murky. But it appears clear that Cools was gunned down to prevent him from making embarrassing revelations about party funding.</p>
<p>On Wednesday another prominent Francophone Socialist official, former regional minister Guy Mathot, was again linked to the killing by newspaper La Libre Belgique. He was named by three of those arrested.</p>
<p>Mathot told Belgian television angrily: &quot;What a lie.&quot;</p>
<p>Tempers flared elsewhere with investigators in the eastern city of Liege -- the city where Cools was shot down at point-blank range -- accusing some Belgian media of having thwarted them by releasing the names of the two suspected killers.</p>
<p>International arrest warrants have been issued for the two, both Tunisian, named as Abdel Jielil Ben Regiel and Abdel Magid Bel Almi. The two men are alleged to have been hired in Sicily.</p>
<p>Seven people have been arrested in the linked scandals of paedophilia, kidnapping and murder and car theft, the chief suspect being Dutroux, a father of three.</p>
<p>One of those arrested for car theft is a detective.</p>
<p>The bodies of young victims were found in properties owned by Dutroux. Othewr properties owned by him are still being searched for clues possibly to the whereabouts of missing girls.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
