<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67861" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Dutch to review law on child sex at 12.</title>
<headline>Dutch to review law on child sex at 12.</headline>
<dateline>THE HAGUE 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Dutch government said on Friday it was reviewing a controversial five-year-old law allowing child sex from 12 years upwards.</p>
<p>&quot;We think that 12 years is very young...we're considering raising the age to 14,&quot; a government spokesman said.</p>
<p>Neither the spokesman, nor Prime Minister Wim Kok in a written statement on the move to parliament, specifically linked it with the unfolding Belgian paedophilia scandal.</p>
<p>That unfolding horror story of child kidnapping, sexual abuse and murder in which four girls have been found dead since August has attracted widespread Dutch media coverage.</p>
<p>Under amendments to the Dutch criminal code adopted in 1991, non-coercive sex with children aged 12 to 16 is only punishable if a complaint is brought by the minor concerned, their parent or guardian or the national child protection agency.</p>
<p>The amendments, which at the time sparked an international media outcry, caused few ripples at home.</p>
<p>Advocates of the lower age limit argue that, by lifting the taboo on under-age sex, it has helped reduce the Dutch rate of teenage pregnancies to one of the lowest in the European Union.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Kok told parliament the government was reviewing the 1991 legislation because it could hamper efforts to combat child prostitution.</p>
<p>&quot;Furthermore one could call into question what is after all a very young age (for sex) of 12 years,&quot; he said in a written answer to parliamentary questions from opposition Christian Democrats published on Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="THE HAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
