<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70306" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: NZ First pushes hard line on violent crime.</title>
<headline>NZ First pushes hard line on violent crime.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Zealand First leader Winston Peters on Tuesday hardened his party's law and order line launching a &quot;two strikes and you're out&quot; policy for violent and sexual offenders.</p>
<p>Peters has been pushing the law and order message on the campaign so far, giving audiences at regional venues on his &quot;kiwi spirit&quot; bus tour statistics of the growth in violent crime in their region.  </p>
<p>But Peters told a public meeting in the South Island city of Nelson today that law and order and personal security were the &quot;sleeper&quot; issues for New Zealand. He said his party would get tough with violent and sexual offenders.</p>
<p>&quot;A person convicted of a violent and/or sexual offence who then reoffends in a similar fashion will receive a mandatory minimum sentence of 10 years,&quot; Peters said.</p>
<p>He said the programme would be backed up with extra funding for adult education and anger management courses in prisons.</p>
<p>Victims would receive reparations, in most cases financial.  </p>
<p>New Zealand First would also establish first, second and third degrees of murder, with a minimum 25 year sentence for first degree murder.</p>
<p>But Peters eased off his attacks on the media for not publishing details of a speech on Monday in which he alleged crimes committed by a man charged with sexual violation resulted from the breakdown in the mental health system.</p>
<p>Media outlets have been advised not to publish the details because the case was sub judice, and Peters said &quot;contempt of court is an offence that we all would wish to avoid&quot;.  </p>
<p>Peters said &quot;legal niceties will not reveal the appalling state of our mental health services&quot;. He said he spoke out because he was not prepared to tolerate people dying because of the failing mental health system.</p>
<p>Solicitor-General John McGrath said he intended to look at all aspects of the speech and its reporting.</p>
<p>-- Wellington newsroom 64 4 4734746</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
