<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70668" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Who ignored clues in the Belgian child sex horror?.</title>
<headline>Who ignored clues in the Belgian child sex horror?.</headline>
<byline>Nieck Ammerlaan</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police and judges in Belgium are washing their dirty laundry in an increasingly shrill public slanging match, accusing each other of making the most mistakes while investigating the shocking deaths of four young girls.</p>
<p>Less than two months after the scandal broke the media say the government is taking the side of the judges and together with rank and file police are crying &quot;cover-up!&quot;.</p>
<p>Accusations and counter-accusations have been flying thick and fast, confusing ordinary people who suspect the girls' lives might have been saved if judges and the police had done their jobs rather than jealously protecting their own pastures.</p>
<p>The increasingly hysterical tone of the row has drowned the question of why the girls died while they were held by a paedophile ring and who is behind the gang.</p>
<p>Revelation after revelation show a stunning lack of communication and coordination between investigators.</p>
<p>The bungling by the Gendarmerie -- the federal police -- and various magistrates has shattered the public's faith in the country's legal system.</p>
<p>The stream of reports on the turf war has underlined the need for reform. Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck has said he is already working on improvements.</p>
<p>One of two reports commissioned by De Clerck into what went wrong blamed the paramilitary Gendarmerie.</p>
<p>It said the force had kept information from public prosecutors to make sure that it could continue to conduct its own investigation -- codenamed Othello -- into the child sex, kidnap and murder case without interference.</p>
<p>As a result clues which would have led detectives to convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux while the girls were still alive were ignored, it said.</p>
<p>An alert eyewitness and tipoffs led investigators to Dutroux in mid-August. In his properties they found two missing girls alive and unearthed the bodies of four others.</p>
<p>The accusation against the Gendarmerie, read out by De Clerck in parliament last week, not only upset the force, but also socialist Interior Affairs Minister Johan vande Lanotte -- responsible for the Gendarmerie.</p>
<p>The other report ordered by the Justice Minister said that there was no truth in allegations that high-level officials had kept silent about Dutroux in return for stakes in the rapist's car theft racket.</p>
<p>But over the weekend it became clear that De Clerck had been selective in his presentation of the conclusions of that report at the request of its author - a senior Belgian judge.</p>
<p>He did not tell parliament that some mistakes had been made by officials in the public prosecutor's office in Charleroi, where Dutroux lived and hid his victims.</p>
<p>Media commentators said De Clerck was protecting the judiciary.</p>
<p>The news outraged Michel Bourlet, public prosecutor in the southern town of Neufchateau, who had unmasked Dutroux after he snatched two girls from the area.</p>
<p>Bourlet said the report's findings were diametrically opposed to what was in his dossier. This had been enough to charge a chief inspector of the Charleroi judicial police with car theft, insurance fraud and forgery.</p>
<p>Bourlet's outburst reinforced the impression of a cover-up in the secretive world of Belgian judges and magistrates.</p>
<p>The largest union of Gendarmerie staff said magistrates were in the habit of quickly classifying the files on prominent Belgians as confidential and letting them rest.</p>
<p>It threatened to open its own files on the establishment.</p>
<p>For its part the judicial police, which works for the magistrates, on Monday lashed out at the Gendarmerie, accusing it of running what virtually amounted to a state within a state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
