<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73038" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germans mull chemical castration for child abusers.</title>
<headline>Germans mull chemical castration for child abusers.</headline>
<byline>Fiona Fleck</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's family affairs minister triggered a national debate on Tuesday over &quot;chemical castration&quot; of paedophiles after a man confessed to sexually abusing and killing a seven-year-old girl in Bavaria.</p>
<p>The 27-year-old electrician, who admitted kidnapping Natalie Astner last Friday on her way to school, confessed he stripped and bound her and committed sexual acts, but denied rape, German prosecutors said. Her naked body was found in a river on Sunday.</p>
<p>The electrician was freed a year ago after serving two thirds of a 5-1/2-year jail term for child abuse -- sparking comparisons in Germany with Marc Dutroux, at the centre of a child abuse scandal in Belgium, who was released three years early from a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
<p>The Astner case has made national headlines, shocking Germans who have asked whether the law is doing enough to prevent known paedophiles offending again.</p>
<p>&quot;We must examine all possibilities to protect children from sexual abuse,&quot; Family Minister Claudia Nolte told the daily Express.</p>
<p>&quot;When perpetrators with sexual disorders cannot be helped with therapy, I can imagine that we should think about chemically reducing their sexual drive,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Deputies from Bavaria's ruling Christian Social Union in the regional parliament said they too would examine chemical measures to prevent sexual offenders repeating their crimes.</p>
<p>Doctors differentiate between surgical castration -- removal of the testicles -- and the use of chemicals to suppress the male sex drive.</p>
<p>California recently introduced chemical castration for some sex offenders. But several German experts argue it fails to prevent offenders repeating their crime.</p>
<p>&quot;It is wrong to think that the perpetrator, whether rapist or paedophile, is under huge sexual pressure and occasionally explodes,&quot; Christian Pfeiffer, the director of Hanover's criminal research institute, told German Radio.</p>
<p>&quot;Research shows...it's aggression against women, children or whoever is concerned. They want to humiliate, debase their partner...because that's what excites them,&quot; Pfeiffer said.</p>
<p>Prison psychologist Werner Hess agreed. He told ZDF television that psychologists should &quot;help offenders to bring their sexual impulses under control&quot;.</p>
<p>Sabine Leutheusser-Schnarrenberger, legal affairs spokeswoman for the liberal Free Democrats, called for more treatment with prison psychotherapists.</p>
<p>&quot;You cannot generalise to say that every sexual offender will re-offend. That would mean there is no cure and not even therapy could help,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
