<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73598" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Twelfth person arrested in Belgian child sex case.</title>
<headline>Twelfth person arrested in Belgian child sex case.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian police made their twelfth arrest on Tuesday in the scandal of child abduction, sexual abuse and murder that has shaken the country to the core.</p>
<p>Marleen De Cockere was charged with criminal association and drug trafficking. Belga news agency said she was also implicated in the illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>De Cockere is the companion of Jean-Michel Nihoul who has been under arrest since August 16 on charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>Nihoul, whose lawyer admits he takes part in orgies with consenting adults, has since also been charged with abduction.</p>
<p>Belgium has been in shock since August 16 when the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were found on a property owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere near the southern city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>The two children had been kidnapped by associates of Dutroux 14 months earlier. He said they starved to death around the start of this year.</p>
<p>The discovery followed the rescue of two other girls -- Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, -- from a secret dungeon in another house owned by Dutroux in Marcinelle, a suburb of Charleroi.</p>
<p>On Friday Belgian television showed the first pictures of the one metre by three metres (three feet by nine feet) dungeon in which Julie and Melissa died, hidden behind a heavy, soundproofed steel and concrete door set in the wall in the basement.</p>
<p>Two more teenagers -- Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal -- were found dead two and a half weeks later at the home of Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing.</p>
<p>Belgian television said several people had been questioned on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Dutroux, who was also involved in an international car theft ring, and accomplice Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice.</p>
<p>Three other people have been charged in relation to the child sex and pornography ring -- including Annie Bouty, a former companion of Nihoul.</p>
<p>Four others -- including Georges Zicot, a chief detective specialising in tackling car theft -- have been charged in connection with the stolen cars.</p>
<p>All but two of the 12 are being held in custody while investigations continue.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
