<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73614" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police make 12th arrest in child sex case.</title>
<headline>Belgian police make 12th arrest in child sex case.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian police, struggling in their investigations into a child abduction, sex abuse and murder scandal, made a breakthrough on Tuesday with a new arrest -- the twelfth in a case that has horrified the nation.</p>
<p>Marleen De Cockere was charged with criminal association and drug trafficking. Belgian media said she was also implicated in the illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>Four young girls have died while in the hands of a paedophile porn ring allegedly run by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Two others were rescued from a cramped secret dungeon in a house owned by Dutroux.</p>
<p>Police, searching for at least seven other girls -- some who have been missing for years -- are engaged in a public slanging match with each other and with the judicial authorities over who made the most mistakes in the mishandled investigations.</p>
<p>Dutroux's own mother, with whom he has not spoken for more than 20 years, denounced him to police as a criminal last year in an attempt to regain possession of her house from him. Police took no action.</p>
<p>De Cockere is the most recent ex-companion of Jean-Michel Nihoul, who has been under arrest since August 16 on charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>Nihoul, a flamboyant Brussels businessman whose lawyer admits he takes part in group sex sessions, has since also been charged with abduction. He denies the charge.</p>
<p>&quot;He is an orgy enthusiast, it's no secret, but they take place...only with consenting adults,&quot; Nihoul's lawyer Virginie Baranyanka said recently.</p>
<p>Belgium has been in shock since August 16, when the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were found on a property owned by unemployed father-of-three Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere near the southern city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>The two children had been kidnapped by associates of Dutroux in June 1995. He said they starved to death early this year.</p>
<p>The discovery followed the rescue of Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, from a secret dungeon in another house owned by Dutroux in Marcinelle, a suburb of Charleroi.</p>
<p>On Friday Belgian television showed the first pictures of the one metre by three metres (three feet by nine feet) dungeon in which Julie and Melissa died, hidden behind a heavy, soundproofed steel and concrete door set in the wall in the basement.</p>
<p>Two more teenagers, Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal, were found dead two and a half weeks later at the home of Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing.</p>
<p>Belgian television said several people had been questioned on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Dutroux, who was also involved in an international car theft ring, and accomplice Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice.</p>
<p>Three other people have been charged in relation to the child sex and pornography ring, including Annie Bouty, another former companion of Nihoul.</p>
<p>Four others -- including Georges Zicot, a chief detective specialising in tackling car theft -- have been charged in connection with the stolen cars.</p>
<p>All but two of the 12 are being held in custody while investigations continue.</p>
<p>Police have seized hundred of pornographic video tapes in raids on properties owned by Dutroux and Nihoul, although Belgian media report that only a fraction are paedophile porn.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
