<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73641" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian sex scandal upsets adult-child relations.</title>
<headline>Belgian sex scandal upsets adult-child relations.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>A paedophile kidnap, sex and murder scandal which has rocked Belgium in the past month has made millions of adults, especially men, fearful of showing physical affection towards children.</p>
<p>Can a father take a bath with his five-year old son or daughter? Is it OK to hug your 10-year old nephew? And what if the neighbours' 12-year old daughter kisses you on the cheek when she meets you on the street?</p>
<p>All such apparently natural manifestations of love are now subject to question.</p>
<p>&quot;My husband used to go take a bath with our (four-year old) daughter. But this affair has made me think. What if she talks about it in school?&quot; said Mieke, a 36-year old Belgian lobbyist.</p>
<p>&quot;At my son's birthday party, one of the boys came over, gave me a hug, said &quot;you are my mummy' and put his head in my lap -- while other parents were there. I was petrified. Because of the Dutroux affair,&quot; said Victor, father of a five-year-old.</p>
<p>The gruesome details of how a paedophile gang, in which convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux is the chief suspect, kidnapped, abused and killed four girls have been headline news nearly every day since mid-August.</p>
<p>Besides killing what faith Belgians had left in the ability of their police and courts to prevent such crimes, it has shattered a widespread belief that atrocities like this could not happen here.</p>
<p>Despite the scandal surrounding the Dutroux case and recent discoveries in the 1991 murder of politician Andre Cools, Belgium is still a low-crime country, where drug warfare, gang violence and sex crimes make headlines because they are rare.</p>
<p>&quot;This is terrible, it is the loss of innocence for a whole country. In my country (the U.S.) this happened a long time ago,&quot; said Nathan, 34, a New York TV producer visiting Belgium.</p>
<p>One long-time resident of the United States, now working in Belgium, said that while it was easy to overstate the concern in America, he had been aware of possible pitfalls as a soccer coach for eight year olds.</p>
<p>&quot;You had to be aware that hugs and other ways of celebrating could be misinterpreted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In Belgium, most men would be less apprehensive about this.</p>
<p>&quot;When my (five-year old) son's friends come to me in the playground and want to wrestle, I wrestle with them, it is the most normal thing in the world,&quot; said a Brussels architect, 34.</p>
<p>&quot;Children are very physical. And taking a bath with your child is the most natural thing in the world,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>An article entitled &quot;The Eros of Parenthood&quot; in the U.S. magazine the New Yorker last February described how not touching children could also be a crime.</p>
<p>&quot;What else can we make of research that tells us paedophiles tend to subscribe to...puritanical views about sex? That, within a family, harshly conservative values are a risk factor for sexual abuse. Or that sexual abuse is more likely to occur in families where there is an absence of physical affection?&quot;</p>
<p>Luk Goethals, 42, a book keeper in Ghent, agrees.</p>
<p>He said the Dutroux case had not changed his behaviour towards children but there was a risk that the media attention about would stifle men's natural reactions to children.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope we will be able to continue experiencing intimacy with our own children and those of our friends,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
