<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73706" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Justice ministers to broach child sex trade.</title>
<headline>Justice ministers to broach child sex trade.</headline>
<byline>Janet McEvoy</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>With the European Union's attention focussed as never before on the problem of cross-border crime, EU justice ministers gather in Dublin on Thursday to seek concrete solutions to the child sex trade.</p>
<p>With the 15-nation bloc reeling from revelations of child murder, prostitution and pornography in Belgium, ministers will seek to put meat on the many good intentions expressed since the scandal hit the world's headlines in August.</p>
<p>&quot;Recent events brought home to us all the obscene and shocking crimes perpetrated against children on our continent,&quot; Irish Premier John Bruton, whose country is current EU president, recently told the European Parliament.</p>
<p>The world reacted with horror when the bodies of Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, kidnapped from their Liege homes in June 1995, were found on August 17, 1996 in a property owned by convicted rapist Marc Dutroux in south Belgium. They had been starved to death.</p>
<p>The bodies of Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal, abducted in August 1995 from the Belgian seaside town of Ostend, were found on another property associated with Dutroux three weeks ago.</p>
<p>Two other girls were rescued, and the ensuing investigation revealed links between the Belgian ring and the Czech Republic and Slovakia and links with trafficking in stolen cars.</p>
<p>Most agree, the four girls are the tip of the iceberg in a growing child sex trade which respects no borders and has no limits.</p>
<p>EU members, jealous of their own police and judicial systems, have previously been reluctant to extend the EU's competence to lead the fight against cross-border crime, which also involves trafficking in drugs, women, cars and nuclear materials and money laundering.</p>
<p>But EU officials hope that the EU will be now so shaken that national governments will now put aside their reservations.</p>
<p>Bruton said Ireland would urge the ministers to extend the mandate of the EU's embryonic police agency Europol, based in the Dutch capital The Hague, so that it can deal with the child sex trade.</p>
<p>EU Justice Commissioner Anita Gradin told Reuters she would urge the EU governments to urgently ratify the convention which will put Europol fully to work.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone should go home and ratify the Europol convention. If we want to get hold of these gangs who are stealing, abducting children then you need a Europol that's effective,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Until the convention, previously delayed by a row between Britain and its EU partners over the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice, is ratified Europol can not start vital work analysing data provided by various police forces.</p>
<p>Gradin said she would also urge the increased practice in member states of trying at home the many Europeans who go overseas as &quot;sex tourists&quot; to indulge in sex with children.</p>
<p>Belgium has said it will push for a Europe-wide solution to combat use by paedophile and pornography networks to advertise their wares on the internet, which is little policed and where anonymity can be assured.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
