<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76635" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bonn minister to examine law as abused girl buried.</title>
<headline>Bonn minister to examine law as abused girl buried.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gray</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's justice minister pledged on Wednesday to examine ways to keep a closer eye on convicted sex offenders as the seven-year-old victim of an horrific attack which sparked nationwide outrage was buried.</p>
<p>Edzard Schmidt-Jortzig said it was time to consider additional therapy for sex offenders and to release them early from prison only with the consent of an external medical expert.</p>
<p>His call came as friends and family of little Natalie Astner attended her funeral in the tiny Bavarian village of Epfach. Thousands of flowers and wreaths from across Germany decorated the local chapel where the ceremony took place.</p>
<p>&quot;Dear Natalie, this picture and these flowers are for you&quot; read a note scrawled in childish handwriting and attached to a bunch of flowers placed on a bridge above the river where Natalie's body was found.</p>
<p>&quot;I can well understand the anger and horror unleashed by the crimes against Natalie,&quot; Schmidt-Jortzig said in a statement. &quot;Everything possible must be done to prevent such crimes.&quot;</p>
<p>Natalie was abducted on her way to school on Friday, sexually abused, battered unconscious and left to drown in the river by a sex offender who was released after serving two-thirds of a 5-1/2-year sentence for child abuse.</p>
<p>The case, and heartbreaking pictures of Natalie on the front page of newspapers across the country since her abduction, has prompted calls for chemical castration of paedophiles, stiffer sentencing and an end to early releases for sex offenders.</p>
<p>The mix of outrage and frustration in Germany in the wake of Natalie's death has been reminiscent of the mood in neighbouring Belgium, where investigators have uncovered a child porn ring allegedly run by a sex offender also released early from prison.</p>
<p>But Schmidt-Jortzig, a former law professor, cautioned that while he would consider new measures, the current German system offered valuable ways of dealing with sex offenders which should not be discarded lightly.</p>
<p>The minister, a member of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's liberal Free Democrat coalition partners, said letting offenders out early allowed the courts to attach certain conditions to their freedom such as attending regular therapy sessions.</p>
<p>&quot;If we free sex offenders only after they have served their entire sentence, these possibilities disappear and the risk of repeat offences would rise,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Suspending a part of the sentence protects the public from new offences,&quot; he said. &quot;Abandoning the suspension would by no means lead to more security for the public.&quot;</p>
<p>Bavaria's ruling Christian Social Union (CSU) has spearheaded the calls for tougher action, including stricter guidelines for early release and forcing offenders to attend therapy sessions even after they have served their full term.</p>
<p>Commentators have been divided on the issue, with some backing Bavaria's call to look at the possibilities of chemical castration while others have echoed Schmidt-Jortzig in defending postwar Germany's liberal tradition in law and order matters.</p>
<p>&quot;What happens if a violent criminal serves his complete sentence? Is he a different person after seven years than he was after five?&quot; the liberal Sueddeutsche Zeitung asked.</p>
<p>&quot;It does not help to throw offenders in a cell, keep them there for a predetermined time and then let them out again.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
