<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78982" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Justice ministers agree measures to fight child sex.</title>
<headline>Justice ministers agree measures to fight child sex.</headline>
<byline>Janet McEvoy</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union justice ministers, reacting to a Belgian child-murder and sex scandal, on Thursday agreed to extend the scope of the EU's police agency Europol so it could help fight the sex trade in children and women.</p>
<p>Irish Justice Minister Nora Owen told reporters the EU reached agreement on the plan and said it was the quickest and most effective response to a form of crime thrown into the world spotlight by the discovery of four murderered girls in Belgium.</p>
<p>&quot;We intend to fight against the work of criminals in the trafficking of people in the same way as we fight against drugs trafficking,&quot; Chief of the Hague-based agency Juergen Storbeck told reporters after the agreement was made.</p>
<p>The agreement, which includes a move to exchange police officers throughout the EU for training and set up centres to help fight the sex trade will be formalised at another meeting of EU ministers.</p>
<p>Storbeck said the agency, which already helps fight drugs trafficking and money laundering, could help speed up exchanges of information between different police bureaux in the 15-nation EU and carry out strategic analysis.</p>
<p>EU Justice Commissioner Anita Gradin said that Europol should be able to start its new work in The Hague in a couple of months, but said that only when EU governments ratified the Europol convention would the EU feel the full benefit.</p>
<p>&quot;We need that (the convention) to do the long-term work that's necessary for tackling the questions voters are worried about,&quot; Gradin told a news conference.</p>
<p>Although Europol can help exchange information it is unable, until the convention is ratified, to set up a central database of missing children.</p>
<p>EU members, traditionally reluctant to increase the EU's crime-fighting role, were stung into action after the discovery of the bodies of four murdered girls in Belgium highlighted the world trade in child sex and pornography.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very impressed. In the 20 years I've been in the business I've never seen such speed of agreement,&quot; Europol's Storbeck said.</p>
<p>Other ideas for tackling the child sex trade will be considered further, including an idea advanced by Belgium for harmonised jail sentences.</p>
<p>Although there was broad agreement that European &quot;sex tourists&quot; who travel overseas to indulge in sex with children, could be tried at home it remained to be agreed on exactly how this should be done, Belgian Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck told reporters.</p>
<p>With Europol's help information on missing children and people suspected of abducting them could be exchanged between criminal, customs and border police in less than an hour, and it could help coordinate parallel investigations in member states, Storbeck said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
