<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81731" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Four released, six detained in Belgian sex horror.</title>
<headline>Four released, six detained in Belgian sex horror.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Magistrates released four people but kept the six key suspects in jail on Friday in Belgium's horrific child kidnapping, rape, murder and car theft scandal.</p>
<p>Chief suspect Marc Dutroux, his second wife Michelle Martin, and associates Michel Lelievre, Michael Diakostavrianos, Jean-Michel Nihoul and Annie Bouty remain in jail.</p>
<p>But the court, which must decide each month whether imprisonment remains necessary before trial, opted to release chief police detective Georges Zicot, alleged car theft scam companion Gerard Pinon, Dutroux associate Claude Thirault and Nihoul's latest girlfriend Marleen De Cokere.</p>
<p>The charges against the four, ranging from car theft to fraud and drugs trafficking, remain in place.</p>
<p>Two others -- insurance agent Thierry Dehaan and scrap metal dealer Pierre Roschow -- have already been conditionally released, although the charges remain.</p>
<p>The affair has already turned up the bodies of four abducted young girls and that of Dutroux' associate Bernard Weinstein, revitalised the search for at least seven other missing Belgian children and propelled the world into action.</p>
<p>Hundreds of pornographic video tapes have been seized, some featuring Dutroux, and soundproofed secret holding cells for the children have been found in some of the six houses the jobless father of three and convicted rapist owned.</p>
<p>The imprisoned Dutroux has purposely changed his image -- he now wears a diffrent haircut, glasses and a beard -- to disguise himself.</p>
<p>Nihoul, an admitted orgy enthusiast, is reputed to have at the least participated in orgies with De Cokere and others including people in high places.</p>
<p>The case has exposed gaping holes in cooperation between the different police forces investigating the disappearances of the children and the activities of Dutroux -- released early in 1992 from a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
<p>It has also held the Belgian judicial system up to a limelight that it does not welcome.</p>
<p>It has exposed the political nature of judicial appointments in a linguistically, culturally and economically divided country that even its advocates admit to be somewhat less than law-abiding.</p>
<p>It has also exposed the fact that rivalries between different judicial areas can mean serious crimes go effectively unpunished or even uninvestigated.</p>
<p>An interesting point on Friday was the fact that Dutroux lawyer Julien Pierre has applied for investigating magistrate Jean Connerotte, who with public prosecutor Michel Bourlet has broken the case wide open, to be removed on the grounds of bias.</p>
<p>Connerotte and Bourlet both had dinner last weekend with a group of people, including the parents of some of the dead children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
