<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82227" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Klaas killer sentenced to die by California court.</title>
<headline>Klaas killer sentenced to die by California court.</headline>
<byline>Fritz Faerber</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif. 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 42-year-old parolee was sentenced to death for the 1993 murder of 12-year-old Polly Klaas at a bitter court hearing on Thursday where he charged that the victim's father had molested the girl.</p>
<p>&quot;It is the order of this court that you shall suffer the death penalty,&quot; Santa Clara County Superior Court Judge Thomas Hastings told Richard Davis, who showed little remorse.</p>
<p>Klaas was kidnapped at knifepoint on Oct. 1, 1993, from a slumber party at her home in Petaluma in northern California while her mother slept down the hall. Police said Davis led them to her body, hidden under plywood and brush, two months later.</p>
<p>The body was badly decomposed but her skirt and nightgown had been pushed above her waist and her legs were spread apart.</p>
<p>In a videotaped interview with police in 1993, Davis confessed to strangling Klaas with a piece of yellow cloth. He adamantly denied trying to sexually molest her, but was convicted of that crime as well.</p>
<p>Before he was sentenced, Davis read a statement to the court in which he accused Klaas's father, Marc, of molesting his own daughter.</p>
<p>&quot;The main reason I know I did not attempt any lewd act that night was because of a statement the young girl made to me when walking her up the embankment: 'Just don't do me like my dad,'&quot; Davis said.</p>
<p>Klaas family members sobbed while others in the audience gasped and someone shouted &quot;Burn in Hell, Davis!&quot;. An enraged Marc Klaas stood as if to lunge at Davis, swore at him and was restrained by deputies who escorted him out of the courtroom.</p>
<p>Hastings said handing down a death sentence was always traumatic for a judge, but he told Davis: &quot;You've made it very easy today by your conduct.&quot;</p>
<p>He ordered Davis to be taken to San Quentin state prison near San Francisco. Under California law, the death penalty will automatically be appealed, a process that can take 10 years or more.</p>
<p>Outside court, Klaas called Davis a &quot;toxic pollutant&quot; and said his accusation &quot;shows the depths to which this individual will go to continue to inflict pain and suffering and agony in the continued victimisation of my family.&quot;</p>
<p>California Gov. Pete Wilson praised the judge and jury for rendering justice. &quot;We cannot call ourselves a civilised society if dangerous repeat felons are allowed to roam our streets and prey upon our innocent citizens,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Davis was found guilty of first-degree murder as well as kidnap, robbery, assault and other crimes in June and the jury recommended in August he receive the death penalty.</p>
<p>Hastings rejected a defence motion on Thursday for a retrial based on allegations of jury misconduct and he also denied a motion for the death penalty recommendation to be lowered to life in prison without possibility of parole.</p>
<p>Hastings also rejected defence arguments that Davis's harsh upbringing helped mitigate his crimes.</p>
<p>&quot;I cannot find that some alleged deprivation in your lifestyle caused you to brutally stalk, kidnap and murder Polly Klaas with the intent to sexually assault her,&quot; he told Davis.</p>
<p>In his statement, Davis said that &quot;for what it's worth&quot; he offered his &quot;sincere apology&quot; to Klaas's mother, Eve Nichol, and to &quot;certain members of the Klaas family.&quot;</p>
<p>But the gray-haired Davis made a number of complaints about the way his case was handled, saying police should have provided him with a lawyer when they first interviewed him after his arrest.</p>
<p>Addressing the court before sentencing, Marc Klaas told Davis: &quot;When you get where you're going, say hello to Hitler, say hello to (serial killer Jeffrey) Dahmer and say hello to (serial killer Ted) Bundy and good riddance and the sooner you get there, the better off we all are.&quot;</p>
<p>Davis had also caused an uproar after his conviction in June when he made an obscene gesture toward television cameras and the Klaas family in court.</p>
<p>Public outrage over Klaas's murder spurred California's drive to pass a &quot;three strikes, and you're out law&quot; mandating tough sentences for repeat offenders.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
