<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26568" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. News finds only 5 TV shows suitable for all.</title>
<headline>U.S. News finds only 5 TV shows suitable for all.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. News &amp; World Report screened the pilots for 34 television shows debuting this fall and rated only five &quot;suitable for all ages.&quot;</p>
<p>In its Monday edition, the magazine said a poll it conducted of 373 parents with children younger than 18 found that 62 percent of families want a television ratings system that sheds light on programme content.</p>
<p>Spurred by the poll the magazine created its own ratings system that graded programmes for sexual content, violence, language, horror and age appropriateness.</p>
<p>Of the 34 pilots, only five were rated &quot;suitable for all ages&quot; -- &quot;Life with Roger&quot; to air on the Warner Brothers cable network on Sunday nights, &quot;Cosby&quot; on CBS Monday nights, &quot;Promised Land&quot; on CBS Tuesday nights, &quot;Nick Freno: Licensed Teacher&quot; on the WB Wednesday nights and &quot;Clueless&quot; on ABC Friday nights.</p>
<p>Twenty-six of the pilots reviewed were rated &quot;12,&quot; suggested parental advisory for children 12 and under.</p>
<p>&quot;Dark Skies,&quot; a programme that will air on NBC Saturday nights, got the only &quot;17&quot; rating, suggested parental advisory for children 17 and under, because of its violence, horror and occasional vulgarities, the magazine said.</p>
<p>It noted that several programmes, including &quot;Sabrina, the Teenage Witch,&quot; &quot;Suddenly Susan&quot; and &quot;Life's Work&quot; were not ready for previewing and were not included.</p>
<p>The magazine's poll of parents, conducted Aug. 12-14, had a margin of error of plus or minus 6 percentage points.</p>
<p>According to the poll 27 percent felt the television ratings system to be created by the networks by January 1997 should be modelled on the motion picture ratings.</p>
<p>But 62 percent wanted a system naming programme content such as adult language or violence.</p>
<p>Thirty-eight percent of the parents polled watch television with their children nightly, 30 percent a few nights a week, and 11 percent about once a week.</p>
<p>Fifty-one percent said at least one of their children had television in their room, compared to 47 percent who did not. Two percent said they did not know.</p>
<p>Most parents said they were &quot;very concerned&quot; or &quot;somewhat concerned&quot; about obscene language, references to sex, visual images of nudity and references to casual sex in television programmes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
