<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="28440" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German TV moves to satisfy growing appetite for news.</title>
<headline>German TV moves to satisfy growing appetite for news.</headline>
<byline>Toni Straka</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sex, soap operas and game shows have lost their lustre for ratings-hungry German television stations as broadcasters seek to build audiences with hard-hitting news rather than titillation.</p>
<p>Responding to growing demand for fast and accurate information, nearly all nationwide broadcasting stations have expanded their news coverage or plan to do so soon.</p>
<p>The new approach is replacing the widespread assumption only a few years ago that Germany's audience of 80 million would only tune in for light entertainment.</p>
<p>Even the &quot;Tagesschau&quot;, the public ARD network's stodgy 8 p.m. broadcast considered the benchmark for serious TV news in Germany, is undergoing its first major facelift in four decades in response to the new interest in the news.</p>
<p>The stone-faced newscasters, many of whom are stars after 20 or more years on screen, will still read some reports from sheets of paper, a quaint touch Germans say gives the 15-minute show more credibility.</p>
<p>But the programme, which a critic once said would enjoy high ratings even if it were broadcast in Latin, will expand and adopt a slightly flashier appearance for the record-setting 8.5 million viewers it draws every evening.</p>
<p>&quot;We are looking into the biggest redesign the Tagesschau has seen in 40 years, including a new studio and introducing new and improved graphic elements in early 1997,&quot; said editor-in-chief Ulrich Deppendorf.</p>
<p>Deppendorf will jazz up news presentation in a 15-minute early edition of Tagesschau at 5 p.m. starting in January, replacing announcers with journalists reporting on camera.</p>
<p>While other stations spend millions of marks for their upgrades, ARD's investment in a new look seems cheap at 1.5 million marks ($1 million) in the high-stakes TV world where often talk shows command a similar price -- per show.</p>
<p>Tagesschau should not stray too far from its decades-old concept, competitors say. They consider it the prototype for news Germans wants to see -- and like to watch it themselves.</p>
<p>&quot;The dry Tagesschau got engraved in our minds for 40 years. No German has accepted 'infotainment' as serious news since,&quot; says Karl-Ulrich Kuhlo, founder of n-tv, a news station majority owned by Cable News Network (CNN) of Turner Broadcasting.</p>
<p>Aimed at professionals, n-tv will expand its news coverage in place of featured programmes from October this year.</p>
<p>From 6 to 9 a.m., viewers will see an hour-long mix of world and business news on a rotating basis with continuous updates in place of programmes like health magazines, Kuhlo said.</p>
<p>Germany's other private TV stations -- which in their early days established small news operations only to interrupt a steady mix of shows, movies and commercials flooding the country's living rooms -- are gearing up considerably as well.</p>
<p>Pro 7, which in 1997 becomes the first German station to raise capital by way of a public share issue, now employs about 120 people in its newsroom and has opened several news bureaux. &quot;Five years ago, it was a handful,&quot; said news editor Claudia Merkle.</p>
<p>A new studio, a new design and expanded news coverage introduced at the beginning of this year is beginning to pay off. A daily average of one million viewers zapped to Pro 7's news in July, after a low of 800,000 earlier this year.</p>
<p>More news programmes in the afternoon and late at night are under consideration, Merkle said.</p>
<p>Sat 1, once a station devoted to replaying family-oriented series and talk shows, veils its news projects in secrecy. A spokeswoman declined to comment before a news conference next month to present new programming highlights.</p>
<p>The biggest news impact at Sat 1 might come from Bild-TV, a screen version of Germany's mass-circulation Bild daily better known for spectacular headlines than facts-only reporting.</p>
<p>&quot;But we have one problem. We don't know their concept and which persons will do it,&quot; the spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>VOX, one of the first stations to attempt producing a full programme like the public stations, recently introduced live newsbreaks for events like the Olympics park bomb attack.</p>
<p>But the station was only a distant runner-up to Germany's biggest private TV station, RTL, in broadcasting news several hours after the tragedy.</p>
<p>Satisfied with its current news programme, VOX increasingly supplements its daily news with broadcasts done by a team from the weekly magazine Der Spiegel, said director Andrej Henkler.</p>
<p>Market-leader RTL has leapt into the information age, dropping the late-night bare-breasts show Tutti Frutti and introducing early morning news over the years.</p>
<p>Its latest move led to live coverage of breaking news and follow-ups every two hours but it has no plans to copy other news stations further.</p>
<p>&quot;We are a mass broadcaster and reach 21 to 25 percent of 14 to 49-year-olds with our news,&quot; said editor-in-chief Hans Mahr. &quot;We are number one (in terms of viewers) at any time of the day,&quot; he claimed.</p>
<p>RTL is not resting on its laurels. Autumn could bring news about news on RTL, said Mahr: &quot;It will certainly not be a programme aimed at small groups. We only do mass programmes. Our viewers are not interested in political discussions.&quot;  $1=1.4793 Mark)  020233 GMT sep 96</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
