<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="31504" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada licenses 23 new specialty TV channels.</title>
<headline>Canada licenses 23 new specialty TV channels.</headline>
<dateline>OTTAWA 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadians will soon have a lot more choice on their televisions, from all-news and history channels to gardening, comedy, cartoons, music and sports.</p>
<p>The government's broadcast regulatory agency, the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission on Wednesday licensed 23 new specialised channels, bringing to 54 the number of Canadian speciality services it has licensed.</p>
<p>Always sensitive to the influence of Canada's American neighbours, the CRTC was careful to point out how the channels would have high levels of Canadian content and how services already up and running had thrived.</p>
<p>&quot;These services are on the air because Canadians are watching them. These are not marginal services, struggling for audiences and survival,&quot; CRTC Chairwoman Francois Bertrand told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;They are staples of Canadian television, financially successful, attracting viewers, securing a place for Canadian culture and creativity.&quot;</p>
<p>Seven of the new services will use existing technology and be available within a year. The other 16, to be running within three years, are designed to use the new digital technology that will permit a much larger number of channels.</p>
<p>Two companies were given the right to go head-to-head with the government's Canadian Broadcasting Corporation's news channel -- CTV Television Network Ltd. in English and Tele-Metropole Inc. in French.</p>
<p>CTV will also be operating two sports channels.</p>
<p>Toronto's Globe and Mail will be operating a new business news channel by September 1999 in conjunction with WIC Western International Communications Ltd. and 24 percent by Canadian Satellite Communications Inc..</p>
<p>Shaw Communications Inc.'s YTV Canada Inc., which says it has the most successful speciality channel in Canada, won the rights to launch a second children's channel, called TreeHouse TV.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OTTAWA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
