<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36601" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: MCA's TV unit showing signs of life.</title>
<headline>MCA's TV unit showing signs of life.</headline>
<byline>Jerry Dubrowski</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>MCA Inc., once regarded as a fading giant in the television market, is starting to show signs of regaining some of its former glory.</p>
<p>Bolstered by a new management team, and a series of important alliances at home and abroad, MCA is transforming its lineup to land more programmes in prime-time, particularly in the highly lucrative half-hour segment.</p>
<p>This fall, the studio is doubling the number of pilots introduced into prime-time -- bringing the total number of MCA/Universal programmes airing this fall to nine. In addition, MCA has two dramas in the works for mid-season.</p>
<p>While it's unclear how many of the new shows will survive, MCA TV Group Chairman Greg Meidel is upbeat about the new season.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a great slate this year,&quot; Meidel said in an interview. &quot;We've got our hour business up and running and now with (the programing deal with Germany's RTL) providing working capital, it's taken some of the burden off the hour business and allowed us to get into the half-hour business.&quot;</p>
<p>For much of the 1970s and 80s, MCA dominated the prime-time lineup with dramas such as &quot;The Rockford Files&quot;, &quot;Columbo&quot;, &quot;Magnum P.I.&quot; and &quot;Murder, She Wrote&quot;.</p>
<p>However, in recent years, MCA's influence has dwindled as the market shifted away from hour-long action/dramas to 30-minute sitcoms such as &quot;Friends,&quot; &quot;Seinfeld&quot; and &quot;Frasier&quot;.</p>
<p>Meidel, who was hired last year from News Corp.'s Fox Television unit, has made rebuilding MCA's network development the No. 1 priority.</p>
<p>To strengthen its comedy lineup, MCA recently acquired a 50 percent stake in Brillstein-Grey Entertainment, the creative force behind such popular comedies as &quot;NewsRadio&quot; and &quot;The Jeff Foxworthy Show.&quot;</p>
<p>Then it signed a pair of lucrative programming deals with German media giants Kirch Group and the RTL broadcast group that will provide MCA with $2.5 billion over the next 10 years.</p>
<p>Meidel said the deals will not only provide MCA with capital for new projects, but they also give the company a foothold in the all important international market, where demand for top-rated programmes has sparked a buying frenzy.</p>
<p>&quot;Free enterprise is taking over,&quot; he said. &quot;When you go from state-run, state controlled broadcast operations to competition ... where you only have advertising revenue as the primary source of income, there's only one way you get more money than the other guy and that is with better ratings.&quot;</p>
<p>Over the next five years, Meidel predicted MCA's international business could account for as much as 60 percent of total revenues, almost double today's level, as MCA expands into Latin America and Asia.</p>
<p>For MCA, the push overseas is critical.</p>
<p>Unlike Walt Disney Co., Time Warner Inc. and News Corp.'s Fox, which all have access to established broadcast or cable networks, MCA has had to go it alone.</p>
<p>While MCA and its parent company Seagram Co. Ltd. have not ruled out an acquisition or network alliance in the future, Meidel said MCA was devoting the bulk of its energy to improving its lineup and strengthening its USA Network, the cable channel jointly owned with Viacom Inc.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a luxury when you have a distribution component in the domestic marketplace but there's still no substitute for hits,&quot; he said. &quot;Once you establish a track record of producing hits then they're going to come to us.&quot;</p>
<p>This fall, MCA is launching two new dramas and two new comedies to go along with the five returning programmes.</p>
<p>In addition, it is planning a mid-season drama called &quot;One L,&quot; based on the popular Scott Turow book about his first year in law school and &quot;Feds,&quot; about the U.S. attorney's office in New York.</p>
<p>Meidel promises the fast-paced &quot;One L&quot; will be to law what Warner Bros' top-rated E.R. is to medicine.</p>
<p>But as successful as MCA's hour-long dramas have been, the comedy segment is where the studio is hoping to make its mark.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to have a balanced portfolio,&quot; Meidel said. &quot;Our international business is driven by the hours and it's driven by theatrical, and our business in the states is driven by the comedies. The good news is the hour business has improved dramatically because basic cable is now reaching a point where they can be very, very competitive in pricing.&quot;</p>
<p>Just a few years ago a top-rated drama would fetch as much as $300,000 an episode. But with cable and broadcast stations clammoring for content, the price has risen to $1 million.</p>
<p>However, a top-rated comedy programme such as NBC's &quot;Friends&quot; could easily command $4 million an episode.</p>
<p>This fall, MCA's comedies include &quot;Mr. Rhodes&quot; starring comedian Tom Rhodes and &quot;Something So Right&quot; starring Mel Harris and Jere Burns.</p>
<p>Further out, Meidel would like to have one daily series on the air next year and develop a late-night talk show along the lines of Arsenio Hall's programme.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there's a huge opportunity for an ethnic late-night show,&quot; he said. &quot;Since Arsenio Hall went away, that big urban marketplace has been left in a void.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
