<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="40119" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Study says U.S. parents revolting against violence.</title>
<headline>Study says U.S. parents revolting against violence.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Large numbers of parents in the United States are stomping out of movie theatres and turning off TV sets because of overt violence in entertainment, a survey said Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear that the time has come to stop this media madness, and parents across America know it,&quot; said John Nelson, a trustee of the American Medical Association which funded the poll.</p>
<p>The survey found that 66 percent of all adults among the 800 people questioned had turned off a TV programme or left a movie theatre because of violence on the screen. Among parents who were in the company of children the turn-off, walk-out level was 75 percent.</p>
<p>The survey also said 68 percent of parents want a stronger movie rating system, 81 percent want a rating system for TV shows and computer games and 72 percent want one for music.</p>
<p>&quot;Our kids spend more time today learning about life through media than any other source. We know media violence leads to real life violence,&quot; said Nelson, an obstetrician from Salt Lake City who is the father of eight.</p>
<p>&quot;Our children learn by example, whether it be from positive role models like caring parents, Mr. Rogers, Michael Jordan or from destructive influences like Mortal Kombat, gangsta rap, Power Rangers and Terminator One and Two,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only is our country's overdose of media violence contributing to a generation of individuals who are aggressive and insolent, they are young people who are also suffering the effects of couch potato syndrome and brain drain,&quot; said Nelson.</p>
<p>His comments were prepared for delivery at a news conference at the headquarters of the largest U.S. doctors' group at which the survey was to be released.</p>
<p>The AMA also said it was distributing a physician's guide to media violence to 60,000 doctors to help educate them and in turn their patients on the dangers of violence in entertainment.</p>
<p>David Walsh, founder of the National Institute on Media and the Family who helped the AMA draw up the guidelines, said &quot;It is tragically ironic that at the very time we are wringing our hands about violent behaviour among young people, we are simultaneously entertaining them with it.&quot;</p>
<p>The telephone survey was conducted early last month by Global Strategy Group Inc. of New York and had an error rate of plus or minus 3.5 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
