<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41975" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Politics discussed backstage at Emmys, no airplay.</title>
<headline>Politics discussed backstage at Emmys, no airplay.</headline>
<byline>Sue Zeidler</byline>
<dateline>PASADENA, Calif 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Politics got little airplay at the Emmy Awards Sunday, although several celebrities spoke backstage about the political backlash facing the television industry in this election year.</p>
<p>&quot;There's too much whining in this culture. If you like what you watch, you can watch it. If you don't, you can just turn it (TV) off,&quot; comedian Dennis Miller told reporters backstage after receiving two Emmys for his variety show, &quot;Dennis Miller Live.&quot;</p>
<p>By &quot;whining&quot;, Miller referred to the increasing criticism by President Clinton, Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole, lobby groups and legislators who have said that television airs too much on-screen sex and violence.</p>
<p>The issue was sensitive in the television industry since the government recently ordered it to come up with its own rating system, or face imposition of standards by regulators.</p>
<p>&quot;Television has been Washington's silent 'whipping boy' far too long,&quot; said Richard Frank, president of the Academy of Television Arts &amp; Sciences, in the show's programme.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact is television is delivering programming 24 hours a day over more than 100 channels. It relentlessly educates, informs and entertains our country and around the world. With that much quantity it doesn't always get it right, but many times it does,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>While the violence issue was a popular topic behind the scenes, the Emmys presentation was decidedly upbeat, as it avoided politics and instead highlighted television's positive accomplishments through a nostalgic look at the last 50 years.</p>
<p>The show's producer Dick Clark told the L.A. Times Saturday that he hoped controversy would be absent from the show.</p>
<p>&quot;I really don't anticipate that anything like that is going to happen,&quot; Clark told the Times. &quot;This is really about celebrating television.</p>
<p>Indeed, the show's host, Paul Reiser, started the broadcast by joking about his own political apathy.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm just in TV. I don't know much about politics, but I know you need a village to get cable,&quot; Reiser said in a quip about Hillary Clinton's book on parenting &quot;It Takes A Village.&quot;</p>
<p>As celebrities arrived at the gala event to march up the traditional red carpet under a blazing California sun, two supporters of Republican candidates Bob Dole and Jack Kemp were among the cheering onlookers. They held placards that said, &quot;Dole and Kemp, In God We Trust; Go To Church and Not to Hell.&quot;</p>
<p>Meanwhile, some of television's most celebrated stars came out in favour of TV's harshest critics. &quot;The politicians are right,&quot; said legendary television show host Steve Allen.</p>
<p>&quot;If the American people matter any more, about 80 percent of them feel that television is not only disgusting, but that it's disgustingly vulgar. My concern is that if we don't clean up our act, we're going to get censorship and that would be terrible,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Several Emmy winners who have children expressed concern about television's subject matter.</p>
<p>Julia Louis-Dreyfus, star of &quot;Seinfeld,&quot; who  won the Emmy for best supporting actress in a comedy series, told reporters &quot;I'm happy when I can find shows that my son can watch and when he can't watch, I turn off the T.V.&quot;</p>
<p>Dennis Franz, who won best actor for his role in &quot;NYPD Blue&quot; said he was not opposed to monitoring television for certaing age groups, but added &quot;there's a large population of adults who want to see adult entertainment they can enjoy.&quot;</p>
<p>Actor Tim Conway told reporters, &quot;I like to watch the news and the weather channel. At least you won't see any violence on the weather channel.&quot;</p>
<p>The only overtly political wisecrack made during the prime-time awards show came from Garry Shandling, who quipped, &quot;I just ran some of my jokes past Dick Morris' hooker last night and she said they were okay.&quot;</p>
<p>Shandling was poking fun at President Clinton's disgraced advisor, who recently resigned after it was disclosed he told a prostitute sensitive campaign information.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PASADENA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
