<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49907" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bonn joins Ankara in attacking Kurdish-language tv.</title>
<headline>Bonn joins Ankara in attacking Kurdish-language tv.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The German government on Thursday joined Turkey in attacking a Kurdish-language satellite television station which broadcasts from western Europe to the Middle East.</p>
<p>A parliamentary written answer, reported by the parliamentary news service HIB, said British-based Med-TV was a &quot;propaganda mouthpiece&quot; of the banned Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK), which wants independence or autonomy in southeast Turkey.</p>
<p>Med-TV denies all links with PKK and its guerrillas although members of the party participate in televised debates. It says it is independent and has millions of viewers.</p>
<p>The German government, however, said that countless news and political programmes on Med-TV reported the actions, ideology and aims of the PKK &quot;uncritically and without comment&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The borders of objective reporting are regularly violated (in Med-TV broadcasts),&quot; the government said, in its reply to a question from deputies of the Party of Democratic Socialism.</p>
<p>Top functionaries from the PKK, which is outlawed in Germany and Turkey, were given airtime on a regular basis to spread their views, it said, according to HIB.</p>
<p>&quot;According to the German government, the PKK uses Med-TV as a &quot;mouthpiece for its propaganda',&quot; the HIB report said.</p>
<p>Ankara, which forbids broadcasts in Kurdish in Turkey, also says Med-TV is a mouthpiece for Kurdish guerrillas. Nearly 19,500 people have been killed in Turkey in the PKK's 12-year campaign.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
