<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="63056" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ulster TV says expects a better year in 1997.</title>
<headline>Ulster TV says expects a better year in 1997.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ulster Television Plc said on Wednesday that it expects a better year in 1997 with improving economic indicators, particularly the widely expected increased growth in consumer expenditure.</p>
<p>The company said 1996 was proving to be a difficult year for ITV with regard to advertising revenue, although there were some significant regional variations.</p>
<p>&quot;The short-term market remains slow and, for the year as a whole, we continue to expect that ITV is likely to achieve an overall year-on-year increase in line with inflation,&quot; Chairman J.B.McGuckian said in a results statement.  </p>
<p>&quot;We expect to achieve a broadly similar outcome, thus consolidating our market share of ITV revenue at around the two percent level,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Ulster TV said operaring costs for the second half of 1996 are not expected to vary significantly from the corresponding period in 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;Investment income will be lower following the 10.5 million sterling special dividend paid on July 1 this year, thus reducing future income from short-term deposits,&quot; said McGuckian.</p>
<p>Earlier, Ulster TV announced a 27 percent rise in pre-tax profits to 4.67 million pounds sterling for the six-months to June 30.  </p>
<p>Advertising revenue, which accounts for more than 95 percent of turnover, increased by 2.6 percent over the corresponding period in 1995.</p>
<p>Ulster TV said it had increased its share of total television viewing in Northern Ireland during the six-month period by 0.7 percent to 41.4 despite the increasing accessibility and number of new television channels.</p>
<p>ITV experienced a decline of two percentage points to 35.3 percent, it said.</p>
<p>With the introduction of cable television to Northern Ireland, the growth of satellite television and the imminent arrival of digital television services, new opportunities were emerging, the company said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We will continue to investigate and evaluate these, with a view to developing new revenue streams in areas where we can use our experience and skills and which are complimentary to our core broadcasting and programme-producing operation,&quot; McGuckian said.</p>
<p>Ulster TV said it was presently assessing feasibility of introducing new programme services on its guaranteed digital spectrum allocation following the the introduction of the 1996 Broadcasting Act.</p>
<p>The Act introduced a legislative and regulatory framework for the development of digital terrestrial televison and also further liberalising the restrictions on media and cross-media ownership.</p>
<p>The company said the ownership provisions will make possible further consolidation within ITV as well as greater ownership integration between newspapers and television.</p>
<p>-- Damien Lynch, Dublin Newsroom +353 1 6603377</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
