<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73034" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy's Telepiu sees deals with U.S. majors soon.</title>
<headline>Italy's Telepiu sees deals with U.S. majors soon.</headline>
<byline>Jude Webber</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian pay-TV operator Telepiu hopes to lure subscribers to Europe's first digital satellite service by hooking up with big U.S. entertainment names such as Disney, a source close to the company said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The source, speaking on condition of anonymity, said Telepiu expected its digital satellite operations to break even at the 1.2 million subscribers mark in about three years, and predicted steady growth for its analogue pay-TV channels.</p>
<p>Telepiu's digital satellite service DStv this month kicked off Telepiu'calcio, a pay-per-view package of live Italian soccer league matches it sees as the force driving subscriptions towards its goal of 100,000 to 120,000 by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The source said Telepiu was close to signing other deals.</p>
<p>&quot;I am convinced that there are no more than 10 or 15 channels that really add value,&quot; the source told Reuters.</p>
<p>Among them were Walt Disney Co, children's TV channel Nickelodeon which is owned by Viacom and HBO, a unit of Time Warner Inc. &quot;Most are in the pipeline and (programming deals) will be announced soon,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Telepiu expects sporting events to continue to be the main attraction for digital satellite television. It has signed an exclusive 10-year deal to broadcast Formula One motor racing in near video-on-demand form from next March, taking advantage of the Hot Bird 2 satellite which will be on stream.</p>
<p>That will mean viewers will have five parallel channels showing each grand prix in different ways, enabling the armchair racegoer to watch the event in his or her preferred format.</p>
<p>Telepiu, backed by the deep pockets of Germany's Kirch group and Dutch-based Nethold which each have 45 percent, already offers the three existing Telepiu channels, the Cartoon Network, BBC World, CNN, the Discovery Channel and Viacom's MTV on DStv.</p>
<p>The source saw more movie programming plus other music and leisure channels. &quot;In 12- to 18- months we will have a very mixed digital bouquet,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>He expected subscribers to Telepiu's analogue service -- its three core pay-TV stations -- to grow to some 900,000 by the end of 1996 from 800,000 now.</p>
<p>Italy's television market is a regulatory mess as parliament has yet to pass controversial regulation and set up a watchdog for the media and telephony sectors. Analysts say that despite this, its embryonic nature still makes it attractive.</p>
<p>With a vast array of national broadcasters -- state television RAI has three channels, former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's Mediaset has another three and media mogul Vittorio Cecchi Gori has two -- plus a staggering 700 local broadcasters, pay television has been fairly slow to take off.</p>
<p>Penetration is around four percent but analysts expect Italy to catch up.</p>
<p>&quot;Eventually we will see as many networks as everywhere else with the possible exception of cable,&quot; said Paul Kagan of Kagan World Media consultancy, which held a conference in Rome.</p>
<p>Italy is not yet &quot;cabled up&quot; and the regulatory framework for future cable operators has yet to be decided, meaning satellite services have the head start. &quot;The prospects for digital television are excellent,&quot; Kagan said.</p>
<p>Mediaset, which is shut out of offering pay-TV under the media legislation drafted by the centre-left government unless it sells one of its channels, was sanguine about the risks.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not contemplating that the end of general television is just around the corner,&quot; Mediaset vice-president Giovanni Stabilini told the conference.</p>
<p>&quot;The area where everyone is now betting big bucks is pay-TV,&quot; he said later. &quot;We might be lucky enough to be saved by the government.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
