<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77349" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK TV body to relax programme sponsorship rules.</title>
<headline>UK TV body to relax programme sponsorship rules.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's commercial television regulator said it planned to relax restrictions on television programme sponsorship, a move meant to help finance a growing number of new channels.</p>
<p>The Independent Television Commission (ITC) said it expected to enact revised sponsorship rules in January 1997, in response to requests from companies for the right to sponsor more programmes.</p>
<p>Television programme sponsorship really only got started in Britain about six years ago and the ITC initially placed tight restrictions on sponsorship for fear sponsors might unduly influence programme content.</p>
<p>But Frank Willis, ITC's director of advertising and sponsorship, told reporters the commission had decided sponsorship had not so far hurt television programme quality.</p>
<p>&quot;It (programme sponsorship) has come of age,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said sponsorship was now seen by the ITC as a needed source of finance, especially as developments in cable, satellite and digital television promised rapid growth in the number of channels over the next few years.</p>
<p>Willis said the ITC's proposed revision relaxed the existing rules, without going too far.</p>
<p>&quot;It's controlled evolution. We haven't pulled out the stops and said 'Let it rip. Anything goes,'&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The ITC has presented its proposals for a revised ITC Code of Programme Sponsorship to media groups, trade bodies and British and European authorities, and expects to finalise the revised code in January.</p>
<p>Companies in Britain spend about 22 million pounds ($34 million) last year on television sponsorship, a small percentage of the amount spent on advertising.</p>
<p>But companies say they want the right to sponsor more television programmes, since this often provides them with a better way to get their message to consumers who are turned off by advertising.</p>
<p>The revised sponsorship code will affect Britain's two terrestrial commercial stations, ITV and Channel 4, as well as cable and satellite television.</p>
<p>Most British viewers watch ITV, Channel 4 and two publically-funded British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) channels.</p>
<p>Willis said cable and satellite television only reached about 25 percent of British homes and 33 percent of British children so far, but the audience is growing.</p>
<p>A new commercial station, Channel 5, is due to be launched in a few months and Willis said Britain expected to have some 20 digital terrestrial stations by 1998.</p>
<p>-- London Advertising Newsdesk +44 171 542 2792</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
