<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13335" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police in sex-abuse hunt for kidnap girls.</title>
<headline>Belgian police in sex-abuse hunt for kidnap girls.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police searchers returned on Sunday for a third time to a house at the centre of Belgium's child sex-abuse scandal that has horrified Europe.</p>
<p>In just over a week two young girls have been found dead, from starvation, two have been freed from a dungeon-like secret compartment and an international hunt has started for at least two others.</p>
<p>Police sought clues on the two girls missing in a grim saga of death, kidnapping and pornography that has raised fears of a group of paedophiles operating in European cities.</p>
<p>Police searched at the house in Sars-La-Bouissiere owned by chief suspect Marc Dutroux for the third time since the bodies of eight-year-old paedophile victims Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were found there a week ago.</p>
<p>Julie's father, Jean-Denis Lejeune, went with them to see for himself where his daughter and her friend had died of starvation nine months after being abducted in June 1995.</p>
<p>Recriminations have steadily built up over how convicted child rapist Dutroux managed to prey on children unhindered for so long -- with allegations of protection in high places.</p>
<p>Dutroux and associate Michel Lelievre have been changed with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice. Three other people face charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>Dutch police are also holding a 74-year old Dutchman in connection with the disappearance of An and Eefje, although a spokesman said no direct link had yet been established.</p>
<p>Dutroux was questioned through the night on Saturday, and Belgian RTL television said a police inspector had also been questioned. There was no immediate confirmation.</p>
<p>Public prosecutor Michel Bourlet, who has said Dutroux featured on some of the more than 300 paedophile porn video tapes that have been seized, is due to hold a news conference later on Sunday (Eds 1900 GMT).</p>
<p>Dutroux was charged a week ago after police rescued two young girls from a concrete dungeon in the basement of one of the six houses he owns in and around Charleroi.</p>
<p>A day later Dutroux led police to the bodies of the two eight-year-old girls. He also admitted kidnapping two other girls, An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, a year ago.</p>
<p>The fate of the girls is unknown, but there has been speculation they were sold into prostitution in Slovakia or the Czech Republic where Dutroux was a frequent visitor. Belgian police have visited Bratislava and will visit Prague.</p>
<p>At least part of the speculation in the Belgian media of high-level protection for Dutroux and his accomplices is based on leaked documents cataloguing a high degree of police bungling, incompetence and indifference.</p>
<p>Among the revelations are the that the gendarmerie was running a surveillance operation codenamed &quot;Othello&quot; against Dutroux in 1995 -- when both Julie and Melissa and An and Eefje were kidnapped.</p>
<p>They show that the gendarmes were aware that Dutroux was building cells in some of his houses for holding children, yet this information was either not passed on to other police forces searching for the missing girls or was overlooked when it was.</p>
<p>They also show that police investigating a theft visited Dutroux late last year at the house where Julie and Melissa were being held but accepted his word that the children's cries they could hear came from neighbours.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck has admitted that mistakes were made and ordered an inquiry at the same time as stressing there were no indications of a cover-up.</p>
<p>There is also widespread disbelief that no one appeared to question how Dutroux, an unemployed father of three with no visible means of support, managed to own six houses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
