<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13332" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian paedophile hunt moves to new area.</title>
<headline>Belgian paedophile hunt moves to new area.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police with mechanical diggers began excavating in another part of the southern city of Charleroi on Sunday in a search for clues to two missing, kidnapped girls, Belgian radio reported.</p>
<p>It said 40 officers, with excavation equipment and dogs trained to find bodies, moved into the property of a German demolition expert known for close contacts with the chief suspect in a child sex-abuse scandal, Marc Dutroux, who has admitted kidnapping An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks a year ago.  </p>
<p>The radio also said a police inspector had been arrested in connection with investigations into the scandal involving death, kidnapping and pornography. But there was no official confirmation and public prosecutor Michel Bourlet would only confirm that more people had been questioned.</p>
<p>Besides the two missing girls, two have so far been found dead and two have been rescued from a secret dungeon.</p>
<p>The radio said searchers at the demolition yard in the suburb of Courcelles were likely to work through the night and appeared hopeful of finding fresh clues to the whereabouts of An and Eefje.</p>
<p>Dutroux and associate Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice. Three other people face charges of criminal association.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
