<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14707" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police win backing in child sex case probe.</title>
<headline>Belgian police win backing in child sex case probe.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian detectives gained new support for their investigations into a widening child sex scandal when Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck vowed nothing would stand in the way of a successful conclusion to the case.</p>
<p>De Clerck on Monday tried to head off increasing public concern that the increasingly complex probe into the deaths of two eight-year-old girls, victims of a paedophile gang, might be cut short.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation will continue with all possible means, without obstacles and without any intervention,&quot; De Clerck told a news conference. &quot;I, like all the government, want us to get to the bottom of this case as quickly as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>The two girls, Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune, disappeared in June 1995 and were found dead just over a week ago. Chief suspect Marc Dutroux, 39, said they had starved to death and led police to their bodies buried in his garden.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued from a dungeon in another of Dutroux' six houses. Dutroux, a convicted sex offender, has also admitted kidnapping two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, who were 19 and 17 respectively at the time of their disappearance a year ago. They are both still missing.</p>
<p>Together with an associate Michel Lelievre, Dutroux has been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>Michelle Martin, Dutroux' second wife, has been charged as an accomplice and three men are facing charges of criminal association. One of these, Michael Diakostavrianos, is due to be formally charged on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Investigators in the southern Belgian village of Neufchateau said on Monday they had made a 10th arrest in connection with their inquiries into the scandal which has horrified the nation and attracted international attention.</p>
<p>Pierre Rochow, son of a scrap metal dealer, was arrested on charges of taking part in a criminal association concerning theft and receiving stolen goods.</p>
<p>His arrest followed three others on Sunday related to a car and truck theft ring, including that of senior police detective, Georges Zicot.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been linked with several people arrested for organised vehicle theft, and police now are investigating both this and the child sex scandal jointly.</p>
<p>Police have seized more than 300 video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux -- magazines, childrens' clothing and drugs, alleged to have been used to pacify young victims.</p>
<p>Searches resumed on Monday at Dutroux' house in the village of Sars-La-Buisierre where the bodies were found. They were led by Superintendent John Bennett, a British police officer who oversaw excavations in the so-called &quot;House of Horrors&quot; murder case in England two years ago, and involved the use of sophisticated radar imaging equipment.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the arrest of Chief Detective Zicot has added a new dimension to the scandal, fuelling speculation about how such activities escaped detection for so long.</p>
<p>Newspapers and campaigners have questioned whether Dutroux might have enjoyed protection from high places. Justice Minister De Clerck has said he has no information to this effect.</p>
<p>Belgian media have also expressed concern about possible political or judicial pressure being exerted in the investigation after comments made on Friday by the public prosecutor in charge, Michel Bourlet.</p>
<p>Bourlet told Belgian television that he would successfully conclude the investigation &quot;if I am allowed to&quot;.</p>
<p>De Clerck insisted that &quot;in this investigation he has not been hindered&quot;.</p>
<p>The minister has however said that mistakes were indeed made during the investigation into the deaths of Russo and Lejeune, and he has promised a full &quot;inquiry into the inquiry&quot;, including the possibility of disciplinary action.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
