<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14713" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium vows no curbs on child sex investigation.</title>
<headline>Belgium vows no curbs on child sex investigation.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nothing will stop Belgian detectives plumbing the murky depths of a child sex scandal and bringing their investigation to a successful conclusion, Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck vowed on Monday.</p>
<p>De Clerck was heading off fears the increasingly complex investigation into the deaths of two eight-year-olds at the hands of a convicted sex offender might be cut short before the affair was completely unravelled.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation will continue with all possible means, without obstacles and without any interventions,&quot; De Clerck told a news conference. &quot;I, like all the government, want us to get to the bottom of this case as quickly as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>Belgian media have expressed worries about possible political or judicial pressure being exerted in the investigation after comments made by the public prosecutor in charge, Michel Bourlet, last Friday.</p>
<p>Bourlet told Belgian television that he would successfully conclude the investigation &quot;if I am allowed to,&quot; and said he was talking from &quot;past experience&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I can confirm that in this investigation he has not been hindered,&quot; De Clerck said.</p>
<p>De Clerck has admitted however that mistakes were indeed made during the investigation into the deaths of young Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune and has promised a full &quot;inquiry into the inquiry&quot; including the possibility of disciplinary action.</p>
<p>Leaked police documents catalogue a high degree of police bungling, incompetence and indifference in the case. Vital information was either not passed on by investigators in one area to those in another, or if received, was not acted on.</p>
<p>Lejeune and Russo, who disappeared in June 1995, were found dead just over a week ago. Chief suspect Marc Dutroux led police to their bodies buried in his garden.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been charged with abducting two girls who were rescued from one of his houses and had been sexually abused. He has also admitted kidnapping two other girls -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks -- who are still missing.</p>
<p>Investigators have arrested nine other people since in connection with their inquiries into Dutroux.</p>
<p>The media and campaigners have also questioned whether, given he remained undetected so long, Dutroux might have enjoyed protection from high places.</p>
<p>De Clerck has said he has no information to this effect.</p>
<p>The minister said a cabinet meeting on Friday was expected to adopt promised new measures on sex offenders. These include tougher rules on early release from jail, and a review of how offenders are followed while on conditional release.</p>
<p>Dutroux, 39, was released for good behaviour in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
