<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15077" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium makes 10th arrest in Dutroux case.</title>
<headline>Belgium makes 10th arrest in Dutroux case.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian investigators said on Monday they had made a 10th arrest in connection with their inquiries into a rapidly widening child sex scandal which has rocked Belgium and drawn headlines across the world.</p>
<p>A court official in the southern Belgian village of Neufchateau said Pierre Rochow, son of a scrap metal dealer, had been arrested on Sunday on charges of taking part in a criminal association concerning theft and receiving stolen goods.</p>
<p>His arrest follows three others on Sunday in connection with a car and truck theft ring, including that of senior police detective Georges Zicot.</p>
<p>The central figure in the sex scandal, Marc Dutroux, has been linked with several people arrested for organised vehicle theft and police are now investigating both rings jointly.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted multiple child rapist, spent nearly four months in prison after being charged with car theft and related crimes last December.</p>
<p>His arrest then came after he had locked up Rochow and two others following an argument over the theft of a truck.</p>
<p>Dutroux has since been charged, with an associate, with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children. Belgian media said searches at his house in the village of Sars-La-Buisierre resumed on Monday.</p>
<p>They said Superintendent John Bennett, the British police officer who oversaw excavations in Britain's &quot;House of Horrors&quot; murder case, led the searches which involved the use of sophisticated radar imaging equipment.</p>
<p>Following Zicot's arrest, speculation has spread that a paedophile gang involved in killing and kidnapping children had received high level protection to avoid detection. His arrest added weight to questions over how the gang, thought to have been led by Dutroux, avoided detection for so long.</p>
<p>&quot;More indications of high level protection for Dutroux,&quot; said the leading Dutch-language newspaper De Standaard. It said an unlikely series of judicial blunders, plus documents and testimonies pointed directly to political and/or judicial cover.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck admitted last week mistakes were made and ordered an inquiry.</p>
<p>Newspapers feared the prosecutor in charge of the scandal, Michel Bourlet, might be hampered in his efforts to solve the scandal. He made a comment on television last Friday implying his investigation could be stopped short.</p>
<p>But De Clerck told a news conference on Monday no political or judicial pressure had been put on Bourlet in this case.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation will continue with all possible means and nothing will be put in the way,&quot; De Clerck said.</p>
<p>Two kidnapped eight-year-old girls have been found dead, two other girls have been rescued and police are hunting at least two more girls who have been missing for a year.</p>
<p>Police have seized more than 300 video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux -- magazines, childrens' clothing and drugs allegedly used to pacify young victims.</p>
<p>Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin has been charged as an accomplice and three men face charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>Zicot's connection was through one of Dutroux's accomplices, Bernard Weinstein, the prosecutor said. Dutroux admitted killing Weinstein after a disagreement over truck theft.</p>
<p>His body was found with those of Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, both 8, in a house belonging to Dutroux, who said they starved to death nine months after being abducted in June 1995.</p>
<p>Two other girls were rescued from a dungeon in another of Dutroux's six houses and police are hunting for at least two more whom Dutroux admitted kidnapping a year ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
