<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15082" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Outrage over Belgian child sex scandal grows.</title>
<headline>Outrage over Belgian child sex scandal grows.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Speculation that a paedophile gang involved in killing and kidnapping children received high level protection to avoid detection spread through Belgium on Monday following the arrest of a senior police detective.</p>
<p>The arrest on Sunday added weight to speculation about how the gang, thought to have been led by convicted rapist Marc Dutroux, avoided police detection for so long.</p>
<p>&quot;More indications of high level protection for Dutroux,&quot; said the leading Dutch-language newspaper De Standaard. It said an unlikely series of judicial blunders, plus documents and testimonies pointed directly to political and/or judicial cover.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck admitted last week that mistakes were made and ordered an inquiry. He did not confirm or deny the suggestions that Dutroux might have received protection, saying only that he had no such information.</p>
<p>De Clerck will hold a news conference at 1400 GMT.</p>
<p>Newspapers feared the public prosecutor in charge of the case, Michel Bourlet, might be hampered in his efforts to solve the scandal.</p>
<p>Het Nieuwsblad said in a front-page open letter it was worried by a comment made by Bourlet on television last Friday implying his investigation could be stopped short.</p>
<p>Bourlet said all the people identified on seized video tapes would be prosecuted, provided he was allowed to do so.</p>
<p>Two kidnapped eight-year-old girls have been found dead, two other girls have been rescued and police are hunting at least two more girls who have been missing for a year.</p>
<p>Police have seized more than 300 paedophile video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux -- magazines, childrens' clothing and drugs used to pacify the young victims.</p>
<p>Dutroux, convicted in 1989 for multiple child rape, and associate Michel Lelievre have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
<p>Michelle Martin, Dutroux's second wife, has been charged as an accomplice and three men are facing charges of criminal association.</p>
<p>But the arrest on Sunday of Chief Detective Georges Zicot, a specialist in tackling vehicle theft in the southern city of Charleroi, added a new dimension to the scandal. Zicot will be charged with truck theft, insurance fraud and document forgery.</p>
<p>Gerard Pignon, owner of a warehouse where the alleged stolen vehicles were stored, and insurer Thierry Dehaan were also arrested. Zicot's connection was through Bernard Weinstein, one of Dutroux's accomplices, the public prosecutor said.</p>
<p>Dutroux has admitted killing Weinstein after a disagreement over truck theft, he said.</p>
<p>Weinstein was found dead with the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in a house near Charleroi belonging to Dutroux, who said they starved to death nine months after being abducted in June 1995.</p>
<p>Two girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne, were rescued from a dungeon in another of Dutroux's six houses 10 days ago and police are hunting for at least two more, An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, whom Dutroux admitted kidnapping a year ago.</p>
<p>Recriminations have steadily built up over how Dutroux managed to remain at liberty for so long -- with allegations of protection in high places. Leaked police documents catalogue a high degree of police bungling, incompetence and indifference.</p>
<p>Police in Amsterdam said they had released a 74-year old man held in connection with the Belgian investigation.</p>
<p>&quot;We couldn't find any link between him and the Belgian case so he was released,&quot; spokesman Klaas Wilting told Reuters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
