<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16390" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: Slovak women visited Dutroux, police say.</title>
<headline>Slovak women visited Dutroux, police say.</headline>
<byline>Peter Laca</byline>
<dateline>BRATISLAVA 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Marc Dutroux, the chief accused in Belgium's sensational child murder and sex abuse case, visited Slovakia a number of times and about 10 young Slovak women went to Belgium at his invitation, police said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>But they have difficulty remembering what happened there, perhaps because of drugs, and are unsure whether they were filmed for pornography, Rudolf Gajdos, head of the Slovak office of Interpol, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Although Gajdos spoke of &quot;girls&quot; his deputy, Eva Boudova, said the case involved about 10 young women in their early 20s.</p>
<p>&quot;The police interrogated several Slovak girls who said that they had been invited by Mark Dutroux to visit Belgium,&quot; Gajdos said.</p>
<p>&quot;The girls said they went to Belgium voluntarily and the police suspect that they were used to act in pornographic films.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The police suspect (the girls) were under the influence of drugs as some girls admitted they took unspecified pills.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We have suspicions of a rape, but the police still have to find the victim,&quot; Gajdos added.</p>
<p>Dutroux's last visit to Slovakia was reported to have been as recent as July.</p>
<p>Slovak police are also cooperating with Belgium in the search for An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, who went missing last August.</p>
<p>Dutroux, 39, who was charged last week with the abduction and illegal imprisonment of two other girls aged 14 and 12, is one of several suspects in the Marchal and Lambrecks case.</p>
<p>Last Saturday he led police to the bodies of two other girls, aged eight, who died of starvation this year after their abduction in June, 1995.</p>
<p>The Czech office of Interpol said on Friday it would neither confirm nor deny that Dutroux had been in the Czech Republic, Slovakia's western neighbour and former federation partner.</p>
<p>Belgian police said an officer had visited Bratislava to talk with Slovak detectives about An and Eefje and other disappearances, and he planned to go also to Prague.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRATISLAVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
