<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17517" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police search garden of scandal house.</title>
<headline>Belgian police search garden of scandal house.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police on Tuesday intensified digging at a house owned by Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in Belgium's child sex scandal as the hunt for missing children continued.</p>
<p>A police official in Brussels told Reuters that the search for missing children was continuing but that a team of investigators was focussing on excavations in Jumet.</p>
<p>Public prosecutor Michel Bourlet said Dutroux had been brought to the house late on Monday night and had given vague indications where police investigators should dig.</p>
<p>&quot;No bodies have been found. Dutroux is cooperating in the investigation, but I have the impresssion that he is making us go around in circles,&quot; Bourlet told Reuters by telephone.</p>
<p>Earlier, neighbours in the southern Belgian village of Jumet said they had seen a handcuffed Dutroux brought to the house late on Monday. The house was inhabited at one time by Dutroux' dead accomplice Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>The area around the house -- a run-down building in an old industrial neighbourhood -- was cordoned off in a 300-metre (yard) radius. The house's garden was hidden from view with blue plastic sheeting, but bystanders could see the digging arm of a yellow crane lifting debris and scrap from the yard.</p>
<p>Several sniffer dogs were brought to the site, which swarmed with police and media.</p>
<p>Earlier, a police helicopter ordered down two press helicopters which were flying low over the scene.</p>
<p>Bourlet said Dutroux, who has been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment, continued to answer questions.</p>
<p>&quot;(Dutroux) continues to speak to us,&quot; he said. Earlier this week Bourlet described Dutroux as a manipulative character.</p>
<p>Dutroux led police to the bodies of eight-year-olds Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune and of Weinstein on August 17. They were buried in the garden of one of this other houses.</p>
<p>Dutroux has admitted killing Weinstein. The two girls starved to death earlier this year in a homemade cell while Dutroux was serving a short sentence for car theft.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued on August 15 from a dungeon in another of Dutroux' six houses.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted sex offender, has also admitted kidnapping two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, who were 19 and 17 respectively at the time of their disappearance a year ago. They are both still missing.</p>
<p>The police official told Reuters that police were still looking for at least three other Belgian girls who disappeared in the last five years, but that it was not sure that Dutroux was involved in their disappearance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
