<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17587" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police dig at scandal house, no bodies yet.</title>
<headline>Belgian police dig at scandal house, no bodies yet.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police on Tuesday intensified digging at a house owned by Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in Belgium's child-killing and sex-abuse scandal.</p>
<p>Public prosecutor Michel Bourlet confirmed that Dutroux had been brought to the house late on Monday night and had given vague indications where police investigators should dig. But he added no bodies had been found so far.</p>
<p>&quot;No bodies have been found. Dutroux is cooperating in the investigation, but I have the impresssion that he is making us go around in circles,&quot; Bourlet told Reuters on the telephone.</p>
<p>Earlier, neighbours told Reuters they saw a handcuffed Dutroux brought to the house late on Monday, where he stayed until about 1 a.m. on Tuesday. The house was inhabited at one time by Dutroux' dead accomplice Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>Around 9 a.m. (0700 GMT), about 30 police officers brought an excavator and what looked like high-tech search equipment to the house, neighbours said.</p>
<p>The entire area was cordoned off in a 300-metre radius around the house, while two police helicopters hovered overhead and dozens of investigators combed the premises.</p>
<p>Several sniffer dogs specialised in searching for bodies were brought on the site.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
<p>Just over a week ago, the bodies of eight-year-olds Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune and of Weinstein, whom Dutroux has admitted killing, were found buried in the garden of another house belonging to Dutroux.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued from a makeshift dungeon in another of Dutroux' six houses.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted sex offender, has also admitted kidnapping two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, who were 19 and 17 respectively at the time of their disappearance a year ago. They are both still missing.</p>
<p>Bourlet told Reuters that Dutroux continued to answer investigators' question, but denied rumours in the Belgian media that An and Eefje had been found.</p>
<p>&quot;(Dutroux) continues to speak to us,&quot; he said. Earlier this week Bourlet described Dutroux as a manipulative character.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
