<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19033" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: Dutroux suspected in murder of Slovak woman.</title>
<headline>Dutroux suspected in murder of Slovak woman.</headline>
<byline>Peter Laca</byline>
<dateline>BRATISLAVA 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Marc Dutroux, the chief accused in a Belgian child murder and sex abuse scandal, is suspected of murdering a young Slovak woman, the Slovak office of Interpol said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Rudolf Gajdos, head of Slovak Interpol, told a news conference Dutroux was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one Slovak woman.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the police versions in the case of the murder of young gypsy woman in Topolcany, western Slovakia, this July, is a suspicion that Mark Dutroux could have been involved in the murder,&quot; Gajdos said without elaborating on the age of the victim and on the other versions.</p>
<p>Slovak police, Interpol, and Belgian police have been following leads on Dutroux's activities in Slovakia and the neighbouring Czech Republic where he is known to have made frequent visits.</p>
<p>Gajdos said the police sketch of the suspected murderer was &quot;60 percent identical with Dutroux's portrait&quot;, and that Dutroux was known to have been in Topolcany around the time of the woman's murder.</p>
<p>&quot;Topolcany and the area around this town were reported to have been the most visited places by Dutroux and his accomplices in Slovakia,&quot; Gajdos said.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted child rapist and unemployed father-of-three, led police 11 days ago to the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of another of the six houses he owns around the southern Belgian city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>&quot;The Belgian police also informed us that Dutroux, together with one other man, had (also) planned the kidnapping of at least one Slovak woman,&quot; Gajdos said.</p>
<p>&quot;The plan apparently failed due to difficulties in crossing the border,&quot; he added, but did not elaborate.</p>
<p>The Slovak police are also investigating visits by about 10 Slovak women, aged 17 to 22, to Belgium, at the invitation of Dutroux.</p>
<p>The women said they went to Belgium voluntarily and police suspect they were used to act in pornographic films, Gajdos said earlier this week.</p>
<p>But he added they had difficulty remembering what happened during their visits to Belgium, perhaps because of drugs, and were unsure whether they were filmed for pornography.</p>
<p>Dutroux, 39, who was charged last week with the abduction and illegal imprisonment of two girls aged 14 and 12, is also suspected in the disappearance of Belgians An Marchal, 19, and Eefje Lambrecks, 17, who went missing a year ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRATISLAVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
