<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19781" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: DERYCKE WANTS INTERNATIONAL APPROACH TO SEX CRIME.</title>
<headline>DERYCKE WANTS INTERNATIONAL APPROACH TO SEX CRIME.</headline>
<byline>Trevor Datson</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian foreign affairs minister Erik Derycke said on Wednesday the horrific paedophile ring unfurling in his home country must not divert attention from the global scale of the tragedy of sex abuse.</p>
<p>On the second day of the Stockholm world conference on commercial sexual exploitation of children, Derycke said the tragedy in Belgium must not be allowed to dominate the congress.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be very selfish of us to only to address the situation we are now trying to live through. Everything is related, and what can happen in a protected society such as ours can happen all over the world,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>As delegates to the 130-nation conference got down to the serious work of turning the ambitious declarations of keynote speakers into practical action, Belgian police continued their search for young victims of sex abuse.</p>
<p>Belgians fear police may find the remains of as many as five youngsters at a house owned by Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in a child sex, killing and kidnapping scandal.</p>
<p>Derycke expressed his gratitude for expressions of sympathy following the killings of eight year-olds Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune and the disappearance of four other children.</p>
<p>But he said that despite its high profile, the Dutroux case was just one more reminder that child sex abuse is not limited to the Far East or developing countries.</p>
<p>&quot;Today, these two little girls rest in peace, side by side, in their regained innocence together with all the other victims whom maybe no one remembers, not even by name.&quot;</p>
<p>Although Belgian legislation on child prostitution and pornography is among the strictest in the world, Derycke said the recent tragedies had proved paperwork was not enough in Belgium or elswhere.</p>
<p>&quot;We already have a lot of international treaties...but I have the impression that a lot of countries think that by signing treaties the problem is solved,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Derycke said Justice Minister Stefaan de Clerck would announce measures on Friday to tighten up existing Belgian rules, but the core of the problem could only be tackled at an international level.</p>
<p>&quot;A worldwide system for combating these hideous crimes will primarily be brought about through real multilateral cooperation ...such a subject should be part of the negotiations now held in New York on the creation of an International Criminal Court.&quot;</p>
<p>Many of the speakers at the conference have drawn attention to the socio-economic inequalities that often force children into sex slavery, but Derycke went one step further.</p>
<p>&quot;It is the most extreme result of an ultra-liberal economic system where everything is possible and everything can be bought, even the body of a child,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
