<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24498" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: More Austrian arrests in child abuse scandals.</title>
<headline>More Austrian arrests in child abuse scandals.</headline>
<byline>Steve Pagani</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian police arrested two men on Friday for suspected sexual abuse of children aged between four and 15 living in a shelter for refugees in the city of Linz, police said.</p>
<p>The two Austrians, one aged 59 and the other 37, lived near the shelter for refugee children and had allegedly enticed their victims to their homes with offers of sweets and money during months of abuse, police said.</p>
<p>&quot;Two men have been placed under arrest under suspicion of sexually abusing children from the refugee shelter,&quot; said a police spokesman in Linz, 200 km (120 miles) west of Vienna.</p>
<p>Police declined to reveal the nationalities of the children at the home, though the vast majority of refugees currently living in Austria come from the former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>Pyschologists counselling the boys and girls reported that the children had said the men had done evil things to them, the Austrian news agency APA reported.</p>
<p>The arrests were made just two days after Vienna police detained three men on charges of child sex abuse and producing child pornography in a suspected &quot;child-for-hire&quot; network spread across central Europe.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Nikolaus Michalek said he was shocked by the arrests and said the courts would deal harshly with those convicted of child abuse crimes.</p>
<p>Michalek said Austrians would be morally culpable if they knew abuse was being perpetrated and failed to report it.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important that people do not try to ignore what is going on. Whoever does that is at least morally, possibly criminally, culpable,&quot; he told the Salzburger Nachrichten daily in an interview published in its Saturday edition.</p>
<p>News of yet more instances of child abuse in Austria will heighten the revulsion expressed in local media over the child abuse and murder of young girls in Belgium.</p>
<p>Belgian Marc Dutroux, alleged to be the dominant person in a paedophile pornography ring, has been named by police in the Slovak capital, Bratislava, as a suspect in the murder of one Slovak woman and the kidnapping of another.</p>
<p>Bratislava is an hour's drive away from Vienna.</p>
<p>Austrian police declined to comment on whether there was a connection between the Belgian case and the Vienna arrests.</p>
<p>Two of the men detained in Vienna are Austrian citizens, one born in Slovakia and the other in the Czech Republic. The third is Polish, police said. All three denied the charges on Friday.</p>
<p>Vice squad officers seized box-loads of videos and other pornographic material from the home of one of the suspects at the start of a major investigation into the procuring of children, some as young as seven, to paedophiles in the region.</p>
<p>Police sources said the hunt for others connected to the ring could involve neighbouring Slovakia, the Czech Republic and Germany.</p>
<p>The Austrian current affairs magazine News launched a major investigative report into the Vienna-based network which provided clients in the Austrian capital with a choice of 70 girls, largely from Slovakia, aged between seven and 13.</p>
<p>News presented its evidence to police this week before the arrests were made.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
