<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24515" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Campaigners try to tackle child sex abusers.</title>
<headline>Campaigners try to tackle child sex abusers.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian authorities toughened rules for sex offenders against children on Friday and Norway set up a cybercop to patrol the Internet for child pornography.</p>
<p>Belgian police, searching for the bodies of missing girls in a sensational child abuse and killing case, found &quot;hot spots&quot; in two houses owned by chief suspect Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>At an international conference in Stockholm, taking place this week as the Belgian case makes headlines around the world, experts said that Southeast Asia remained the major destination for child sex tourists with young girls sold for $300 a week in Cambodia.</p>
<p>Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene, in his first public statement on the case that has horrified Europe, said everything possible would be done to ensure it would never happen again.</p>
<p>&quot;Children represent our future. They deserve a happy childhood. We must protect and guarantee their rights. Everything must be put in place so that this drama is never repeated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted child rapist, was arrested and charged two weeks ago with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children. His arrest and the arrest of up to nine others has triggered a Europe-wide search for a paedophile ring.</p>
<p>Belgians were outraged to find that Dutroux was released from jail on a majority opinion 10 years early - despite advice to the contrary from his own mother.</p>
<p>The Belgian cabinet on Friday approved tougher rules on the early release of convicted child sex offenders.</p>
<p>At the World Congress Against Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children, which has attracted over 1,000 delegates to Stockholm from 130 countries, campaigners outlined measures to crack down on paedophiles' use of the Internet.</p>
<p>Norway's ombudsman for children, Trond Waage, said to date there was very little action that could be taken to stop the distribution of child pornography on the Internet.</p>
<p>But he said the establishment last week of a international body to monitor child pornography on the net, a task taken on by the Norwegian branch of Save the Children, was firm action against paedophiles using the net.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a kind of a cybercop,&quot; Waage told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;We need some visible cops on the net. If you undertake these kinds of criminal activities someone will monitor you.&quot;</p>
<p>Save the Children will try to monitor any child pornography on the Internet and is encouraging other net surfers to pass on information that will be handed to the police.</p>
<p>In Finland an Internet specialist said on Friday he was closing his remailer -- an anonymous forwarding system -- after rejecting allegations it was used as a conduit for child porn.</p>
<p>Johan Helsingius, whose remailer is one of the largest in the world with over half a million users, said in a statement he was closing down the system because the legal issues governing the Internet in Finland are unclear.</p>
<p>&quot;The legal protection of users needs to be clarified. At the moment the privacy of Internet messages is judicially unclear,&quot; said Helsingius.</p>
<p>&quot;I have also personally been a target because of the remailer for three years,&quot; he said on Friday. &quot;Unjustified accusations affect both my job and my private life.&quot;</p>
<p>The Stockholm conference, which ends on Saturday, has heard that child prostitution has started to emerge in eastern Europe as the tourist industry develops and overseas money pours in.</p>
<p>But Ron O'Grady, head of lobby group End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT), said Southeast Asia remained the world's worst hit area with more countries getting involved.</p>
<p>&quot;Paedophiles and child sex tourists are definitely looking for new areas as laws get tighter in these countries,&quot; O'Grady told Reuters outside the Stockholm conference.</p>
<p>&quot;As Vietnam and Cambodia develop their tourism industry along the lines of Thailand they are being affected by these problems more and more.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
