<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25096" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian cabinet agrees tougher rules on sex crimes.</title>
<headline>Belgian cabinet agrees tougher rules on sex crimes.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Belgian cabinet approved tougher rules on Friday on the early release from jail of convicted child sex offenders as the country continued to reel from the discovery of a paedophile sex ring led by rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has approved certain new measures,&quot; Justice Minister Stefaan de Clerck told reporters.</p>
<p>He said the measures included setting up a special tribunal of magistrates responsible for vetting requests for early release which would work on the basis of unanimity.</p>
<p>Up to now the decision on early release has been left to the Justice Minister and based on a majority of opinions from people ranging from the original prosecutor in the case to social workers, psychiatrists and prison staff.</p>
<p>&quot;The Minister of Justice will no longer be involved in deciding conditional release,&quot; De Clerck told a news conference after the first cabinet meeting since the affair broke two weeks ago.</p>
<p>Victims of sexual abuse would receive more help, abusers would be treated in special centres and be more closely monitored on their release and there would be better international coordination between police forces, he said.</p>
<p>He added that 8,000 existing files would be reopened.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene, in his first public statement on the scandal of paedophile abduction, porn and death that has horrified Europe, said everything possible would be done to ensure that it would never happen again.</p>
<p>&quot;Children represent our future. They deserve a happy childhood. We must protect and guarantee their rights. Everything must be put in place so that this drama is never repeated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dutroux, released from jail on a majority opinion 10 years early in 1992 from a 13-year sentence for multiple child rape, was arrested and charged two weeks ago with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>In two weeks of searching police have so far discovered the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of one of the six houses Dutroux owns in and around the southern city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>They have rescued two other sexually abused girls -- Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne -- from a dungeon in another of his houses and are searching for at least two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks -- whom Dutroux admits kidnapping.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
