<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25205" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian teachers prepare to explain horror to kids.</title>
<headline>Belgian teachers prepare to explain horror to kids.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Teachers are preparing to try explaining the horrors of Belgium's paedophile sex and murder case to children when school starts on Monday, and will step up efforts to make them more wary of adults.</p>
<p>&quot;We know we will get questions about the Dutroux case, and we are preparing for it,&quot; Myriam Eynikel, a primary school teacher in Brussels' Strombeek suburb, told Reuters on Friday.</p>
<p>Eight-year olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were found two weeks ago buried in the garden of a house owned by Marc Dutroux, the main suspect in the child sex case that has traumatised Belgium and sent waves of indignation across Europe.</p>
<p>Two other girls kidnapped by Dutroux and abused were rescued. The search is still on for other victims.</p>
<p>Massive media coverage of the case has made children as young as six or seven aware of the atrocities.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope all teachers will talk to the children about this, this is a task for the schools,&quot; Flemish regional Education Minister Luc Van den Bossche told Belgian radio RTBF.</p>
<p>Eynikel and her colleagues agreed earlier this week to invite the Fund for Kidnapped and Missing Children to speak to teachers and parents in October. Afterwards, lessons will focus for a week on kidnap prevention.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, she will rely on experience with her own eight- year old on how to answer questions about the unanswerable.</p>
<p>&quot;My daughter is terrified, she is glued to every newscast. We have tried to tell her there are adults with bad intentions, without focussing on the sex-abuse aspect,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Schools here have some experience with making youngsters aware of kidnap risk, as the disappearance of Julie and Melissa in June 1995 inspired many training programmes.</p>
<p>One of them is Parents-Secours, whose five educators have spoken to more than 6,000. In the coming weeks they will be speaking in schools nearly every day.</p>
<p>Myriam Graillet of Parents-Secours said the group teaches children to recognise potentially dangerous situations.</p>
<p>Children are told that it is acceptable to say &quot;No&quot; to an adult. They learn to develop defensive attitudes -- like referring strangers who ask for directions to adults, running to shops or houses when they are approached by someone suspicious or start shouting when they think they are in danger.</p>
<p>&quot;This provides some protection against the neighbourhood paedophile, but not against kidnappers using force,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Paul Marchal, father of 19-year old An who was kidnapped by Dutroux last year and is still missing, told Reuters parents and teachers should speak as frankly as possible to their children.</p>
<p>&quot;Be concrete. Tell your five-year-olds that if they go with a stranger, they will not see mummy and daddy anymore,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In Bla Bla, a children's programme on RTBF television, children made drawings of the horrors they had seen on television: dungeons, iron bars, small bodies underground, a policeman chasing Dutroux -- all in bright pencil colours.</p>
<p>The series' talking puppet Bla Bla echoed many children's bewilderment that Dutroux himself was a father of three. &quot;He is just like the other adults, like our parents,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>One of the children, eight-year old Aurore, had brought a dead insect in a bottle of water to the studio.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a centipede. I say it is Dutroux and his wife. I want to torture them. Sometimes I put the bottle in the fridge, so that they are very very very cold,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Child psychologist Jean-Yves Hayez told the children Dutroux was a sick man, who was probably treated badly himself when he was a child, and said there are more good adults than bad ones.</p>
<p>&quot;Because everybody is talking about bad people now that doesn't mean that there are a lot of bad people,&quot; Hayez told the children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
