<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25699" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Charges to be laid against Belgian detective.</title>
<headline>Charges to be laid against Belgian detective.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior police detective is due to be formally charged on Friday in connection with Belgium's paedophile abduction, porn and death scandal as police with dogs and radar equipment resume their hunt for bodies.</p>
<p>Georges Zicot, a chief police detective in the southern city of Charleroi, was arrested on Sunday. He faces charges of car theft, insurance fraud and forgery.</p>
<p>Three other people also face charges in connection with the car theft ring uncovered by police investigating a paedophile sex gang allegedly led by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been linked to organised vehicle theft and police are investigating the child sex and theft ring together.</p>
<p>At the same time the Belgian cabinet in its first meeting since the summer break is to adopt tougher rules on the early release from prison of convicted sex offenders.</p>
<p>Belgium has been in shock since Dutroux led police on August 17 to the bodies of eight-year-olds Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune in the garden of a house he owns at Sars-La-Buissiere.</p>
<p>Dutroux was released 10 years early in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for raping five children.</p>
<p>Police have been digging for more bodies since Tuesday in Jumet, a suburb of Charleroi, at one of Dutroux's other five houses in the area.</p>
<p>&quot;The dogs will be used in the basements to see if there are any bodies there,&quot; Gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin told reporters as searches ended on Thursday. In all, 11 sites will be explored.</p>
<p>Belgian radio said police would travel to Bratislava and Prague to search for missing Belgian children.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman. Interpol's Slovak office has said he was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one other Slovak woman.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Belgian gendarmerie's special disappearances squad said they were likely to contact colleagues in Austria investigating what seemed to be a &quot;child-for-hire&quot; network spread across central Europe.</p>
<p>Searches for bodies and clues in Belgium have focused on teenagers An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, who Dutroux, 39, has admitted kidnapping a year ago. Their fate remains unknown.</p>
<p>Dutroux's accomplice Bernard Weinstein, who he admitted killing, was found next to Julie and Melissa. Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued on August 15 from a dungeon in another of Dutroux's houses.</p>
<p>Dutroux has said Julie and Melissa, who were abducted in June 1995, starved to death early this year while he was in jail for car theft.</p>
<p>Originally Dutroux told police he had murdered Weinstein for letting the girls die. But he then charged his story to having killed him after falling out over car thefts.</p>
<p>Belgian newspapers, citing well informed sources, reported on Friday that Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin -- also under arrest -- had admitted that it was she who had failed to feed the children out of fear of facing them in their cell.</p>
<p>In their investigations police have so far seized up to 400 videos -- some featuring Dutroux -- children's clothing, magazines and a gun.</p>
<p>Ten people have so far been arrested including Martin who has been charged as an accomplice. Dutroux, a father of three, and associate Michel Lelievre are charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
<p>The affair has grabbed world headlines and prompted wider debate on trade in children, prostitution, paedophilia, and the role of the Internet computer network in spreading the sickness.</p>
<p>Belgian media reported on Thursday an unemployed man had been arrested in Flanders for trying to sell 3,000 pornographic photographs via the Internet -- one third were of children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
