<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26582" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Two Belgian teenagers found in Germany, sent home.</title>
<headline>Two Belgian teenagers found in Germany, sent home.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two young Belgian women missing since Thursday have been found in Cologne, Germany, and sent home, police in the German city said on Sunday.</p>
<p>The Cologne police said in a statement that Rachel Legeard, 18, and Severine Potty, 19, were found at 3:45 p.m. (1345 GMT) on Saturday sleeping in a hollow in the ground beside a motorway in the Buchforst area of Cologne.</p>
<p>One of the women told Cologne police she and her companion had been asked for directions at a bus stop in Liege, Belgium, at around 3 p.m. on Thursday by a man aged around 40 sitting in the passenger seat of an old Mercedes-Benz car with German licence plates. She said she remembered nothing else until she was woken up in Cologne.</p>
<p>The young women were turned over to police in Liege on Saturday night. Liege is about 120 km (75 miles) southwest of Cologne.</p>
<p>Liege police said in a statement on Sunday that the girls were unharmed. &quot;The young girls have been examined by a doctor and seem, considering the circumstances, in good condition.&quot;</p>
<p>The statement added that, based on the young women's statements, it appeared they had been kidnapped.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a kidnap,&quot; Marianne Legeard, mother of one of the young women told Belgian television station VTM, which showed filmed coverage of the girls' return home.</p>
<p>The young women were reported missing after they failed to return home to the village of Nandrin from a shopping trip to Liege on Thursday.</p>
<p>On Saturday Belgian police had declined to comment on whether they suspected a link with the Marc Dutroux case, the paedophile kidnap, sex abuse and murder scandal which has rocked Belgium in recent weeks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
