<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26611" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian child sex crime searches to restart.</title>
<headline>Belgian child sex crime searches to restart.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police resume digging for bodies on Monday in houses owned by Marc Dutroux, the chief suspect in Belgium's child sex scandal, while teachers brace for a barrage of questions from shocked children starting the new school year.</p>
<p>After resting for the weekend following two gruelling weeks of searching in the six houses owned by convicted child rapist Dutroux in and around the southern city of Charleroi, police will return to one in the city's Jumet suburb.</p>
<p>Radar-imaging equipment, used in Britain's &quot;House of Horrors&quot; serial murder investigation, located two suspicious underground cavities in the cellar of the house on Friday.</p>
<p>These will be investigated on Monday, as will an &quot;anomaly&quot; found by the equipment in another Dutroux house in the suburb of Marcinelle, where they found two other sexually abused girls -- Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne -- in a dungeon.</p>
<p>Police will also return to another house where trench-like cells for holding kidnapped children were found.</p>
<p>In two weeks of hunting police have discovered the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of another of Dutroux's houses in Sars-La-Buissiere near Charleroi.</p>
<p>They are still searching for at least two others -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks -- whom Dutroux admits kidnapping.</p>
<p>The discovery of the web of paedophile abduction, porn and death has horrified Europe, prompted the government into tightening the rules on early release from jail of sex offenders and triggered calls for a global war against the trade.</p>
<p>Dutroux, an unemployed electrician, was released 10 years early in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for raping five children.</p>
<p>This, and the fact that he has fathered three children by his two wives, has bewildered adults and children alike.</p>
<p>&quot;We know we will get questions about the Dutroux case, and we are preparing for it,&quot; Myriam Eynikel, a primary school teacher in Brussels' Strombeek suburb, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;My daughter is terrified, she is glued to every newscast. We have tried to tell her there are adults with bad intentions, without focusing on the sex-abuse aspect,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene summed up the national mood when announcing tougher sex offence rules on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Children represent our future. They deserve a happy childhood. We must protect and guarantee their rights. Everything must be put in place so that this drama is never repeated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The hunt for missing girls has spread beyond Belgium's borders. Belgian police have visited Slovakia and the Czech Republic, and have contacted colleagues in Austria and Germany.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman. Interpol's Slovak office has said he was also believed to have planned the kidnapping of at least one other Slovak woman.</p>
<p>Dutroux has said Julie and Melissa starved to death early this year while he was in jail for car theft.</p>
<p>Belgian newspapers said his second wife Michelle Martin -- also under arrest -- has admitted that she failed to feed the children out of fear of facing them in their cell.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the affair including Martin who has been charged as an accomplice. Dutroux and an associate are charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
