<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27386" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Austria holds four men in alleged child porn ring.</title>
<headline>Austria holds four men in alleged child porn ring.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian police said on Monday they were holding a total of four men on suspicion of producing child pornography in an international child prostitution ring spanning central Europe.</p>
<p>A fourth suspect, a 48-year-old Austrian citizen from Salzburg, was arrested on August 31 and is in detention by court order pending further investigation, a police spokeswoman told Reuters.</p>
<p>Three others, aged between 40 and 51 and based in Vienna, were arrested last week and also remain in detention pending investigation. Two are Austrian citizens, one born in Slovakia and the other in the Czech Republic. The third is Polish.</p>
<p>In what marked the start of a major operation to hunt down suspected child sex abusers in Austria, vice squad officers last week seized boxes of videos and other pornographic material from the home of one of the four suspects.</p>
<p>Police said the search for others involved in the child sex trade ring could spill over into neighbouring Slovakia, the Czech Republic and Germany.</p>
<p>Police declined to comment on whether there was any connection between the arrests and a Belgian child pornography scandal in which at least two young girls were murdered.</p>
<p>Belgian Marc Dutroux, alleged to be the ringleader in a paedophile pornography circuit, has been named by police in the Slovak capital Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of one Slovak woman and the kidnapping of another.</p>
<p>The series of sex scandals has deeply shocked Austrians, already troubled by last week's revelations of another alleged sex case in Linz, 200 km (120 miles) west of Vienna, involving the abuse of refugee children as young as four.</p>
<p>The prosecuting attorney in Linz said on Monday that two Austrian men arrested for suspected sex abuse of children from a refugee home had been released pending further investigation.</p>
<p>The news of the releases provoked an outcry from social workers, who expressed concern about the young victims' safety.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't seem to be sensible that the two alleged culprits are free again,&quot; said Josef Weidenholzer, head of the social organisation Volkshilfe in Linz. &quot;Someone must not have been thinking what consequences this could have.&quot;</p>
<p>The men were alleged to have lured children from the refugee shelter by offering them between 500 and 5,000 schillings ($50 to $500) for sex, sources close to the investigation said.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the men allegedly focused on little girls and the other only dealt with little boys,&quot; Weidenholzer said.</p>
<p>Austrian current affairs weekly News last week published a investigative report into extensive child sexual exploitation in the region.</p>
<p>It said the ring provided clients in Vienna with a choice of 70 girls, largely from Slovakia, aged between seven and 13.</p>
<p>The Volkshilfe, which has been investigating the refugee sex abuse claims for an undisclosed period, said that case also probably involved a larger ring of professional child abusers.</p>
<p>&quot;The sums of money involved are too large and our investigations have shown the contact between the children and their abusers was frequent,&quot; Weidenholzer said. &quot;There were certainly more people involved in this terrible tragedy.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
