<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27870" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian school begins in grim mood over sex crimes.</title>
<headline>Belgian school begins in grim mood over sex crimes.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian children returned to school on Monday after the summer break in a grim mood over the deaths from starvation of two eight-year-old girls while in the hands of a paedophile sex gang.</p>
<p>As the schools reopened police began fresh searches for bodies and clues at four of the six houses in and around the southern city of Charleroi owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, key suspect in an affair that has shaken all Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;I find what they did disgusting. We should do the same to them,&quot; one young girl at a small school in the village of Herbeumont told RTBF television. &quot;They should be killed.&quot;</p>
<p>Claudy Labiouse, the school's head teacher, handed out sheets of paper to the children for them to write down their feelings or questions about the scandal.</p>
<p>At some schools in the Flemish part of the country pupils turned up wearing white T-shirts as a gesture of solidarity with two other girls -- An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks -- who Dutroux admits kidnapping a year ago. The girls' fate remains a mystery.</p>
<p>Dutroux led police on August 17 to the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in the garden of a house he owns in Sars-La-Buissiere, south west of Charleroi.</p>
<p>Two days earlier police had rescued Laetitia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, from a basement dungeon in Dutroux' house in another Charleroi suburb. Both had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>On Monday, following a weekend of rest after two gruelling weeks of searches, police returned to both the houses.</p>
<p>They also resumed digging at the Dutroux' house in the Charleroi suburb of Jumet, formerly occupied by Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits murdering.</p>
<p>His body was found next to Julie and Melissa.</p>
<p>Investigators using special British radar-imaging equipment to locate underground cavities that may contain bodies, found two &quot;hot spots&quot; in the cellar of the house on Friday. British police superintendent John Bennett was in Jumet on Monday.</p>
<p>Police plan to demolish a shed in the garden where they spent three days digging last week, excavate the whole area to a depth of five metres (yards) and begin digging the &quot;hot spots&quot;.</p>
<p>Investigators, who met on Monday in Charleroi to set out a timetable for their searches, also finished emptying another Dutroux house in the Charleroi suburb of Marchienne-au-Pont, the home of Michel Lelievre who like Dutroux has been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment of children.</p>
<p>Police have already found trench-like cells dug in the cellar of the house along with evidence of occupation by abducted children, and plan further searches.</p>
<p>The discovery of the web of paedophile abduction, porn and death has horrified the country, prompted the government to tighten the rules on early release of sex offenders and triggered calls for a global war against the child sex trade.</p>
<p>Dutroux, an unemployed electrician, was released 10 years early in 1992 after serving only three years of a 13-year sentence for raping five children.</p>
<p>This, and the fact that he has fathered three children by his two wives, has bewildered adults and children alike.</p>
<p>The hunt for missing girls has spread beyond Belgium's borders. Belgian police have visited Slovakia and the Czech Republic, and have contacted colleagues in Austria and Germany.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been named in Bratislava as a suspect in the murder of a young Slovak woman and the planned kidnapping of at least one other.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the Belgian affair including Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
