<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29906" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Police unearth bones in Belgian child sex scandal.</title>
<headline>Police unearth bones in Belgian child sex scandal.</headline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian police found what appeared to be human bones on Tuesday while searching a property owned by Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in the country's paedophile abduction, pornography and murder scandal.</p>
<p>&quot;We discovered bones, probably of a human nature,&quot; Gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin told reporters outside the house in the Charleroi suburb of Jumet that was formerly occupied by Dutroux associate Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>&quot;They will be exhumed and taken for an autopsy this afternoon. The identification process will follow -- that will take some time, several days even if necessary,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>He refused to speculate on whether there could be more than one body.</p>
<p>Police have been digging in and around the house, one of six owned by Dutroux, for the past week. The bones were found in a shed in the garden.</p>
<p>Public Prosecutor Michel Bourlet, leading the hunt for a paedophile sex gang and its victims, was at the site as was police pathologist Jean-Pol Beauthiez and an ambulance.</p>
<p>Boudin urged the media not to speculate about the identity of the remains saying: &quot;We don't know&quot;</p>
<p>He said searches were suspended when the bones were found. It was not clear when they would resume.</p>
<p>The find follows discovery of the bodies of two eight-year-old children and that of Weinstein on August 17 at a house owned by Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere, south of Charleroi.</p>
<p>Dutroux, who admits murdering Weinstein, said the two children, Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, starved to death earlier this year, some nine months after being abducted</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne, were rescued from another of Dutroux's houses 12 days ago.</p>
<p>Dutroux, a convicted child rapist, has admitted kidnapping at least two others, An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks.</p>
<p>No human remains had been found previously at the house in Jumet.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
