<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30456" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Two bodies found in Belgian sex scandal.</title>
<headline>Two bodies found in Belgian sex scandal.</headline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police searching a property owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in Belgium's paedophile sex scandal, unearthed two decomposing bodies on Tuesday, a medical source told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;They have found two bodies in an advanced state of decomposition,&quot; the source said on condition of anonymity. There was no immediate official comment.  </p>
<p>The source said the bodies were not of young children but of adolescents or adults.</p>
<p>The Belga news agency, citing a judicial source, said the remains of at least two people had been found at the house in the Charleroi suburb of Jumet formerly occupied by Dutroux accomplice Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>Dutroux has said he murdered Weinstein and also admitted kidnapping An Marchal, 17, and Eefje Lambrecks, 19, in the port of Ostend a year ago. The fate of the two girls remains a mystery.</p>
<p>Several other Belgian girls have gone missing in recent years. Their files are all now pooled in Neufchateau, nerve centre of an international paedophile hunt.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
