<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30486" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police find bones in paedophile's house.</title>
<headline>Belgian police find bones in paedophile's house.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>JUMET, Belgium 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police searching a property owned by convicted rapist Marc Dutroux, chief suspect in Belgium's paedophile abduction, sex and death scandal, on Tuesday found what they said were probably human remains.</p>
<p>&quot;We discovered bones, probably of a human nature,&quot; Gendarmerie spokesman Major Jean-Marie Boudin told reporters outside the house in the Charleroi suburb of Jumet that was formerly occupied by Dutroux associate Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>&quot;They will be exhumed and taken for an autopsy this afternoon. The identification process will follow -- that will take some time, several days even...if DNA tests are necessary,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Boudin refused to speculate on whether there could be more than one body, but shortly afterwards two hearses arrived and the funeral parlour said a third had been ordered. Reporters saw one coffin being taken away.</p>
<p>Dutroux has said he murdered Weinstein and also admitted kidnapping An Marchal, 17, and Eefje Lambrecks, 19, in the port of Ostend a year ago. The fate of the two girls remains a mystery.</p>
<p>Several other Belgian girls have gone missing in recent years -- including an eight-year-old Zairean on Monday afternoon. Their files are all now pooled in Neufchateau, the nerve centre of the international paedophile hunt.</p>
<p>Boudin urged reporters not to speculate about the identity of the remains, saying &quot;we don't know&quot;.</p>
<p>Police have been digging around the Jumet house, one of the six owned by Dutroux in or near Charleroi, for the past week. The bones were found underneath a concrete slab in a shed in the garden.</p>
<p>Public Prosecutor Michel Bourlet, leading the hunt for a paedophile sex gang and its victims, visited the site, as did police pathologist Jean-Pol Beauthiez.</p>
<p>Boudin said searches were suspended from the moment the bones were found. He said they would resume later in the afternoon and finish at nightfall.</p>
<p>The discovery of the bones follows that of the bodies of two eight-year-old children and Weinstein on August 17 at a house owned by Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere south of Charleroi.</p>
<p>Dutroux said the two girls -- Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo -- starved to death earlier this year, some nine months after being abducted.</p>
<p>Two other girls -- Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne -- were rescued from another of Dutroux's houses 12 days ago. Both had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>No remains had been found previously at the house in Jumet.</p>
<p>The discovery of the paedophile web has horrified the country, prompted the government to tighten the rules on early release of sex offenders and triggered calls for a global war against the child sex trade.</p>
<p>The fact that Dutroux was released early from a 13-year sentence for child rape, and that he has fathered three children by his two wives, has bewildered adults and children alike.</p>
<p>The hunt for missing girls has gone international. Belgian police have visited Slovakia and the Czech Republic, and have contacted colleagues in Austria and Germany.</p>
<p>Dutroux is a suspect in Bratislava in the murder of a Slovak woman and the planned kidnapping of at least one other.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the Belgian affair including Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin.</p>
<p>Police have found trench-like cells for holding kidnapped children in one of Dutroux' houses, have seized more than 300 paedophile porn video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux -- quantities of magazines, childrens clothing and a gun.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JUMET, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
