<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33172" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium mourns two dead girls, searches continue.</title>
<headline>Belgium mourns two dead girls, searches continue.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium went into mourning on Wednesday for two teenage girls found dead on Tuesday at a property owned by a convicted child rapist, while police hunting a paedophile gang continued searching for more bodies.</p>
<p>The badly decomposed bodies of An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks were found buried in a metal container 2.5 metres (yards) under a property in Charleroi owned by Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Their remains, in white coffins, were taken back to their home town of Hasselt in the middle of the night on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The hope is dead,&quot; newspaper La Derniere Heure said. &quot;The worst&quot;, was Vers L'Avenir's banner headline. &quot;There was still hope of life - until yesterday,&quot; Dutch language daily De Morgen said. &quot;Rest in Peace&quot;, was Het Nieuwsblad's simple slogan.</p>
<p>Dutroux has admitted kidnapping the two on August 22 last year with accomplice Michel Lelievre who is also under arrest.</p>
<p>Hasselt was subdued. Flags hung at half mast, girls at An's school wore black armbands and a steady trickle of people arrived at the town hall to sign a condolence register.</p>
<p>The mood of grim resignation was in marked contrast to the eruption of grief that accompanied the discovery on August 17 and burial five days later of the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo at another Dutroux' house.</p>
<p>Dutroux said the two children, abducted in June 1995, starved to death earlier this year.</p>
<p>But the revulsion was just as deep. &quot;I am deeply moved by all that has happened...all the young girls who have disappeared,&quot; one young woman told RTBF television in Hasselt.</p>
<p>On Wednesday police made more searches at the house where the bodies of Julie and Melissa were found, as well as continuing digging at Keumiee near Namur and investigating at Jemappe-sur-Sambre near Charleroi.</p>
<p>The house in the Jumet suburb of the city of Charleroi where An and Eefje were found was formerly occupied by Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing and who he accuses of the murders.</p>
<p>The girls were identified by a wristwatch belonging to Eefje, and their dental records.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene sent sent his condolences to the parents and pledged to never let their fate be repeated.</p>
<p>&quot;This is truly monstrous. We must do everything we can to make sure this doesn't happen ever again,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne, were rescued from another of Dutroux's houses on August 15. Both had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>At least seven other Belgian girls have gone missing in recent years. Their files are all now pooled in Neufchateau, nerve centre of the international paedophile investigation.</p>
<p>Discovery of the child sex abuse web stunned the country, forced tougher rules on early release of sex offenders and prompted calls for a global war against the child sex trade.</p>
<p>The fact that Dutroux was released early from a 13-year sentence for child rape, and that he has fathered three children by his two wives, has bewildered adults and children alike.</p>
<p>There have also been allegations of police bungling or worse. One of the people held is chief detective Georges Zicot.</p>
<p>The hunt for missing girls has spread well beyond Belgium's borders. Investigators have visited Slovakia and the Czech Republic and contacted colleagues in Austria and Germany.</p>
<p>Authorities in Bratislava suspect Dutroux of the murder of a Slovak woman and the planned kidnapping of at least one other.</p>
<p>Nine people are now under arrest in the Belgian affair, including Dutroux's second wife Michelle Martin.</p>
<p>Police have found trench-like cells allegedly for holding kidnapped children in one of Dutroux's houses and seized hundreds of pornographic paedophile video tapes -- some featuring Dutroux himself -- plus magazines, childrens clothing and a gun.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
