<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33203" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian rapist plays power game amid suicide fears.</title>
<headline>Belgian rapist plays power game amid suicide fears.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Child rapist Marc Dutroux, at the centre of a paedophile web in which at least four Belgian girls were kidnapped and killed, is a psychopath playing a subtle game which may end in suicide, psychotherapists said.</p>
<p>&quot;That would be the trump card -- he commits suicide and takes all his secrets with him and holds everyone up to ridicule,&quot; Dirk Vanmaercke told Belgian VTM television.</p>
<p>Dutroux is being monitored every seven and a half minutes, day and night, to stop him committing suicide in jail like British &quot;House of Horrors&quot; serial killer Fred West, who hanged himself in jail before he could be tried.</p>
<p>Psychotherapists said Dutroux, released early in 1992 after being sentenced to 13 years for raping five children, was calling all the shots and would try to stretch the investigation out as long as possible with a calculated mix of truth and lies.</p>
<p>&quot;He knows he holds the key and they (investigators) don't,&quot; said Vanmaercke on Dutroux, described by the prosecutor in charge of the investigation as &quot;so impassive, it's frightening&quot;.</p>
<p>Dutroux has admitted kidnapping eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo, who were found dead on August 17 at a house he owns near the city of Charleroi.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, the decomposed bodies of teenage girls An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks were found buried under a shed in the garden of another of the houses owned by Dutroux, who admits kidnapping the two on August 22 last year.</p>
<p>Earlier last month, two other girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne, were found alive in another of Dutroux's houses. Both had been sexually abused.</p>
<p>Psychotherapists said Dutroux would cling on to his power and secrets for as long as possible.</p>
<p>&quot;He will give information gradually. He is intelligent enough to know that if he gives (all the information), the game is over,&quot; Vanmaercke said.</p>
<p>&quot;He enjoys having everyone jump for him, he knows precisely what has happened, repeated it hundreds of times in his fantasy, he enjoys creating chaos around him,&quot; said Carine Hutsebaut, who interviewed and monitored 15 European child killers.</p>
<p>She said investigators were pulled into Dutroux's evil games and &quot;show some understanding for them&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;They have to take part in (Dutroux's) power game ...they have to beg for information, make him feel important, in a way this man, who is jailed, is king,&quot; Vanmaercke said.</p>
<p>Hutsebaut said Dutroux even enjoyed the interrogations and trips to crime scenes because they meant he was still in society and not in permanent seclusion in jail.</p>
<p>She said psychopaths like Dutroux were good at reading investigators' body language.</p>
<p>&quot;You cannot show disgust...although they give so many details to see how the interrogators react, see how much power they can have over them,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Briton Ray Wyre, who trains investigators in interviewing criminals, said it was useless to try and make Dutroux show remorse or feelings.</p>
<p>Dutroux originally said he killed accomplice Bernard Weinstein for letting Julie and Melissa starve to death. But he later changed his story to having murdered him over a car theft deal. Newspapers reported he was buried alive.</p>
<p>&quot;The way (Dutroux) explains it, he's almost the savior of these girls, he killed out of indignity that the girls died...can you see what a strategist he is?&quot; Vanmaercke said.</p>
<p>Wyre said the discovery of the two girls -- one of them held for three months, the other for a week -- alive would help investigators in dealing with Dutroux.</p>
<p>&quot;Their information will be crucial in identifying how this person feels, how he thinks, how he dealt with them, how he talked to them,&quot; Wyre said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
