<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33668" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Hope dies for missing children in Belgian sex case. [CORRECTED 08:06 GMT]</title>
<headline>Hope dies for missing children in Belgian sex case. [CORRECTED 08:06 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hope that more children missing in Belgium's child sex and murder scandal could be found alive has evaporated following the discovery of two more bodies.</p>
<p>&quot;The hope is dead,&quot; newspaper La Derniere Heure said on Wednesday in reaction to the confirmation on Tuesday that the bodies were those of An Marchal, 17, and Eefje Lambrecks, 19, kidnapped last year by convicted rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>&quot;There was still hope of life -- until yesterday,&quot; Dutch language daily De Morgen said.</p>
<p>Belgium has been in shock since the discovery on August 17 at a house owned by Dutroux of the bodies of eight-year-old girls Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo.</p>
<p>However, two other girls -- Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne -- were earlier found alive (corrects from &quot;later found alive&quot;) at another of Dutroux's six homes, raising hope that a claim by him that more bodies would be found in the investigation would turn out to be false.</p>
<p>&quot;Dutroux did not -- unfortunately -- lie: the bodies of An and Eefje have been unearthed,&quot; La Derniere Heure said.</p>
<p>Police and invesigators are still chasing clues into the disappearance of several other children in the widening paedophile scandal, in which nine people have so far been arrested.</p>
<p>The inquiry has spread to the Czech Republic, where Dutroux is alleged to have also carried out some of his crimes, and investigators have contacted their counterparts in Germany and Austria.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, as the bodies of An and Eefje were being unearthed, police began new searches at two other Dutroux properties. There were no immediate results.</p>
<p>Newspaper Le Soir reported on Wednesday that more arrests were imminent following raids at several locations around the country.</p>
<p>Sex tapes seized in the raids implicate several of those alleged to be at the centre of the Dutroux affair as well as others, Le Soir said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
