<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="37688" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium arrests four suspects in Cools murder.</title>
<headline>Belgium arrests four suspects in Cools murder.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police arrested four people on Friday in connection with the murder of Belgian politician Andre Cools five years ago, a killing that led police to a high-level corruption scandal.</p>
<p>A judicial source in Brussels, confirming the four arrests, told Reuters: &quot;At least one of them has been charged with murder. Some of them have made partial confessions.&quot;</p>
<p>Another judicial source said the apparent breakthrough in the Cools investigation might have been due in part to wider powers granted to magistrates investigating the paedophile sex scandal that has rocked Belgium in the past three weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been an important breakthrough in the investigation into the murder of Andre Cools,&quot; Belgian Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck told Belgian television BRTN.</p>
<p>Those arrested on Friday included Richard Taxquet, who was charged in 1992 over an alleged 500 million franc ($17 million) securities fraud that had been linked to Cools' murder.</p>
<p>Taxquet was the former private secretary of Alain Van der Biest, a socialist minister in the regional government of Wallonia, the French-speaking southern part of Belgium.</p>
<p>Belgium's national news agency Belga reported that Taxquet had been arrested on suspicion of killing Cools and trying to kill Cools' girlfriend.</p>
<p>Cools, a politician from Belgium's francophone socialist party, was shot dead in Liege on July 18, 1991, when leaving his girlfriend's appartment.</p>
<p>The investigation into the murder revealed corruption involving the purchase of Agusta helicopters by the Belgian army in the late eighties.</p>
<p>The resulting scandal led to the resignation of four ministers, the suicide of a general and the resignation of Belgian NATO secretary-general Willy Claes.</p>
<p>Claes was forced to quit last October after being implicated in a political slush fund scandal uncovered by the Cools murder investigators.</p>
<p>They said Italian helicopter firm Agusta and French aviation giant Dassault paid more than 100 million Belgian francs ($3 million) into secret Socialist Party accounts in return for lucrative contracts when Claes was economic affairs minister. He repeatedly denied any knowledge of the payments.</p>
<p>The scandal forced three francophone Socialist Party leaders, Guy Coeme, Guy Mathot and Guy Spitaels, to resign early in 1994 while foreign minister Frank Vandenbroucke, a former Flemish Socialist Party president, quit in March 1995.</p>
<p>Air force general Jacques Lefebvre killed himself in a Brussels hotel room in March last year over the Dassault affair.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
