<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39349" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium mourns, buries two more child sex victims.</title>
<headline>Belgium mourns, buries two more child sex victims.</headline>
<dateline>HASSELT, Belgium 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium grieved and buried its dead on Saturday - two teenage girl victims of a paedophile kidnapping, sexual abuse and murder gang found dead five days ago just over a year after they were abducted.</p>
<p>Hundreds of people thronged the streets of this Dutch-speaking east Belgian town and white flags were everywhere as Eefje Lambrecks and her friend An Marchal were buried in two separate services televised to the nation.</p>
<p>The two were kidnapped in August last year by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux and accomplice Michel Lelievre -- both currently under arrest for abduction and illegal imprisonment.</p>
<p>The girls were found dead on Tuesday on a property in the city of Charleroi that was formerly home to Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing and who he blames for murdering the two.</p>
<p>The discovery sent the nation into mourning for the second time in as many weeks after the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were found at a house owned by Dutroux south of Charleroi. The little girls had starved to death.</p>
<p>Julie and Melissa were buried on August 22 -- the anniversary of the abduction of An and Eefje -- in the city of Liege in what was tantamount to a state funeral.</p>
<p>Two other girls, Laetitia Delhez and Sabine Dardenne were rescued on August 15 from  do-it-yourself dungeon in another Dutroux' house in Charleroi.</p>
<p>Eefje, the older of the two girls, was buried first on Saturday. Her white coffin lying just in front of her parents at the service in Banneux Church attended by hundreds of friends and well-wishers as a choir accompanied by flute and guitar sung some of her favourite songs.</p>
<p>Outside in the sunshine hundreds more people stood in silence -- some clasping each other -- watching the service on a huge screen as it was beamed live around the country.</p>
<p>As the coffin was carried out people clapped to show their support for the family and their courage and released white balloons to show solidarity with other dead and missing Belgian children.</p>
<p>Two hours later it was An's turn across town at Hasselt Cathedral. Her white coffin -- with a fluffy toy sitting on it -- was likewise in front of her parents Jean-Paul and Betty.</p>
<p>Sitting just behind them were Gino and Carine Russo, the parents of Melissa.</p>
<p>As people filed past the coffin, a selection of An's favourite CD's played and they placed white flowers on and around the casket. This service too was beamed around the country.</p>
<p>The francophone La Derniere Heure newspaper perhaps best summed up the mood of the linguistically-divided nation, printing over a black front page carrying one picture each of An and Eefje the Dutch words &quot;Onze Kinderen&quot; (Our Children).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HASSELT, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
