<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39893" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian ex-minister arrested in Cools murder probe.</title>
<headline>Belgian ex-minister arrested in Cools murder probe.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Belgian judiciary arrested former regional minister Alain Van der Biest on Sunday in connection with the unsolved murder of a socialist politician five years ago.</p>
<p>Belgian media said that Van der Biest had been detained in connection with the killing of Andre Cools following testimony by his former personal secretary Richard Taxquet.</p>
<p>Taxquet was arrested on Friday along with three others in connection with the Cools case. Police have also issued an international arrest warrant for Pino Di Mauro, Van der Biest's former driver, a judicial source said.</p>
<p>&quot;I confirm that Mr. Van der Biest has been arrested. He has again stated his innocence... these accusations are not new and were already vague when they were first made,&quot; Van der Biest's lawyer, Jean-Luc Dessy, told RTBF television.</p>
<p>Dessy was allowed to visit his client in the Lantin prison, close to the eastern town of Liege, where Van der Biest has been placed in solitary confinement for the next three days.</p>
<p>Asked whether he could confirm that Taxquet had accused Van der Biest of masterminding Cools' assassination, Dessy said: &quot;Mr. Van der Biest is surprised by what has happened.&quot;</p>
<p>Belgian media said the Liege judiciary had accused Van der Biest of the murder of Cools and the attempted murder of his girlfriend. Cools was shot on July 18, 1991, as he left the woman's flat.</p>
<p>Van der Biest's last official position was as a minister for interior affairs in the regional government of Wallonia, the French-speaking southern part of Belgium, in 1990-92, a post from which he had to resign following the Cools murder investigation.</p>
<p>Van der Biest had risen to power under the wing of Cools, patriarch of the Parti Socialiste (PS), the party which has been the main political force in Wallonia for decades.</p>
<p>In the 1980s Van der Biest was leader of the socialist faction in the federal parliament and held ministerial rank in the federal government.</p>
<p>Both Van der Biest and Taxquet were questioned in 1992 over an alleged 500 million franc ($17 million) securities fraud that had been linked to Cools' murder.</p>
<p>But the judiciary had not pursued the Van der Biest/Taxquet trail and neither had been arrested.</p>
<p>Late on Sunday afternoon, one of the chief police investigators into Cools' murder resigned following television reports about his alleged role in covering up Van der Biest and Taxquet's roles in the affair.</p>
<p>&quot;In the light of new developments in the Cools investigation and the doubts expressed by some regarding the professional integrity of Chief Commissioner Raymond Brose, he has informed us he no longer wishes to be part of the investigative team,&quot; Liege Public Prosecutor Anne Thily said in a communique published by national news agency Belga.</p>
<p>Investigators have never discovered the reasons for Cools' assassination, but their search led them to discover rampant corruption in another affair -- the purchase of Agusta military helicopters in the late 1980s.</p>
<p>That scandal brought down former leading Belgian politician Willy Claes, forced to resign as NATO secretary-general in October 1995. Four Belgian federal government ministers had to resign in 1994 and 1995 over the same affair.</p>
<p>Belgian media have speculated that the apparent breakthrough in the Cools investigation seems to have been brought about by the investigation into the paedophile sex, kidnapping and murder ring which has shocked Belgium over the past three weeks.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck said on Friday &quot;an important breakthrough&quot; had been made in the Cools probe, but added that there was &quot;no direct link&quot; between the two cases.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
