<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="42529" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police find weapons in Cools murder probe.</title>
<headline>Belgian police find weapons in Cools murder probe.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The five-year-old search for the murderer of a leading Belgian politician appears to have made a major step forward with the arrest of a prime suspect and the discovery of what police think are the weapons used in the crime.</p>
<p>Andre Cools, patriarch of the socialist party in Wallonia, Belgium's French-speaking southern half, was shot on July 18, 1991.</p>
<p>The assassins were never found, but the investigation in the Cools affair has shaken Belgium to the core. It has uncovered a corruption scandal which led to the resignation of Belgian Nato Secretary General Willy Claes in October 1995 and the resignation of four Belgian government ministers in 1994-95.</p>
<p>A judicial source told Reuters late on Sunday that army engineers had dredged up two revolvers from a canal near the eastern town of Liege.</p>
<p>Investigators have never discovered the reasons for Cools' assassination, but their search led them to discover rampant corruption in another affair -- the purchase of Agusta military helicopters in the late 1980s. That scandal brought down former leading Belgian socialist politician Willy Claes, forced to resign as NATO secretary-general in October 1995.</p>
<p>Belgian media have speculated that the apparent breakthrough in the Cools investigation seemed to have been brought about by the investigation into the paedophile sex, kidnapping and murder ring which has shocked Belgium over the past three weeks.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck said on Friday &quot;an important breakthrough&quot; had been made in the Cools probe, but added that there was &quot;no direct link&quot; between the two cases.</p>
<p>The army engineers who found the two revolvers were led there by Domenico Castellino, one of four men arrested on Friday in connection with the Cools probe.</p>
<p>&quot;Castellino himself had indicated where we could find the weapons,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>Castellino was one of four men arrested on Friday in connection with the Cools investigation. Another one was Richard Taxquet, former personal secretary of Alain Van der Biest, a minister in the Wallonia government who was forced to resign in 1992 for alledged involvement in a securities fraud.</p>
<p>Van der Biest was arrested early on Sunday after 12 hours of questioning. Belgian media said the Liege judiciary has accused him of murder of Cools, following testimony given by Taxquet.</p>
<p>&quot;I confirm that Mr Van der Biest has been arrested. He has again stated his innocence,&quot; Van der Biest's lawyer, Jean-Luc Dessy, told RTBF television.</p>
<p>Dessy was allowed to visit his client in the Lantin prison, close to Liege, where Van der Biest has been placed in solitary confinement for the next three days.</p>
<p>Van der Biest had risen to power under the wing of Cools, the power broker of the Parti Socialiste (PS), the party which has been the main political force in Wallonia for decades.</p>
<p>In the 1980s Van der Biest was leader of the socialist faction in the federal parliament and held ministerial rank in the federal government.</p>
<p>Both Van der Biest and Taxquet were questioned in 1992 over an alleged 500 million franc ($17 million) securities fraud that had been linked to Cools' murder.</p>
<p>On Sunday afternoon, one of the chief police investigators into Cools' murder resigned following reports about his alleged role in covering up Van der Biest's involvement in the affair.</p>
<p>&quot;In the light of...doubts expressed by some regarding the professional integrity of Commissioner Raymond Brose, he has informed us he no longer wishes to be part of the investigative team,&quot; the Liege public prosecutor said in a statement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
