<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43392" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.African police probe child sex syndicate.</title>
<headline>S.African police probe child sex syndicate.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African police said on Tuesday detectives from its Child Protection Unit (CPU) were investigating reports that an international crime syndicate was abducting and selling children.</p>
<p>&quot;I can confirm this, that definitely there are indications of an international syndicate operating in this country concerning the trafficking of children and drugs,&quot; police CPU Superintendent Sharon Schutte told national television.</p>
<p>A young woman, who first told police one year ago that she had belonged to a syndicate trading in children, was rushed into a police witness protection programme this week.</p>
<p>The woman, whose identity was shielded, told the South African Broadcasting Corporation that she was initiated into a satanists' ring at the age of 10 and was forced into the syndicate two years later, in 1989.</p>
<p>She said she knew of 36 children who were sold abroad for sexual exploitation and alleged that notorious South African paedophile Gert van Rooyen was a member of her satanists' cell.</p>
<p>Pretoria police said last month they were probing a link between the child sex scandal rocking Belgium and the disappearance of five girls in South Africa up to eight years ago.</p>
<p>Van Rooyen and his lover Joey Haarhof were linked by police to the disappearance of the girls, aged 11 to 13. Van Rooyen shot Haarhof and himself in 1990 during a car chase as police closed in on them. The girls were never traced.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
