<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="44865" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police in raids linked to child sex case.</title>
<headline>Belgian police in raids linked to child sex case.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police ended a series of raids on homes and offices around the city of Charleroi early on Tuesday in connection with investigations into Belgium's scandal of child abductions, sexual abuse, murder and car theft.</p>
<p>Radio said a total of 15 houses and offices were searched over a 12-hour period, including an office occupied by the city's judicial police, and 23 people were questioned.</p>
<p>Eight of these were members of the judicial police, three were gendarmes and six were related to chief detective Georges Zicot who was arrested two weeks ago during investigations into the paedophile porn and car theft gang led by Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>There was no immediate confirmation because all the main figures in the scandal that has shaken the country to the core and raised serious questions about the judicial system were either out continuing investigations or in court.</p>
<p>Zicot appeared in court in Liege on Tuesday morning to formally appeal against the charges he faces of car theft, insurance fraud and forgery.</p>
<p>Two others, insurance fraud investigator Thierry Dehaan and car lot owner Gerrard Pinon who have also been charged in connection with car theft, were in court alongside Zicot.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in Neufchateau, the nerve centre of the international paedophile porn hunt, Annie Bouty was appearing in court to have the charges against her of criminal association confirmed.</p>
<p>Bouty, a disbarred lawyer, is the former companion of Jean-Michel Nihoul a Brussels businessman who has also been charged with criminal association in relation with the sex abuse and pornorgaphy side of the investigations.</p>
<p>To date police have rescued two young girls kidnapped by Dutroux and his accomplice Michel Lelievre, and unearthed the bodies of four more as well as that of an accomplice, Bernard Weinstein, whom Dutroux admits killing.</p>
<p>Dutroux, Lelievre, Nihoul and Dutroux' second wife Michelle Martin -- charged as an accomplice -- are due to have the charges against them renewed on Friday September 13 -- a formality that has to take place every four weeks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
