<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46736" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian king sparks debate on twin murder scandals.</title>
<headline>Belgian king sparks debate on twin murder scandals.</headline>
<byline>Nieck Ammerlaan</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium's King Albert has triggered a national debate by urging politico-judicial reforms amid damaging twin scandals over a &quot;contract&quot; murder of a party leader and horrifying child sex-abuse.</p>
<p>The king, trying to restore public confidence in law and order, touched off controversy whether the sovereign has a right to intervene.</p>
<p>The country has been rocked by daily revelations of a paedophile gang abducting, torturing and killing girls, plus murder charges against a former government minister for a Mafia-style political assassination of a rival ex-minister.</p>
<p>Public anxiety has worsened with accusations of police bungling, corruption and coverups. Details in both cases are still unfolding.</p>
<p>Some analysts say the king's call on Tuesday for a fundamental review of the judiciary represents government views, but others say that constitutionally he overstepped the bounds.</p>
<p>Under the Belgian constitution, public statements by the king require the backing of the government.</p>
<p>King Albert asked Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck to ensure the country's child sex scandal is cleared up fully.</p>
<p>Four young girls have so far been found dead, two have been rescued and a further seven are being searched for.</p>
<p>The four died as captives of a gang led by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, who led police to their bodies.</p>
<p>By making the call for full clarity King Albert stepped into national judicial affairs as reports abounded of investigating magistrates ignoring informers' reports and police investigators failing to relay key information to each other.</p>
<p>Belgians' feeling of distrust of the judiciary grew further with a sudden spate of arrests last weekend in the unresolved murder of Belgian socialist politician and ex-minister Andre Cools in July 1991.</p>
<p>The arrests came after an annonymous and extraordinarily detailed tipoff to stymied investigators last week.</p>
<p>It led them to pick up a lead that had lain dormant for more than two years, overtaken by a probe into bribery scandals involving politicians of Cools' francophone socialist PS party.</p>
<p>The PS is currently part of the ruling coalition government.</p>
<p>Media reports have said PS supporters steered investigators away from leads which could have pointed to a settling of scores between career politicians.</p>
<p>The appointment of judges is a political affair.</p>
<p>One of five suspects charged with the murder of Cools, is Belgian ex-minister Alain van der Biest, a leading PS member. He has denied any involvement in the killing.</p>
<p>National news media quoted lawyers in the case as saying Cools was the victim of a Mafia-style contract killing by two hired assassins, probably of Tunisian origin, living in Sicily. Some circumstances remain obscure.</p>
<p>Justice Minister De Clerck has pledged to look into the investigations of the Dutroux and Cools cases.</p>
<p>But Belgians' confidence in politics, politicians and the judiciary has been seriously damaged.</p>
<p>By calling for a more humane and efficient judiciary with better controls and training and for investigators, King Albert -- bitterly criticised for his silence by the parents of missing children -- sought to polish his own image and that of the judicial system.</p>
<p>But some analysts said the king was dabbling in politics.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
