<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46832" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian police question sixth man on Cools murder.</title>
<headline>Belgian police question sixth man on Cools murder.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian police investigating the assassination of a leading Belgian politician questioned a sixth man on Wednesday, while five suspects arrested at the weekend had their charges of murder confirmed in court.</p>
<p>The affair, coming on top of the child abduction, sex, murder and car theft scandal, has shocked the country deeply and prompted calls for a thorough overhaul of the judicial and political systems.</p>
<p>Former government minister Alain Van der Biest, his then- private secretary Richard Taxquet and three others have been charged with the murder near Liege on July 18, 1991 of Andre Cools, patriarch of the country's francophone Socialist Party.</p>
<p>The latest man to be detained was Van der Biest's erstwhile driver, Pino Di Mauro, who was taken into custody late on Tuesday after returning from holiday in France.</p>
<p>An international warrant requiring Di Mauro to present himself had been issued, and Belgian radio said he returned from holiday and made contact with the authorities himself after hearing about it on the French news.</p>
<p>&quot;Di Mauro has been apprehended and is currently being questioned in connection with the Cools investigation,&quot; a police spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>A court in Liege, south eastern Belgium, decided on Wednesday to renew the charges against the five other men. The move was necessary if the men were to be kept in detention.</p>
<p>A former minister in the Wallonia government, Van der Biest has repeatedly stated his innocence in the Cools affair.</p>
<p>He was forced to resign from his regional government post in 1992 for alleged involvement in a 500 million franc securities fraud thought to be linked to Cools's murder.</p>
<p>Investigations into the death of Cools, who is believed to have been on the verge of blowing the whistle on corruption in the Liege branch of the Socialist Party when he was gunned down, have uncovered a trail of bribery and other scandals.</p>
<p>Up to now though police had not appeared close to finding Cools's murderers.</p>
<p>New momentum was injected into the case on September 3 after a witness came forward under condition of anonymity with a testimony, according to Belgian media.</p>
<p>The witness's detailed account had not however given the names of Cools's killers, the motive nor the origin of funds believed to have been paid for his assassination.</p>
<p>Police discovered at the weekend two guns which they believe were used when Cools was shot in the car park outside a block of flats near Liege where he had been visiting his girlfriend.</p>
<p>The army engineers who found the two revolvers were led there by Domenico Castellino, one of the five men under arrest and who has admitted hiring and hiding the two hit-men who shot Cools.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
