<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47551" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Child sex, crime, murder and politics rock Belgium.</title>
<headline>Child sex, crime, murder and politics rock Belgium.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium, usually known for its beers and the European Union headquarters, has suddenly hit world headlines for altogether darker reasons -- paedophilia, murder and political assassination.</p>
<p>Shock after shock has shaken the country as investigators unearthed the bodies of four abducted young girls, confiscated paedophile porn tapes, and uncovered a catalogue of police bungling, inefficiency and possible complicity.</p>
<p>If three weeks of that was not enough, investigators pounced at the weekend and arrested a former government minister on charges of murdering another former minister five years ago.</p>
<p>Suggestions of a canker at the core of not just the Socialist Party, of which the two were members, but of the whole political and judicial system have abounded.</p>
<p>Add to that potent brew a spate of murderous attacks with machine guns and assault rifles over the past eight months on security vans -- attacks that have killed four people and wounded 14 -- and the question starts to be whether the country is in terminal moral decline.</p>
<p>Interior Minister Johan Vande Lanotte insisted that Belgium was not the Wild West.</p>
<p>His stance was, however, somewhat undermined by two robberies late last month at shooting clubs in which some 50 weapons -- including Kalashnikov AK47s -- were stolen.</p>
<p>No question was asked in the media as to what the clubs were doing with assault rifles in the first place.</p>
<p>Shootings, killings and widespread allegations that the central European and Italian mafias are already well entrenched in various segments of the country's commercial life, are facts that most Belgians deplore but shrug their shoulders and accept.</p>
<p>Child kidnapping, sexual abuse, pornography and murder are another matter altogether, and Belgians are being forced to realise that they are not -- like the infamous SPARTACUS international paedophile network run from Belgium by a Briton -- events that are conveniently confined to other countries.</p>
<p>The rescue on August 15 of 14-year-old Laetitia Delhez and 12-year-old Sabine Dardenne from a home-made dungeon in the basement of a house owned by convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux heralded a spate of happy headlines and stories that skated carefully around the fact that this was paedophilia in Belgium.</p>
<p>The discovery two days later of the bodies of eight-year-olds Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo in a house owned by jobless father-of-three Dutroux sent the nation into shock.</p>
<p>Grim scenes of police digging, using sniffer dogs, special British radar and a Dutchman whose speciality is sniffing out dead bodies sent shivers down the country's collective spine.</p>
<p>The discovery after two-and-a-half weeks of the bodies of Eefje Lambrecks, 19, and An Marchal, 17, on the property of a house formerly occupied by Bernard Weinstein, an accomplice whom Dutroux admits killing was almost the final straw.</p>
<p>Tales of police incompetence, lack of communication and rivalry between different judicial regions that could arguably have contributed to the deaths of the four girls prompted calls for a complete review of the justice system, as did the arrest in a related inquiry of a chief police detective.</p>
<p>But the final blow, and the one that could still have dire consequences for the country's political system, was the sudden arrest last weekend of five people, including former Socialist government minister Alain Van der Biest for the murder on July 18, 1991, of Socialist patriarch Andre Cools.</p>
<p>The fact that five years of enquiries had failed to pinpoint the murderers or the motives, and the key investigators on the Dutroux case had been thrown off the Cools case in 1992 due to judicial rivalry, served to highlight the crisis of confidence.</p>
<p>It was not helped by King Albert launching into the debate on Tuesday with an appeal for a more efficient justice system.</p>
<p>In a bid to head off the avalanche, the government has launched enquiries into the enquiries. Others have called for a parliamentary investigation. The only thing that is sure is that Belgium will never be quite the same again.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
