<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49856" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Man released in Belgian &quot;Dutroux affair&quot; probe.</title>
<headline>Man released in Belgian &quot;Dutroux affair&quot; probe.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Belgian court on Thursday freed insurance investigator Thierry Dehaan, an acquaintance of detective Georges Zicot who has been charged with theft and fraud in a case connected to the country's child sex scandal.</p>
<p>&quot;The court has decided to release Thierry Dehaan provisionally -- it's what we asked for,&quot; Dehaan's lawyer, Marc Neve, told Belgian radio. Dehaan was arrested on charges of fraud related to stolen vehicles.</p>
<p>But the court renewed charges against Zicot and businessman Gerard Pinon, Belgian radio said. All three were arrested on August 25, and their charges must be regularly renewed as a formality if they are to remain in detention.</p>
<p>Marc Dutroux is the chief suspect in a child sex ring and murder scandal that has shaken the country. He has also been linked with organised car theft.</p>
<p>Police are investigating the child sex and stolen car rings jointly.</p>
<p>Pinon is charged with receiving stolen vehicles. Zicot -- a specialist in tackling vehicle theft -- was arrested for alleged truck theft, insurance fraud and document forgery.</p>
<p>Talking of his client, Dehaan's lawyer added, &quot;In our eyes there was no trace of guilt. What he did was in the framework of his job. All the necessary answers were given to the questions that were asked (about him) at the start.&quot;</p>
<p>Neve added that Dehaan had spent a difficult time in jail. &quot;He was held near Dutroux -- he was devastated.&quot;</p>
<p>A total of nine people are currently under arrest -- seven in relation to the child sex ring investigation and two -- Zicot and Pinon -- in connection with the stolen car ring.</p>
<p>The seven include Dutroux himself -- on charges of kidnapping and illegal imprisonment of children -- and his second wife Michelle Martin, charged as an accomplice.</p>
<p>Dutroux has also admitted murdering another accomplice, Frenchman Bernard Weinstein, and on August 15 led police to the bodies of two eight-year-old girls buried in his garden.</p>
<p>The remains of two teenage girls were later found in another house where Weinstein used to live and where Dutroux was a frequent visitor.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
