<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49884" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium seeks to curb paedophile porn on Internet.</title>
<headline>Belgium seeks to curb paedophile porn on Internet.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A keyword search of the World Wide Web for &quot;pedophiles&quot; (sic) produces 1,000 items, one for &quot;pedophilia&quot; 2,000. Searching deeper finds thousands more -- and by no means all give advice on how to protect children.</p>
<p>That is one reason why the Belgian government, facing a national scandal over the discovery of a child abduction, sexual abuse and murder gang is calling for an urgent Europe-wide solution.</p>
<p>&quot;The amount of strong pornographic pictures, including bestiality, that is exchanged is enormous,&quot; Marc Van Achter of Antwerp Judicial Police's computer crime unit told a conference in Brussels on Wednesday.</p>
<p>One Web site is the Pedosexual Resources Directory which advertises itself as an impartial information point about sex with children, but goes into great detail about everything.</p>
<p>Belgian Telecommunications Minister Elio Di Rupo said on Thursday he would present the cabinet with his preliminary ideas for cooperating with the justice ministry in tackling the spread of paedophile porn on the Web.</p>
<p>But, with the fingers of the Web spread across the planet, Di Rupo also acknowledged that no country could act in isolation, and he therefore called in a statement for urgent and concerted European action.</p>
<p>Belgium has been reeling for the past month from the discovery of the bodies of four young girls and the rescue of two others -- victims of a gang seemingly led by convicted multiple rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>The seizure of hundreds of pornographic video tapes and quantities of magazines has woken the country to the horror in its midst to which it had turned a blind eye in the past.</p>
<p>The sheer quantity of the material seized, and the fact that Dutroux and an accomplice were known to have visited the Czech Republic and Slovakia several times, have led to the conclusion that there must have been overseas links.</p>
<p>The Web is one such channel for paedophile material -- the more attractive to its users in that policing and regulation are virtually unknown and because anonymity can be assured.</p>
<p>The amount of pornography -- including paedophile material -- available on the system is astounding.</p>
<p>Different web sites and news groups offer information on sex with children -- boys and girls -- as well as pictures and contacts.</p>
<p>Many of these sites carry warnings that the material to be viewed is hard core and may break the law. But that would tend to attract rather than repel all but the faintest-hearted of browsers.</p>
<p>One net service supplier has estimated that one news group alone, Alt.sex.pedophilia, has 3,000 active users.</p>
<p>&quot;Recent statistics from one of the biggest (internet service) providers in Belgium showed that around 95 percent of accesses to newsgroups concerned sex. It's very clear that people are only interested in that and nothing else. It's a very big problem,&quot; Van Achter said.</p>
<p>Claude Lelievre, the childrens' ombudsman for Belgium's francophone community, told Belgian radio it would be extremely difficult to censor all the millions of bits of information washing across the web every day.</p>
<p>Using smart censorship chips to filter out information containing certain key words is certainly possible, but generally they would only work on a terminal-by-terminal basis. In any case a change in a word and they could be bypassed.</p>
<p>Lelievre says self-censorship is the only effective way. He wants posters to be clearly displayed in the country's growing number of cybercafes to warn browsers away from porn sites.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
