<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50641" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Murdered Belgian politician's son alleges cover-up.</title>
<headline>Murdered Belgian politician's son alleges cover-up.</headline>
<byline>Nick Antonovics</byline>
<dateline>LIEGE, Belgium 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The family of murdered Belgian politician Andre Cools said on Thursday his killers must have believed they had protection in high places.</p>
<p>&quot;You don't kill a former minister without certitude of impunity...To escape justice you have to rely on protection of some sort,&quot; Cools's son Marcel told a news conference.</p>
<p>Cools was speaking just days after six men, including former minister Alain Van der Biest who, when a family friend, became godfather to his daughter, were charged with orchestrating his father's death.</p>
<p>Andre Cools, a former government minister, was gunned down outside his mistress's home on July 18, 1991.</p>
<p>According to lawyers for the accused, witnesses have told investigators that the murder was a Mafia-style contract killing carried out by two Tunisian hitmen for 750,000 Belgian francs ($25,000) at the behest of local political rivals.</p>
<p>Cools declined to say if he believed Van der Biest was guilty but added that the last time they had met -- at his father's funeral -- Van der Biest &quot;obviously wanted to avoid looking at us&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Twenty years ago I asked him to be the godfather of my daughter...If it turns out he killed my father it means he also assassinated the grandfather of his goddaughter,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Over the past five years the inquiry into Cools's death and the role he played as one of the bosses in Belgium's Francophone Socialist Party has uncovered corruption at the highest levels of Belgian government.</p>
<p>The scandal led to the resignation of four ministers, NATO Secretary General Willy Claes, and the suicide of a top general.</p>
<p>But until charges were brought this week against Van der Biest, his private secretary Richard Taxquet, former chauffeur Pino Di Mauro, as well as Carlo Todarello, Cosimo Solazzo and Domenico Castellino, the inquiry had meandered for years.</p>
<p>The sudden development, coming in the wake of revelations in Belgium's separate inquiry into a murderous paedophile ring, has led to allegations of, at best, judicial incompetence and, at worst, an official cover-up.</p>
<p>&quot;Everything is political in this country,&quot; Cools told the news conference when asked if he believed the accused had enjoyed political protection.</p>
<p>The fact the judge now leading the child sex probe was involved in one facet of the Cools murder inquiry before he was ordered to drop the case has also raised the suspicion of a link between the two affairs.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't imagine (a link) but there are so many unimaginable things in this country that who knows?&quot; Cools said.</p>
<p>Cools family lawyer Georges Dehousse said the family had lost confidence in Veronique Ancia, the magistrate leading the murder inquiry, as well as Belgium's prosecutor general Jacques Velu, and wanted parliament to investigate their behaviour.</p>
<p>&quot;(The family) asks that a public parliamentary inquiry be urgently set up into the malfunctioning of the political, judicial and police system in the framework of the investigation into the assassination of Andre Cools,&quot; Dehousse said.</p>
<p>They also asked for European Court of Justice judge and former Belgian Justice Minister Melchior Wathelet to have his diplomatic immunity lifted so he could be questioned about his role in the inquiry.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there has been a curious way of carrying out this inquiry and if it had been done differently we would have found (the killers) earlier. That's clear,&quot; Cools said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIEGE, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
