<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53469" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU justice chief urges Europol role on child sex.</title>
<headline>EU justice chief urges Europol role on child sex.</headline>
<byline>Janet McEvoy</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union's justice chief pleaded with the 15-nation bloc's governments on Friday to stop preventing the Union from fighting cross-border crime such as child-sex rings.</p>
<p>Justice Commissioner Anita Gradin said an urgent ratification of the Europol Convention to put the Hague-based police agency to work was one concrete way member states could help fight the child-sex trade which has shocked the world.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone should go home and ratify the Europol Convention. If we want to get hold of these gangs who are stealing, abducting children then you need a Europol that's effective,&quot; she told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>The child-sex trade has been thrown into the international spotlight after the discovery in Belgium of the bodies of four young girls and the rescue of two others -- victims of a gang alleged to have been led by convicted multiple rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Gradin said she hoped solid ideas on how to fight the child-sex trade would emerge at an informal meeting of EU justice ministers in Dublin on September 26-27, following the good intentions expressed at a world conference on the issue in Stockholm last month.</p>
<p>She said that while urgent ratification of the long-delayed Europol Convention would have immediate results, it would take time to take other measures, notably preventing the use of the internet to promote paedophilia and child pornography.</p>
<p>Until the Europol Convention is ratified the EU crime-busting agency cannot carry out vital work pooling and analysing lists of missing children sent by police agencies in the bloc.</p>
<p>An Irish member of the European Parliament, Mary Banotti, has suggested the police agency set up a special centralised database to help search for missing children and young people under the age of 15.</p>
<p>Gradin said on Friday that until the convention is ratified Europol could not run such a database.</p>
<p>Among the ideas Gradin will float at the Dublin meeting are urging more EU countries to try people who travel abroad to buy sex with children.</p>
<p>Under the plans investigators would also be able to travel to child-sex havens, particularly in southeast Asia, to video interviews with child victims rather than putting them through the traumatic process of being flown to Europe to appear in public as witnesses.</p>
<p>While she favoured tougher controls to prevent use of the Internet to advertise paedophile services and child pornography, she feared any plans to impose censorship on the internet would meet resistance from EU governments on freedom of expression grounds.</p>
<p>&quot;This is really the most difficult thing because we are turning to the question of constitution and constitutional right. There are people who are using loopholes so they can distribute this filth,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Ratification of the Europol Convention was seriously delayed due to a dispute between Britain and its EU partners over the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice over the agency.</p>
<p>Even though EU leaders settled that problem at their last summit in Florence in June, not a single EU member has yet ratified the convention.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
