<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53502" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Parents of Belgian child sex gang victims fight on.</title>
<headline>Parents of Belgian child sex gang victims fight on.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>LIEGE, Belgium 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The mourning parents of two eight-year-old Belgian girls, victims of a paedophile gang, vowed on Friday to continue their fight for answers from the judiciary and to protect other children from a similar fate.</p>
<p>The nation was plunged into shock on August 17 when convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux led police to the bodies of Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune buried in his garden. He said the girls, who went missing in June 1995, had starved to death.</p>
<p>&quot;The parents' fight continues to get answers and the truth, to raise levels of vigilance, to change the structures of the system and mentalities so that what has happened is never repeated,&quot; said Carine Russo, Melissa's mother.</p>
<p>Speaking at an emotionally charged news conference in Liege, southern Belgium, the two sets of parents were flanked by the families of 13 other abducted children, all united in grief and determination to find out the truth of their offspring's fate.</p>
<p>They included the parents of An Marchal and the father of Eefje Lambrecks -- teenage girls whose remains were dug up at another house owned by Dutroux. Also present were the parents of two girls found alive, though sexually abused, in a makeshift dungeon at a third property belonging to Dutroux.</p>
<p>&quot;It is because we have the same revulsion, the same anger, the same impression of not having been heard for months on end -- and in some families, for years -- that we feel solidarity and have invited them here,&quot; said Louisa Lejeune.</p>
<p>One by one the parents, brothers and sisters of children presumed abducted in the last 11 years gave brief testimonies of their despair, sense of isolation and frustration.</p>
<p>&quot;I have never had any concrete responses from the law -- I want parents to be listened to,&quot; said the mother of Sylvie Carlin, 19, who disappeared in December 1994 in Sars-La-Buissiere, near Charleroi.</p>
<p>One of the youngest to speak was 18-year-old Nabela Ben Aissa, whose sister Loubna disappeared from near her home in Brussels in 1992, aged six.</p>
<p>&quot;We form a big family here today -- united in our grief, in the questions we're asking, in our search for truth,&quot; she said, fighting to hold back tears.</p>
<p>Julie's mother said the Russo and Lejeune families had received 40,000 letters of support, and had benefited from a committee of friends and professionals.</p>
<p>&quot;Our wish is that each parent of a victim can have a support group to help them,&quot; she said. Made up of lawyers, psychologists, doctors, teachers and so on, these groups could also be approached by people aware of children being exploited.</p>
<p>&quot;The priority is to combat every kind of paedophilia and to save and free every child victim,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Police investigating the case have been praised for making seven arrests in quick succession on charges of child kidnapping or criminal association, including Dutroux himself.</p>
<p>But they also face sharp criticism for past bungling, with vital information not being passed from one division to another, and a question mark over whether Dutroux enjoyed high-level protection to remain undetected for so long.</p>
<p>&quot;The police have made several spectacular arrests, and already people are saying that the criminal network is a small one, as though it was all resolved,&quot; said Carine Russo.</p>
<p>&quot;I say no. We're far from finished with this criminal world, far from having eradicated the root of evil.&quot;</p>
<p>The two families said they continued to demand access to the essence of their daughters' files, which had been denied them since Julie and Melissa disappeared, adding they had not even been allowed to identify their daughters' bodies themselves.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIEGE, Belgium"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
