<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53560" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Europol needs powers to fight child sex trade.</title>
<headline>Europol needs powers to fight child sex trade.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union's justice chief on Friday urged the 15-nation bloc's governments to urgently ratify a convention allowing the Europol police agency to play a crucial role in fighting the child sex trade.</p>
<p>Justice Commissioner Anita Gradin said that until the convention making Europol fully operational was ratified it could not carry out vital work pooling and analysing lists of missing children sent by police agencies in the bloc.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone should go home and ratify the Europol convention. If we want to get hold of these gangs who are stealing, abducting children then you need a Europol that's effective,&quot; she told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Gradin will float ideas on how to fight the child sex trade in Europe at an informal meeting of EU justice ministers in Dublin on September 26-27.</p>
<p>She said they would include urging more EU countries to follow the practice of trying in their home countries men who travel abroad to buy sex with children.</p>
<p>An Irish member of the European Parliament, Mary Banotti, has suggested the police agency set up a database to help search for missing children and young people under the age of 15.</p>
<p>Gradin said on Friday that until the convention is ratified Europol could not run such a database.</p>
<p>Ratification of the convention was seriously delayed by a dispute between Britain and its EU partners over the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice over the agency.</p>
<p>Even though EU leaders settled that problem at their last summit in Florence in June, not a single EU member had yet ratified the convention.</p>
<p>The child sex trade has been thrown into the international spotlight after the discovery in Belgium in August of the bodies of four young girls and the rescue of two others -- victims of a gang apparently led by convicted multiple rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
