<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53721" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Former Belgian PM advocates judicial shakeup.</title>
<headline>Former Belgian PM advocates judicial shakeup.</headline>
<byline>Yves Clarisse</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former Prime Minister Wilfried Martens says the twin paedophilia and murder scandals now rocking Belgium poses a major challenge to Belgium's political structures.</p>
<p>&quot;I am sad that we have lost time,&quot; the man who held power for 10 years in the 1980s and is arguably the father of modern Belgium, told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;With all the institutional reforms that we have implemented in this country, much energy was not used on the social problems that we have, the reform of the judiciary and the police,&quot; Martens added.</p>
<p>Belgium has been racked by grief, guilt and anger as the two scandals have unfolded over the past month, begining with the rescue of two sexually-abused young girls on August 15, the discovery of the bodies of four more over the next three weeks and culminating last weekend in the arrest for murder of a former government minister.</p>
<p>Marc Dutroux and eight others -- including Dutroux' second wife -- have been charged with offences ranging from abduction and illegal imprisonment to car theft and forgery.</p>
<p>In the political murder case, six people, including former Socialist minister Alain Van der Biest and his former private secretary Richard Taxquet -- a policemen -- have been charged with the murder in July 1991 of Socialist Party patriarch Andre Cools.</p>
<p>Investigators have revealed a trail of police and judicial bungling, incompetence, inefficiency and in-fighting that has led to allegations of a cover-up and possible complicity and triggered calls for a major reform of the entire system.</p>
<p>Martens supports the reforms that have been adopted to calm the undercurrent of tensions between Dutch and French speaking regions in this linguistically-divided country.</p>
<p>But he believes that politicians have focused too narrowly on these inter-communal issues.</p>
<p>&quot;We cannot undergo a reform of the state every 10 years,&quot; he said. &quot;The creativity and energy should be conserved for other problems,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Martens condemned attempts by certain Flemish politicians to take advantage of the scandals, whose main protagonists come from the francophone Wallonia region, to acclerate the dismantling of the country.</p>
<p>&quot;We need a unified effort to fight this curse that exists in our country. We will resolve nothing through separatism. This is not a Walloon problem,&quot; Martens, president of the Christian Democrat group in the European Parliament.</p>
<p>One of the most urgent changes, he said, was ending the system whereby magistrates are politically-appointed.</p>
<p>&quot;The majority of magistrates have integrity and are capable, but it has become clear that the lacuna we have found have been due in large part to the political influence in the nominations,&quot; he said. &quot;I believe that we have to put an end to this.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that the (Belgian) parliament will, through the commission of enquiry that has been decided, clarify the situation,&quot; Martens said.</p>
<p>He added that current circumstances were &quot;dangerous for democracy&quot; because of the degree to which people had lost confidence in the political system.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
