<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56040" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium said to issue warrants for alleged killers.</title>
<headline>Belgium said to issue warrants for alleged killers.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium has issued international arrest warrants for the two alleged assassins of leading politician Andre Cools who was gunned down on July 18, 1991, Belgian media said on Monday.</p>
<p>After the mafia-style murder the two men, of Tunisian origin, had travelled back to Sicily where their last address was known to police, Belgian BRTN radio said.</p>
<p>Cools, a former Socialist minister, was shot at point-blank range in the car park outside his mistress's appartment near the eastern Belgian city of Liege.</p>
<p>Belgian RTBF television said the men had been named by Interpol as Abdel Jielil Ben Regiel and Abdel Magid Bel Almi, aged 26 and 19 at the time.</p>
<p>They had been living in the Agrigento region, but it was unclear whether they were still in Sicily or even whether they were still alive, reports said.</p>
<p>The Belgian foreign ministry had no comment, and Liege public prosecutors could not be reached for comment.</p>
<p>Six people, including former government minister Alain Van der Biest, have been arrested and charged with orchestrating Cools's murder.</p>
<p>Van der Biest denies any involvement in the killing.</p>
<p>The arrests came after an anonymous witness told police that a Belgo-Italian -- one of those arrested -- associated with organised crime had driven to Sicily to collect two men and later drove them back to Sicily. The witness also supplied other details of the preparations for the alleged murder.</p>
<p>It remains unclear who ordered the killing or why, although the murder has been linked to an announcement by Cools that he would make revelations at the end of the summer of 1991 about corruption in the francophone Socialist Party.</p>
<p>According to lawyers for some of the accused, witnesses told investigators the murder was a contract killing for 750,000 Belgian francs ($25,000).</p>
<p>Over the past five years the inquiry into Cools's death and the role he played as one of the bosses in the Socialist Party has uncovered corruption at the highest levels of Belgian government.</p>
<p>The scandal led to the resignation of four ministers and NATO Secretary General Willy Claes and the suicide of a top general.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
