<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56149" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: War of words between Belgian regions heats up.</title>
<headline>War of words between Belgian regions heats up.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Relations between Belgium's French-speaking and Flemish communities soured further on Monday when the Flemish leader Luc Van den Brande accused his counterpart in Francophone Wallonia of dishonesty.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically I must come to the conclusion that you are politically, intellectually and institutionally dishonest,&quot; the Flemish regional prime minister said in an open letter to Walloon leader Robert Collignon.</p>
<p>Speaking at this weekend's annual Wallonia festival, Collignon had urged federal Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene to make clear whether he backed Van den Brande's &quot;separatist&quot; drive.</p>
<p>Both Dehaene and Van den Brande are Flemish Christian Democrats.</p>
<p>&quot;You know very well I am not a separatist,&quot; Van den Brande said in the letter. &quot;For a long time I had the illusion we could have a loyal cooperation. After your repeated personal attacks, I am beginning to doubt this seriously.&quot;</p>
<p>The two regions live in a constant state of nervous tension with impoverished Wallonia threatening to break up Belgium's federal structure and join France whenever it feels calls for more independence from wealthy Flanders are becoming too loud.</p>
<p>Things came to a head again recently when a leading Flemish politician accused Walloon authorities of being lax in vetting applicants for social security.</p>
<p>The outburst came after it emerged that a Walloon couple embroiled in a case of child sex abuse, kidnapping and murder had received generous benefits, while the husband -- a convicted child rapist -- owned a dozen houses.</p>
<p>In the affair, which has made headlines since mid-August, the bodies of four young girls were unearthed, while two were rescued from the hands of the chief suspect, Marc Dutroux. His wife, Michelle Martin, is accused of being an accomplice.</p>
<p>Revelations about the Dutroux gang were followed by more about the separate, Mafia-style killing of former minister Andre Cools in July 1991, and about suspected corruption in both cases, leaving the country in a state of shock and mistrust of politicians and the justice system.</p>
<p>The two affairs have also highlighted the lack of a strong common identity in Belgium which became a state just over 150 years ago.</p>
<p>Both are based in Wallonia -- a coincidence which some politicians in the Dutch-speaking northern half of the country have used to call for further separation between the two regions which received extensive powers in a reform in 1993.</p>
<p>Their calls and the accusation of laxity against the Walloons have put Collignon on the defensive.</p>
<p>He was also infuriated by Flemish media he said had been &quot;spitting on Wallonia in these difficult circumstances&quot; and had painted the region in a despicable and scandalous light.</p>
<p>The affairs have changed the image of Belgium from a quiet backwater where food and beer are good to a seemingly lawless state where mafia-style corruption infects politics and paedophiles enjoy police protection and lavish social security benefits.</p>
<p>The image of Wallonia, where industry is in decline, has become even worse. It is seen as a place where an army of marginalised unemployed is turning to any illegal trafficking, the mafia is finding willing recruits and social security contributions are being abused.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
