<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56829" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Trial of Belgian PM kidnap gang member begins.</title>
<headline>Trial of Belgian PM kidnap gang member begins.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Basri Bajrami, dubbed the Houdini of Belgian crime because of the number of times he escaped from jail, went on trial on Monday, the last member of what was once Belgium's most wanted gang.</p>
<p>He is being tried on several counts of robbery and murder committed as a member of the notorious Haemers Gang, which wrought havoc across Belgium in the 1980s and kidnapped a former prime minister.</p>
<p>The trial could not have come at a worse time for a country reeling from the twin scandals of political assassination and paedophile kidnapping, rape and murder that have brought Belgium's already shaky judicial system under attack.</p>
<p>Bajrami, who broke out of a Belgian prison in 1993 in an escape that would have had movie directors drooling, consulted frequently with his defence team as the jury of six men and six women were chosen amid tioght security.</p>
<p>Bajrami last appeared in a Belgian court in April 1993, shortly before his escape. But the case had to be adjourned because such was the fear of the Haemers Gang that not enough jurors could be found.</p>
<p>Presiding judge Marc de la Court warned the jury on Monday that they must discuss the case with no one except themselves. The quantity of evidence was &quot;enormous&quot;, amounting to more than 134 folders each with more than 1,000 pages, he said.</p>
<p>Bajrami has already been tried and sentenced to death in absentia on charges related to his membership of the gang.</p>
<p>The death penalty was erased from the statute books in June, but nevertheless under Belgian law the trial must be held again now Bajrami, 41, is in jail again.</p>
<p>The Haemers Gang's career culminated in the kidnapping in January 1989 of former Belgian prime minister Paul Vanden Boeynants. He was released after a month for a ransom reputed to have been more than $1.5 million.</p>
<p>The leader of the gang, Patrick Haemers, was caught in Brazil in May 1989 and extradited to Belgium. He hanged himself in prison in 1993.</p>
<p>Bajrami's notoriety was enhanced by his dramatic escape from a Brussels jail in 1993, recorded by news cameras filming a prison riot. A hostage was spreadeagled across the windshield of the escape car, his head through the sunroof, and the gangster's pistol jammed in his mouth.</p>
<p>Bajrami was extradited to Belgium two years later from his native Macedonia.</p>
<p>The spectre of the Haemers Gang continues to haunt Belgium.</p>
<p>A central suspect in the so-called Dutroux affair of child kidnapping, sexual abuse, pornography and murder -- named after the key suspect Marc Dutroux -- is Jean-Michel Nihoul.</p>
<p>Nihoul, who had prevously been charged only with criminal association, was charged on Thursday with abduction after police rejected the alibi for the night in question that had been provided by a former associate of Patrick Haemers.</p>
<p>Nihoul has admitted only to a passing acquaintance with Dutroux, who has confessed to abducting or involvement in the abduction of six young girls.</p>
<p>But he was identified as being in the vicinity when Laetitia Delhez, 14, was kidnapped on August 9. She was rescued six days later. But four young girls have been found dead and the Dutroux affair has shocked Belgium.</p>
<p>The arrest one week ago of six people, including a former government minister, on charges of having murdered another former Socialist minister, turned shock into disgust at the Belgian judicial and political system.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
