<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58755" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Free Belgian gang members feared behind new kidnaps.</title>
<headline>Free Belgian gang members feared behind new kidnaps.</headline>
<byline>Nieck Ammerlaan</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian parents, shocked by the killing of four girls by a paedophile gang, have been jolted again by fresh kidnappings which media speculate may be the work of gang members still at large.</p>
<p>Since mid-August, when the activities of the gang led by a convicted child rapist came to light, five more teenage girls disappeared mysteriously, although all reappeared soon afterwards.</p>
<p>It is unclear who snatched the youngsters, but newspapers say they fear members of the gang who are still free are thumbing their noses at the police.</p>
<p>&quot;Kidnaps to intimidate the investigators?&quot; Het Laatste Nieuws headlined its coverage on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Police have declined to confirm or deny the speculation.</p>
<p>Four people have been arrested in the paedophilia, kidnapping and murder case.</p>
<p>The chief accused is unemployed father-of-three Marc Dutroux who has served time for child sex abuse. His wife, Michelle Martin, is alleged to have been an accomplice.</p>
<p>In a case which has overturned Belgium's image as a quiet backwater where beer and food are the main preoccupations, the bodies of four young girls have been unearthed. Two more girls were rescued from Dutroux.</p>
<p>He and another alleged accomplice, Michel Lelievre, have been charged with abduction and illegal imprisonment. Brussels businessman Michel Nihoul has been charged with criminal association and involvement in one of the abductions.</p>
<p>The case highlighted the anxieties of parents of missing children -- at least 13 are unaccounted for -- but when more girls began disappearing nerves tensed all over again.</p>
<p>Last Friday, a 12-year-old Moroccan girl was snatched in the Brussels area. She was found the following morning.</p>
<p>On Saturday a 13-year-old and a 15-year-old vanished in Bouillon, in southern Belgium. They were found safe early on Sunday near the French border where they told police two men had grabbed them.</p>
<p>From the eastern town Liege, Rachel Legeard, 18, and Severine Potty, 19, were kidnapped. Several days later they were found in Germany not far from the Belgian border.</p>
<p>Four of the five girls said they had been pulled into a car and drugged -- an approach reminiscent of the way Dutroux is accused of grabbing his victims from the street.</p>
<p>But police doctors found no traces of sexual abuse. No ransom was demanded.</p>
<p>Some social analysts said the kidnappers, identified by the girls from Bouillon only as two men in a car with Belgian licence plates, could be members of the gang still at large who were out to show police they could still hit where it hurt.</p>
<p>&quot;The kidnappings are pinpricks, warning shots,&quot; said one analyst, who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>There has been other evidence of intimidation attempts.</p>
<p>Investigators in the southern town of Neufchateau, where the probe into the Dutroux case is concentrated, have donned bullet-proof jackets. The investigating judge and magistrate are being driven around in armoured cars.</p>
<p>Other analysts, however, regard the latest kidnappings as the work of paedophile copy-cats or as coincidental and receiving more attention than normal because of the Dutroux case.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
