<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64626" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Gendarmerie defends itself in Belgian scandals.</title>
<headline>Gendarmerie defends itself in Belgian scandals.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Belgian Gendarmerie, stung into reaction by accusations in the media of blundering or worse in the country's twin scandals of paedophile porn and political murder, hit back on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;These allegations are scandalous and totally without foundation,&quot; Colonel Willem Vanden Broeck told a news conference.</p>
<p>But no sooner had he spoken than Justice Minister Stefaan de Clerck told a special session of parliament that Liege Public Prosecutor, Ann Thily, investigating the Gendarmerie investigations had found a major breakdown in communications.</p>
<p>Belgian and international media have repeatedly suggested that the legal and judicial authorities were either incompetent or corrupt in the investigations into the kidnap and killing of four young girls by a gang led by convicted rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>Likewise allegations of incompetence and political meddling have surfaced in more than five years of investigations into the murder of influential Socialist politician Andre Cools.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not pretend everything the Gendarmerie did in the Dutroux case was perfect. But we have done all we could and more and have nothing to hide,&quot; General-Major Herman Fransen said.</p>
<p>Leaked documents show the Gendarmerie was running a covert surveillance operation codenamed &quot;Othello&quot; against Dutroux from 1993 to 1995.</p>
<p>There have been allegations that the information gathered was either supressed or not given sufficient urgency when it was passed on to investigators into missing children.</p>
<p>The Gendarmerie flatly denied these accusations.</p>
<p>But de Clerck, citing Thily, said information being passed to the Liege Gendarmerie by their colleagues investigating Dutroux in Charleroi was not passed to the local magistrate investigating the disappearance of two eight-year-old girls.</p>
<p>Fransen strongly defended the actions of his force.</p>
<p>&quot;It is thanks to the work of the Gendarmerie that Dutroux was arrested...without this work and a vigilant witness Dutroux would still be at large,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vanden Broeck and Fransen admitted that Dutroux had simply outwitted the Gendarmerie investigators for years.</p>
<p>&quot;Dutroux was extremely intelligent, cunning and malicious, and it was not possible to get evidence,&quot; Vanden Broeck said.</p>
<p>Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo were kidnapped from their Liege homes in June 1995. Their bodies were found on August 17 1996 buried on a property owned by Dutroux in Sars-La-Buissiere south of Charleroi. They had been starved to death.</p>
<p>Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal were abducted in August 1995 from Ostend. Their bodies were found buried on another property associated with Dutroux in Charleroi on September 3 this year.</p>
<p>Police were led to the bodies by Dutroux himself, arrested on August 13 after an alert eyewitness remembered the colour, make and half the number plate of a van near the spot where Laetitia Delhez, 14, had disappeared four days before.</p>
<p>It was quickly traced to Dutroux who eventually admitted the abduction and showed police a secret dungeon in another of his Charleroi houses where Laetitia and another girl, Sabine Dardenne who had been missing since May, were found alive.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that one day we will have the opportunity to show you the cages that Dutroux built to illustrate to you quite how ingenious he was,&quot; Fransen said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
