<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64657" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian establishment flays itself over scandals.</title>
<headline>Belgian establishment flays itself over scandals.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium's political elite, led by Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene, launched into an agonised public soul-search on Thursday, trying to restore public confidence devastated by scandals over child sex and murder.</p>
<p>&quot;We must ask ourselve what we have done wrong -- each of us, in politics, in the judiciary, the police, in the media, and the population in general -- so as to prevent a repetition of these events,&quot; Dehaene told a special session of parliament.</p>
<p>Louis Michel, leader of the opposition Wallonia Liberal Party, told the house that &quot;The people have lost confidence in the justice system, in the government and in the country's institution.&quot;</p>
<p>And Patrick Dewael, faction leader of the opposition Flemish Liberal Party, added: &quot;The citizens of this country are furious about the government's inability to deal with society's most urgent needs, notably a reform of the judicial system.&quot;</p>
<p>Dehaene vowed that any serious police errors in the cases would be punished and promised more support in future for the families of victims, who have complained of the inhumanity of the law.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll put the accent on the central place of the victims and their families and we'll provide the necessary means in terms of staff to let the judiciary attach more importance to this aspect,&quot; Dehaene told a special session of parliament.</p>
<p>Belgian police are trying to solve the murder of Belgian politician five years ago, and - separately - investigating the deaths of four girls at the hands of a paedophile gang where the chief suspect is a convicted child rapist, Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>But in both cases, which have shocked the country in different ways, police have been accused of bungling and missing vital chances - incompetence or corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;If it appears that during early phases of the investigation serious errors have been made, they will be punished,&quot; Dehaene told parliament of the so-called &quot;Dutroux&quot; affair.</p>
<p>He said the conclusions of an inquiry into both investigations would be presented to parliament's justice commission as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Stefaan De Clerck said a report by Liege Public Prosecutor Ann Thily confirmed there had been major communications breakdowns in the child kidnap investigation between different police divisions and levels of authorities.</p>
<p>The gendarmerie, however, has denied it is at fault.</p>
<p>The parents of eight-year-olds Julia Lejeune and Melissa Russo, who disappeared in June 1995 and were found dead in Dutroux's garden on August 17, have complained bitterly over the slow progress made by police.</p>
<p>They - and parents of other abducted children - say they have not taken seriously by the police, and add they were not even allowed to identify Julie's and Melissa's bodies.</p>
<p>As well as more support for victims' families, other judicial reforms have been promised including tougher rules on the early release of child sex offender prisoners from jail.</p>
<p>But some past law changes have still not been implemented.</p>
<p>Dehaene said the judiciary should do its utmost to make progress in the investigation into the 1991 mafia-style murder of politician Andre Cools.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation into the murder raised many questions and led to a general feeling of mistrust of our institutions. The judiciary now must go to the heart of the matter,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In the case of the killing of Cools, a former Socialist minister, party-appointed investigators have attempted to divert inquiries leading to party members, judicial sources claim.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not pretend that everything the Gendarmerie has done in the Dutroux case was perfect,&quot; Gendarmerie General-Major Herman Fransen told a news conference. &quot;But we have done all we could and more and have nothing to hide.&quot;</p>
<p>He added: &quot;If the Cools case has received new impetus recently it is thanks to the Gendarmerie investigating team.&quot;</p>
<p>Investigation of the Cools murder led to the discovery of high-level corruption in an army helicopters contract in the late 1980s, which triggered the resignation of four Belgian government ministers and of NATO Secretary-General Willy Claes, a Belgian former economics minister.</p>
<p>Until a few weeks ago, however, investigators did not learn much about the killing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
