<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65306" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EU parliament demands action on child sex.</title>
<headline>EU parliament demands action on child sex.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Chalmers</byline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG, France 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Parliament pressed the European Union on Thursday to act to curb child sex and trafficking rings, saying the fight against sexual abuse of children must be an &quot;absolute priority&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The scourge of paedophilia, trade in children and sexual exploitation is constantly increasing, not only in isolated cases but also through transnational networks and sex tourism, which involve extreme violence,&quot; the parliament said in a resolution.</p>
<p>&quot;Combatting the sexual exploitation of children must be an absolute priority for all EU member states, and the European Union must support their efforts,&quot; deputies said.</p>
<p>The text urged EU governments to create the legal frameworks for police and justice departments to pool efforts to break up child prostitution networks and to pursue those EU nationals involved in child &quot;sex tourism&quot; outside the 15-country bloc.</p>
<p>Other suggested measures included the establishment of a central register of abducted children, more money for Europol -- the bloc's embryonic police force -- to fight such crimes and special training for those pursuing sex criminals.</p>
<p>But a last-minute amendment backing the creation of an EU register of convicted paedophiles was defeated.</p>
<p>Parliament's call to action follows Belgium's unfolding horror story of child kidnapping, sexual abuse and murder in which four girls have been found dead since August and another two have been rescued alive from captors' hands.</p>
<p>Belgian police have arrested nine people on a series of charges since finding the girls alive, including convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>The affair has revolted the country and raised questions of police bungling and political cover-up.</p>
<p>Euro-MPs also called for action to stop criminals using the Internet to disseminate pornography and to deal in women and children. They urged the European Commission to look into technical and legal measures, at European and global level, to combat the use of the information superhighway for criminal purposes.</p>
<p>They said a strong regulatory framework for controlling the networks was needed to ensure that people's personal and social rights were enhanced by the advent of the new technology.</p>
<p>Parliament's calls came the day after Irish Prime Minister John Bruton pledged to use his country's tenure of the six-month EU presidency to push for coordinated EU action.</p>
<p>&quot;Recent events brought home to us all the obscene and shocking crimes perpetrated against children on our continent,&quot; Bruton said in a speech to Euro-MPs.</p>
<p>His remarks followed those of European Justice Commissioner Anita Gradin, who urged last week that EU's 15 countries end their foot-dragging over the issue.</p>
<p>She said an urgent ratification of the Europol Convention to launch the Hague-based police agency was one concrete way they could fight the child-sex trade which has shocked the world.</p>
<p>Among the ideas Gradin will float at a Dublin meeting of EU justice and home affairs ministers on September 26-27 are that countries should try people who travel abroad to buy child sex.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
