<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65446" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgium vows punishment for bungling in scandals.</title>
<headline>Belgium vows punishment for bungling in scandals.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene said on Thursday that any serious errors in the investigation of Belgium's paedophile sex, kidnap and murder cases would be punished.</p>
<p>&quot;If it appears that during earlier phases of the investigation serious errors have been made, they will be sanctioned,&quot; Dehaene told parliament which convened early to discuss the twin paedophilia and political murder scandals which have rocked the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The justice minister has ordered an inquiry into the investigation of the child kidnappings. He has just received the report and will inform parliament about it,&quot; Dehaene said.</p>
<p>He said the inquiry conclusions would be presented to parliament's justice commission as soon as possible.</p>
<p>The prime minister gave no information about the contents of the report.</p>
<p>Belgian media said on Thursday it was highly critical of police cooperation and procedures.</p>
<p>Dehaene also said the judiciary should do its utmost to make progress in the investigation into the 1991 mafia-style murder of politician Andre Cools.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation into the murder raised many questions and led to a general feeling of mistrust of our institutions. The judiciary now must go to the heart of the matter,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Members from all parties will take the floor at 2 p.m. (1200 GMT) in parliament's extraordinary session which was convened at the request of the opposition, two weeks before the parliamentary year had been due to start.</p>
<p>Parties were expected to back the setting-up of a committee of inquiry into judicial bungling in the investigations of the Cools murder and the activities of a paedophile ring which claimed the lives of four young girls in the past year.</p>
<p>There have been allegations of cover-ups in both cases.</p>
<p>In the child sex case, police officers are suspected of having been involved in a car theft racket led by paedophile gang leader and convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux.</p>
<p>In the case of the killing of Cools, a former Socialist minister, party-appointed investigators have attempted to divert inquiries leading to party members, judicial sources  say.</p>
<p>The investigation into the Cools murder led to the discovery of high-level corruption in an army helicopters contract in the late 1980s, which triggered the resignation of four Belgian government ministers and of NATO Secretary-General Willy Claes, a former economics minister.</p>
<p>&quot;Together we must ask ourselves what has gone wrong,&quot; Dehaene said.</p>
<p>&quot;We must also wonder what we have done wrong ourselves, each of us, in politics, in the judiciary, the police, in the media, and the population in general so as to prevent a repeat of these events.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
