<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79021" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian mayor backs calls to raze &quot;Horror House&quot;.</title>
<headline>Belgian mayor backs calls to raze &quot;Horror House&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>BELGIUM 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The mayor of Charleroi in southern Belgium on Thursday backed calls to demolish a house where two dead Belgian girls were unearthed, victims in a child kidnapping, sex abuse and murder scandal.</p>
<p>The decomposed bodies of teeanage friends An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, missing for a year, were found on September 4 under a shed in the grounds of a house in the Jumet suberb of Charleroi, last lived in by Frenchman Bernard Weinstein.</p>
<p>Belgian news agency Belga quoted the Charleroi city mayor Jacques Van Gompel as saying he fully supported a petition signed by more than 3,000 people which demanded the detached chalet-style house be razed to the ground.</p>
<p>&quot;We want the house to go because here in the neighbourhood it is the &quot;House of Horror'. We want a green space with a memorial to the little victims of paedophilia,&quot; local resident Nadine Lips told Belgian television.</p>
<p>Van Gompel had contacted Interior Minister Johan Vande Lanotte and was now awaiting government approval.</p>
<p>Convicted child rapist Marc Dutroux, who is chief suspect in the scandal, has admitted abducting An and Eefje and murdering Weinstein whom he said was his accomplice.</p>
<p>Belgium was shock and outraged on August 17 when Dutroux led police to the bodies of two other girls - eight-year-olds Melissa Russo and Julie Lejeune - in the garden of a house he owned in Sars-La-Buissiere south west of the city.</p>
<p>The youngsters disappeared in June 1995.</p>
<p>Two days earlier there had been rejoicing when Laeticia Delhez, 14, and Sabine Dardenne, 12, were rescued from a home-made dungeon in another of Dutroux's houses in the Charleroi area.</p>
<p>Dutroux has been charged with abduction, illegal imprisonment and the murder of Weinstein, whose body was found alongside those of Julie and Melissa. In all 12 people have been arrested in relation to the alleged kidnapping and paedophilia ring and a linked car theft investigation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
