<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15744" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Nissan aims to raise its RV share.</title>
<headline>Nissan aims to raise its RV share.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nissan Motor Co Ltd aims to raise its share of the domestic recreational vehicle market with a new heavy sport-utility vehicle that was previewed on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to raise our share (in Japan's heavy sport-utility vehicle market) by two to three percentage points to about 27 percent through sales of the new Terrano Regulus,&quot; Nissan president Yoshikazu Hanawa told reporters at a preview of the new model.</p>
<p>The vehicle opens a new market -- the luxury version of a heavy sport-utility vehicle.</p>
<p>Japan's overall demand for heavy sport-utility vehicles stands at about 18,600 per month. Nissan said no other Japanese makers have a model in the same market segment. Regulus will be positioned in the same segment as Chrysler Corp's Grand Cherokee.</p>
<p>The Terrano Regulus was developed as a new generation personal sport-utility vehicle with an image of premium quality, Hanawa said.</p>
<p>Regulus features a cleaner, more silent but powerful 3.2-litre intercooler-turbo diesel engine, Hanawa said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We set a conservative sales target -- 1,000 a month. I think we can expect more though,&quot; Hanawa said. The domestic selling price of Regulus will range from 2.763 million to 3.399 million yen.</p>
<p>Terrano Regulus was aimed at people in their 40s and 50s, another Nissan official said. The vehicle is is equipped with dual airbags and anti-lock brake system as standard.</p>
<p>Hanawa said Nissan will also start selling the Terrano Regulus in the autumn in the United States through its Infiniti luxury car sales network.</p>
<p>Nissan plans to export more than 1,000 Terrano Regulus a month, to be marketed as Infiniti QX4 to compete with Toyota's Land Cruiser and Chrysler's Grand Cherokee, another Nissan official said.</p>
<p>Toyota sells its Land Cruiser in the United States under the model name of LX450 at about 1,000 a month.</p>
<p>Chrysler now sells about 30,000 Grand Cherokees a month in the United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C313">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
