<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="28198" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan August vehicle sales slip, but pickup seen.</title>
<headline>Japan August vehicle sales slip, but pickup seen.</headline>
<byline>Mitsuo Suzuki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's domestic automobile sales fell in August but are likely to pick up in September as new models bring buyers into the showrooms, industry sources say.</p>
<p>Domestic vehicle sales fell 2.1 percent from a year earlier to 290,144 in August after rising in July, the Japan Automobile Dealers' Association said on Monday.</p>
<p>An uncertain economy means Japan's domestic automobile sales have fluctuated since February, when they marked a 21st successive month of year-on-year gains.</p>
<p>&quot;It is still unclear at the moment whether Japan's domestic vehicle sales have started recovering, because the decline was just because August 1996 had 22 sales days against 23 in August of 1995,&quot; an association official told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;But in September, domestic sales are expected to post gains because several new models -- Mazda's Demio, Mitsubishi's Galant, and Toyota's Carina and Windom, are expected to contribute to boosting sales,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Domestic sales by Toyota Motor Corp rose 0.1 percent from a year earlier to 106,121 in August because of good sales of recreational vehicles -- the Ipsum and Land Cruiser Prado, but Nissan's fell 3.7 percent to 54,361 due to poor demand for its mainstay medium-class sedans.</p>
<p>Honda sales gained 26.9 percent to 32,541, marking the 20th successive month of year-on-year gains, helped by robust demand for its recreational vehicles such as the Step Wagon, CR-V and Orthia. Mitsubishi's fell 13.8 percent to 27,660 because of poor demand for its sedans and recreational vehicles.</p>
<p>&quot;Domestic sales will post gains in and after September as new models come out fully in all market segments,&quot; said Nobuaki Yanachi, Kankaku Research senior analyst.</p>
<p>Toyota will make a big drive to boost its domestic sales by providing large incentives to dealers for achieving its targeted 40 percent share of the domestic market. It will also launch its mainstay luxury sedan Mark II on September 5, Yanachi said.</p>
<p>Toyota's share stood at 38 percent in the January-August period this year against 39 percent in the same period a year earlier, industry data shows.</p>
<p>Toyota expects new models of the Carina, Windom and Mark II to help it post a single-digit gain in September and a double-digit gain from October onwards, a Toyota spokesman said.</p>
<p>Among other gainers, Fuji Heavy marked a steep 33 percent rise to 7,368 in August, with customers welcoming an improvement in the engine performance and handling of its mainstay Legacy sedan and station wagon. Suzuki gained 8.5 percent to 4,212 due to good sales of its station wagon Crescent Wagon.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
