<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="40239" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Fuji Heavy seen posting bigger group profit.</title>
<headline>Fuji Heavy seen posting bigger group profit.</headline>
<byline>Mitsuo Suzuki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>A weaker yen and strong demand for the Subaru station wagon in the United States are expected to raise Fuji Heavy Industries Ltd's group profit this business year, industry analysts said on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Fuji Heavy's group current profit is likely to be 15 billion yen ($137 million) in the year to March 1997 because of improving business at SIA and SOA (its units in the United States),&quot; Nikko Research Center senior analyst Noriyuki Matsushima said.</p>
<p>Fuji Heavy, the pioneer of four-wheel-drive cars in Japan, did not give a forecast for 1996/97 group profit. It posted a group current profit of 10.89 billion yen ($99.9 million) in the last business year against a profit of 6.22 billion yen ($57.0 million) in 1994/95.</p>
<p>Subaru Isuzu Automotive Inc (SIA), owned 51 percent by Fuji Heavy and 49 percent by Isuzu Motors Ltd, in Lafayette, Indiana, produces Legacy sedans and station wagons, Isuzu's Rodeo sport-utility vehicle, and pickup trucks. Subaru of America (SOA) is Fuji Heavy's sales unit in the United States.</p>
<p>&quot;We estimated Fuji Heavy's group current profit at 21 billion yen ($192 million) because of good sales of its Legacy in the United States,&quot; Nomura Research analyst Seiji Sugiura said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our Legacy Outback series faces strong demand in the United States,&quot; a Fuji Heavy spokesman said.</p>
<p>The Legacy Outback sport-utility wagon is a version of the Legacy Wagon, with a bigger minimum road clearance than normal Legacy models for increased ability to run over rough roads.</p>
<p>Fuji Heavy earlier said its vehicle exports would rise to 75,000 units in the year to March 31, 1997, up from a May forecast of 67,000 due to the weaker yen and strong demand for the Legacy in the United States</p>
<p>In May, Fuji Heavy estimated its 1996/97 vehicle exports at 67,000 against 62,000 vehicles in 1995/96. Fuji Heavy is owned 4.2 percent by Nissan Motor Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Sales of Subaru cars in the United States rose a steep 22.8 percent from a year earlier to 74,600 in the January to August period, helped by robust demand for the Legacy Outback.</p>
<p>SIA will also revise up its production of Legacy models to 97,000 units in calendar 1996 from an earlier projected 94,000, the spokesman said. SIA's facilities for Subaru cars have an output capacity of 84,000 units a year and SIA workers are now working overtime to keep up with strong demand.</p>
<p>Fuji's parent current profit may reach Fuji's projected 20 billion yen ($183 million) in 1996/97 because the yen has fallen in value against the dollar to near 110, Matsushima said.</p>
<p>In May, Fuji Heavy forecast parent current profit of 20 billion yen in 1996/97, up from 10.11 billion yen ($92.7 million) the year before.</p>
<p>&quot;Our latest estimate of Fuji's 1996/97 parent current profit was 13 billion yen ($119 million) assuming a yen/dollar rate of 105 but maybe we are too conservative on Fuji's parent profits,&quot; Matsushima said.</p>
<p>However, Fuji Heavy will face tough business conditions in the year starting April 1997 because of tougher domestic sales competition and a lack of new model launches, the analysts added. ($1=109 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
