<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="48587" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Honda to raise '97 prices less than 1 pct.</title>
<headline>Honda to raise '97 prices less than 1 pct.</headline>
<dateline>TORRANCE, Calif. 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>American Honda Motor Co said it was raising sticker prices on its 1997 Accords by an average 0.4 percent, or $74, while 1997 Civic prices would rise 0.7 percent, or $106.</p>
<p>Accord and Civic account for more than 80 percent of Honda's total U.S. sales, meaning that the automaker's average price increase for all 1997 models will be less than one percent, said spokesman Andy Boyd.</p>
<p>American Honda is a unit of Honda Motor Co Ltd.  </p>
<p>Including destination charges, the Accord will start at $15,495.  An Accord LX with automatic transmission, which accounts for nearly half of all Accord sales, will start at $19,385, an increase of $100, or 0.5 percent.</p>
<p>Civic prices start at $10,945.  Civic CX and DX models receive 14 inch wheels, up from 13 inches before, for 1997. There are no other major equipment changes.</p>
<p>Honda said prices of its 1997 Passport sport/utility vehicle and del Sol convertible are unchanged from last year. Prices for the 1997 Odyssey and new Prelude will be announced later.</p>
<p>Honda is now the second major Japanese automaker to keep 1997 price increases below those of Detroit's Big Three. Last week, Toyota Motor Corp announced that manufacturer's suggested retail prices will rise an average of 1.4 percent, while prices on a comparably equipped basis will go up 0.7 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORRANCE, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
