<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49633" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Isuzu defends Trooper from attack.</title>
<headline>Isuzu defends Trooper from attack.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Isuzu Motors Thursday defended its Trooper sport/utility vehicle against a Consumers Union charge that it was prone to roll over, calling the magazine's testing flawed and unscientific.</p>
<p>Isuzu officials told a news conference that since the Consumers Union report on Aug. 20, it had conducted its own test and had one run by an independent consultant and that the Trooper was found to be safe.</p>
<p>&quot;All of the analysis that we have done so far confirms that the Trooper is a safe, reliable vehicle,&quot; said Terry Maloney, senior vice president and general manager of American Isuzu Motors Inc.</p>
<p>The finding, in CU's magazine Consumer Reports, said the Trooper and the Acura SLX, another sport/utility, tipped up on two wheels in its test, &quot;demonstrating that these sports utility vehicles have too great a tendency to roll over in certain situations.&quot;</p>
<p>It rated the two vehicles -- the Acura is built by Isuzu on the Trooper frame -- as &quot;not acceptable.&quot;</p>
<p>Acura earlier defended the safety of its SLX.</p>
<p>Mahoney said that CU test drivers cut corners while speeding in and out of a cone obstacle course, creating the tendency to tip, while other vehicles tested were driven over the same course with fewer sharp turns, avoiding a tendency to roll over.</p>
<p>He said the CU test was not scientific because the driver could influence the result knowingly or unknowningly by the way he manipulated the vehicle.</p>
<p>Officials at CU were not immediately available for comment on Isuzu's charges.</p>
<p>Norihiko Oda, Isuzu vice president for product engineering and government relations, said the analysis by the outside consultant showed that the CU driver made sharper turns with the Trooper than were made with other vehicles.</p>
<p>He said any such vehicle could be made to roll over under the right conditions and the right driver imput.</p>
<p>Mahoney said Trooper sales fell off a bit after the CU report.</p>
<p>Asked if Isuzu would sue CU, Maloney said too many lawsuits were already being filed, adding &quot;We're hoping there can be some dialogue to resolve this matter.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Isuzu would appreciate a correction in CU's Consumer Reports magazine.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
