<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80483" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Novel Suzuki model so far fails to win audience.</title>
<headline>Novel Suzuki model so far fails to win audience.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>It was supposed to be Suzuki Motor Corp.'s answer to those adventuresome '90s hipsters who pursue so-called extreme sports, like skyboarding and women's boxing.</p>
<p>But the only thing extreme about Suzuki's X-90 is its dismal sales record.</p>
<p>In the first eight months of 1996, Suzuki sold 2,825 of the X-90 -- a stubby, T-top hybrid between a two-seat sports car and sport/utility vehicle. Company officials predicted they would sell 1,000 a month when the vehicle was introduced a year ago.</p>
<p>Adding further insult are sales promotions usually reserved for day-old doughnuts: buy one, get one free.</p>
<p>At Bob Saks Oldsmobile in Farmington Hills, Mich., a person can buy a 1996 Cutlass Supreme for $19,900 and receive an X-90 on a free one-year lease.</p>
<p>Suzuki has long been a small player in the domestic vehicle market, reaching a sales peak in 1987 with 83,334 units. In 1988, the company was battered by news and consumer group reports that its Samuri minisport-utility was prone to tip over. The company denied the charges, but sales never recovered, falling to 32,751 in 1995.</p>
<p>Last year Suzuki introduced the X-90 and two other new vehicles. They were designed to help the Japanese automaker forge a new image in the minds of American buyers, who mostly associate the company with the rollover controversy.</p>
<p>One year later, the X-90 is far below even its modest sales targets.</p>
<p>&quot;The X-90 has probably been their most disappointing product next to the Samuri,&quot; said Steve Kosowski, product and market analyst for AutoPacific Inc., a consulting firm in Santa Ana, Calif.</p>
<p>What went wrong?</p>
<p>Analysts say the concept was flawed. The vehicle is a two-door model with virtually no trunk space and minimal interior storage -- not good for buyers with supposedly active lifestyles.</p>
<p>&quot;It's kind of the answer to the question that nobody asked,&quot; Kosowski said.</p>
<p>Positioned as a four-wheel drive, go-anywhere runabout, the X-90 has also been criticised for limited power, excessive road noise and mediocre handling.</p>
<p>Also unfortunate is the fact that competition is stiffer in the mini sport/utility segment.</p>
<p>The RAV4 from Toyota Motor Corp. has proven to be a hit with price-conscious buyers looking for a practical car-based vehicle. Later this year Honda Motor Co. Ltd. will enter the field with its CR-V.</p>
<p>Suzuki officials are sticking behind their product, however, arguing that it will take time for the X-90 to create sufficient awareness and generate a following. Promotions like the one at dealer Bob Saks are aimed at doing just that, said Anne Bryan, a spokeswoman for American Suzuki.</p>
<p>&quot;The X-90 is a very unique car and people either love it or hate it,&quot; she said. &quot;It just needs a chance to catch on.&quot;</p>
<p>Bryan declined to outline Suzuki's 1997 model year advertising plans. But she said the automaker is considering boosting the profile of the X-90. Meantime, Suzuki is not planning any special incentives or pricing changes.</p>
<p>For their part, Suzuki dealers are bravely touting the vehicle as a niche product that needs to find its niche.</p>
<p>&quot;It's just for a certain populace of the country,&quot; said Ken Chancey, sales manager at Kirill Suzuki in Jacksonville, Fla. &quot;We sell all the ones we get.&quot;</p>
<p>But Chancey thinks Suzuki should bring the price down. Because the X-90 only has two seats, it has trouble competing with the Suzuki Sidekick, which comes in a four-door version.</p>
<p>For 1997, a four-wheel drive X-90 with manual transmission starts at $15,019, after delivery charges. But an automatic transmission, air conditioning and other options can push the price past the $17,000 mark.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
