<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13367" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Calcutta's mentally ill pray for Mother Teresa. [CORRECTED 22:36 GMT]</title>
<headline>Calcutta's mentally ill pray for Mother Teresa. [CORRECTED 22:36 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Arindam Nag</byline>
<dateline>CALCUTTA 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Teresa Singha joined thousands of Indians in prayer on Sunday (corrects day from Saturday) for her 85-year-old namesake Mother Teresa, who gave her the chance five years ago to rebuild a life shattered by mental illness.</p>
<p>Abandoned by her mother when she was just seven, life was difficult for Teresa Singha until 1991. She tried to commit suicide five times. Then she came to live at Shanti Daan (Gift of Peace), a home for the care of mentally ill women set up by Mother Teresa in India's eastern city of Calcutta.</p>
<p>Now 25, she is one of several women gradually putting together the broken pieces of their lives within the serenity of Shanti Daan.</p>
<p>On Sunday she sat down with scores of mentally ill girls to pray for the recovery of Mother Teresa, now battling for life against a weak heart and malarial fever.</p>
<p>&quot;I heard Mother is sick, that is sad,&quot; Teresa Singha said. &quot;I was told that when she first met me she blessed me before I touched her feet.&quot;</p>
<p>On Sunday a spokeswoman for Mother Teresa's missionary order said that the Nobel peace laureate's condition had improved slightly. Earlier, doctors had said her heart problem was under control but she had low-grade fever.</p>
<p>Like the rest of the 180 women in the home, Teresa Singha's family abandoned her after her mental illness worsened. Some had even been jailed as &quot;potential hazards to society&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Mother was the first person to open her hands when the West Bengal government said it did not know what to do with these women,&quot; said Sister Jovita, the nun in charge of Shanti Daan.</p>
<p>Sister Jovita is a Missionary of Charity, the religious order Mother Teresa founded 47 years ago to look after the poor. It has run Shanti Daan since it was set up in 1988.</p>
<p>Teresa is not very sure how she came to Shanti Daan, but Sister Jovita says she was a domestic helper in several homes before she &quot;was abused&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;She lost her normal self. She was handed over to us by another voluntary organisation,&quot; the nun said.</p>
<p>Alo Ghosh, 40, was deserted by an alcoholic who married her after the death of her first husband. Her second husband ran off with all her money and jewellery.</p>
<p>When she became mentally ill, neighbours paid off the police to put her in jail, she said. But today she is much better and is slowly regaining her memory.</p>
<p>Alo and Teresa both prayed for Mother Teresa on the weekend. They plan to celebrate Mother Teresa's birthday on Monday, along with the Missionaries of Charity.</p>
<p>Mother Teresa will turn 85 only on Tuesday but traditionally the Missionaries of Charity celebrate it a day earlier.</p>
<p>Conditions in most Indian jails are bad with inmates complaining of torture, poor food and ill-treatment.</p>
<p>Alo said some of the mentally ill used to be given electric shocks by jail officials. &quot;Some girls used to be beaten too,&quot; she said. She misses her first husband but she likes staying at Shanti Daan, she said.</p>
<p>After 20 minutes of conversation, she cried:&quot;Mother will be allright, isn't it?.....How can she die, we are all praying,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CALCUTTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
