<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="43173" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: J&amp;J sets for schizophrenia drug competition.</title>
<headline>J&amp;J sets for schizophrenia drug competition.</headline>
<byline>Richard Jacobsen</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Facing imminent competition that could slow the pace of its fast-growing schizophrenia drug, Johnson and Johnson is hoping to fight off erosion by broadening uses of Risperdal in an expanding market.</p>
<p>J&amp;J is betting that new entries into the booming anti-psychotic drug market, including Eli Lilly and Co's Zyprexa, will increase the overall number of people treated with the new class of drugs.  </p>
<p>And as the market for new schizophrenia becomes crowded, J&amp;J is running clinical trials aimed at showing its drug's use outside schizophrenia, a senior J&amp;J executive said.</p>
<p>&quot;We like the fact that we are established very broadly in this marketplace,&quot; said Bruce Given, group vice president for the U.S. division of J&amp;J's Janssen Pharmaceutica, said in a recent interview.</p>
<p>About 40 percent of Risperdal's sales are for schizophrenia, while 26 percent are in manic depression, 10 percent in dementia and 24 percent in other ailments, Given said.  </p>
<p>Risperdal was launched in the U.S. in 1994 and was the fastest drug to reach $100 million in sales in J&amp;J's history. Cowen and Co analysts pegged its worldwide sales at $435 million in 1995, estimating sales of $750 million in 1999.</p>
<p>But last week, Lilly said it had received an approvable letter from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for Zyprexa, an indication that final marketing approval for the drug could come within weeks.  </p>
<p>Risperdal has been shown have fewer side effects than Sandoz AG's Clozaril, the first of a new class of anti-psycotics on the market, but is viewed as less effective, industry analysts said.   Meanwhile, Zyprexa is seem as being</p>
<p>as effective as Clozaril but without the side effects.  Some analysts liken the drug's potential to that of Lilly's anti-depressant Prozac, with sales estimates for Zyprexa topping $1 billion a year by 2000.</p>
<p>Zyprexa &quot;is going to slow Risperdal's growth rate but I think (J&amp;J's) accurate in saying that the market's going to expand quite a bit,&quot; Cowen and Co's Ian Sanderson said.  </p>
<p>The Lilly drug will be only the next in a new wave of schizophrenia drugs heading to the market.</p>
<p>Expected to gain FDA approval in the next 12 months are Abbott Laboratories Inc's Serlect, Zeneca Group Plc's Seroquel, and Pfizer Inc's Ziprasidone.</p>
<p>&quot;Rather than these products slugging it out head to head, what's more likely is that we're going to convert a very old product mix to a more modern&quot; one, Given said.</p>
<p>Risperdal's sharp growth has came from patients converting old drugs such as haloperidol, and bringing on previously untreated patients.</p>
<p>J&amp;J estimates that the U.S. market for anti-psychotics has grown to $1 billion from $360 million before Risperdal was launched.  Analysts estimate the market could more than double by the end of the decade.</p>
<p>About one in 100 people in the U.S. is schizophrenic and only half of all schizophrenics are believed to receive treatment.</p>
<p>The growth in the market for anti-psychotics could mean &quot;Risperdal (will be) losing share in a market that's expanding so fast that Risperdal's growth could maintain itself,&quot; NatWest Securities analyst Jack Lamberton said.</p>
<p>--New York Newsdesk, 212-859-1733</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
