<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53426" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Family seeks control of John E. du Pont's estate.</title>
<headline>Family seeks control of John E. du Pont's estate.</headline>
<dateline>MEDIA, Pa. 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>- Relatives of chemicals heir John E. du Pont, who is awaiting trial on murder charges, filed a court petition on Friday to take control of the multimillionaire's estate.</p>
<p>The court action came soon after two defence lawywers notifed the judge in charge of the murder case that they had been fired and wanted to withdraw from the trial.</p>
<p>Du Pont is charged with murdering Olympic champion wrestler David Schultz, but the trial has been held up while authorities determine whether he is mentally competent.</p>
<p>The guardianship petition seeks to have the Orphans Court name du Pont's sister, Jean Shehan, 73 years old, of Coral Gables, Florida, and his nephew, James McConnell Jr., 43, of Rapidan, Virginia, as guardians of the estate. The petition notes that du Pont inherited $88 million.</p>
<p>The relatives say du Pont has shown signs of incompetence, claiming to be the Dalai Lama for North America. That is also an issue in the murder trial.</p>
<p>Lawyers Richard Sprague and William Lamb filed petitions to withdraw with Judge Patricia Jenkins on Tuesday and met with her on Wednesday.</p>
<p>They informed her that du Pont saw them leave a psychiatric examination on Monday in the company of a prosecution expert and accused them of plotting against him. He said they were part of a CIA plot. The district attorney did not object to the withdrawal.</p>
<p>Jenkins did not rule on the lawyers' petitions and promised to have a decision by Monday.</p>
<p>If Sprague and Lamb leave the defence team, the trial may not start Sept. 30 as scheduled. It may also delay a hearing on du Pont's competence Sept. 20. If the family wins its guardianship petition, they would have final say on hiring new lawyers.</p>
<p>Du Pont had been a coach and wrestling enthusiast at Villanova University and later built an Olympic-scale training centre on his estate, Foxcatcher Farm. He hired Schultz to be his coach.</p>
<p>Prosecutors already have decided that du Pont, 58, will not face the death penalty for the January shooting of Schultz. Du Pont remains in Delaware County Jail after defence lawyers lost an attempt to move him to a psychiatric hospital.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEDIA, Pa."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
