<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64442" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Court doctors hold chemicals heir incompetent - report.</title>
<headline>Court doctors hold chemicals heir incompetent - report.</headline>
<dateline>MEDIA, Pa. 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A psychiatric report requested by a Delaware County judge found chemicals heir John E. du Pont was probably unable to assist the defence in his murder trial, the Philadelphia Daily News reported Thursday.</p>
<p>Du Pont is charged with murdering Olympic champion wrestler David Schultz, but the trial has been held up while authorities determine whether the defendant is competent.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a significant probability, based on the totality of the evidence, that John E. du Pont lacks the capacities consistent with competence to stand trial,&quot; said the report written by Drs. Thomas Guthetil of Harvard University and Theodore Barry of Philadelphia.</p>
<p>They said du Pont was not faking his condition, the newspaper said. The report was sealed by the judge but obtained by the Daily News.</p>
<p>The doctors reported to Judge Patricia Jenkins that du Pont had been uncooperative so they could not make findings with &quot;medical certainty&quot; and concluded only on probability.</p>
<p>This is likely to be enough for the defence team to seek postponement of a hearing on du Pont's competence scheduled for Friday, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Another legal development is a petition by family members to assume control of his $80-million estate.</p>
<p>The guardianship petition seeks to have the Orphans Court name du Pont's sister, Jean Shehan, 73, of Coral Gables, Florida, and his nephew, James McConnell Jr., 43, of Rapidan, Virginia, as guardians. The petition notes that du Pont has inherited $88 million.</p>
<p>The relatives say du Pont has exhibited signs of incompetence, claiming to be the Dalai Lama for North America.</p>
<p>A further complication is the withdrawal of lead lawyers Richard Sprague and William Lamb. They had said that du Pont saw them leave a psychiatric examination two weeks ago in the company of a prosecution expert and accused them of plotting against him. He said they were part of a CIA plot.</p>
<p>With Thomas Bergstrom, a former federal prosecutor, now the lead defence lawyer, the trial may not start Sept. 30 as scheduled. It may also delay Friday's competency hearing.</p>
<p>Du Pont had been a coach and wrestling enthusiast at Villanova University and later built an Olympic-scale training centre on his estate, Foxcatcher Farm. He hired Olympic champion Schultz to be his coach.</p>
<p>Prosecutors already have decided that du Pont, 58, will not face the death penalty for the January shooting of Schultz. Du Pont remains in Delaware County Jail after defence lawyers lost an attempt to move him to a psychiatric hospital.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEDIA, Pa."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
