<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64892" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FDA panel approves Teva's multiple sclerosis drug.</title>
<headline>FDA panel approves Teva's multiple sclerosis drug.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Food and Drug Administration advisory committee recommended Thursday that the agency approve a drug developed by Teva Pharmaceutical Industries for treating multiple sclerosis.</p>
<p>The move boosted the Israeli drugmaker's stock, which closed at $47, up $3.50, on Nasdaq.</p>
<p>The stock rallied after the FDA advisory committee recommended the agency approve the company's Copaxone drug that is used to reduce flareups caused by the disease, for which there is no known cure.</p>
<p>The panel's recommendations are not binding but the FDA typically follows the advice of its advisory committees.</p>
<p>Teva, Israel's largest pharmaceutical company, has been known as a leading generic drugmaker.</p>
<p>Copaxone is key to the company's drive to become a full-fledged drug maker, analysts said. They estimated the drug could have worldwide sales of $300 million by the year 2000, given a late 1996 or early 1997 final FDA approval. Teva had 1995 sales of $668 million.</p>
<p>&quot;Copaxone clearly changes the nature of the company,&quot; Dillon Read analyst Jerry Treppel said.</p>
<p>Final FDA approval in the fourth quarter could send the stock to over $60, according to NatWest Securities analyst Jack Lamberton.</p>
<p>Hoechst AG's Hoechst Marion Roussel drug unit is Teva's marketing partner for Copaxone.</p>
<p>The National Multiple Sclerosis Society estimates there are between 250,000 to 350,000 people in the United States with the central nervous system disease.</p>
<p>If approved, Copaxone will go up against two FDA-approved MS treatments. Chiron Corp.'s Betaseron, marketed by Schering AG and launched in July 1993, and Biogen Inc.'s Avonex, introduced in May.</p>
<p>Betaseron carries a claim on its label that it reduces flare-ups of MS, while Avonex carries an additional claim that it slows the disease's progression.</p>
<p>Analysts said they expected Copaxone's labeling to be limited to a claim of reducing flare-ups of the disease. The FDA committee recommendation did not say the drug slows the progession of MS.</p>
<p>MS leads to the degeneration of the sheath of myelin protecting the nerves in the brain and spinal cord, leading to patients slowly losing control of their movement, speech and bodily functions.</p>
<p>Unlike Betaseron and Avonex, which are forms of proteins known as interferons, Copaxone is made up of four amino acids that work by inhibiting the destruction of the myelin sheath.</p>
<p>This new approach could boost Copaxone's chances for approval as well as a marketing angle, analysts said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
