<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68843" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pennsylvania hearing told of du Pont's &quot;delusions&quot;.</title>
<headline>Pennsylvania hearing told of du Pont's &quot;delusions&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>MEDIA, Pa. 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two former attorneys for multimillionaire John du Pont, listing what they said were his delusions, testified Friday that du Pont said the Republican Party, not he, had killed an Olympic wrestler.</p>
<p>Fired defence attorney Richard Sprague, testifying at a competency hearing, said that during the nine months since du Pont was arrested in the Jan. 26 shooting death of wrestler David Schultz, he had never expressed rational knowledge of why he was in jail.</p>
<p>Sprague quoted the defendant as saying Schultz had been killed by the Republicans because du Pont, the 57-year-old heir to a chemical company fortune, did not contribute to the party.</p>
<p>Sprague said du Pont had continually pressed his defence team to &quot;see Bill Clinton&quot; to get him out of jail, &quot;and if Mr. Clinton didn't do what he wanted, he would see that a plane went over the White House and dropped eggs.&quot;</p>
<p>Sprague said when he joked about scrambled eggs, du Pont became angry and shot back, &quot;You don't trifle with the Dali Lama and make jokes.&quot;</p>
<p>The hearing on du Pont's competency to stand trial will continue Saturday before Delaware County Common Pleas Judge Patricia Jenkins. She has set a Jan. 30 trial date.</p>
<p>Psychiatrists are expected to testify for both sides about whether du Pont knows the nature and quality of the charges against him and can participate in his own defence.</p>
<p>On cross-examination by Special Assistant District Attorney Dennis McAndrews, Sprague acknowledged that du Pont had signed a contract stipulating $300-an-hour fees for him and other attorneys in his firm.</p>
<p>He said that so far he had billed du Pont $1.5 million.</p>
<p>Du Pont fired Sprague and fellow attorney William Lamb Jan. 10, claiming they were conspiring with the CIA, the two lawyers testified.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEDIA, Pa."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
