<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69421" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Psychiatrists say du Pont thinks he is Dalai Lama.</title>
<headline>Psychiatrists say du Pont thinks he is Dalai Lama.</headline>
<dateline>MEDIA, Pa. 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Defence psychiatrists said on Saturday that John E. du Pont, the chemicals heir on trial for murder, was a dangerous paranoid schizophrenic who thought he was the Dalai Lama of North America.</p>
<p>They told a Delaware judge that du Pont was not faking insanity to appear mentally incompetent before his trial for the murder of Olympic champion wrestler David Schultz.</p>
<p>Du Pont, a wrestling enthusiast, built an Olympic-scale training centre on his estate, Foxcatcher Farm and hired Schultz to be his coach. Schultz was shot dead in January.</p>
<p>Two defence psychiatrists said du Pont, 58, was psychotic months and probably years before Schultz was shot in January.</p>
<p>Dr. Robert Sadoff, a Philadelphia forensic psychiatrist, said du Pont suffered strong delusions, heard &quot;the voice of God,&quot; suspected that any telephone was bugged and repeatedly called himself the Dalai Lama for North America.</p>
<p>Sadoff dismissed the idea that du Pont was faking insanity and said the jailed heir did not see himself as mentally ill.</p>
<p>He said du Pont feared that an insanity defence would be grounds for stripping him of his wealth. Family members are suing to assume control of his $80-million estate, citing the incompetency proceedings.</p>
<p>The lead defence lawyers withdrew from the case after du Pont accused them of plotting against him with the CIA.</p>
<p>Prosecutors have already decided that du Pont will not face the death penalty for the shooting of Schultz. Du Pont remains in Delaware County Jail after defence lawyers lost an attempt to move him to a psychiatric hospital.</p>
<p>Jail staffers testified that du Pont behaved himself, but several said they had heard him claim to be the Dalai Lama.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEDIA, Pa."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
