<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="22472" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Labour &quot;dictator&quot; Blair takes to campaign trail.</title>
<headline>Labour &quot;dictator&quot; Blair takes to campaign trail.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>British opposition leader Tony Blair took to the campaign trail on Thursday hit by fresh criticism of his leadership style from the left wing of his Labour party.</p>
<p>The latest attack on Blair came from member of parliament Austin Mitchell, who accused him of paying lip service to Labour's rank and file and said the revamped party's policy-making process was no more democratic than North Korea's.</p>
<p>Writing in the New Statesman magazine, Mitchell also praised Blair for being in better tune with the instincts of British voters than were veteran Labour activists-- a reference to New Labour's more centrist swing away from  old-style Socialism.</p>
<p>&quot;So we have a Faustian compact with Tony Blair, on a back me or sack me basis. Tony'll win for us. In return we've put our souls, our party and our dreams in his hands,&quot; Mitchell wrote.</p>
<p>There is little evidence that earlier attacks on Blair over the summer by left-wingers have hurt Labour, which still enjoys a 21-point lead over the ruling Conservatives, according to an opinion poll in The Times newspaper on Thursday.</p>
<p>But Blair's lieutenants, eager to scotch any impression of internal bickering in the run-up to an election no more than nine months away, were quick to portray Mitchell as isolated.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Mitchell has said colourful eccentric things about every Labour leader since he was elected to parliament,&quot; Robin Cook, the party's foreign affairs spokesman, told BBC radio.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course you can find lone voices outside but the significant thing is that Tony Blair has carried the party overwhelmingly in all the major changes that have gone through.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair, who was campaigning in Wales and northwest England, on Wednesday shrugged off personal criticism as trivial and the &quot;flotsam and jetsam&quot; of politics.</p>
<p>Mitchell himself tried to blunt the impact of his article, telling the BBC he did not see Blair as a dictator.</p>
<p>&quot;What I was saying was that Tony Blair is a winner and in touch with the mood of the country. People like Tony Blair and he is going to lead us to victory,&quot; Mitchell said.</p>
<p>But Prime Minister John Major's Conservatives, who must call an election by next May, tried to capitalise on the controversy as evidence of growing splits in Labour ranks.</p>
<p>&quot;When did you hear a Tory backbencher describe John Major as running his party like one of the most extreme dictators in the world today? That's what we have Austin Mitchell saying,&quot; Deputy Prime Minister Michael Heseltine told BBC radio.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
