<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26276" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's Blair sticks to his guns as election looms.</title>
<headline>UK's Blair sticks to his guns as election looms.</headline>
<byline>Alan Wheatley</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British opposition chief Tony Blair said on Sunday he would not abandon his firm leadership style or moderate policies to placate increasingly vocal critics on the left wing of his Labour party.</p>
<p>Returning to the political fray after the summer break, a defiant Blair pledged to lead Labour into the next election offering a middle way between its old-style socialist policies and a ruling Conservative party that he said had grown stale.</p>
<p>&quot;As a country we shouldn't have to chose between a clapped-out Tory party that has failed the country, that has really no fresh ideas or energy to offer Britain, and switching the clock back under Labour.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a different way forward, where we are creating a more just, more fair society but we are also encouraging and rewarding enterprise and initiative. And that's the type of society I think the vast majority of people in Britain want to live in,&quot; Blair told BBC television's &quot;Breakfast with Frost&quot;.</p>
<p>Labour under Blair has carved out a twenty percentage point lead in opinion polls that the Conservatives, in power since 1979, will find it hard to overturn in the eight months before Prime Minister John Major must call a general election.</p>
<p>But a vocal rump of veteran left-wingers is increasingly concerned that Blair has bought popularity by abandoning Labour's ideals and is running the party like a dictator.</p>
<p>Blair was unrepentant, however. He agreed some in the party found change uncomfortable but said only by modernising itself could Labour be fit to lead Britain into the 21st century.</p>
<p>&quot;We can't live on the old ways, just like Britain can't live on its past. We've got a great past as a country but if we're going to have a great future we've got to put behind us some of the traditions of the past.</p>
<p>&quot;And exactly the same way for the Labour party: if you want to address the future you've got to modernise, and even though I will listen, I can't do something that I believe to be wrong,&quot; Blair, who has headed the party for two years, said.</p>
<p>The Labour leader in effect challenged critics who say he ignores others' views to back him or sack him.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't act on some arrogant assumption that I always know best. But in the end leaders have got to lead. We've had six years of weak leadership in this country... I can only lead in the way that I do,&quot; the Labour leader said.</p>
<p>Anticipating a Conservative pre-election onslaught on Labour as a tax and spend party, Blair said he had no plans to raise taxes and he did not believe that &quot;soaking the rich&quot; was the way to tackle unemployment and get people off welfare.</p>
<p>Blair claimed a new survey showed that businessmen, once Labour's implacable foes, were warming to its economic policies.</p>
<p>A Sunday Times poll of the chief executives of 50 leading companies showed 82 percent of them expected higher taxes and more inflation under Labour. But 44 percent said Labour would be no worse at running the economy and 48 percent backed the party's plans for a minimum wage.</p>
<p>Blair, who will step up the charm offensive in London on Wednesday when he launches &quot;Labour's Business Prospectus&quot;, said more and more firms were making financial donations to Labour.</p>
<p>&quot;Increasingly the Labour party is the party of business as well in this country. I think that will be a great breakthrough for Britain. I think it's absolutely appalling if you end up with one party that's supposed to be the party of business and the other party, not,&quot; the Labour leader said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
