<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39122" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British Conservatives pounce on Labour u-turn.</title>
<headline>British Conservatives pounce on Labour u-turn.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's opposition Labour Party, hot favourites to win the next general election, came in for a heavy pounding on Saturday from the ruling Conservatives, who pounced gleefully on the party's about-turn on Scottish policy.</p>
<p>Labour said on Friday that it had changed its mind about holding a second referendum on whether the Scottish parliament it plans to set up if elected should be able to raise taxes.</p>
<p>&quot;This is disarray day,&quot; Deputy Prime Minister Michael Heseltine told a rally of Conservative supporters. &quot;Labour is in cock-up country.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour announced earlier this week that it would hold two referendums before granting the parliament tax-raising powers.</p>
<p>On Friday, though, the party changed its mind and said it would hold only one.</p>
<p>Heseltine, whose party's support languishes at about 15 percent in opinion polls in Scotland, denounced the plans for a tax-raising body as &quot;a recipe for disaster&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It would devastate Scotland,&quot; he said to loud applause. &quot;Scottish prosperity would move south to England and Wales.&quot;</p>
<p>Both Conservatives and Labour have already begun campaigning for the next general election, which must be held by May 1997. Prime Minister John Major has ruled out going to the polls this year.</p>
<p>Labour has an opinion poll lead of around 20 points over the Conservatives, but its biggest rival in Scotland is the Scottish Nationalist Party (SNP), which had 29 percent support in the latest Scottish opinion poll.</p>
<p>SNP leader Alex Salmond said Labour's policy switch showed no one in Scotland could trust the opposition party.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
