<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="57024" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Seaside conferences kick off countdown to election.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Seaside conferences kick off countdown to election.</headline>
<byline>Alan Wheatley</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Can opposition Labour leader Tony Blair recover from policy stumbles over Scotland and trade unions and hang on to his large opinion poll lead?</p>
<p>Or will the &quot;feelgood factor&quot; finally come to Prime Minister John Major's rescue and hand his Conservative party an unprecedented fifth consecutive term in office?</p>
<p>With Britain's election no more than eight months away, the annual round of party conferences starting next week provides an opportunity for both men to rally their troops ahead of what promises to be a bitterly fought campaign.</p>
<p>If the opinion polls are to be believed, only an accident of gigantic proportions can prevent Blair from becoming the first Labour prime minister since 1979.</p>
<p>Like Major, Blair has a deep distrust of polls. After all, they failed to predict the Conservatives' victory in April 1992.</p>
<p>But with Labour enjoying a lead of around 20 percentage points for the past two years, political analysts say it would be equally foolish to ignore the polls' consistent message.</p>
<p>&quot;The assumption that the polls are more likely than not to be wrong is itself not justified by experience. They have a much better rate of prediction than by-elections, let alone mere hunch or guesswork,&quot; William Rees-Mogg said in The Times.</p>
<p>&quot;What they are saying, more or less unanimously, is that there is now a signficant chance of an overwhelming Labour victory,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>An ICM poll had Labour 15 points ahead in their September poll. But the latest monthly Gallup poll in early September put Labour 33 points in front.</p>
<p>This was down just one percentage point, even though the Conservatives reaped extensive publicity in the intervening month from a poster depicting Blair with demonic eyes.</p>
<p>&quot;The Tories are gradually eroding Labour's lead in the Gallup poll but the process is so far proving glacial. It will take an avalanche for them to win next time,&quot; said politics professor Anthony King.</p>
<p>Aides say Major, who has until May to call the election, will use the Conservative conference in the southern resort of Bournemouth to reinforce his main election theme: that Labour's facade of moderation hides dangerous policies, such as a minimum wage, that would derail Britain's economic recovery.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to expose what the Labour Party stands for. What is happening would be put at risk if the policies were changed by change of government,&quot; he said last week.</p>
<p>Major is trailing in large part because of a feeling among voters that it is time for a change after 17 unbroken years of Conservative rule.</p>
<p>But deep divisions within the ruling party over Europe are also to blame, and these could resurface in Bournemouth if Major is isolated at a special European Union summit in Dublin on October 5 -- just two days before the Conservatives gather.</p>
<p>The task facing Blair at Labour's conference, which takes place in the northwestern resort of Blackpool from September 30 to October 4, is two-fold: to erase an impression of disarray left by recent policy-making bungles and to reassure moderate floating voters without alienating traditional Labour leftists.</p>
<p>In the two years since Blair became Labour leader, he has bent the party to his will and seemingly left little to chance in his pursuit of office by ruthlessly concentrating power.</p>
<p>But the image of a disciplined government-in-waiting was badly dented by quick U-turns on the terms of a referendum to approve Labour's plans for a Scottish parliament and by ill-thought out plans to crack down on public sector strikes.</p>
<p>Under the headline &quot;New Labour, new dither,&quot; the Financial Times commented that the party could afford a few gaffes but not at the rate it had been making them recently.</p>
<p>&quot;Labour's confusion will add credence to the claim of its critics that it has been so absorbed with marketing a brand image that it has neglected to think carefully about what was to be put inside the wrappers,&quot; the paper said in an editorial.</p>
<p>A senior member of Blair's front-bench team said the angry response of union leaders to the party's ideas for taming militant unions can only have helped Labour by pointing up to the general public how moderate and responsible it has become.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the task at Blackpool would be to restore discipline and play safe.</p>
<p>&quot;Hopefully we've now put it to bed and learned the lesson that you don't do too much policy this side of the election -- you just say what we want to achieve,&quot; the front-bencher said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
