<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="63141" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Major pins hopes on demon eye ads, friendly press.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Major pins hopes on demon eye ads, friendly press.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Red demonic eyes that stare from advertising billboards across Britain are meant to scare voters out of voting for the opposition Labour party.</p>
<p>They also remind a country preparing for a bruising election campaign of a basic truth of recent British politics: when the ruling Conservatives are in trouble, they turn for support to two trusted allies -- a friendly press and advertising gurus Maurice and Charles Saatchi.</p>
<p>The Saatchi brothers have been producing vote-swinging advertisements for the Conservatives since the 1979 election when Margaret Thatcher swept to power.</p>
<p>Papers such as the top-selling Sun tabloid have reinforced the message, as in 1992 when its polling day headline warned: &quot;If (Labour leader Neil) Kinnock wins today, will the last person to leave Britain please turn out the lights.&quot;</p>
<p>Now, with Labour more than 20 points ahead in opinion polls and eight months at most before a new election, the Conservatives are again pressing into service the Saatchis' genius for influencing undecided electors.</p>
<p>On the surface it has not been a success. When posters appeared showing Labour leader Tony Blair as the possessor of the demon eyes, over the slogan &quot;New Labour, New Danger&quot;, it was not just Blair who cried foul.</p>
<p>Church leaders criticised the ads and the Saatchis earned a mild rebuke from the Advertising Standards Authority.</p>
<p>Labour has hit back with ads of its own saying &quot;Same old Tories, same old lies&quot;, provoking commentators to predict a no-holds-barred campaign when Prime Minister John Major calls the election, probably in April or May next year.</p>
<p>Unbowed, the Conservatives have continued the campaign, with the latest ad showing the demon eyes staring out of an empty purse to ram home the party's insistence that Labour would cripple Britons with huge tax hikes.</p>
<p>The Conservatives, with the support of big business, have traditionally had far more money to spend on advertising than Labour, which gets most of its funds from the trade unions.</p>
<p>Other parties, including the minority Liberal Democrats, have even smaller budgets and only fair-weather media friends. They rely on free, all-channel TV air time given by law to all sizeable parties ahead of elections to put their views across.</p>
<p>At the 1979 election, a Saatchi campaign mocking Labour's economic record, with posters showing a long queue of unemployed over the slogan &quot;Labour isn't working&quot;, was widely seen as influencing the result.</p>
<p>In 1992, their &quot;Labour's Tax Bombshell&quot; campaign helped to reinforce voter unease about Labour's fiscal plans and to bring Major a narrow 21-seat victory against the odds.</p>
<p>Major recognised the Saatchis' contribution last month by naming Maurice as a new member of the upper House of Lords.</p>
<p>Newspapers also claim credit for the Conservatives' remarkable run of four consecutive election victories.</p>
<p>Few experts doubt that, when the chips have been down, the Conservatives have enjoyed a huge advantage over their opponents in selling their message.</p>
<p>Among the national tabloid dailies, the Sun, Daily Mail and Daily Express, as well as London's Evening Standard, traditionally back the Conservatives, with only the Daily Mirror rooting for Labour.</p>
<p>The Daily Telegraph and the Times, among heavyweight dailies, are also pro-Conservatives while the Guardian supports Labour.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the Sun wot won it&quot;, that paper crowed after its trenchant support for the Conservatives before their surprise 1992 election victory.</p>
<p>But this time round, Labour's disadvantage in the media and advertising battle may be less pronounced.</p>
<p>The party's funds are on a more solid footing thanks to an expanding membership and it has recently won unprecedented moral and financial support from Britain's normally staunchly Conservative business world.</p>
<p>Some newspapers which in past elections have given uncritical backing to the Conservatives show signs of either switching sides or at least being more even-handed.</p>
<p>&quot;In this situation, yes, perhaps for the only time in my life, I can imagine the possibility of supporting Mr Blair,&quot; Max Hastings, editor of the Evening Standard, declared in May.</p>
<p>There is also a suspicion that the Express has become less fervent in supporting the Conservatives since its parent company came under the control of Labour peer Lord Clive Hollick, though Hollick has denied influencing the paper's editorial line.</p>
<p>Even the Sun has allowed Blair space to set out his ideas following a much-publicised trip he made to Australia to visit its proprietor, Rupert Murdoch.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
