<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68664" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain's Labour holds poll lead despite rows.</title>
<headline>Britain's Labour holds poll lead despite rows.</headline>
<byline>Paul Mylrea</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's opposition Labour Party is holding onto its opinion poll lead despite rows over whether modernising leader Tony Blair intends to sever its traditional links with the trade unions and distance it from socialism.</p>
<p>The Sunday Times said its new poll showed Labour, fighting to end 17 years of Conservative rule at an election now less than eight months away, was 19 points ahead of the ruling party.</p>
<p>The NOP poll gave Labour 50 points, one down on last month, and the Conservatives 31, an increase of one point. The minority Liberal Democrats had 14 points, one down on last month.</p>
<p>&quot;The Labour lead... is down by two points from last month, but is bang in line with the average of the past four months,&quot; the newspaper said, adding that what it called the &quot;rough couple of weeks&quot; had yet to significantly eat into the lead.</p>
<p>Blair, who has wrenched his party from the left to the political centreground since taking over the helm two years ago, has been battered by media stories accusing him of wanting to ditch &quot;socialism&quot; as a description of the party's beliefs.</p>
<p>The stories also said Blair planned to sever Labour's links with the trade unions, which founded and traditionally funded the party.</p>
<p>Blair, who Conservatives have portrayed with demonic red eyes in a poster campaign designed to paint a Labour government as dangerous, dismissed both stories as groundless.</p>
<p>And the poll showed voters the media stories had failed to turn voters away from Labour. Most voters, while sceptical about whether Labour could cut its ties with the unions, said such a move would not affect their vote.</p>
<p>Most of those polled were also sceptical about the latest claim of the Conservatives' &quot;demon eyes&quot; poster campaign -- that they were 700 pounds better off under the current government and Labour would snatch that money back in taxes.</p>
<p>Only 13 percent believed they were better off at all, while 43 percent said they were worse off and only 27 percent believed the Conservatives would improve their economic lot.</p>
<p>The NOP poll was carried out by interviewing 1,546 adults at 75 sampling points across the country last Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
