<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69142" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Coalition call divides British Liberals.</title>
<headline>Coalition call divides British Liberals.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>BRIGHTON, England 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's minority Liberal Democrats hit rocky pre-election waters on Sunday when one of their 25 legislators suggested they should aim for a coalition government with the opposition Labour Party.</p>
<p>The proposal, by home affairs spokesman Alex Carlile, was immediately attacked by the party's deputy leader Alan Beith, who said this week's annual party conference was &quot;not about cosying up to other parties&quot;.</p>
<p>With a general election due by next May, the Liberal Democratss, Britain's number three party, are hoping to use the conference as a launchpad for their most impressive electoral performance since World War Two.</p>
<p>But the surprise call by Carlile rocked a leadership concentrating on this objective. He told BBC television he foresaw a time when there could be two main parties in Britain.</p>
<p>A conservative party like the one that has run the country since 1979 would confront &quot;a liberal or social democrat or democratic socialist party, and I don't think the terminology matters very much,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;In a country in which the public want greater consensus among political parties, if the Labour Party is prepared to put Liberal Democrat principles into practice...then I would expect Paddy Ashdown to be interested in taking seats in the British government,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Liberal Democrat leader Ashdown has already made clear that if no party has a majority in Parliament after the next election, he would prefer to see a Labour government under moderate Tony Blair than another term of Conservative power.</p>
<p>But, mindful of the need to woo Conservative voters, he has avoided committing the party to seeking a coalition with Labour, a party he condemned as lacking principle on Sunday.</p>
<p>Beith insisted that the conference should focus on how to maximise the party's performance at the election.</p>
<p>&quot;All our effort is concentrated on winning the political power to gain for the people of this country...the things we put before them in the election campaign. That is what the conference is about,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Liberal Democrats, meeting in the southern resort of Brighton, are the first of the three main parties to hold pre- election conferences in successive weeks.</p>
<p>Following abysmal Conservative performances since the 1992 general election, the Liberals are now Britain's second party of local government behind Labour.</p>
<p>But their prospects at national level are bleaker, and they currently stand at just 14 percent in the opinion polls, against their 18 percent of the vote at the 1992 election.</p>
<p>At best, say political pundits, the party could win 30 to 40 seats in the 659-member House of Commons.</p>
<p>Ashdown, asked on BBC television about his ambitions for the election, replied: &quot;As many seats as we can get and as many Liberal Democrat votes as we can achieve across the country.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour are about 20 points ahead of the Conservatives in the polls -- a position in which they hardly need to contemplate the possibility of a coalition with the Liberals.</p>
<p>Ashdown praised Blair for his jettisoning of socialist policies that used to be sacred to Labour, but questioned whether he had found ideals to replace them.</p>
<p>&quot;What do they believe in? How deep does the Blair revolution go? People don't ask these sort of questions abiut the Liberal Democrats,&quot; he told interviewer David Frost.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRIGHTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
