<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69164" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British Liberals prepare for election battle.</title>
<headline>British Liberals prepare for election battle.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>BRIGHTON, England 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The curtain went up on Sunday on Britain's most crucial party conference season for years when Liberal Democrat activists arrived in the southern resort of Brighton to set out their general election wares.</p>
<p>But political observers questioned whether the annual gathering of Britain's third party represents Act One of the main political drama, or a show on the fringe.</p>
<p>For while the Labour opposition and ruling Conservatives hope to use their conferences in the following two weeks as launchpads for an election victory next April or May, the Liberals aspire merely to influence in the next parliament.</p>
<p>At best, say political pundits, the party could win 30-40 seats in the 659-member House of Commons, and find itself the junior partner in a coalition with Labour, which would be the first non-Conservative government in Britain since 1979.</p>
<p>Party leader Paddy Ashdown, asked on BBC television about his ambitions for the election, replied: &quot;As many seats as we can get and as many Liberal Democrat votes as we can achieve across the country.&quot;</p>
<p>The Liberals, who struggle against a British electoral system which benefits their bigger rivals, at present hold 25 parliamentary seats -- comparative luxury for a party which almost disappeared from the House of Commons in the 1950s.</p>
<p>Yet although, following abysmal Conservative performances since the 1992 general election, they are now the second party in local government, their hopes for a breakthrough in national politics could be thwarted by the &quot;Blair factor&quot;.</p>
<p>In making his party favourite to win the forthcoming election -- it leads the Conservatives by 20 points in the polls -- moderate leader Tony Blair has stolen Liberal clothes.</p>
<p>Labour has adopted constitutional reforms such as a bill of rights which were once the smaller party's trade mark, and has moved much closer to the Liberals' pro-European stance.</p>
<p>But Ashdown said electors would have to ask themselves what Labour now stood for after Blair had ditched so many of its traditional socialist beliefs.</p>
<p>&quot;What do they believe in? How deep does the Blair revolution go? People don't ask these sort of questions about the Liberal Democrats,&quot; he told interviewer David Frost.</p>
<p>The narrowing of differences between Labour and the Liberals has pushed the smaller party down to around 14 percent in the polls from 18 percent at the 1992 general election.</p>
<p>They are trying to fight back by being bolder than Labour -- daring for example to contemplate raising taxes to pay for higher spending on education.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to confront issues instead of dodging them. The notion is, for a third party in our position, an important one,&quot; said Lord Richard Holme, the party's election supremo.</p>
<p>The party's successes in local elections in recent years is buoying the spirits of activists gathering in Brighton.</p>
<p>If they can win parliamentary seats where they run local councils, the breakthrough will, they say, be assured.</p>
<p>But the Liberals' opponents are dismissive, saying even many of the people who vote Liberal reject key party policies such as its support for a single European currency.</p>
<p>Conservative Party chairman Brian Mawhinney called a news conference last week to denounce the Liberals as &quot;a radical left-wing party committed to threatening policies&quot;.</p>
<p>A party spokeswoman was undisturbed. &quot;Once they would have ignored us,&quot; she said. &quot;Now they see us as a threat.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRIGHTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
