<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71111" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK Liberal boss sees tie with Labour possible.</title>
<headline>UK Liberal boss sees tie with Labour possible.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>BRIGHTON, England 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of Britain's minority Liberal Democrats, who could hold the balance of power after elections next year, said on Monday a centre-left coalition with the Labour party was possible but unlikely.</p>
<p>&quot;All options are open,&quot; Paddy Ashdown told BBC radio in the southern resort of Brighton where his party is holding its pre-election annual conference.</p>
<p>Opinion polls give Labour, led by Tony Blair, a better-than-ever chance of ousting the ruling Conservatives of Prime Minister John Major in a general election which must be held by next May.</p>
<p>Speculation was rife at the Liberals' conference about the possibility of an Ashdown-Blair alliance which could produce the first two-party government in Britain since World war Two if Labour failed to win an overall majority at the election.</p>
<p>Ashdown's venture into controversial conjecture about a post-election deal was prompted by a surprise intervention on the issue from one of his 25 members of parliament on Sunday.</p>
<p>Alex Carlile said he could see the day when Labour and the Liberals might merge to form a centre-left party to confront the Conservatives, and urged Ashdown to take a cabinet seat if Blair offered him one.</p>
<p>Ashdown was asked by a BBC interviewer whether he accepted this suggestion.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing is ruled in, nothing is ruled out,&quot; he replied. &quot;Is it possible we will do what you suggest? Yes. Is it likely viewed from the moment? No.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair has moved Labour away from many of its old socialist stances, winning converts who have given it a 20 point lead over the Conservatives in opinion polls.</p>
<p>His success has also trimmed support for the Liberals, who currently stand at about 14 percent in the polls. However, impressive successes in local government ballots since the 1992 general election have raised Liberal optimism.</p>
<p>Labour's lead would have to narrow dramatically and the Liberal showing improve before a hung parliament, in which no party holds an overall majority, became a likelihood.</p>
<p>Labour's chief parliamentary business manager, asked by BBC radio about Ashdown's musings on the possibility of coalition, said: &quot;We will cross that bridge if we come to it. We don't anticipate being in that situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Ashdown praised Blair for changing some of his party's policies, but said the transformation was far from complete.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Blair is moving his party on to our ground, using our language. The more he does that, the more he validates our programme, but they have a long, long, long way to go.&quot;</p>
<p>An opinion poll commissioned by the Daily Mirror newspaper showed on Monday that more a third of Britons would like to see a Liberal-Labour coalition if Labour did not win an overall majority in parliament.</p>
<p>Another 25 percent favoured the two parties agreeing a programme of legislation without Liberals actually entering the government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRIGHTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
