<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73371" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scottish firms oppose Labour's planned parliament.</title>
<headline>Scottish firms oppose Labour's planned parliament.</headline>
<byline>Karen Iley</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The separate Scottish parliament planned by the opposition Labour Party would damage companies operating in Scotland and deter others from setting up there, according to firms polled by Reuters.</p>
<p>A Scottish parliament with tax-raising powers would definitely have a detrimental effect on business, they said, but factors other than tax could also hamper the success of firms operating north of the border.</p>
<p>The poll surveyed 12 companies operating in Scotland between September 17 and 20.</p>
<p>All 12 of the companies surveyed stated that a Scottish parliament with tax-raising powers would harm Scottish business in the short term, but this number was halved if the parliament had no authority to levy taxes.</p>
<p>Labour, ahead in opinion polls, plans to set up a Scottish parliament if it wins the next election, but only if the Scottish people back an assembly with tax-raising powers in a referendum.</p>
<p>Scottish businesses are worried that an increase in taxes north of the border would deter investors and make them more inclined to site their operations in other parts of Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;A very large part of Scottish development in the last five years has been inward investment. An extra two or three pence in the pound in Scotland would simply swing the pendulum the wrong way,&quot; said one company spokesman.</p>
<p>&quot;Paying more tax would reduce the ability to invest and would certainly make us less competitive against England, which doesn't seem to make any sense at all,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>However, one respondent said a tax increase was not guaranteed under a separate Scottish parliament, and he felt devolution could benefit Scottish business because &quot;most Scots would like to see some form of parliament. It would give Scotland renewed confidence in their own destiny&quot;.</p>
<p>While tax is the main gripe for the majority of companies, other factors such as uncertainty, inconvenience and bureaucracy were also cited as reasons for opposing Labour's plans.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
