<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74777" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British Liberals hesitate to flirt with Labour.</title>
<headline>British Liberals hesitate to flirt with Labour.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>BRIGHTON, England 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Activists in Britain's minority Liberal Democrat party are coming round to the idea they might have to enter a coalition with Labour after the next election.</p>
<p>But they do not relish the prospect and say they would not trust Labour leader Tony Blair to honour his side of any deal on power-sharing.</p>
<p>&quot;You never trust the buggers. You deal with them, you strike deals, but you stand over them all the time and see that they honour those deals,&quot; veteran councillor Tony Greaves told a fringe meeting at the party's annual conference on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Blair has repudiated his party's socialist past, steering it to the centre ground traditionally occupied by the Liberals, recruiting some 250,000 new party members and giving Labour a 20 point lead in the opinion polls.</p>
<p>The transformation prompted some senior Liberal Democrats to utter warm words this week about possible cooperation.</p>
<p>Member of parliament Alex Carlile said if Blair offered Liberal leader Paddy Ashdown a cabinet seat, he should take it. Elder statesman Lord Bill Rodgers even suggested Liberals might vote Labour in seats where their own party had no chance.</p>
<p>But according to inner city councillors, whose principal local opponents are Labour, the only circumstances in which the party should consider &quot;getting into bed with Labour&quot; is if an election due in eight months led to a so-called hung parliament, where no party wins an overall majority.</p>
<p>Greaves said if Liberal Democrat members joined a government in which Labour had a majority &quot;it would split the party&quot;.</p>
<p>Other activists argued that if Labour had no overall majority, Liberals should give them general, but not total, support without joining them in government.</p>
<p>&quot;The Liberal Democrats could sustain a Labour government in office, but only on issue-by-issue support, and by retaining their own status outside government as an independent party,&quot; the party's radical Liberator monthly said in an editorial.</p>
<p>The Liberals stand at about 14 percent in opinion polls, but activists hope the election will give the party several new MPs to add to the 25 seats it has in the 651-member House of Commons. Labour's support stands at more than 50 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRIGHTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
