<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77381" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scottish Nationalists say &quot;we can pay our way&quot;.</title>
<headline>Scottish Nationalists say &quot;we can pay our way&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>INVERNESS, Scotland 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scottish nationalists insisted on Thursday an independent Scotland would be more than able to pay its own way and presented their plans for economic development.</p>
<p>A document published by the Scottish National Party (SNP) at its annual conference in Inverness said Scotland would be the 21st richest country in the world if it escaped from  union with the rest of Britain.</p>
<p>It outlined an economic strategy designed boost industry and jobs by cutting taxes -- including Britain's &quot;unfair&quot; level of tax on the national drink, whisky.</p>
<p>&quot;Scotland is a wealthy country, richer than New Zealand, Finland and Iceland -- small countries which are prosperous and more than pay their way in the world,&quot;, the SNP said in its publication, the Economic Case for Independence.</p>
<p>The party said its economic priorities would be to reach full employment, invest in education and training, build a modern infrastructure, develop industry and reform taxation.</p>
<p>The SNP is in bullish mood at what will be its final annual conference before the next British general election, which Prime Minister John Major must call by the end of next May.</p>
<p>&quot;We are subsidised by nobody -- the revenues from our country are used to prop up the ailing UK economy,&quot; SNP leader Alex Salmond told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;We are constrained by policies which are inappropriate for Scotland and directly harm our people and prosperity.&quot;</p>
<p>SNP Treasury spokesman John Swinney accused the ruling Conservatives and the opposition Labour party of indulging in &quot;scaremongering&quot; against Scotland and its case for independence.</p>
<p>The SNP said Conservative figures which showed that Scotland received an annual subsidy from the United Kingdom amounting to eight billion pounds ($12 billion) were &quot;dishonest&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Far from being subsidised by eight billion pounds, Scotland pays 400 million pounds ($600 million) to stay in the Union...a price not worth paying,&quot; the SNP document said.</p>
<p>It said government figures failed to take into account Scotland's share of the overall British public deficit, revenues from North Sea oil and gas as well as privatisation proceeds.</p>
<p>Scottish income tax contributions were underestimated and Scotland's receipt of defence expenditures were overestimated.</p>
<p>Official figures from the Scottish Office, however, show government spending per head in Scotland at 5,553 pounds ($8,655) in 1993/94 compared with 4,871 pounds ($7,592) for Britain as a whole.</p>
<p>A series of near-farcical reverses in Scottish policy by Labour -- the biggest party in Scotland -- has seen support for the SNP, which has four legislators in the British parliament, rise to 29 percent.</p>
<p>Labour, riding high in British opinion polls, wants to hold a referendum on a devolved parliament for Scotland if it wins the next general election.</p>
<p>Senior figures in the Conservative government have derided SNP economic proposals for independence as lacking any grasp of reality. The SNP said that independent analysis of its programme showed employment would grow by more than 100,000 in the first four years after independence.</p>
<p>The party forecast annual inflation at around 3.4 percent in the same four year period and predicted: &quot;The Scottish economy will throw off the deadening influence of the Union to achieve sustained low inflation growth and higher employment.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INVERNESS, Scotland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
