<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77907" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scotland's Nationalists say &quot;we can pay our way&quot;.</title>
<headline>Scotland's Nationalists say &quot;we can pay our way&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>INVERNESS, Scotland 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scottish nationalists insisted on Thursday that an independent Scotland would become a tiger economy, dismissing as a &quot;myth&quot; suggestions that their country depended on British subsidies.</p>
<p>But economic debate at the Scottish National Party's annual conference was blown off course after a top party official compared the opposition Labour Party's Scottish affairs spokesman to a World War Two Nazi propagandist.</p>
<p>Labour is the SNP's principle enemy in Scotland, where the nationalists accuse it of standing in the way of independence.</p>
<p>But the jibe about wartime traitor William Joyce, better known as the Nazi propaganda broadcaster Lord Haw Haw, distracted attention from the SNP's drive to hammer home its economic message.</p>
<p>&quot;We in Scotland have a new Lord Haw Haw and his name is George Robertson,&quot; said SNP policymaker Alex Neil, who accused Robertson of seeking to sap the morale of the Scottish people.</p>
<p>An angry Alex Salmond, the SNP leader, said he would be talking to Neil later. Neil accused the media of &quot;mischief making&quot;, while Robertson spoke later of SNP &quot;desperation&quot;.</p>
<p>The SNP is in bullish mood at what will be its final annual conference before the British general election, which Prime Minister John Major must call by the end of next May.</p>
<p>A series of near farcical reverses in Scottish policy by the opposition Labour Party, which wants a Scottish assembly but stops short of independence, has seen support for the SNP, which has four MPs in the British parliament, rise to 29 percent.</p>
<p>After his attack on Robertson, Neil insisted that independence was a prerequisite for economic lift-off in Scotland. &quot;Scotland could be the tiger economy of Western Europe,&quot; he said in a reference to the growth economies of Asia.</p>
<p>An SNP document launched at the conference said an independent Scotland would be the world's 21st richest country.</p>
<p>The SNP document outlines an economic strategy designed to cut taxes and boost industry and jobs. Its goals included full employment, investment in training, infrastructure and industry together with tax reform to increase business competitiveness.</p>
<p>Current &quot;unfair&quot; taxes on whisky would be cut.</p>
<p>&quot;Scotland is a wealthy country, richer than New Zealand, Finland and Iceland -- small countries which are prosperous and more than pay their way in the world,&quot; the SNP said in its publication, the Economic Case for Independence.</p>
<p>The SNP said Conservative figures which showed Scotland received an annual subsidy from the United Kingdom amounting to eight billion pounds ($12.47 billion) were &quot;dishonest&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Far from being subsidised by eight billion pounds, Scotland pays 400 million pounds to stay in the Union -- the price of the Union -- a price not worth paying,&quot; the SNP said.</p>
<p>The SNP said the government's figures ignored Scotland's share of the British public deficit, North Sea oil and gas revenues and Scotland's share of privatisations.</p>
<p>The figures also underestimated Scottish income tax contributions and overstated the amount of defence spending received by Scotland, the SNP said.</p>
<p>Official figures from the Scottish Office, however, show government spending per head in Scotland at 5,553 pounds ($8,655) in 1993/94 compared with 4,871 pounds for Britain as a whole.</p>
<p>Senior figures in the Conservative government have derided SNP economic proposals for independence as unrealistic. ($1=.6416 Pound)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INVERNESS, Scotland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
