<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79949" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Labour's Blair leads, but is party behind him?.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Labour's Blair leads, but is party behind him?.</headline>
<byline>Paul Mylrea</byline>
<dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>His &quot;demon&quot; eyes stare from posters across Britain, courtesy of John Major's Conservatives.</p>
<p>The ruling party, battling to hold on to power after 17 years in office, are portraying Labour leader Tony Blair as a bogeyman, eager to endanger the country's economic recovery.</p>
<p>Ironically, the Conservatives' slogan &quot;New Labour, New Danger&quot; has struck more of a chord with left-wing Labour supporters than with wavering voters.</p>
<p>With Blair up to 20 points ahead in opinion polls, few are prepared to rock the Labour boat openly before the election due before May 1997.</p>
<p>But the whisperings of discontent at Blair's discarding of Labour's socialist dogma surface almost daily in the press, hurting the party more than any external attack.</p>
<p>&quot;A major western political party has fallen into the hands of someone with a background not from that party,&quot; said Labour party activist Tony Coello after reports that Blair was now considering easing party links with the unions.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of people are disappointed.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair, a high-powered lawyer with little in common with the party's working-class roots, has ditched old-style socialism for a platform designed to appeal to business and the middle class.</p>
<p>Old ideas such as universal welfare and the redistribution of wealth through tax are near-heresy in New Labour, replaced with work programmes for the unemployed and praise for entrepreneurs.</p>
<p>Many traditional Labour voters are bemused by the speed of change. &quot;Whether the leadership has got it right...I just don't know,&quot; said Malcolm Speake, a Labour councillor in the central English city of Birmingham, once the heart of Britain's industrial powerhouse but now struggling to come to terms with structural change.</p>
<p>Most of the open dissent has come from within the team who will form Blair's government, known as the shadow cabinet.</p>
<p>Under party rules, the top posts go to people voted for by Labour members of parliament, a system which burdens Blair with people selected for their skill at winning support from internal party factions rather than aptitude for government.</p>
<p>In time, Blair has indicated he will ditch this system, too.</p>
<p>But for now, saddled with people unhappy with his low tax platform -- like veteran Clare Short, who represents a swathe of inner-city Birmingham -- he has simply shuffled them into low key jobs. Short, for example, is now in charge of overseas aid.</p>
<p>Add in a press traditionally pro-Conservative and the hothouse atmosphere of parliament where MPs and journalists rub shoulders and trade gossip detached from the real world, and you have fertile ground for stories of dissent.</p>
<p>Blair is seeking to outflank the parliamentary party by balloting members on Labour's draft manifesto for the election.</p>
<p>Blair has dubbed it the &quot;contract with the people&quot; -- in a brazen copy of the Republican party's &quot;Contract with America&quot; campaign which swept them to control of Congress.</p>
<p>But members will have to accept or reject the draft as it stands, with no chance of changing it. Faced with this choice, some members will give their backing -- with bad grace.</p>
<p>&quot;No matter how people grit their teeth, there will be a healthy vote of endorsement to the leadership,&quot; Coello said. &quot;People are biting their lip, they don't want to be blamed for defeat.&quot;</p>
<p>Political analysts say this attitude could return to haunt Blair after the election.</p>
<p>A report last month by researchers at Hull University suggested that Blair could face regular defeat in parliament from his own left-wingers if he has less than a 60-seat majority in the 651-strong House of Commons.</p>
<p>Advisers to Blair dismiss such studies, arguing that older, traditional Labour MPs are stepping down and the new intake is likely to be very pro-Blair. Activists also dismiss the dissent, pointing to a huge surge in new members since Blair took over.</p>
<p>&quot;The press are trying to build up dissension,&quot; said Cecily Gale, another activist in the Edgbaston area of Birmingham.</p>
<p>&quot;It's been a real culture change and the influx of new members is extremely high,&quot; she told Reuters. &quot;People realise we can't go back to the 1970s...Instead, people are looking ahead at what's going to happen at the end of the 1990s and in 2000.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair retains an unshaken confidence that he has taken the right road, one he believes most members will follow him down.</p>
<p>In a tantalising glimpse of his post-election plans, Blair has hinted that he is determined not to be halted by internal dissent, even if this means ditching the left and forging some kind of alliance with the minority Liberal Democratss.</p>
<p>Blair used an interview in the Observer newspaper this month to minimise the distance between Labour and the Liberals.</p>
<p>In a clear threat that he could seek backing from the Liberals if left-wing rebels in his own party make governing difficult, Blair said: &quot;New Labour has the chance to build a genuine radical movement of the centre and centre-left for the future.&quot;</p>
<p>Left-wingers would be left isolated or forced out. A natural home would be the breakaway Socialist Labour Party set up by firebrand miners' leader Arthur Scargill after he quit Labour in protest at what he called Blair's betrayal of state ownership.</p>
<p>Blair's aides were quietly delighted at Scargill's departure, seeing it as reinforcing the party leader's message that he had distanced himself from old policies linked inextricably in voters' minds to the industrial strife of the 1970s.</p>
<p>For any traditionalists who still believe Blair will eventually be forced to trim his reforming zeal by pressure from within the party, Blair delivered an uncompromising message.</p>
<p>&quot;In the brutal game of tactics, we shall continue to do what is necessary to win, because without winning, radical politics will never happen at all,&quot; he told the Observer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIRMINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
