<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80922" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scottish nationalists aim to break British power.</title>
<headline>Scottish nationalists aim to break British power.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>INVERNESS, Scotland 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scottish nationalist leader Alex Salmond said on Friday an independent Scotland could become the economic &quot;tiger&quot; of Europe and called on members to break the power of the British state over their country.</p>
<p>The Scottish National Party (SNP) chief said Scotland would only flourish &quot;when it ruled itself and took part in the counsels of the world&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Our objective is to break the power of the state of the United Kingdom over the Scottish people,&quot; Salmond told the party's last annual conference before a general election that must be called by next May.</p>
<p>He called on Scots &quot;to rise and be a nation again&quot;.</p>
<p>The SNP, which espouses purely peaceful, political methods, is in buoyant mood, with opinion poll support boosted to at least 29 percent by a series of Scottish policy gaffes by the opposition Labour Party, the biggest party in Scotland.</p>
<p>The SNP have four members of the British parliament, and will need a big swing to boost that number significantly because of the British &quot;first-past-the-post&quot; voting system.</p>
<p>Salmond said in a statement released before his keynote speech that on current growth levels Ireland would become more porsperous than Britain by the year 2000.</p>
<p>Ireland currently boasts the highest growth rate in the european union of around seven per cent per annum.</p>
<p>&quot;But compared to Scotland, Ireland has next to no resources,&quot; Salmond wrote. &quot;They have used their imagination and human resources in order to drive their economy forward.</p>
<p>&quot;With the freedom of independence, Scotland could combine our own talents with the nation's abundant resources, and make Scotland the &quot;tiger economy&quot; of Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>Salmond devoted a large part of his speech to the SNP faithful, meeting in the Highland capital Inverness, to knocking his opponents. &quot;You couldn't place a cigarette paper between their policies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Salmond said the Conservative government in London was responsible for the mishandling of the crisis over mad cow disease, asserting that &quot;the livelihoods of our rural communities have been sacrificed and jeopardised to Tory (Conservative) Party internal politics&quot;.</p>
<p>Labour, which has in recent months come up with a series of contradictory statements on a possible Scottish parliament, were no more than &quot;tartan Tories&quot; who could not be trusted with the Scottish constitution.</p>
<p>Salmond based his forecast of Scotland's prospects as a European &quot;tiger&quot; -- a reference to the small but dynamic &quot;tiger economies&quot; of Asia -- on research carried out for the party by the House of Commons library in London.</p>
<p>It said that Irish gross domestic product per head was projected &quot;to have exceeded that of Wales in 1995 and will exceed that of Scotland, and the UK as a whole, by the year 2000&quot;, provided Ireland maintained recent high growth rates.</p>
<p>The SNP maintains that an independent Scotland would be the 21st richest country in the world.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INVERNESS, Scotland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
