<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82085" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scotland could be &quot;tiger&quot; of Europe - nationalists.</title>
<headline>Scotland could be &quot;tiger&quot; of Europe - nationalists.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>INVERNESS, Scotland 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of the Scottish National Party (SNP) said on Friday that an independent Scotland could become the economic &quot;tiger&quot; of Europe and cited the growth rates now seen in Ireland.</p>
<p>SNP chief Alex Salmond, who was delivering a keynote speech to the party's annual conference in Inverness later on Friday, said Ireland would in three years' time be more prosperous per head of population than England.</p>
<p>&quot;On current growth levels, Ireland will become more prosperous than the UK and Scotland by the year 2000. They have already overtaken the Welsh,&quot; Salmond said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;But compared to Scotland, Ireland has next to no resources. They have used their imagination and human resources in order to drive their economy forward.</p>
<p>&quot;With the freedom of independence, Scotland could combine our own talents with the nation's abundant resources, and make Scotland the 'tiger economy' of Europe,&quot; Salmond said.</p>
<p>Salmond based his forecast on research carried out for the party by the House of Commons library in London.</p>
<p>This concluded that Irish gross domestic product per head was projected &quot;to have exceeded that of Wales in 1995 and will exceed that of Scotland, and the UK as a whole, by the year 2000&quot;, provided Ireland maintained its recent high growth rates.</p>
<p>The SNP maintains that an independent Scotland would be the 21st richest country in the world. Some economists think Salmond's forecasts for the Irish economy are several years too optimistic.</p>
<p>The SNP, holding its last annual conference before a general election that must be held by next May, are enjoying strong support of 29 percent at the polls, largely due to a series of Scottish policy gaffes by Labour, their main rivals.</p>
<p>But the party was still struggling to contain the crisis that erupted after a senior party figure compared the opposition Labour party's Scottish affairs spokesman to a World War Two Nazi collaborator.</p>
<p>SNP deputy policy chief Alex Neil used a podium speech to liken Labour's Scottish spokesman George Robertson to Lord Haw Haw, the Nazi broadcaster who was hanged for treason in 1946.</p>
<p>Labour called for Neil to resign, and under pressure from the SNP leadership he apologised for any personal slight to Robertson.</p>
<p>Margaret Ewing, an SNP member of the British parliament, sought to play down the gaffe, accusing the media of looking for splits in party ranks. She described Neil's remarks as &quot;a joke that maybe misfired&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INVERNESS, Scotland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
