<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82519" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Nationalists say Scots economy could match Ireland.</title>
<headline>Nationalists say Scots economy could match Ireland.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>INVERNESS, Scotland 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of the Scottish nationalists said on Friday that an independent Scotland could by the end of the century match the strong economic growth rates now being seen in Ireland.</p>
<p>But the Scottish National Party was still struggling to contain the crisis that erupted after a senior party figure compared the opposition Labour Party's Scottish affairs spokesman to the World War Two Nazi collaborator Lord Haw Haw.</p>
<p>The damaging row diverted media attention from attempts by the party to present a reasoned economic case for Scottish independence.</p>
<p>SNP leader Alex Salmond, who delivers a keynote speech to the party's annual conference in the Highland capital of Inverness later on Friday, said Ireland would in three years' time be more prosperous than England.</p>
<p>An independent Scotland, shorn of the shackles of being part of Britain, could match this, he asserted.</p>
<p>&quot;On the millennium, Ireland will be more prosperous than England,&quot; Salmond said on BBC Radio Scotland.</p>
<p>The SNP maintains that an independent Scotland would be the 21st richest country in the world. Some economists think Salmond's forecasts for the Irish economy are several years too optimistic.</p>
<p>The SNP, holding their last annual conference before a general election that must be held by next May, are enjoying strong support of 29 percent at the polls, largely due to a series of Scottish policy gaffes by Labour, their main enemies.</p>
<p>SNP deputy policy chief Alex Neil caused a storm on Thursday when he used a podium speech to compare Labour's Scottish spokesman George Robertson to Lord Haw Haw, the Nazi propaganda broadcaster who was hanged for treason in 1946.</p>
<p>Labour called for Neil to resign, and under pressure from the SNP leadership he apologised.</p>
<p>Margaret Ewing, an SNP member of the British parliament, sought to play down the gaffe, accusing the media of looking for splits in party ranks. She described Neil's remarks as &quot;a joke that maybe misfired&quot;.</p>
<p>Neil himself maintained he was justified in launching a political attack on Robertson. &quot;If George has taken the particular analogy as a personal insult, then I apologise. It's not meant on a personal basis, it's a political comment.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INVERNESS, Scotland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
