<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14196" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Romania govt blasted for neglecting AIDS children.</title>
<headline>Romania govt blasted for neglecting AIDS children.</headline>
<byline>Karin Popescu</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Romanian health workers on Monday blasted their government for relying on foreign help to care for thousands of neglected children suffering from AIDS.</p>
<p>&quot;Romania has 54 percent of Europe's juvenile AIDS cases, but the health ministry and government are totally indifferent and ignore these poor souls, who are running out of time,&quot; said Manuela Canepescu of International Children's Services.</p>
<p>Thousands of Romanian children were infected with the HIV-virus that leads to AIDS (Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome) by contaminated blood and poor hospital hygiene during the last years of communism.</p>
<p>&quot;Romanian society bears responsibility for infecting 98 percent of more than 3,500 children with HIV through injections and transfusions between 1986 and 1989,&quot; said Canepescu, a Romanian official working for a British charity.</p>
<p>&quot;All that was done so far from the social point of view was done by foreign charities, with funds from abroad. It is time for Romanians to deal with the problem,&quot; Canepescu told a news conference. Some 1,250 children have died of AIDS already.</p>
<p>Revolution and the execution of Stalinist dictator Nicolae Ceausecu in 1989 ended the taboo on discussing AIDS and lifted the lid on the horrendous state of Romanian healthcare.</p>
<p>Harrowing television images of abandoned children slowly dying from AIDS in Romanian orphanages stunned the world and foreign medical charities rushed to provide care.</p>
<p>Money poured in as charities like the &quot;Romanian Angel Appeal&quot; set up in 1990 by the wives of the Beatles and Elton John helped renovate squalid buildings housing AIDS children in Bucharest and the Black Sea port city of Constanta.</p>
<p>Volunteers from abroad continue to help local Romanian charities provide rudimentary treatment for infected children.</p>
<p>Health ministry assistance has never gone beyond promises, say careworkers, who blame poor management and not the country's poverty for their lack of funds.</p>
<p>The leftist government has failed to initiate programmes to prevent the spread of HIV and AIDS or to set up adequate social services, they add.</p>
<p>&quot;In Constanta, where we have more than 1,000 cases of child AIDS and 70 adults, there is not one government care worker specialising in AIDS,&quot; Canepescu said.</p>
<p>Those infected face ostracism from a society that still does not properly understand how the disease spreads.</p>
<p>Doctor Rodica Matusa, head of the Constanta hospital, which has the largest childrens' AIDS clinic in Romania, urged the health authorities to change laws which she said &quot;mocked those people who are not guilty of causing their disease.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;To oblige a person with HIV or AIDS to renew their medical certificate every year to confirm the disease and get a ridiculous 20,000 lei ($6) a month for food is too much to ask of these poor people,&quot; Matusa said.</p>
<p>Foreign charity workers backed the assessment of their Romanian counterparts. While local health workers no longer dismiss AIDS children as a lost cause the government has not yet abandoned that attitude, they say.</p>
<p>The government last week sacked Health Minister Iulian Mincu, formerly the personal doctor of Ceausescu, who was heavily criticised by local doctors for slowing down reforms, squandering foreign aid and mismanagement of resources.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
