<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17360" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli bulldozer destroys Jerusalem Arab project.</title>
<headline>Israeli bulldozer destroys Jerusalem Arab project.</headline>
<byline>Sami Aboudi</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel hoisted a bulldozer over the walls of Jerusalem's Old City at dawn on Tuesday and destroyed an Arab building, reigniting the battle for land between Arab and Jew.</p>
<p>Palestinians called a two-hour general strike and marched in protest against the demolition of the incomplete building, intended as a centre for the handicapped, and which the Israeli Municipality of Jerusalem said was being constructed without a permit.</p>
<p>&quot;This building was intended to serve Palestinians in the Old City and posed no threat to the Israelis,&quot; Palestinian Legislative Council member Ahmed Hashem Zighayer told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a war that has been declared on us and we want our people to come and see the site where they declared the war,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Arab residents said Israeli police closed off the area of Burj al-Laqlaq neighbourhood as a crane lifted a bulldozer over the city walls when most people were still asleep.</p>
<p>The bulldozer, which was too big to have entered through the city's gates, flattened the building.</p>
<p>Palestinian lawmakers said the demolition was the latest sign of a tougher Israeli policy towards the city's 165,000 Arabs since the right-wing government of Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu won office in May.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear that the policy of the Likud government is to kill the peace process. The demolition of this building today is but an example of this policy,&quot; Palestinian Legislative Council member Ahmed al-Batsh said at the scene.</p>
<p>Palestinian President Yasser Arafat summoned foreign diplomats to convey what the Palestinian News Agency WAFA said was his deep concern over Israel's practices in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>&quot;These attempts and measures are a part of a premeditated policy to Judaise Arab Jerusalem, to empty... its inhabitants and to encourage settlement building inside Jerusalem's neighbourhoods,&quot; WAFA quoted Arafat as saying.</p>
<p>Palestinian cabinet members Hanan Ashrawi and Hassan Tahboub and Legislative Council President Ahmed Korei led a march of about 100 people from the demolition site through the Old City.</p>
<p>Korei, better known as Abu Alaa, who negotiated the 1993 Israel-PLO self-rule deal said Palestinians wanted to know &quot;if this is peace or a cover for continuing the occupation...This is peace by a bulldozer and by a tank.&quot;</p>
<p>The demolition came a day after the PLO bowed to Netanyahu's demand to close Palestinian offices in Jerusalem. Netanyahu made the closure of the three offices a condition for resuming peace negotiations with the Palestine Liberation Organisation (PLO).</p>
<p>Palestinians accuse Netanyahu of delaying the implementation of the self-rule accord with Arafat's Palestinian Authority in order to secure better terms on sensitive issues such the Jewish presence in Hebron and East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>&quot;The building destroyed in the Old City was unoccupied. It was destroyed because it was built without a permit just as all buildings built without a permit are,&quot; a municipality spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Israeli police said the building was funded by the Palestinian Authority for use as a social club.</p>
<p>Hayel Sandouka, president of the al-Laqlaq Tower Centre, a charitable organisation helping Palestinians in the Old City, denied this. He said building was funded by private charities including organisations from Canada and Sweden.</p>
<p>He said the 150 square metre (1,600 square feet) building was part of a large project that would include a handicapped centre, a home for the elderly and a kindergarten.</p>
<p>Palestinians regard East Jerusalem as the capital of a future state. The fate of Jerusalem is to be negotiated during talks on the final status of Arab lands Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
