<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="32400" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: MEPs want support for local job-creation schemes.</title>
<headline>MEPs want support for local job-creation schemes.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>There is huge potential for creating jobs through small-scale local initiatives in the service sector which the European Union could do much to promote, MEPs are expected to say on September 5.</p>
<p>The European Commission has identified 17 areas where the demand for services currently outstrips supply, ranging from home help, child care and public transport to security services, tourism and environmental management.</p>
<p>However, it acknowledges that this job-creating potential will not be fully realised without some active encouragement and is considering a European strategy to do just that, COM(95)273.</p>
<p>In a report which is due to be approved by MEPs on Thursday, German Christian Democrat Edgar Schiedermeier says the Commission and the EU member states could contribute significantly by tackling the legal, fiscal, administrative and financial barriers which prevent local job inititatives from flourishing.</p>
<p>Schiedermeier suggests they should adopt coherent EU and national policies which respond to the changing job market.</p>
<p>These include:</p>
<p>- enabling people to combine several jobs or work part-time without losing all their unemployment benefit;</p>
<p>- offering an initial boost for new firms which are likely to have a profitable local market once local handicaps such as lack of capital or inadequate infrastructure are overcome;</p>
<p>- providing long-term aid designed to make solvent those socially useful services which have great job-creating potential but which are not profitable under present market conditions.</p>
<p>Schiedermeier's report urges the Commission to exploit the possibilities offered by the EU's Structural Funds 1994-1999 for creating local services like facilities for children and the elderly.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
