<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39926" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Aid workers find &quot;hell&quot; in starved Liberian town.</title>
<headline>Aid workers find &quot;hell&quot; in starved Liberian town.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A United Nations aid agency on Sunday said it would deliver the first food for eight months on Monday to the besieged town of Tubmanburg in western Liberia where relief workers found a living hell of starving people.</p>
<p>The World Food Programme (WFP) said a team that reached the jungle town on Saturday believed more than half its estimated 35,000 inhabitants were suffering from extreme hunger and that hundreds of skeletal children were on the verge of death.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a green hell,&quot; a WFP statement quoted its Liberia country director Tarek Elguindi as saying after he visited the town, 70 km (45 miles) northwest of the capital Monrovia.</p>
<p>&quot;The children have swollen bellies, their eyes are swollen, their skin is cracked and in some cases the flesh on the feet has fallen off,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Officials of the Rome-based WFP and other aid agencies took advantage of peace moves by rival factions in Liberia's conflict to enter Tubmanburg, which had been cut off by fighting and associated insecurity since February.</p>
<p>Elguindi said one member of the assessment team had rated the situation as &quot;worse than in Somalia in terms of the concentration of hungry people and the severity of the cases&quot;.</p>
<p>He said inhabitants forced to forage in the jungle had lived on soup from boiled tree leaves and eaten a wild red flower.</p>
<p>&quot;I've never seen such a massive number of hungry people,&quot; Elguindi said. &quot;When I saw the situation, I started to cry&quot;.</p>
<p>The last WFP food aid reached the town in January. The statement said 15 people were dying there a day and that Monday's truck delivery would consist of corn, soya, beans, oil and sugar to feed malnourished children.</p>
<p>Representatives of three other agencies will join the WFP mission, which the statement said would continue on Tuesday with the arrival of six trucks carrying enough rations to feed 7,500 people for about two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;WFP will each day deliver an additional 7,500 two-week ration package until the population completely re-emerges from the jungle and everyone is fed,&quot; the agency said.</p>
<p>Fighting round Tubmanburg pitted faction leader Alhaji Kromah's ULIMO-K faction against one-time allies in Roosevelt Johnson's ethnic Krahn ULIMO-J faction. The two groups signed a peace pact on Friday.</p>
<p>That and Kromah's handover of weapons on Saturday were the latest in a series of moves agreed by Liberia's rivals under pressure from West African leaders to end more than six years of civil war and disarm an estimated 60,000 fighters.</p>
<p>Charles Taylor, who launched the war in 1989 and commands the largest force, has promised to start disarming his men this month when he expects to demobilise about 3,000.</p>
<p>The war has killed well over 150,000 people in Liberia, which was founded by freed American slaves in 1847.</p>
<p>Elguindi warned that other areas of Liberia ravaged by fighting could be enduring similar conditions to Tubmanburg.</p>
<p>He said the WFP hoped to be allowed access some time in the next two weeks to Cape Mount county, where no relief supplies have arrived since March and many inhabitants had fled.</p>
<p>&quot;Whoever finds them will find the same situation as Tubmanburg,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LIBER">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
