<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="52385" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australian Yachting: Peter Campbell's Rhumbline Column.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australian Yachting: Peter Campbell's Rhumbline Column.</headline>
<text>
<p>By Peter Campbell*</p>
<p>SUMMER SEASON OPENS ON A HIGH NOTE</p>
<p>The Sydney summer sailing season, both inshore and offshore, opened on a high note last weekend. Most encouraging for clubs which have faced dwindling fleets in recent years was the 46-boat fleet which turned out for the Cruising Yacht Club's first short ocean race off Sydney Heads.</p>
<p>This is the largest first race fleet in years, despite the fact that many boats are still on their way back from the Queensland regattas. The fleet also included two maxis, Brindabella and Condor of Currabubula.</p>
<p>GEORGE SNOW's Brindabella spreadeagled the fleet but the freshening northerly breeze favoured the small boats as they ran back to harbour under spinnaker. In fact, the smallest yacht in the fleet, ROD SKELLET's Epic Venture, had a clear handicap win in the IMS racer division and also in the Performance Handicap division two.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, SKELLETT was not aboard, with LEE KILLINGWORTH on the helm. The Ord Minnett staffer was in a company conference down at Bowral but was quick on the phone late Saturday afternoon to find out the results.</p>
<p>- - - - - -</p>
<p>NEW ALLOWANCES FOR CRUISER RACER YACHTS</p>
<p>One of the vexed questions facing ocean racing yacht owners and the clubs which conduct ocean racing around Australia is the that of time allowances for yachts described as Cruiser Racers under the International Measurement System (IMS) rule which is now used worldwide to provide handicap results for long races.</p>
<p>The time allowance, in which a yacht's elapsed time is reduced by a percentage before the actual IMS handicap is applied, was introduced in Australia last year to allow genuine cruiser racer yachts to compete more equitably again racer (grand prix) yachts in events such as the Sydney to Hobart race. Unfortunately, according to Australian Yachting Federation (AYF) chief measurer, JOHN GREEN, there was a stampede to build cruiser racers which are in truth racers pretending to be cruisers and which have a hull shape designed to exploit the weaknesses of VPP.</p>
<p>The VPP (Velocity Prediction Program) is the key to IMS handicapping under various conditions, such as wind strength and direction.</p>
<p>At the request of the Cruising Yacht Club of Australia, a working party set up by the AYF's Offshore Committee has come up with a secret formula to overcome this problem and, hopefully, provide older and slower yachts with a more suitable cruiser racer allowance.</p>
<p>The time allowances issued so far by the AYF would appear to close the loophole as far as modern cruiser racers are concerned by extending the allowances well beyond the one percent originally recommended and used in the Sydney to Hobart last year.</p>
<p>At the same time, the working party has also produced time allowances for racer yachts.</p>
<p>However for the coming season, the AYF Offshore Committee's policy is that the allowance be used by club race committees for the Cruiser Racer division only in the 1996-97 offshore season.</p>
<p>Measurer GREEN stressed that the allowance is not an arbitrary, performance-based allowance, but is the result of a highly technical analysis of offshore race results. However, the accuracy of the allowances cannot be gauged until some races are run and analysed.</p>
<p>- - - - - -</p>
<p>NAVY YACHTS FOR WEST COASTER</p>
<p>The Ocean Racing Club of Victoria (ORCV) this year is celebrating the 25th running of the Melbourne to Hobart race around the rugged West Coast of Tasmania and the club expects a fleet of at least 60 boats with a strong Navy contingent.</p>
<p>Five Swarbrick S111 sloops from Naval establishments around the country, including Jervis Bay in NSW and Western Australia, will be competing the West Coaster and other linked events.</p>
<p>One of the 36-footers will be made available to a crew from the Royal Navy College at Dartmouth in England while the Royal New Zealand Navy may also have an entrant.</p>
<p>At least one Admiral plans to compete. PETER BRIGGS regularly races in offshore events out of Melbourne as navigator aboard Charlotte of Cerberus and won the ORCV's summer crown last season.</p>
<p>The 25th celebrations will begin with a Legends Dinner at the Royal Brighton Yacht Club on October 23. The racing will start before Christmas with races for the Australian Performance Handicap Championship, which includes the West Coaster race.</p>
<p>- - - - - -</p>
<p>WOODEN BOAT FESTIVALS IN SYDNEY &amp; HOBART</p>
<p>A magnificent display of classic and wooden yachts, cruisers, skiffs and launches of all shapes and sizes,  old and new will be assembled at Pyrmont Bay and at the Australian National Maritime Museum, Darling Harbour, for this year's Classic and Wooden Boat Show over the weekend of October 12-13.</p>
<p>One star of the show will be the beautiful yacht Cambria, 34.5 metres long on the deck with a graceful 5.7 metre bowsprit and a towering  45 metre mast. Cambria was built in 1928 and fully restored last year under the direction of IAIN MURRAY.</p>
<p>Hobart will again host the Australian Wooden Boat Festival at Constitution Dock on November 15-17,  also with a fleet of classic craft as well as exhibitions of the art of wooden boat building and their maintenance.</p>
<p>The oldest boat on display will be a 12-foot Huon pine clinker dinghy built by the convict Walter Paisley in 1871.</p>
<p>- - - - - -</p>
<p>AUSTRALIANS CONQUER AMSTERDAM CANALS</p>
<p>Each year the city of Amsterdam stages a unique sailing event called the Battle of Amsterdam in which invited sailors, including world and Olympic champions, compete single-handed in 4.20 metre LOA replicas of America's Cup yachts in a series of races on the canals.</p>
<p>Wind is provided by ten large blowers placed on barges which are capable of blowing 30 knots over the small canal course.</p>
<p>World Dragon class champion NICK ROGERS from the Royal Yacht Club of Tasmania was invited to compete last year, placing third overall.</p>
<p>This week ROGERS became the 1996 winner, beating fellow Aussie and Olympic silver medallist MITCH BOOTH in a hard-fought grand final. Earlier they had eliminated a strong fleet of European sailors in fleet and match racing.</p>
<p>ROGERS is off again overseas this weekend to defend for the RYCT the historic Seawanhaka Cup on Long Island Sound, New York. ROGERS won the Cup at Cowes, England, several years back.</p>
<p>Next week the defence is being held back at the Seawanhaka Corinthian Yacht Club to mark the club's 125th anniversary and the 100th anniversary of the introduction of this competition as an international amateur version of the New York Yacht Club's America's Cup, now dominated by multi-millionaires and professional sailing crews.</p>
<p>The Seawanhaka Cup maintains that status and while it has been sailed for in recent years in the vintage Dragon class, this year's series will be in Etchells keelboats.</p>
<p>*Peter Campbell is editor of Offshore Yachting magazine.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
