<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56129" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac urges rollback of French state economy.</title>
<headline>Chirac urges rollback of French state economy.</headline>
<dateline>POITIERS, France 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac said on Monday the public sector was overweight and called for state spending cuts and reform to create a broader market-based economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The main handicap in France today is that the market sector economy is too small compared to the managed economy,&quot; Chirac told industry bosses and employers' representatives.</p>
<p>&quot;We have too few producers and there are too many obstacles in their way. We must therefore reduce public spending, rethink it and constantly improve its productivity. But, even more, we must enlarge the merchant base of our economy,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chirac, speaking at the 50th anniversary celebrations of the French employers' federation, the Conseil National du Patronat Francais (CNPF), highlighted that public spending and social transfers accounted for 55 percent of output.</p>
<p>His call came two days before the centre-right government of Prime Minister Alain Juppe presents its final plans for a spending-cut budget to get France ready next year for European monetary union.</p>
<p>Juppe's government has already slated a string of state companies including France Telecom for full or partial privatisation in the near future.</p>
<p>Chirac said the state had to reform to facilitate business creation because businesses were the &quot;life force&quot; of the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;After years of slippage, the best thing the government can do is reform itself. Reforms in favour of corporations are reforms in favour of our country.&quot;</p>
<p>Chirac said corporations had the right to expect better support from their government. &quot;Businesses have duties but they also have rights,&quot; he said -- the right to fewer formalities, accessible financing, a modern legal system and the right to be supported in exports or in research and development efforts.</p>
<p>Chirac and the CNPF have had sometimes prickly exchanges over the government's role in the economy. On separate occasions earlier this year, Chirac criticised French banks as badly managed and lashed out at companies for not hiring more in response to payroll tax cuts.</p>
<p>Chirac said better organisation by employers and greater labour market flexibility would help create jobs. French unemployment is at a record 12.5 percent.</p>
<p>Reducing the work week would help, Chirac said.</p>
<p>He said government efforts to cut France's budget deficit were vital and had allowed interest rates to fall significantly in the past year. They had also underpinned the currency.</p>
<p>Chirac cautioned businesses that they must pursue dialogue with their employees if they wanted to remain competitive and reaffirmed his commitment to minimum labour standards, the so-called European social model.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no efficient company without dialogue between management and workers...there is no competitive economy without solidarity in society,&quot; he said. &quot;There is no strong Europe without cohesion in our societies. That is why I am committed to the European social model.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="POITIERS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
