<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72985" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: New signs of U.N. push for landmine ban.</title>
<headline>New signs of U.N. push for landmine ban.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Nicholas Doughty, Diplomatic Correspondent</p>
<p>Led by the United States, pressure is growing to ban landmines that kill tens of thousands of people, most of them innocent civilians, around the globe every year.</p>
<p>Speakers at the 185-nation U.N. General Assembly in New York have lined up to denounce the scourge of anti-personnel mines and to appeal for fresh efforts to ban their production, stockpiling and use.</p>
<p>A U.N.-sponsored conference in Geneva agreed to limit the use of some landmines in May, but stopped short of a ban because some countries argue they should remain a legitimate form of military defence.</p>
<p>&quot;We must end the carnage caused by anti-personnel landmines -- the hidden killers that murder and maim more than 25,000 people every year,&quot; U.S. President Bill Clinton said in a speech to the U.N. General Assembly on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Today I renew my appeal for the swift negotiation of a worldwide ban on the use, stockpiling, production and transfer of anti-personnel mines. Our children deserve to walk this earth in safety.&quot;</p>
<p>The 15-nation European Union, many of whose countries have agreed to stop exports of landmines, said on Tuesday it would give priority to dealing with the issue.</p>
<p>Irish Foreign Minister Dick Spring, whose country holds the EU presidency and speaks for the bloc, said more than 110 million landmines had been sown worldwide and that they had disabled a quarter of a million people.</p>
<p>&quot;It is an incredible and obscene irony that at a time when the United Nations ... is continuing its vital work of mine clearance, further millions of anti-personnel landmines are deployed annually,&quot; Spring said.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council has asked member states to contribute to a fund that will help with de-mining in countries like Bosnia, Angola, Afghanistan and Cambodia.</p>
<p>Millions of mines lie in these countries, often sown in uncharted areas. They continue to kill when farmers or women and children step on them, long after the conflict has ended.</p>
<p>Many of them are designed to maim by blowing off legs or inflicting other wounds. This makes sense from a military point of view, since a wounded soldier needs others to remove him from the battlefield, further reducing troop numbers.</p>
<p>Angolan Foreign Minister Venancio de Moura told the U.N. assembly on Monday that there were over 10 million mines in his country alone and that more than 10,000 people had been mutilated by them.</p>
<p>&quot;My government supports all efforts towards a total ban on the production, use and export of ... anti-personnel landmines,&quot; de Moura said.</p>
<p>&quot;The only viable solution ... is a total worldwide ban,&quot; said Danish Foreign Minister Niels Helveg Petersen.</p>
<p>Following the 55-nation Geneva conference, the United States said in May it would seek a global ban on landmines by the year 2001. Almost 40 other nations support a total ban.</p>
<p>The Geneva conference agreed to outlaw undetectable anti-personnel mines and is due to reconvene in the year 2001 to consider progress and possible further moves.</p>
<p>But critics say the agreement encourages the use of more advanced mines which will still be permitted in the meantime.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
