<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30846" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: N.Korea wants to send medical team for war veteran.</title>
<headline>N.Korea wants to send medical team for war veteran.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea has proposed to send a medical team to the South as an &quot;emergency measure&quot; to save the life of a Korean War veteran who has been held there since the war ended, Pyongyang's official media said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the North Korean Measure Committee for Rescuing Unconverted Long-Term Prisoners in South Korea was quoted as saying that Pyongyang wanted to send a medical group to South Korea to save Kim In-so from &quot;the jaws of death&quot;.</p>
<p>North Korea also proposed that Kim's two daughters be allowed to enter the South to look after their father, the spokesman said in a statement carried by the official Korean Central News Agency, monitored in Tokyo.</p>
<p>The spokesman said Kim has been in &quot;critical condition caused by a cerebral haemorrhage&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect that a relevant organ of South Korea will show an affirmative response to the emergency measure taken by us and guarantee the safety of the personnel of our side and provide them with convenience,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Kim, an unrepentant communist, was captured during the 1950-53 Korean War and released after spending more than 30 years in a southern jail. He submitted a petition to the International Red Cross in 1993 asking for his repatriation to the North.</p>
<p>Last Saturday North Korean Red Cross president Li Song-ho asked his South Korean counterpart Kang Young-hoon that Kim be immediately repatriated to the North.</p>
<p>Pyongyang made the latest proposal to send a medical team because Seoul rejected the North's demand for the immediate return of the war veteran, the North Korean spokesman said.</p>
<p>While refusing to return the war veteran, the South Korean Red Cross' Kang on Monday repeated his earlier call for the resumption of talks with leaders of the North Korean Red Cross.</p>
<p>South Korea in 1993 unconditionally repatriated Li In-mo, a northern partisan seized by the South during the war and jailed for more than three decades.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
