<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39184" id="root" date="1996-09-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Beijing alarmed by surge in industrial accidents.</title>
<headline>Beijing alarmed by surge in industrial accidents.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1996-09-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Beijing authorities, alarmed by a surge in the number of deaths from industrial accidents, convened an emergency meeting to try to curb such casualties, the Capital Economic Information Daily said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Forty workers were killed in industrial accidents in August, compared with 143 in the first seven months of 1996 or an average of 20.4 a month, the newspaper said. It gave no reason for the increase.</p>
<p>Beijing Vice-Mayor Jin Renqing convened an emergency meeting this month and decided that officials must adopt measures to curb the rise in the number of deaths from industrial accidents.</p>
<p>A total of 155 industrial accidents were reported in the Chinese capital in the first eight months, 68 of them at construction sites, it said.</p>
<p>Eighty-four building workers were killed, accounting for 45.9 percent of the total, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>A construction boom in Beijing has attracted thousands of out-of-town farmers to work as construction workers.</p>
<p>Separately, 62 miners were killed in 51 mining accidents in Beijing, the newspaper said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
