<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53131" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Israeli air raid heightens fear in Lebanon.</title>
<headline>Israeli air raid heightens fear in Lebanon.</headline>
<byline>Kamel Jaber</byline>
<dateline>NABATIYEH, Lebanon 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli helicopters rocketed suspected Hizbollah targets after a clash with the pro-Iranian group in south Lebanon on Friday, heightening fears that the Jewish state might mount a broad military offensive.</p>
<p>Lebanese security sources said the helicopters fired two rockets into Jabal al-Rafi in Iqlim al-Toufah ridge, a Hizbollah bastion north of Israel's south Lebanon occupation zone.</p>
<p>There was no immediate word on casualties.</p>
<p>Hours earlier Israeli soldiers ambushed members of the group who had infiltrated the Israeli-held border zone, killing one guerrilla, Israeli security sources said.</p>
<p>Hizbollah claimed responsiblity for the infiltration and said its guerrillas ambushed an Israeli patrol, wounding several soldiers.</p>
<p>The helicopter attack was the first Israeli air raid on Lebanon in more than a month. On August 8, Israeli planes blasted Hizbollah targets in the eastern Bekaa Valley.</p>
<p>The Israeli army said two helicopters were sent in after Israeli soldiers spotted &quot;suspicious figures&quot; in Jabal al-Rafi.</p>
<p>&quot;The helicopters fired at a building in which the terrorists apparently were hiding,&quot; the army added in a statement.</p>
<p>A senior Lebanese Foreign Ministry official said on Thursday Beirut was taking seriously a warning by Israel's proxy militia in south Lebanon of widescale Israeli retaliation if Hizbollah guerrillas stepped up their attacks on Israeli troops.</p>
<p>Lebanese Foreign Minister Faris Bouez described the warning in remarks published on Friday as blackmail aimed at forcing Lebanon to accept the Jewish state's peace proposals.</p>
<p>&quot;We reject this blackmail and threats which are aimed at dragging Lebanon to accept vague Israeli proposals,&quot; Bouez was quoted as saying in Syria's official press after his talks with Syrian President Hafez al-Assad on Thursday.</p>
<p>Israel launched a bloody 17-day blitz it called Operation Grapes of Wrath against Hizbollah guerrillas in Lebanon in April, killing 200 people after tit-for-tat bombardments of civilian areas by the two sides.</p>
<p>An April 26 understanding that ended the onslaught banned both parties from firing from or at civilian targets on both sides of the Israeli-Lebanese border. However, it did not rule out guerrilla attacks on Israeli troops inside the buffer zone.</p>
<p>The Israeli sources said that before Friday's air raid an Israeli patrol fired machineguns and rocket-propelled grenades at guerrillas in Wadi Slouki in the western sector of the 15-km (nine-mile) wide zone.</p>
<p>In Beirut, Hizbollah said in a statement: &quot;A group of resistance fighters infiltrated into the Wadi Slouki valley and ambushed Israeli soldiers patrolling on foot at 7:30 a.m. with machineguns and rocket-propelled grenades, inflicting a number of injuries among them.&quot;</p>
<p>The statement made no mention of the killing of a Hizbollah guerrilla, which was confirmed in the Israeli army statement.</p>
<p>&quot;A Hizbollah terrorist was killed by Israeli army fire and it is possible that another terrorist was hit in a clash between an Israeli army force and a Hizbollah squad in the central sector of the security zone in south Lebanon. There were no Israeli casualties,&quot; the army statement added.</p>
<p>Later, Israeli gunners shelled targets north of the zone, the Lebanese security sources added.</p>
<p>Hizbollah, fighting a guerrilla war to oust the Jewish state from south Lebanon, has killed 18 Israeli soldiers this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NABATIYEH, Lebanon"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
