<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61293" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Eleven North Koreans shot to death in South Korea.</title>
<headline>Eleven North Koreans shot to death in South Korea.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eleven North Koreans who landed in the enemy South from a submarine were found dead on Wednesday, possibly shot by one of their number who also used the gun on himself, a defence ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>A 12th was captured alive after a massive search while another eight or nine were still at large, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Authorities described the North Koreans as infiltrators, and angrily denounced the incident as a breach of an armistice agreement that ended the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the dead infiltrators had a gun on him and we think he killed himself after shooting the others,&quot; the spokesman told a news conference.</p>
<p>The captured North Korean, Lee Kang-soo, 31, gave a different account, telling interrogators the submarine drifted into South Korean waters after developing engine trouble, television news reports said.</p>
<p>Lee said the vessel left port in North Korea on Monday and began drifting the following day, Munhwa Broadcasting Corporation news reported.</p>
<p>The submarine was spotted by a taxi driver soon after midnight on Tuesday. It was stranded on rocks nine kilometres (5.6 miles) south of the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>Authorities said it apparently hit a reef while returning to the North after dropping off infiltrators on a beach.</p>
<p>But there was also speculation the submarine could have been sent to pick up an agent or drop off a small unit of spies -- and the mission then went badly wrong.</p>
<p>The 11 dead North Koreans were found on top of a mountain dressed in jeans and sneakers, the defence spokesman said.</p>
<p>Authorities believed a total of around 20 North Koreans landed on a beach south of the border with North Korea. That was double their initial estimate.</p>
<p>On board were automatic weapons and ammunition, along with canned food and shoes.</p>
<p>Thousands of troops and police using sniffer dogs combed terrain around the beach as helicopters roared overhead. They set up checkpoints on all main roads. Naval vessels and a reconnaissance plane joined the search.</p>
<p>As night fell, a curfew was clamped on the area and security forces formed a cordon. The curfew will be lifted at first light on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;This incident is a grave provocation and a definite infiltration against South Korea by North Korea,&quot; the director of operations at the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Kim Dong-shin, told a news conference.</p>
<p>Cabinet ministers who deal with Security-related matters held a meeting chaired by Unification Minister Kwon O-kie and declared the infiltration &quot;a direct threat to our national security&quot;, a unification ministry statement said.</p>
<p>Yonhap news agency quoted a former North Korean commando, captured while on a mission to kill South Korea's president in 1968, as saying the submarine may have been planning to bring home a Pyongyang agent.</p>
<p>&quot;The submarine may have hit rocks by mistake and then all members of the crew fled onto land after finding it impossible to go back,&quot; Kim Shin-jo was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>Adding weight to this speculation were signs of panic flight, with weapons and ammunition abandoned in the boat and personal belongings scattered along a road.</p>
<p>Wednesday's drama was one of the most deadly since 1968 when 31 North Koreans reached the presidential Blue House in Seoul. Twenty-eight were killed in a gunbattle in which 34 Southern troops, police and civilians also died.</p>
<p>Shin Sang-kil, deputy head of operations of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, told reporters troops found a machinegun with 75 rounds of ammunition, a Soviet-made rifle with 100 bullets and 75 other bullets on the vessel.</p>
<p>A written pledge of loyalty to North Korean leader Kim Jong-il was also found. Military clothing, keys and a life jacket were recovered on a nearby road.</p>
<p>The defence ministry said the Sang-o class submarine measured 34 metres (111 ft) in length and weighed 330 tonnes. North Korea has about 10 of these submarines, each capable of carrying 21 people, a ministry official said.</p>
<p>Television pictures showed the grey vessel bobbing helplessly in the water.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
