<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64122" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Blaze of gunfire ends N.Korean espionage drama.</title>
<headline>Blaze of gunfire ends N.Korean espionage drama.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops killed seven more North Koreans on Thursday as one of the deadliest infiltration dramas since the early Cold War drew to a close in a hail of bullets.</p>
<p>An estimated 20 North Koreans came ashore on a beach in the enemy South from a submarine on Wednesday, authorities said.</p>
<p>Altogether 18 have now been shot dead -- 11 in an apparent mass suicide -- and one was captured after a ruthless manhunt by thousands of troops and police. One more is still on the loose.</p>
<p>The search through mountainous terrain was likely to continue because of uncertainty about the exact number of communist agents dropped near the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>Political fallout from the episode threatened to further sour relations between the two Koreas.</p>
<p>South Korean president Kim Young-sam declared the submarine adventure an act of military provocation, but Pyongyang was unrepentant and refused to accept a protest note on the heavily-fortified border.</p>
<p>South Korean security forces took no chances with the heavily-armed North Koreans as they reportedly fled for their lives towards the fortified border that has split the Korean peninsula since the 1950-53 war.</p>
<p>Three were cut down by automatic fire as they crouched by a stream to drink water, military sources in Kangnung said.</p>
<p>Television pictures showed bullet-riddled corpses splayed on the ground. They were dressed in blue jeans and sneakers made in South Korea, suggesting an espionage mission.</p>
<p>Security forces were led to several of the fugitives by alert villagers. In the latest gunfight, two members of the South Korean security forces were wounded, officials said.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the bodies of 11 North Koreans were found huddled together on top of a mountain situated close to a beach where they landed. All had been shot through the head in what was initially described as mass suicide.</p>
<p>However, state television speculated the 11 could have been sacrificed to enable others to travel more quickly. The placing of the fatal bullet wounds suggested the 11 had been executed, it said.</p>
<p>Kim denounced the most serious infiltration since the 1960s at a cabinet meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a simple spy case. I regard it as a kind of military provocation,&quot; an aide quoted Kim as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite food shortages, the reason why North Korea sent armed infiltrators is that they still have not given up their ambition to reunify Korea by force,&quot; Kim said. Impoverished North Korea is on the brink of famine.</p>
<p>North Korea rejected a protest by the U.S.-led United Nations Command in South Korea, a command statement said.</p>
<p>The U.N. Command attempted to hand the message to the North through the border crossing village of Panmunjom, but a Northern military duty officer would not take it, the statement said.</p>
<p>The U.N. Command was the supreme headquarters for international and South Korean forces which repelled North Korean invaders in the Korean War. It now helps supervise the armistice that ended the war.</p>
<p>&quot;I strongly demand that your side immediately take the necessary steps to prevent recurrence of these serious Armistice Agreement violations,&quot; said the letter signed by South Korean general Cha Ki Moon.</p>
<p>&quot;If you fail to do so, the responsibility for the unfortunate consequences will be yours.&quot;</p>
<p>Security forces with sniffer dogs have combed the Kangnung area since the vessel was spotted early on Wednesday wedged on a reef. Helicopters and a reconnaissance plane were also used.</p>
<p>Security was also beefed up around Seoul, with manned checkpoints on bridges leading into the capital and armed police posted conspicuously in busy shopping districts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
