<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64176" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Submarine exposes security gaps in South Korea.</title>
<headline>Submarine exposes security gaps in South Korea.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>By slipping undetected into South Korean waters, a North Korean submarine has highlighted the country's vulnerability to attack by its arch enemy, Seoul defence officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>News media criticised the failure of Southern armed forces to detect the small submarine, found grounded on rocks on the east coast early on Wednesday morning.</p>
<p>On board were around 20 North Koreans.</p>
<p>&quot;We humbly accept the criticism,&quot; a South Korean navy officer, who declined to be named, said in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;In reality, however, it is almost impossible for our navy to detect such submarines.&quot;</p>
<p>Only five or six naval vessels normally keep watch around the South Korean coast, he said. They are backed by maritime police boats without any electronic anti-submarine equipment.</p>
<p>The navy has 180 combat vessels, 60 support vessels and five submarines, according to defence ministry figures.</p>
<p>&quot;Detecting such a small-sized submarine is like searching for a needle in a big river,&quot; the navy officer said, adding each naval vessel on coastal patrol watches over a sea block almost 300 miles (482 km) long and 200 miles (321 km) wide.</p>
<p>&quot;North Korea's situation is similar to ours,&quot; he said, noting North Korea has about 760 combat and support ships and some 90 submarines, including 50 midget-class submarines.</p>
<p>Wednesday's infiltration was made easier by the removal of barbed wires barricades along the coast designed to keep out North Korean frogmen.</p>
<p>&quot;The majority of our ground forces are deployed in the frontline,&quot; an army officer said. &quot;It is somewhat difficult to keep perfect vigilance along coastal areas with the remaining forces. In this context, barbed-wire barriers are a big help in preventing such infiltrations.&quot;</p>
<p>Since 1991, South Korea has removed some 248 miles (400 km) of barbed-wire barriers from its beaches for the convenience of residents and beachgoers.</p>
<p>More barriers are scheduled to be removed.</p>
<p>Wednesday's submarine infiltration is the second time in recent months that defence planners have been embarrassed.</p>
<p>In May a North Korean air force captain who defected in an old-fashioned Soviet-made fighter exposed gaping security holes in the South's air defences.</p>
<p>A series of security lapses allowed Li Chol-su's Mig-19 to scream towards Seoul without raising any alarm in the capital. He was intercepted by several Southern fighters, which guided him to a military air field.</p>
<p>Seoul's mayor apologised for the failure and stripped three civil defence officials of their positions. The country has since staged elaborate civil defence drills.</p>
<p>Seoul is just a few minutes flying time from the border, and within range of North Korea artillery.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended in a truce that sealed the division of the Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>South Korea's 655,000 armed forces, backed by 37,000 U.S. servicemen, confront a 1.1 million strong North Korean military across a 155 mile (250 km) barbed-wire border. It is the largest concentration of enemy forces anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>But U.S. officials say the combat readiness of North Korea, its economy devastated by shortages of food and fuel, is at a low point.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
