<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65174" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Israelis, Hizbollah fight in south Lebanon.</title>
<headline>Israelis, Hizbollah fight in south Lebanon.</headline>
<byline>Kamel Jaber</byline>
<dateline>HOUMINE, Lebanon 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli jets and artillery bombarded Hizbollah guerrilla targets and villages which the group controls in south Lebanon after four Israeli soldiers were wounded in an ambush on Thursday, witnesses said.</p>
<p>The fighting on the last active Arab-Israeli frontline coincided with a visit to the region by U.S. peace envoy Dennis Ross to help jump-start stalled Middle East peace talks.</p>
<p>The witnesses said Israeli jets fired about 10 rockets in three raids into Iqlim al-Toufah -- rugged mountainland used by pro-Iranian Hizbollah (Party of God) guerrillas to attack Israeli forces occupying a south Lebanon border zone.</p>
<p>The Israeli army comfirmed two air strikes, saying that among the targets hit in Jabal Safi in Iqlim al-Toufah some &quot;served as firing positions for terrorists&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;All planes returned safely to base&quot;, it added.</p>
<p>The air raids and concurrent artillery shelling came shortly after Hizbollah guerrillas ambushed an Israeli patrol in the zone, wounding four soldiers, pro-Israeli militia sources said.</p>
<p>Immediately after the ambush, Israeli gunners opened up with heavy artillery fire for hours into Hizbollah-controlled hills and villages in Iqlim al-Toufah, witnesses and SLA sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Israeli forces have fired about 700 to 800 shells of all calibres. At least 50 shells slammed inside the villages of Ain Bouswar and Jba'a. Shelling was also concentrated on the Ain Bouswar-Jarjouh road,&quot; one witness near Iqlim al-Toufah said.</p>
<p>&quot;The shelling is continuing but with less intensity than before,&quot; a pro-Israeli militia source said later, about an hour after the last raid at about 2 p.m. (1100 GMT).</p>
<p>Hizbollah fighters responded with mortar bombs into the zone and fired at least two shoulder-held SAM-7 rockets at the attacking jets, which targeted mainly rugged mountain hideouts and roads used by the Shi'ite Moslem fighters.</p>
<p>A Hizbollah spokesman in Beirut said a civilian woman was wounded in the Israeli shelling on Jba'a, charging that this was a breach of the U.S.-brokered ceasefire agreement that ended a 17-day Israeli blitz on Lebanon in April.</p>
<p>Security sources said a woman was wounded in Jba'a from flying debris caused by an exploding shell.</p>
<p>A senior foreign ministry official in Beirut told Reuters that Lebanon was planning to file a complaint over the Israeli shelling of civilian areas to a five-nation committee monitoring the ceasefire agreement in south Lebanon.</p>
<p>In the ambush, the guerrillas fired machineguns and anti-tank rockets from close range at the patrol between the villages of Rihane and Sojoud, the South Lebanon Army (SLA) militia sources said. Other guerrillas fired a hail of mortar bombs at the patrol before the attack began, they added.</p>
<p>Hizbollah said in a statement earlier its fighters clashed with an Israeli force trying to advance out of the border zone and into the Iqlim al-Toufah highlands near Sojoud.</p>
<p>Thursday's fighting came a day after Lebanese Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri said increased Israeli military action in south Lebanon was unlikely.</p>
<p>Some 200 Lebanese, mostly civilians, were killed in Israel's bloody 17-day blitz -- dubbed &quot;Operation Grapes of Wrath&quot; -- against Hizbollah guerrillas after tit-for-tat bombardments of civilian areas by the two sides.</p>
<p>The ceasefire agreement barred both sides from targeting civilian areas but allowed guerrilla raids on Israeli forces in south Lebanon and granted both sides the right to self-defence.</p>
<p>Thursday's Israeli casualties were the first since August 29, when one soldier was killed in a Hizbollah ambush. Hizbollah guerrillas, who are fighting to oust the Israelis from south Lebanon, have killed 18 Israeli soldiers this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOUMINE, Lebanon"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
