<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65932" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Three North Korean infiltrators killed in S.Korea.</title>
<headline>Three North Korean infiltrators killed in S.Korea.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three North Korean infiltrators were shot and killed by South Korean security forces on Thursday, a defence ministry official in the east coast city of Kangnung said.</p>
<p>They were among an estimated eight agents still at large after around 20 North Koreans landed by submarine on a beach near Kangnung on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The official denied earlier reports that other infiltrators had been captured.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the bodies of 11 infiltrators were found huddled together on top of a mountain. The men had all been shot through the head in what authorities said was a mass suicide.</p>
<p>One other North Korean was flushed out of hiding on Wednesday, leaving eight unaccounted for in the most serious infiltration drama since the 1960s.</p>
<p>Communist espionage agents from North Korean have in the past chosen suicide over capture.</p>
<p>A defence ministry spokesman in Seoul said the fugitives were apparently trying to flee home across the land border.</p>
<p>&quot;Villagers have reported that some suspected infiltrators asked them about roads leading to the Taebaek mountains,&quot; he said. The mountain range straddles the heavily fortified border, sealed since the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
<p>South Korean President Kim Young-sam denounced the infiltration as an act of &quot;military provocation&quot;, the domestic Yonhap news agency reported.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a simple spy case. I regard it as a kind of military provocation,&quot; Yonhap quoted Kim as telling a cabinet meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite food shortages, the reason why North Korea sent armed infiltrators is that they still have not given up their ambition to reunify Korea by force,&quot; Kim was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>The head of the Agency for National Security Planning, Kwon O-kie, was quoted as saying the incident amounted to &quot;infiltration by armed guerrillas&quot;.</p>
<p>Troops with sniffer dogs combed mountains and beaches around Kangnung after a dusk-to-dawn curfew was lifted on Thursday. The submarine remained stranded on rocks.</p>
<p>The North Korean captured on Wednesday was quoted by local media as saying the vessel drifted into Southern waters after developing engine trouble.</p>
<p>His dead colleagues were members of the crew, not trained saboteurs, Lee Kwang-soo, 31, was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>Troops who boarded the abandoned grey craft found automatic guns and ammunition along with canned food and shoes.</p>
<p>The incident has further raised tensions between the two hostile neighbours who face each other across the world's most heavily fortified border.</p>
<p>Pyongyang has not commented on the drama, one of the deadliest since 1968 when 31 North Koreans reached the presidential Blue House in Seoul.</p>
<p>Twenty-eight were killed in a gunbattle in which 34 Southern troops, police officers and civilians also died.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, armed North Korean troops staged illegal exercises in a border buffer zone, and following that scare U.S. President Bill Clinton and South Korean head of state Kim Young-sam made a peace overture to Pyongyang.</p>
<p>They proposed four-way talks, also including China, but North Korea has yet to respond.</p>
<p>However, there had been hopeful signs that Pyongyang was being lured out of its hostile isolation in its desperation for help to ease a food crisis.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
