<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66981" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: N.Korean agents evade capture as U.S. urges calm.</title>
<headline>N.Korean agents evade capture as U.S. urges calm.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops using loudhailers pleaded on Friday with the remnants of a North Korean infiltration group to surrender, while the United States urged &quot;all parties&quot; to stay calm.</p>
<p>Troops blasted the message to a half dozen or so agents they believe may be holed up in a rugged mountain area pitted with disused coal mines.</p>
<p>Helicopters scattered leaflets urging surrender, but by nightfall there was no response and a curfew was imposed until dawn.</p>
<p>There was even speculation the highly-trained operatives may have slipped through a cordon of thousands of troops and police and could be on their way home.</p>
<p>&quot;You are surrounded. If you abandon your weapons and surrender you can live. Most of your colleagues have been shot to death. We urge you to surrender immediately,&quot; an army officer shouted through a loudhailer on a military jeep.</p>
<p>Authorities now believe possibly 26 North Koreans came ashore early on Wednesday from a submarine near the east coast city of Kangnung. So far, 18 have been shot and killed and one has been captured alive.</p>
<p>Political shockwaves from the incident -- one of the deadliest infiltrations of the South since the early Cold War -- spread wider, clouding prospects for a U.S.-South Korean peace initiative for the divided Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended with an armistice negotiated by U.S.-led United Nations forces.</p>
<p>In Washington, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher urged &quot;all parties&quot; to avoid further provocative action. Seoul said it would brief the U.N. Security Council on the drama and Japan denounced the incident as &quot;deplorable&quot;.</p>
<p>North Korea accused South Korea of taking &quot;provocative action&quot; near the border earlier this week but made no reference to the submarine incident in a radio broadcast.</p>
<p>Christopher told a news conference: &quot;We wish that all parties would refrain from taking further provocative actions.&quot; The United States has 37,000 troops stationed in the South to deter any North Korean attack.</p>
<p>Japan hit out at its close neighbour across the sea.</p>
<p>&quot;We have an interest in peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula and it is deplorable that North Korea has brought about this incident,&quot; government spokesman Seiroku Kajiyama told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;The international community will not accept it. We call on North Korea to immediately end these kinds of actions&quot;.</p>
<p>Political analysts said the incident may have damaged the chances of peace on the Korean peninsula by giving ammunition to hardliners in Seoul, who oppose any concessions to the North.</p>
<p>South Korea and the United States are trying to entice Pyongyang to talks, along with China, to work out a peace pact to replace the armistice.</p>
<p>A South Korean foreign ministry statement said Seoul's ambassador to the United Nations would brief members of the Security Council on Friday.</p>
<p>The infiltration was &quot;an obvious violation of the armistice agreement and a grave threat to peace and security on the Korean peninsula&quot;, the statement said.</p>
<p>South Korea is one of 15 members of the Security Council, whose permanent members are the United States, China, Russia, Britain and France.</p>
<p>Media reports said the captured man told interrogators 26 North Koreans landed. Three were saboteurs -- trained to survive behind enemy lines and cover huge distances on foot -- and they were still at large, Lee Kwang-soo reportedly said.</p>
<p>South Korea's spy chief said the saboteurs could have murdered 11 of their collegues, whose bodies were found on top of a mountain on Wednesday. At the time, authorities said they had committed suicide rather than risk capture.</p>
<p>Kwon Young-hae, the Director of the Agency for National Security Planning, was quoted by newspapers as telling a parliamentary committee some of the 11 were killed by bullets fired from behind, suggesting execution-style death.</p>
<p>Security experts suggested the saboteurs sacrificed their comrades so they could move faster and to distract pursuers.</p>
<p>The infiltrators appeared to have been sent &quot;not for simple espionage or reconnaissance missions but for special duties such as guerilla warfare&quot;, Kwon said.</p>
<p>In case they evaded the dragnet around the mines, troops were lying in ambush along roads and mountain passes leading to North Korea, a defence ministry official in Kangnung said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
