<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66987" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: N.Korean agents hold out, U.S. urges calm.</title>
<headline>N.Korean agents hold out, U.S. urges calm.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops using loudhailers pleaded on Friday with the remnants of a North Korean infiltration group to surrender, while the United States urged &quot;all parties&quot; to stay calm.</p>
<p>Troops blasted the message to an estimated half dozen or so agents holed up in a rugged mountain area pitted with disused coal mines, and helicopters scattered leaflets urging surrender after a night of fierce gunfights.</p>
<p>&quot;You are surrounded. If you abandon your weapons and surrender you can live. Most of your colleagues have been shot to death. We urge you to surrender immediately,&quot; an army officer shouted repeatedly through a loudspeaker on a military jeep.</p>
<p>Authorities now believe possibly 26 North Koreans came ashore early on Wednesday from a submarine near the east coast city of Kangnung. So far, 18 have been shot and killed and one has been captured alive.</p>
<p>Political shockwaves from the incident -- one of the deadliest infiltrations of the South since the early Cold War -- spread wider, clouding prospects for a U.S.-South Korean peace initiative for the divided Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended with an armistice negotiated by U.S.-led United Nations forces.</p>
<p>In Washington, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher urged &quot;all parties&quot; to avoid further provocative action. Seoul said it would brief the U.N. Security Council on the drama and Japan denounced the incident as &quot;deplorable&quot;.</p>
<p>North Korea accused South Korea of taking &quot;provocative action&quot; near the border earlier this week but made no reference to the submarine incident in a radio broadcast.</p>
<p>Christopher told a news conference: &quot;We wish that all parties would refrain from taking further provocative actions.&quot; The United States has 37,000 troops stationed in the South to deter any North Korean attack.</p>
<p>Asked if the incident could affect efforts to provide Pyongyang with nuclear technology and humanitarian aid, he added: &quot;Obviously, the episode is a matter of concern but the facts are so murky.&quot;</p>
<p>North Korea is appealing for Western food aid following devastating floods.</p>
<p>The United States is part of an international consortium providing the North with nuclear power plants as part of a deal to end the country's suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>Japan hit out at North Korea over the incident.</p>
<p>&quot;We have an interest in peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula and it is deplorable that North Korea has brought about this incident,&quot; government spokesman Seiroku Kajiyama told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;The international community will not accept it. We call on North Korea to immediately end these kinds of actions&quot;.</p>
<p>Political analysts said the incident may have damaged the chances of peace on the Korean peninsula by giving ammunition to hardliners in Seoul, who oppose any concessions to the North.</p>
<p>South Korea and the United States are trying to entice Pyongyang to talks, along with China, to work out a peace pact to replace the armistice.</p>
<p>A South Korean foreign ministry statement said Seoul's ambassador to the United Nations would brief members of the Security Council on Friday on the drama.</p>
<p>The infiltration was &quot;an obvious violation of the armistice agreement and a grave threat to peace and security on the Korean peninsula&quot;, the statement said.</p>
<p>South Korea is one of 15 members of the Security Council, whose permanent members are the United States, China, Russia, Britain and France.</p>
<p>Domestic media reports said the captured man, Lee Kwang-soo, 31, told interrogators 26 North Koreans landed on a beach. Three were trained saboteurs, two guides and the rest crew members.</p>
<p>The saboteurs -- deadly operatives trained to survive behind enemy lines during war -- were still at large, he said.</p>
<p>A South Korean defence ministry spokesman declined to comment on the reports.</p>
<p>The public in South Korea has reacted with anger and anxiety to the infiltration. Some blame the navy for failing to detect the 34 metre (111 foot) submarine and worry the country is vulnerable to attack from its arch-enemy to the north.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
