<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67115" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Coverup alleged in &quot;friendly fire&quot; accident in Iraq.</title>
<headline>Coverup alleged in &quot;friendly fire&quot; accident in Iraq.</headline>
<byline>Jim Adams</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. Senate subcommittee is investigating allegations by family members of a coverup in the 1994 &quot;friendly fire&quot; shootdown of two U.S. helicopters over Iraq by U.S. fighter planes, a family member and Senate sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>But the investigation has hit a legal snag because the Defence Department objected to committee efforts to depose the Air Force officers who dismissed negligent homicide charges against the two F-15 fighter pilots.</p>
<p>A family member said the Senate Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations was looking into allegations by relatives of some of the 26 Americans and foreign officers killed in the accident that a coverup allowed the two F-15 fighter pilots to escape prosecution.</p>
<p>A Senate source confirmed the investigation but would not say if evidence of a coverup has been found.</p>
<p>&quot;What I am concerned about is that you have general officers who are covering this thing up,&quot; retired Air Force Col. Daniel Piper said in an interview. &quot;When you cover something like this up then somebody else is going to die for the same stupid reason.&quot;</p>
<p>His daughter, Air Force 2nd Lt. Laura Ashley Piper, was among the 26 people killed when the two U.S. F-15 fighter planes mistakenly identified two U.S. Black Hawk helicopters as Iraqi Hinds in the &quot;no-fly&quot; zone in northern Iraq and shot them down with missiles.</p>
<p>The Air Force said it stands by its investigation which led to dismissal of negligent homicide charges against the two F-15 pilots. Higher commands reviewed and approved the action.</p>
<p>Senate investigators hit the legal snag when they tried to depose and take sworn statements from the Air Force judicial officers who dismissed the charges against the pilots.</p>
<p>Deputy Secretary of Defence John White told the subcommittee in a letter Sept. 3 that Congress &quot;has no judicial function or review authority&quot; in the case.</p>
<p>White said Congress's deposition of such officers &quot;poses a grave risk to the integrity of the military justice system&quot; because judicial officers in the future would have to worry about &quot;possible congressional criticism and public censure.&quot;</p>
<p>The Senate subcommittee's chairman, Sen. William Roth, a Delaware Republican, must now decide whether to subpoena the Air Force officers or drop his effort to get their testimony.</p>
<p>They include Maj. Gen. Eugene Santarelli, the 17th Air Force commander who dismissed the charges, and Col. Edward Starr, the Article 32 investigating officer who recommended the charges be dismissed. An Article 32 investigation is similar to a civilian grand jury hearing.</p>
<p>The Air Force said in a statement in December 1994 that a charge of negligent homicide was dismissed against the lead pilot, Capt. Eric Wickson, because &quot;evidence revealed Wickson made a reasonable mistake, under the circumstances, in misidentifying the Black Hawks as Iraqi helicopters.&quot;</p>
<p>It said the second pilot, Lt. Col. Randy May, had been charged with negligent homicide because initial evidence indicated he gave only a vague answer when Wickson asked if he also recognised the helicopters to be Iraqi Hinds.</p>
<p>But it said that charge was dismissed against May because &quot;evidence convinced the investigating officer and Santarelli that May, as wingman, followed proper procedures in yielding control of the action to his lead pilot.&quot;</p>
<p>Piper said he believed there was a coverup, including immunity from prosecution for Wickson, so that all blame could be put on him and then neither pilot would be prosecuted.</p>
<p>But the Air Force said Wickson was given immunity only from being prosecuted on the basis of his own testimony. It said he could have been prosecuted with any other evidence.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
