<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67140" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. sees N. Korea nuclear deal continuing.</title>
<headline>U.S. sees N. Korea nuclear deal continuing.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States said on Friday it does not expect North Korea's attempt to infiltrate the South by submarine to interfere with a landmark nuclear agreement and an offer for peace talks remains on the table.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope very much and do not expect that this incident will affect ... the nuclear freeze that is in place in North Korea,&quot; State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said.</p>
<p>&quot;That agreement is in place (and) is being adhered to by the North Koreans. And KEDO (Korean Peninsula Energy Development Organisation) is working very hard to make sure that that agreement is fully implemented,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Burns stressed: &quot;It's clear to the United States that this incursion represents a serious provocation by North Korea and is a violation of the armistice agreement&quot; between North and South that ended the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
<p>He spoke as a massive search was underway for the remaining North Korean infiltrators who landed by submarine in South Korea. Fierce gunbattles raged through the night.</p>
<p>South Korean security forces believe several agents are holed up around disused coal mines in rugged mountains near the east coast city of Kangnung. They are the remnants of a squad of heavily armed infiltrators that landed on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Authorities initially said about 20 North Koreans sneaked in, but now they say there may have been more. So far, 18 are confirmed to have been shot dead and one captured alive.</p>
<p>This incident wil be &quot;high on the agenda&quot; when Secretary of State Warren Christopher meets his South Korean counterpart next Tuesday on the fringes of the United Nations General Assembly in New York, Burns said.</p>
<p>&quot;The United States is an ally of South Korea. We're very clear about where our priorities are on that peninsula and we think this is provocative act. And we think that South Korea has every right to investigate it, every right to talk internationally about it. And the United States will be quite supportive of the South Koreans throughout this,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Some 37,000 U.S. troops are stationed in the South.</p>
<p>South Korea has described the most serious infiltration since the 1960s as a military provocation. North and South Korea have been technically at war since the 1950-53 Korean conflict ended in a truce.</p>
<p>North Korea is on the brink of famine following devastating floods and has appealed for international aid.</p>
<p>The United States is leading an international consortium called KEDO providing the North with $4.5 billion in nuclear power plants and alternative energy supplies as part of a deal to end the country's suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>Seoul and Washington are also trying to entice Pyongyang to talks, along with China, to work out a peace pact to replace an armistice that sealed the division of the Korean peninsula in 1953.</p>
<p>&quot;The United States and South Korea want to go ahead with the four party (peace) talks because this represents the largest ambition and objective that we have...to achieve a full peace agreement to end the Korean War, and to create a state of peace in the Korean Peninsula,&quot; Burns said.</p>
<p>He said North Korea still has not agreed to the proposal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
