<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68140" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: South Korean troops seek to flush out infiltrators.</title>
<headline>South Korean troops seek to flush out infiltrators.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>A massive search for North Korean infiltrators who landed by submarine in South Korea moved to an area of mine shafts on Friday after fierce gunbattles raged through the night.</p>
<p>Security forces believe several agents are holed up around disused coal mines in rugged mountains near the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>The agents are the remnants of a squad of heavily armed infiltrators that landed on Wednesday.</p>
<p>State television withdrew an earlier report that four had been found dead on Friday.</p>
<p>An army officer pleaded with the men to surrender and save their lives in messages shouted through a loud-speaker mounted on the back of a jeep.</p>
<p>&quot;You are surrounded. If you abandon your weapons and surrender you can live. Most of your colleagues have been shot to death. We urge you to surrender immediately,&quot; the officer boomed.</p>
<p>Authorities initially said about 20 North Koreans sneaked in, but now say there may have been more.</p>
<p>So far, 18 are confirmed to have been shot dead and one captured alive.</p>
<p>A military officer in Kangnung said security forces had found hollows in the ground where several agents may have spent the night.</p>
<p>&quot;I heard gunfire all night and grenades exploding,&quot; said local resident Chang Choon-taik.</p>
<p>Five or six helicopters were flying over the area, which is saturated with armed troops and located about 17 km (10 miles) from a beach where the agents landed.</p>
<p>South Korean authorities have described the most serious infiltration since the 1960s as a military provocation. North and South Korea have been technically at war since the 1950-53 Korean conflict ended in a truce.</p>
<p>On Thursday, troops shot dead seven agents and displayed their bullet-riddled bodies dressed in South Korean-made blue jeans and sneakers.</p>
<p>In Washington, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher urged &quot;all parties&quot; to avoid further provocative action. The United States has 37,000 troops stationed in the South.</p>
<p>&quot;We wish that all parties would refrain from taking further provocative actions,&quot; Christopher told a news conference.</p>
<p>Asked if the incident could affect efforts to provide Pyongyang with nuclear technology and humanitarian aid, he added: &quot;Obviously, the episode is a matter of concern but the facts are so murky.&quot;</p>
<p>North Korea is on the brink of famine following devastating floods and has appealed for international aid.</p>
<p>The United States is part of an international consortium providing the North with nuclear power plants as part of a deal to end the country's suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>In South Korea, the public has reacted with anger and anxiety to the infiltration. Some blame the navy for failing to detect the 34 metre (111 foot) submarine and worry the country is vulnerable to attack from its arch-enemy to the north.</p>
<p>Political analysts said the incident may have damaged the chances of peace on the Korean peninsula by giving ammunition to hardliners in Seoul, who oppose any concessions to the North.</p>
<p>South Korea and the United States are trying to entice Pyongyang to talks, along with China, to work out a peace pact to replace an armistice that sealed the division of the Korean peninsula in 1953.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
