<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68141" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: N.Koreans hunted around tunnels, four said dead.</title>
<headline>N.Koreans hunted around tunnels, four said dead.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>A massive search for North Korean infiltrators who landed by submarine in South Korea moved to an area of mine shafts on Friday, and news reports said four bodies had been found.</p>
<p>Fierce gunbattles raged through the night around the disused coal mines in rugged mountains near the east coast city of Kangnung, residents said.</p>
<p>Authorities initially said about 20 North Koreans sneaked in on Wednesday, but now say there may have been more.</p>
<p>So far, 18 infiltrators are confirmed to have been shot dead and one captured alive.</p>
<p>State television said four bodies were found on Friday, but the Korea Broadcasting System gave no further details.</p>
<p>A defence ministry spokesman in Seoul said he could not confirm the reports.</p>
<p>Munhwa Broadcasting System also reported four dead and said troops were searching for a fifth agent still on the loose after a squad of agents came ashore on a beach.</p>
<p>A military officer in Kangnung said security forces had found hollows in the ground where several agents may have spent the night.</p>
<p>&quot;I heard gunfire all night and grenades exploding,&quot; said local resident Chang Choon-taik.</p>
<p>Five or six helicopters were flying over the area, which is saturated with armed troops and located about 17 km (10 miles) from the beach where the agents landed.</p>
<p>South Korean authorities have described the most serious infiltration since the 1960s as a military provocation. North and South Korea have been technically at war since the 1950-53 Korean conflict ended in a truce.</p>
<p>On Thursday troops shot dead seven agents and displayed their bullet-riddled bodies dressed in South Korean-made blue jeans and sneakers.</p>
<p>In Washington, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher urged &quot;all parties&quot; to avoid further provocative action. The United States has 37,000 troops stationed in the South.</p>
<p>&quot;We wish that all parties would refrain from taking further provocative actions,&quot; Christopher told a news conference.</p>
<p>Asked if the incident could affect efforts to provide Pyongyang with nuclear technology and humanitarian aid, he added: &quot;Obviously the episode is a matter of concern but the facts are so murky.&quot;</p>
<p>He said it was impossible to assess the long-term impact of the incident.</p>
<p>North Korea is on the brink of famine following devastating floods and has appealed for international aid.</p>
<p>The United States is part of an international consortium providing the North with nuclear power plants as part of a deal to end the country's suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>In South Korea, the public has reacted with anger and anxiety to the infiltration. Some blame the navy for failing to detect the 34 metre (111 feet) submarine and worry the country is vulnerable to attack from its arch-enemy to the north.</p>
<p>Political analysts said the incident may have damaged the chances of peace on the Korean peninsula by giving ammunition to hardliners in Seoul, who oppose any concessions to the North.</p>
<p>South Korea and the United States are trying to entice Pyongyang to talks, along with China, to work out a peace pact to replace an armistice that sealed the division of the Korean peninsula in 1953.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
