<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68720" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korea soldier hit in helicopter chase for agents.</title>
<headline>S.Korea soldier hit in helicopter chase for agents.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>A South Korean paratrooper was shot in the head and killed during a helicopter chase for two North Korean agents across rugged mountains on Saturday, hospital officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;He died of head injuries,&quot; an official at a hospital in the east coast city of Kangnung said by telephone.</p>
<p>Television news reports said the 26-year-old sergeant was hit while being winched to the ground to pursue the two communist fugitives on foot.</p>
<p>A defence ministry official in Kangnung said another paratrooper on board the helicopter was also shot, but there were no details of his condition.</p>
<p>The agents are the remnants of a squad of about 26 infiltrators who landed by submarine in the early hours of Wednesday morning on a beach near Kangnung. So far 18 have been shot and killed and one captured alive.</p>
<p>There were several skirmishes on Saturday as a deadly game of cat-and-mouse was played out on mountains and ravines for a fourth day.</p>
<p>According to the testimony of the captured man, Lee Kwang-soo, the remaining fugitives include three saboteurs, two guides and two members of the submarine crew.</p>
<p>Loudspeakers on army jeeps boomed out a recorded message from Lee pleading with his colleagues to give themselves up.</p>
<p>&quot;I am alive and safe,&quot; according to the message, which echoed around mountain canyons. &quot;Our mission has already been finished. I want you to surrender and find a new life along with me in the Republic of Korea.&quot;</p>
<p>Media reports quoted Lee as telling interrogators the submarine, which ran aground on rocks, was the same vessel used to drop two other agents on South Korea's Cheju Island in September last year.</p>
<p>One of those agents was shot and killed in a clash with security forces on the South Korean mainland the following month and the other was captured.</p>
<p>Lee was also reported to have said a submarine pierced coastal defences in the Kangnung area last year.</p>
<p>There was speculation the saboteurs, elite operatives fanatically committed to Pyongyang leader Kim Jong-il, may have evaded the massive dragnet and could be on their way home.</p>
<p>&quot;We are expanding the area of our search operations to prevent them from returning to the North,&quot; the defence ministry official said.</p>
<p>Television pictures have been playing North Korean propaganda film of spy agents displaying awesome combat skills as frogmen, paratroopers and martial art fighters.</p>
<p>The old movie reels show muscular men being beaten with boards studded with nails and female operatives slicing bottles in half with flashing open-hand chops.</p>
<p>Terrified residents around Kangnung bolted their doors at night, and tourist hotels in the region have emptied ahead of the Korean Thanksgiving, the most important holiday in the calendar.</p>
<p>South Koreans have been jolted by the realisation that coastal defences they once thought were almost impregnable can so easily be evaded.</p>
<p>North Korean saboteurs would be in the first wave of any Northern invasion of the South, blowing up key facilities, such as radar installations, and spreading terror among civilians.</p>
<p>Complicating the search were reports that the suspected saboteurs were dressed in South Korean army uniforms and carrying M-16 rifles, standard issue among Southern defence forces.</p>
<p>South Korea's ambassador to the United Nations, Park Soo-kil, briefed Security Council members on the infiltration on Friday. Seoul has said it wants the council to take unspecified action against the North.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended with an armistice negotiated by U.S.-led United Nations forces.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
