<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68765" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Gunfire as North Korea agents play cat-and-mouse.</title>
<headline>Gunfire as North Korea agents play cat-and-mouse.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops skirmished with suspected North Korean saboteurs on Saturday as a deadly game of cat-and-mouse played out in mountains and ravines entered its fourth day.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Joint Chiefs of Staff said two fugitives had been trapped by Southern forces. &quot;There is a standoff,&quot; Kang Jun-kwon told reporters.</p>
<p>A defence ministry official in the east coast city of Kangnung said the men had been spotted by helicopters.</p>
<p>Earlier, exhausted military pursuers showed their frustration at being unable to capture the last of a squad of North Koreans who landed by submarine in the early hours of Wednesday on a beach near Kangnung.</p>
<p>&quot;Day and night searches and ambush operations have come up with nothing, not even traces of the guerrillas,&quot; the ministry official said.</p>
<p>Authorities now believe around 26 agents came ashore. So far 18 have been shot dead and one captured alive.</p>
<p>According to the testimony of the captured man, the remaining fugitives include three saboteurs, two guides and two members of the submarine crew.</p>
<p>There is speculation the saboteurs, elite operatives fanatically committed to Pyongyang leader Kim Jong-il, may have evaded a massive dragnet and could be on their way home.</p>
<p>&quot;We are expanding the area of our search operations to prevent them from returning to the North,&quot; the defence ministry official said.</p>
<p>Television pictures have been playing North Korean propaganda film of spy agents displaying awesome hand-to-hand combat skills. The old movie reels show bare-chested men smashing rocks with their fists, and female operatives slicing bottles in half with flashing open-hand chops.</p>
<p>Terrified local residents bolt their doors at night, and tourist hotels in the region have emptied ahead of the Korean Thanksgiving, the most important holiday in the calendar.</p>
<p>Their fears have been fanned by the testimony of the captured agent who indicated that North Koreans had in the past moved in and out of the area unchallenged.</p>
<p>South Koreans have been jolted by the realisation that coastal defences they once thought were almost impregnable can so easily be pierced.</p>
<p>North Korean saboteurs would be in the first wave of any Northern invasion of the South, blowing up key facilities, such as radar installations, and spreading terror among civilians.</p>
<p>Some would be infiltrated from submarines, such as the one that sneaked in this week but which grounded itself on a shallow reef, South Korean defence experts believe.</p>
<p>Complicating the search are reports that the suspected saboteurs are dressed in South Korean army uniforms and carrying M-16 rifles, standard issue among Southern defence forces.</p>
<p>South Korea's ambassador to the United Nations, Park Soo-kil, briefed Security Council members on the infiltration on Friday. Seoul has said it wants the council to take unspecified action against the North.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended with an armistice negotiated by U.S.-led United Nations forces.</p>
<p>The United States said on Friday it did not expect the incident would damage its landmark nuclear agreement with North Korea under which Pyongyang agreed to freeze its suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope very much and do not expect that this incident will affect ... the nuclear freeze that is in place in North Korea,&quot; State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Burns stressed: &quot;It's clear to the United States that this incursion represents a serious provocation by North Korea and is a violation of the armistice agreement.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
