<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68777" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel hits Lebanon, minister says attack &quot;necessary&quot;.</title>
<headline>Israel hits Lebanon, minister says attack &quot;necessary&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli jets and artillery blasted Hizbollah targets in south Lebanon on Saturday after an Israeli officer was wounded in clashes with Moslem guerrillas there, security sources said.</p>
<p>Israeli Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai said Saturday's strikes were &quot;necessary operations&quot; in retaliation for attacks on Israeli forces by Iranian-backed Hizbollah guerrillas.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying in every possible way to lower the tension in the region. we have no intention of taking extraordinary measures, but we have the obligation to take every necessary operation for the good of our forces working in Lebanon,&quot; Moedechai told Israel's Channel One television.</p>
<p>Israel occupies a belt of territory across southern Lebanon with Lebanese militia proxies and several hundred members of its own security forces ostensibly to protect the Jewish state's northern border from guerrilla assault.</p>
<p>Lebanese security sources said Israeli jets fired several rockets in four attacks into Lebanon's Mlita hill and Jabal Safi in Iqlim al-Toufah ridge which is used by Shi'ite Moslem Hizbollah (Party of God) fighters in operations against Israeli troops occupying the so-called security zone.</p>
<p>It was not immediately known if there were any casualties in the air raids and concurrent artillery bombardment of Iqlim al-Toufah which followed strikes against two Israeli outposts at Sojoud and Beir Kallab and forces stationed nearby.</p>
<p>Israel's army said an officer was wounded in an attack by Hizbollah guerrillas and confirmed the air raids, saying pilots reported accurate hits.</p>
<p>&quot;An Israel Defence Forces officer was lightly wounded this morning after an anti-tank missile was fired at an IDF force which was operating in the north of the eastern sector of the south Lebanon security zone,&quot; the Israeli army said.</p>
<p>&quot;The officer was taken to hospital for treatment. The IDF and SLA returned fire,&quot; it added in a statement.</p>
<p>Pro-Israeli South Lebanon Army (SLA) militia sources said the guerrillas fired mortar bombs and anti-tank rockets.</p>
<p>In Beirut, Hizbollah claimed responsibility for the assault, saying its fighters hit a tank and attacked the Sojoud and Beir Kallab posts.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Israeli jets raided Iqlim al-Toufah hills and artillery bombarded the area, including Hizbollah-held villages, in retaliation for a Hizbollah attack that killed two Israeli soldiers and wounded eight.</p>
<p>Hizbollah fighters, who have killed 20 Israelis this year in south Lebanon, are battling to oust Israel and allied forces from the 15-km (nine-miles) zone they have occupied since 1982.</p>
<p>Saturday's clashes came a day before a scheduled meeting of a five-nation committee monitoring a ceasefire understanding -- which ended a 17-day Israeli blitz on Lebanon in April -- to look into Israeli and Lebanese complaints.</p>
<p>Lebanon has filed a complaint that Israel shelled civilian areas on Thursday. Israel said it would complain the guerrillas fired on its forces from inside three villages.</p>
<p>According to witnesses, some 50 shells slammed inside the villages of Ain Bouswar and Jba'a on Thursday, wounding a civilian woman in Jba'a who was hurt by debris.</p>
<p>Representatives of the United States, France, Syria, Lebanon and Israel will meet on Sunday in the south Lebanon town of Naqoura.</p>
<p>Some 200 Lebanese, mostly civilians, were killed in the April onslaught, dubbed by Israel &quot;Operation Grapes of Wrath&quot;, after tit-for-tat bombardments of civilian areas by both sides.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
