<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69276" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>south korea: Seoul troops say they killed sub's captain.</title>
<headline>Seoul troops say they killed sub's captain.</headline>
<byline>Yun Suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The captain of a grounded North Korean submarine was tracked down by South Korean troops in east coast mountains on Sunday and killed in a gun battle, South Korea's armed forces reported.</p>
<p>The shootout was one of two during the night in the army's manhunt through the thickly-bushed mountains for infilrators from the submarine.</p>
<p>Another infiltrator, dressed in a South Korean army uniform, and two soldiers died in the clashes, a Defence Ministry spokesman said in the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>Security forces also located a third suspected North Korean agent trapped in a hill near the scene of an earlier gunfight and were tightening their net, he said.</p>
<p>The spokesman said that in one shootout last night, a Northern agent and a Southern soldier were killed.</p>
<p>Another Northern infiltrator was killed in a separate gunbattle at dawn, after which a second South Korean soldier died while being rushed to a military hospital, he said.</p>
<p>The ministry official said one of the two North Koreans to be killed was believed to be the captain of the submarine which ran aground off the coast close to the city on Wednesday, carrying an estimated 26 Northern agents.</p>
<p>The other, wearing a Southern army uniform, was identified as a guide, he said, adding a rifle and a grenade were found at the scene. The captain was dressed in civilian clothes.</p>
<p>The latest casualties brought to nine the number of North Koreans killed by Southern forces in five days of a massive hunt for the communist infiltrators.</p>
<p>Eleven other agents were found shot dead, possibly killed by their colleagues, and one was captured alive.</p>
<p>A total of three Southern troops have now been reported killed in a deadly game of cat-and-mouse over mountain trails.</p>
<p>A Southern paratrooper was killed on Saturday. According to some reports he was hit while dangling on a winch line from a helicopter that was lowering him to the ground. Another paratrooper was injured.</p>
<p>The ministry official said the North Korean submarine was being towed by South Korean naval ships to Tonghae port, about 30 km (19 miles) south of Kangnung, for further inspection.</p>
<p>Thousands of troops backed by helicopters have been engaged in a massive hunt to end one of the deadlist operations from the enemy North since the early Cold War.</p>
<p>South and North Korea have remained technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended with an armistice agreement.</p>
<p>Details of the Northern infiltration remain confused, although the Defence Ministry believes that the agents included three elite saboteurs. These three may have been responsible for the execution-style killings of the 11 on Wednesday in a ruthless bid to improve their own survival chances.</p>
<p>Authorities trying to unravel the mystery of the mission -- which ran into serious trouble when the submarine grounded on a reef -- are relying on statements from the captured North Korean agent, who has changed his story several times.</p>
<p>A senior intelligence official at the Joint Chiefs of Staffs denied some earlier news reports that the North Korean submarine was loaded with high explosives and artillery pieces, suggesting the mission could have been intended to stage a terrorist-style attack or destroy key facilities.</p>
<p>&quot;We could not find any such items,&quot; Suh Tae-sok said. But he added that a thorough search of the vessel would be carried out by a joint U.S.-South Korean investigation team later.</p>
<p>The Hankook Ilbo newspaper had earlier quoted Lee Kwang-soo, the captured North Korean man, as telling interrogators the explosives may have been thrown into the sea or hidden on land.</p>
<p>A Defence Ministry statement showed that a total of 1,126 items of belongings of the North Korean agents have so far been siezed during the five-day manhunt operations.</p>
<p>The belongings include two rifles, two pistols, some 900 rounds of ammunition, radios, canned food, a life jacket and two South Korean army uniforms.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
