<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69282" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Two S.Korean soldiers, two agents dead in shootout.</title>
<headline>Two S.Korean soldiers, two agents dead in shootout.</headline>
<byline>Yun suk-bong</byline>
<dateline>KANGNUNG, South Korea 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>One South Korean soldier and two North Korean infiltrators were killed on Sunday during a fierce shootout in rugged east coast mountains, a defence ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>A second Southern soldier later died of his injuries after the clash at dawn.</p>
<p>The latest casualties bring to nine the number of North Koreans killed by Southern forces in a hunt for an estimated 26 communist agents who landed by submarine on Wednesday on a beach near the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>Eleven other agents were found shot dead, possibly killed by their colleagues, and one was captured alive.</p>
<p>A total of three Southern troops have now been reported killed in a deadly game of cat-and-mouse over mountain trails covered with thick vegetation.</p>
<p>A Southern paratrooper was killed on Saturday. According to some reports he was hit while dangling on a winch line from a helicopter that was lowering him to the ground. Another paratrooper was injured.</p>
<p>An army officer in Kangnung said one of the North Koreans killed on Sunday was wearing a Southern army uniform while the other was in civilian clothes. He said a rifle and a grenade were found at the scene.</p>
<p>Thousands of troops backed by helicopters have been engaged in a massive manhunt to end one of the deadlist operations from the enemy North since the early Cold War.</p>
<p>South and North Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended only with an armistice agreement.</p>
<p>Details of the Northern infiltration remain confused, although the defence ministry believes that among the agents were three elite saboteurs, and they may have been responsible for the execution-style killings of the 11 on Wednesday in a ruthless bid to improve their own survival chances.</p>
<p>Authorities trying to unravel the mystery of the mission -- which ran into serious trouble when the submarine grounded on a reef -- are relying on statements from the captured North Korean agent, who has changed his story several times.</p>
<p>The Hankook Ilbo daily on Sunday quoted agent Lee Kwang-soo as telling interrogators the team carried high explosives.</p>
<p>It said this suggested the mission could be have been intended to carry out a terrorist-style attack or to destroy important facilities.</p>
<p>Lee was quoted as saying the explosives may have been thrown into the sea or hidden on land.</p>
<p>Other newspapers focussed on what appeared to be sloppy methods adopted by North Koreans, whose past missions have often been meticulous, and clinically violent.</p>
<p>After abandoning their stricken submarine, they initially left a trail of personal belongings, including keys and clothes, and a life jacket that betrayed their movements.</p>
<p>Two of them barged into a villager's home and stole cigarettes and food at gunpoint, and then left leaving the owner shaken but unharmed. Hardened commandos might have silently killed civilians to cover their tracks.</p>
<p>The three infiltrators shot on Thursday had no survival equipment, wore jeans and sneakers, and had only one pistol between them. Media reports said a taxi driver found them sitting on a rock smoking cigarettes.</p>
<p>One explanation is that some of the agents were members of the submarine crew who never intended to come ashore.</p>
<p>Yonhap news agency quoted investigators as saying they had recovered two artillery pieces with a range of 8 km (5 miles), an anti-tank recoilless gun and a Czech-made machinegun after a thorough search of the submarine.</p>
<p>Divers had successfully removed a timebomb attached to the bottom of the vessel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANGNUNG, South Korea"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
