<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70329" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Seoul dismisses Pyongyang's submarine story.</title>
<headline>Seoul dismisses Pyongyang's submarine story.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Browne</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea said on Monday a submarine found stranded off South Korea last week had drifted there after engine failure, and it demanded the return of the vessel and crew, including bodies of those killed.</p>
<p>It was Pyongyang's first direct comment on a drama that started on Wednesday when an estimated 26 North Koreans came ashore on an east coast beach near the city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>Southern forces have killed nine intruders, found the bodies of 11 believed killed by their own colleagues, captured one North Korean alive, and lost three of their men. One civilian was also killed accidentally by Southern forces as they continued hunting five North Koreans thought still on the loose.</p>
<p>South Korea dismissed Pyongyang's explanation and maintained the intrusion was a military provocation.</p>
<p>&quot;The North Korean explanation about the vessel is nonsense. It is not worthy of consideration,&quot; a defence ministry spokesman told a news conference. &quot;It is nothing but North Korea's habitual deceiptful policy to defuse critism.</p>
<p>&quot;The intrusion was a carefully planned infiltration.&quot;</p>
<p>A statement by Pyongyang's Ministry of the People's Armed Forces carried by the Korea Central News Agency said the vessel was on a routine training mission when it developed engine trouble and ended up on rocks off Kangnung.</p>
<p>&quot;It seemed that its crew were left with no other choice but to get to the enemy side's land, which might cause an armed conflict,&quot; the poorly-worded statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The South side must unconditionally return to the North the submarine and its crew including the dead bodies at once.&quot;</p>
<p>The statement said the submarine carried no heavy weapons and there were only small arms on board.</p>
<p>However, the South Korean Joint Chief of Staff said a rocket launcher had been found on board.</p>
<p>North and South Korea have been technically at war since an armistice ended the 1950-53 Korean conflict and sealed the partition of the peninsula.</p>
<p>South Korea's parliament brushed aside Pyongyang's protestations of innocence and in a rare display of political unity adopted unanimously a resolution condemning the North.</p>
<p>&quot;The act of infiltrating armed troops by a military submarine is not simply an espionage activity but an explicit military provocation and can never be tolerated,&quot; the 299-member National Assembly declared.</p>
<p>It called on the international community &quot;to recognise the reality that the Cold War still persists on the Korean Peninsula and to cooperate in deterring North Korea's aggressive acts&quot;.</p>
<p>In a veiled criticism of the military's handling of the intrusion, the resolution urged the government to take measures to respond to guerrilla operations more quickly and restore the public's trust.</p>
<p>The mission to hunt down the intruders claimed its first civilian fatality when South Korean troops accidentally killed a man clambering up a mountain in search of wild mushrooms, a military official said.</p>
<p>The 56-year-old man was shot in an area where gunbattles had raged sporadically throughout the night.</p>
<p>Two South Korean soldiers were wounded and taken to hospital during the gunbattles, the official said.</p>
<p>President Kim Young-sam visited a mortuary to pay respects to the three Southern soldiers killed in the hunt. He burned incense and paid condolences to bereaved relatives.</p>
<p>In Kangnung, more than 5,000 citizens led by the major staged a rally to denounce the incursion, which has ruined the area's all-important tourist industry ahead of the Korean Thanksgiving holiday.</p>
<p>South Korea is trying to drum up an international campaign against Pyongyang over the incident, one of the deadliest incursions from the North since the early Cold War. It has urged the U.N. Security Council to take action.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
