<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70633" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>DENMARK: Perry dismisses North Korea submarine explanation.</title>
<headline>Perry dismisses North Korea submarine explanation.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>COPENHAGEN 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry on Monday dismissed North Korea's claim that its submarine was on a routine mission when it went aground off South Korea.</p>
<p>But he urged both countries to ease what has become an international shooting incident.</p>
<p>&quot;All of our evidence suggests that this North Korean submarine was not on a routine, mission, and so I would reject the North Korean explanation of the mission,&quot; Perry said of the incident, in which South Korea has shot to death several reported North Korean infiltrators.</p>
<p>Perry spoke at a news conference in Stockholm before flying to Denmark. Pentagon spokesman Ken Bacon told reporters it was not clear what the sub was doing, but that its presence was a provocative act and had raised tensions on the peninsula, where the United States has 37,000 troops.</p>
<p>North Korea said the submarine suffered engine trouble on a routine mission and that the sub ended up on rocks off the South Korean coast last Wednesday. Pyongyang on Monday demanded unconditional return of the sub and the bodies of a number of North Koreans shot to death in South Korea.</p>
<p>But Seoul said it was a carefully-planned and provocative spy mission on the Korean peninsula, one of the most heavily- defended areas on earth since the Korean War.</p>
<p>Southern forces have killed nine intruders, found the bodies of 11 believed killed by their own colleagues, captured one North Korean alive, and lost three of their men.</p>
<p>In Stockholm, Perry urged restraint by both Seoul and Pyongyang.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important to not let this incident escalate and that we want both parties to work to try to keep this from becoming an incident beyond the damage that has already been caused,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;In particular, we still believe it is important to proceed with four-power talks which we proposed some months ago to try to reach finally a peace agreement on the Korean peninsula.&quot;</p>
<p>Washington and Seoul jointly proposed the talks to include North Korea and China, but the plan has been so far rejected by the North.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not routine to find crashed submarines on the rocks and North Koreans ashore,&quot; Bacon told reporters travelling with the secretary aboard his aircraft to Denmark.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't know exactly what was happening,&quot; he said, adding that there no immediate evidence whether or not it involved a North Korean military mission against the South.</p>
<p>Bacon and other U.S. officials said they feared that the incident could slow or derail the process under which North Korea is changing its nuclear power programme to reactors which Washington says will be less likely to provide Pyongyang with material for nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>&quot;This is damaging. It will be damaging to the whole process,&quot; said Bacon.</p>
<p>Bacon said that the United States did not put its troops in the area on alert after the incident. South Korea did.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COPENHAGEN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DENMARK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
