<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70650" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>DENMARK: Perry urges calm in Korea sub incident.</title>
<headline>Perry urges calm in Korea sub incident.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>COPENHAGEN 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry on Monday dismissed North Korea's claim that its submarine was on a routine mission when it went aground off South Korea.</p>
<p>If such an infiltration mission were routine, &quot;it is even more unacceptable,&quot; added Perry's spokesman Ken Bacon.</p>
<p>But the defence secretary urged calm on the peninsula in what has become an international shooting incident.</p>
<p>&quot;All of our evidence suggests that this North Korean submarine was not on a routine, mission, and so I would reject the North Korean explanation of the mission,&quot; Perry said of the incident, in which the South Koreans have shot to death nine intruders.</p>
<p>Perry spoke at a news conference in Stockholm before flying to Denmark on a Scandanavian trip. Pentagon spokesman Ken Bacon later told reporters travelling with Perry that the incident had raised tensions on the peninsula, where the United States has stationed 37,000 troops.</p>
<p>&quot;This appears to be an effort either to bring people in to infiltrate or to bring somebody out that they had taken in earlier. So to call it a routine training mission is completely unacceptable,&quot; said Bacon.</p>
<p>He said the information was coming from the South Koreans, perhaps from a captured North Korean, and that the United States had no direct evidence in the incident which began last Wednesday.</p>
<p>South Korean forces have killed nine intruders, found the bodies of 11 believed killed by their own colleagues, captured one North Korean alive and lost three of their men.</p>
<p>North Korea said the submarine suffered engine trouble on a routine mission and that the sub ended up on rocks off the South Korean coast. Pyongyang on Monday demanded unconditional return of the sub and the bodies of the North Koreans.</p>
<p>But Seoul said it was a carefully-planned and provocative spy mission on the Korean peninsula, one of the most heavily- armed areas on earth since the Korean War.</p>
<p>In Stockholm, Perry urged restraint by both Seoul and Pyongyang on the troubled peninsula.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important to not let this incident escalate and that we want both parties to work to try to keep this from becoming an incident beyond the damage that has already been caused,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;In particular, we still believe it is imortant to proceed with four-power talks whichb we proposed some months ago to try to reach finally a peace agreement on the Korean oeninsula.&quot;</p>
<p>Washington and Seoul jointly proposed the talks to include North Korea and China, but the plan has been so far rejected by the North.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not routine to find crashed submarines on the rocks and North Koreans ashore,&quot; Bacon told reporters travelling with the secretary aboard his aircraft to Denmark.</p>
<p>Bacon and other U.S. officials said they feared that the incident could slow or derail the process under which North Korea is changing its nuclear power programme to reactors which Washington says will be less likely to provide Pyongyang with material for nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>&quot;This is damaging. It will be damaging to the whole process,&quot; said Bacon.</p>
<p>Bacon said that the United States did not put its troops in the area on alert after the incident. South Korea did.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COPENHAGEN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DENMARK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
