<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="71676" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: North Korea demands return of submarine and crew.</title>
<headline>North Korea demands return of submarine and crew.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Browne</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea demanded on Monday the immediate return of a submarine, which it said had strayed accidently into South Korean waters, along with its crew and the bodies of those shot dead.</p>
<p>It was Pyongyang's first direct statement on a drama that began on Wednesday when an estimated 26 North Koreans landed by submarine on an east coast beach near the city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>South Korea has described the incident as an armed provocation.</p>
<p>A statement carried by North Korea's official Korea Central News Agency said the submarine was on a training mission and had drifted into South Korean waters after developing engine trouble.</p>
<p>&quot;The South side must unconditionally return to the North the submarine and its crew including the dead bodies at once,&quot; the spokesman for the Ministry of the People's Armed Forces said in a statement.</p>
<p>So far, Southern forces have killed nine infiltrators and found bodies of 11 others believed to have been killed by their own colleagues. One has been captured alive and a hunt is underway for five thought to be still on the loose.</p>
<p>&quot;A training small submarine of a Korean People's Army unit which left Wonsan port on September 13 and engaged in a routine training on the North's East Sea of Korea might drift about with an engine trouble and strike a rock on the sea off Kangnung,&quot; the poorly-worded statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;It seemed that its crew were left with no other choice but to get to the enemy side's land, which might cause an armed conflict.&quot;</p>
<p>The submarine carried no heavy weapons and there were only small arms on board, according to the statement, which matched in important detail the account given to interrogators by the captured North Korean.</p>
<p>The captured agent also said engine trouble was to blame.</p>
<p>Seoul has said it found heavy artillery on board the submarine, and the defence ministry has speculated the vessel may have been engaged in a commando exercise, possibly to blow up key installations.</p>
<p>South Korean troops shot dead a civilian by mistake on Monday as a massive manhunt entered its sixth day, a military official said.</p>
<p>Kang Chang-shik told a news conference the victim, a 56-year-old man, was spotted by security forces just after dawn walking up a mountain near an area where clashes had occurred sporadically during the night.</p>
<p>&quot;He was going to pick wild mushrooms,&quot; Kang said. &quot;Troops opened fire after sighting him.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Military authorities express regret and again urge all residents within the areas to refrain from moving at night and abide by the night curfew and all recommendations offered by the authorities.&quot;</p>
<p>Kang said two South Korean soldiers were injured and taken to hospital during the overnight gun battles.</p>
<p>It was the first civilian fatality in the manhunt involving tens of thousands of troops and police. Three South Korean troops have also been killed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
