<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72873" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Sub has not sunk North Korean nuclear deal - U.S.</title>
<headline>Sub has not sunk North Korean nuclear deal - U.S.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Worsnip</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States believes it makes sense to go forward with a nuclear deal with Pyongyang despite a North Korean submarine incursion into the South, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We think the nuclear agreement is an extremely important agreement,&quot; Christopher said. &quot;It remains in the interests of both countries and indeed the region as a whole ... for North Korea not to go ahead with a nuclear programme.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We would expect to maintain that freeze and maintain the framework,&quot; Christopher told reporters before a meeting with South Korean Foreign Minister Gong Ro-mung.</p>
<p>Under the October 1994 deal, Pyongyang agreed to halt its nuclear programme, suspected by U.S. intelligence of having created enough plutonium for one or two weapons, in return for modern reactors less able to produce nuclear fuel.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said the Christopher-Gong meeting would focus on an incident last Wednesday in which a submarine from North Korea dropped commandos on a South Korean beach in what South Korean President Kim Young-sam called a military provocation.</p>
<p>The U.S. Defence Department condemned North Korea on Tuesday for the incident, a day after Defence Secretary William Perry rejected in Stockholm, Sweden, Pyongyang's suggestion the submarine ran aground in South Korea accidentally.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's clear from the incursion that this represents a serious provocation, and it's a violation of the (July 27, 1953) armistice agreement,&quot; Captain Michael Doubleday, a spokesman, said. &quot;We condemn it.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The crew, the equipment, the mission profile of the submarine provide overwhelming evidence that it was involved in a hostile and provocative mission against the Republic of (South) Korea,&quot; Doubleday said.</p>
<p>Despite the anger the incident has created in Seoul, Gong told reporters his government had not yet decided whether to ask the United States to resume annual joint military exercises in the South.</p>
<p>South Korea's Defence Ministry said on Tuesday that Seoul would seek to restart the Team Spirit exercises, dropped last year as part of the landmark nuclear deal.</p>
<p>&quot;To my knowledge, we haven't requested resumption of this joint military manoeuvre yet,&quot; Gong said. &quot;I think this has to be first decided within the government, and then I think we have to make consultations with the United States if we so decide.&quot;</p>
<p>Gong said that once &quot;mopping-up&quot; operations had been completed, South Korea and the United States would consult on whether to take &quot;additional steps&quot; at the U.N. Security Council. He did not say what steps might be discussed.</p>
<p>&quot;This incident clearly shows that no genuine peace and security on the Korean peninsula will be achievable without North Korea's acceptance of peaceful coexistence, no matter what progress is made between United States and North Korea.&quot;</p>
<p>Christopher said the nuclear deal was going well. Almost half of North Korea's spent fuel has been safely stored and an international consortium has raised more than $90 million from 20 countries toward the cost of the new reactors, he said.</p>
<p>But he stressed that the United States would continue to stand together with South Korea in the face of any threat to the armistice agreement that ended the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
<p>Earlier President Bill Clinton said in a speech to the U.N. General Assembly that after North Korea's &quot;provocative actions,&quot; it was important to pursue peace for all Koreans.</p>
<p>North Korea has yet to respond definitively to a proposal made in April by Clinton and Kim for four-party talks on a permanent Korean settlement.</p>
<p>Christopher and Gong met on the sidelines of the current U.N. General Assembly session, which both men are attending.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
