<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72888" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. condemns Pyongyang sub as provocation.</title>
<headline>U.S. condemns Pyongyang sub as provocation.</headline>
<byline>Jim Adams</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States condemned North Korea on Tuesday for what it called the hostile provocation of infiltrating South Korea with a submarine, and said it was willing to consider renewing U.S.-South Korea war games.</p>
<p>Defence Secretary William Perry rejected in Stockholm, Sweden, on Monday North Korea's suggestion the submarine ran aground in South Korea accidentally, and the Defence Department followed up Tuesday with the condemnation.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's clear from the incursion that this represents a serious provocation, and it's a violation of the (July 27, 1953) armistice agreement,&quot; Capt. Michael Doubleday, a spokesman, said. &quot;We condemn it.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The crew, the equipment, the mission profile of the submarine provide overwhelming evidence that it was involved in a hostile and provocative mission against the Republic of (South) Korea,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The submarine ran aground off a rugged mountain area off South Korea's east coast last Wednesday, setting off a manhunt in which South Korean security forces have killed nine of the 26 North Koreans aboard and captured one. Eleven were dead at the scene and five were believed to be on the run.</p>
<p>North Korea said the submarine was on a routine training mission when it ran aground. The country demanded the vessel's return.</p>
<p>South Korea's defence ministry said Tuesday that Seoul would try to restart U.S.-South Korea war games as a response. The State Department said it was willing to consider the idea.</p>
<p>&quot;No, of course not. Of course we're not ruling it out,&quot; State Department deputy spokesman Glyn Davies said in response to a question.</p>
<p>He said no decision was expected until later in the year and after consultations with Seoul. The war games have been suspended since 1993 in an effort to calm Korea tensions.</p>
<p>South Korean President Kim Young-sam was reported by Seoul media to be considering policy changes toward North Korea.</p>
<p>But Davies said that so far there has been no formal request to Washington for a change in major policies toward Pyongyang, including a landmark nuclear deal and a U.S.-South Korean proposal for four-way talks with North Korea and China.</p>
<p>The nuclear deal remains in force and the peace talks proposal remains on the table, without a formal response from North Korea, according to U.S. officials.</p>
<p>Perry dismissed Pyongyang's explanation on Monday during a stop in Stockholm but at the same time urged both North and South Korea not to let the incident escalate.</p>
<p>Pentagon spokesman Ken Bacon told reporters travelling with Perry on a Scandanavian trip that the incident had raised tensions on the peninsula, where the United States has stationed 37,000 troops.</p>
<p>&quot;This appears to be an effort either to bring people in to infiltrate or to bring somebody out that they had taken in earlier. So to call it a routine training mission is completely unacceptable,&quot; Bacon said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
