<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74091" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: South Korean defence ministry proposes war games.</title>
<headline>South Korean defence ministry proposes war games.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Browne</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>In an angry response to an incursion by a North Korean submarine last week, South Korea's defence ministry said on Tuesday that Seoul would seek to restart war games with the United States.</p>
<p>A ministry statement represented a potentially grave escalation of a drama that began on Wednesday when 26 North Koreans came ashore from a grounded submarine.</p>
<p>The Team Spirit military exercises were dropped last year as part of a landmark deal between the United States and North Korea under which Pyongyang agreed to scrap its suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>Restarting them could endanger the agreement, the cornerstone of U.S. President Bill Clinton's policy of cautious engagement with Pyongyang's communist government.</p>
<p>&quot;We plan to strongly propose to the U.S. side resuming the joint Team Spirit exercises as soon as possible,&quot; the defence ministry statement said.</p>
<p>The statement appeared to be at odds with official U.S. comments on the intrusion, which have condemned North Korea over the incident but urged restraint.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry on Monday urged both sides to try to limit the damage.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important to not let this incident escalate and that we want both parties to work to try to keep this from becoming an incident beyond the damage that has already been caused,&quot; Perry told reporters in Stockholm.</p>
<p>The U.S. maintains 37,000 troops in South Korea as a deterrent against any Northern attack. It is anxious to prevent the incident from endangering a proposal Washington and Seoul have put to Pyongyang for four-way peace talks, also including China.</p>
<p>Pyongyang had denounced the exercises, held each year since 1976, as being preparations for a nuclear attack.</p>
<p>&quot;North Korea's deliberate military provocation in the east coast has challenged efforts by South Korea and the United States to ease tensions on the peninsula,&quot; the defence ministry statement said.</p>
<p>The proposal to restart the war games would be made in a security meeting in Washington from October 31 to November 1 attended by South Korean defence minister Lee Yang-ho and U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry.</p>
<p>It was unclear whether the defence ministry statement represented official South Korean government policy.</p>
<p>An earlier statement issued by the Foreign Minstry, traditionally more dovish on North Korea policy, made no mention of reactivating Team Spirit.</p>
<p>It said a meeting on Tuesday between Foreign Minister Gong Ro-myung, defence minister Lee Yang-ho and the U.S. ambassador to Seoul, James Laney, had agreed the incursion was a flagrant violation of the armistice agreement that ended the 1950-53 Korean War and a threat to Korean security.</p>
<p>Participants at the meeting, including the commander of U.S. forces in South Korea, John Tilelli, decided on the need for unspecified &quot;strong measures&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Both sides agreed to take strong measures to dissuade North Korea from the anachronistic illusion of unifying the Korean peninsula by military means,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The U.S. and South Korea had agreed to keep a &quot;higher degree of vigilance&quot;, the statement added.</p>
<p>Of the 26 North Koreans that came ashore, nine have been killed by South Korean forces, 11 were found shot dead -- possibly murdered by their own colleagues -- and five are thought to be still on the run.</p>
<p>Three South Korean soldiers and a civilian have also been killed in a manhunt involving tens of thousands of troops and police backed by helicopters.</p>
<p>The decision to scrap Team Spirit exercises was announced in February last year after the nuclear agreement was signed in Geneva in October 1994.</p>
<p>Under the Geneva accord, an international consortium agreed to supply North Korea with two light-water nuclear reactors plus interim fuel supplies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
