<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74189" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: South Korea plans to restart war games with U.S..</title>
<headline>South Korea plans to restart war games with U.S..</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea, responding angrily to last week's incursion by a North Korean submarine, said on Tuesday it would propose restarting joint war games with the United States as soon as possible.</p>
<p>The Team Spirit military exercises were suspended last year as a peace gesture to encourage Pyongyang to keep its side of a deal with Washington to scrap its suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>Pyongyang had denounced the exercises, held each year since 1976, as being preparation for an invasion.</p>
<p>&quot;We plan to strongly propose to the U.S. side resuming the joint Team Spirit exercises as soon as possible,&quot; a defence ministry statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;North Korea's deliberate military provocation in the east coast has challenged efforts by South Korea and the United States to ease tensions on the peninsula,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>An estimated 26 North Koreans came ashore from the submarine found grounded on rocks off the east coast city of Kangnung last Wednesday. Twenty have been shot and killed, one captured alive and a hunt is under way for another five.</p>
<p>&quot;The recent incursion has revealed the real motive behind its demand to scrap the exerises,&quot; the statement added.</p>
<p>The proposal to restart the war games would be made in a security meeting in Washington from October 31 to November 1 attended by South Korean defence minister Lee Yang-ho and U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry, the statement said.</p>
<p>North Korea on Monday said the submarine strayed into Southern waters after developing engine trouble while on a training exercise. It demanded the immediate return of the vessel and crew, including bodies of those killed.</p>
<p>South Korea maintains the incident was a carefully-planned military infiltration.</p>
<p>The decision to scrap Team Spirit exercises was announced in February last year after the nuclear agreement was signed in Geneva in October 1994.</p>
<p>Under the Geneva accord, an international consortium agreed to supply North Korea with two light-water nuclear reactors plus interim fuel supplies.</p>
<p>The defence ministry statement said the Team Spirit exercises were essential to maintain a strong defence against the North and would deter future sea incursions.</p>
<p>Team Sprit was replaced by smaller-scale exercises codenamed Foal Eagle. They involved the majority of the 37,000 U.S. troops stationed in South Korea and 655,000 South Korean troops.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
