<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75414" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Seoul sends mixed signals over submarine incursion.</title>
<headline>Seoul sends mixed signals over submarine incursion.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>A deadly incursion by a North Korean submarine has exposed uncertainty in South Korea over how to handle the Pyongyang threat, Western diplomats said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>They said a series of seemingly contradictory signals has highlighted divisions within the government over relations with the communist North.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, the ministries of defence and foreign affairs appeared to be at odds, and President Kim Young-sam suggested a policy change on North Korea may be imminent</p>
<p>The Defence Ministry issued a statement saying that Seoul would seek to reactivate Korean-U.S. war games.</p>
<p>The annual Team Spirit games, which involved up to two million troops, including Korean reservists, were halted to help defuse a nuclear crisis.</p>
<p>Scrapping Team Spirit smoothed the way for the 1994 agreement between Washington and Pyongyang under which North Korea agreed to halt its suspected nuclear weapons programme.</p>
<p>However, several hours after the Defence Ministry announcement, South Korean Foreign Minister Gong Ro-myung said in New York that nothing had been decided, and in any case, such a move would require consulations with Washington.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, a Defence Ministry spokesman said: &quot;Our decision has yet to be finalised after consultations with related parties of the government.&quot;</p>
<p>Also perplexing were President Kim's comments to Japanese journalists, reported in the local media.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm seriously considering reviewing our policy toward North Korea,&quot; Kim was quoted as saying, but without elaboration.</p>
<p>Kim's comments flew in the face of emphatic assertions by the Foreign Ministry that last week's incursion by the submarine, which put 26 North Koreans ashore, would not change Seoul's basic stand towards the North.</p>
<p>&quot;There is confusion,&quot; said one Western envoy.</p>
<p>Doves in the Foreign Ministry and hawks in the Defence Ministry have long tussled over North Korea policy, according to diplomats.</p>
<p>The hawks have been strengthened by an anti-Pyongyang mood sweeping South Korea following violent leftist protests at a Seoul university campus last month.</p>
<p>&quot;The tide is clearly anti-North Korea at the moment,&quot; said another diplomat.</p>
<p>But he added: &quot;Peaceful unification, dialogue and the occasional gesture of support for North Korea is the only policy South Korean can follow.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They will talk tough but still continue a policy of engagement.&quot;</p>
<p>Kang Suk-seung, a North Korea expert at the Ministry of Unification, said Seoul would continue to press for a &quot;soft-landing&quot; for North Korea, which is beset by crippling food and energy shortages.</p>
<p>The collapse of North Korea would be a shattering blow to the South Korean economy.</p>
<p>&quot;This incident would not bear a drastic change in the government's unification policy to seek a political and economic soft-landing in North Korea,&quot; Kang said.</p>
<p>Of the 26 infiltrators, nine have been killed by South Korean security forces, 11 were found shot dead, possibly murdered by their own colleagues, one was captured and five are thought to be still on the run.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the Defence Ministry reported a fourth South Korean fatality, an army corporal who died in hospital after being wounded in a gunbattle on Monday.</p>
<p>A joint funeral service for the other three soldiers was held in a military hospital in Seoul on Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
