<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78520" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: North Korea vows &quot;strong&quot; measures over killings.</title>
<headline>North Korea vows &quot;strong&quot; measures over killings.</headline>
<byline>Teruaki Ueno</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea said on Thursday that it would take &quot;strong&quot; measures against South Korea for killing North Koreans who landed in the South from a submarine last week.</p>
<p>The decision was made at an emergency meeting of the North Korean government, political parties and other organisations, the official Korean Central News Agency (KCNA) reported.</p>
<p>&quot;The meeting adopted a decision to take a strong counter-measure against the dangerous acts of the Kim Young-sam regime,&quot; KCNA said in a report monitored in Tokyo.</p>
<p>&quot;The meeting participants bitterly denounced the South Korean puppets for brutally killing soldiers of the Korean People's Army who could not but go ashore in Kangrung, South Korea, after an accident during their regular training on September 18,&quot; KCNA said.</p>
<p>&quot;The South Korean puppets should be made to pay dearly for that, it was stressed at the meeting,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The broadcast did not specify what measures might be taken.</p>
<p>An estimated 26 North Koreans went ashore in South Korea from a submarine on Wednesday last week. Nine have since been killed by South Korean security forces, 11 were found shot dead -- possibly murdered by their own colleagues -- and one was captured. South Korean authorities have been searching for the others.</p>
<p>Thousands of troops backed by helicopters have been engaged in a massive manhunt to end one of the deadliest North-South clashes since early in the Cold War.</p>
<p>In its first direct statement on the incident, North Korea demanded on Monday the immediate return of the submarine -- which it said had strayed accidentally into South Korean waters -- along with its crew and the bodies of those shot dead.</p>
<p>Seoul immediately dismissed North Korea's explanation for the incursion as &quot;not worthy of consideration&quot;.</p>
<p>While urging both sides to calm down, U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry also dismissed North Korea's claim.</p>
<p>&quot;All of our evidence suggests that this North Korean submarine was not on a routine mission, and so I would reject the North Korean explanation of the mission,&quot; he said on Monday.</p>
<p>South and North Korea have been technically at war since their 1950-53 conflict ended only with an armistice agreement.</p>
<p>In an angry response to the incursion, South Korea's Defence Ministry said on Tuesday that Seoul would seek to restart war games with the United States.</p>
<p>The &quot;Team Spirit&quot; military exercises were dropped last year as part of a landmark 1994 deal between the United States and North Korea, under which Pyongyang has agreed to scrap a nuclear programme Washington believes is intended for weapons' production.</p>
<p>Reviving the war games could endanger the nuclear agreement, the cornerstone of U.S. President Bill Clinton's policy of cautious engagement with Pyongyang's communist government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
