<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82870" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: N.Korea warns retaliation if sub crew not returned.</title>
<headline>N.Korea warns retaliation if sub crew not returned.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea will exercise its &quot;right to retaliate&quot; if South Korea fails to return a submarine and its surviving and dead crew members that landed in the South last week, Pyongyang's official media said on Friday.  </p>
<p>South Korea estimates 26 North Koreans went ashore in the South from a submarine on Wednesday last week. Its security forces say they have since killed nine, while 11 were found shot dead -- possibly murdered by their own colleagues -- and one was captured.</p>
<p>&quot;As victims, we have the right to retaliate on the offenders,&quot; said a statement carried by the official Korean Central News Agency (KCNA), which reiterated Pyongyang's assertion that the submarine accidentally drifted into the South's waters.</p>
<p>&quot;The South Korean authorities must immediately stop their ill-intentioned campaign over our wrecked boat and return our submarine and surviving and dead crewmen immediately and unconditionally,&quot; said the statement on KCNA, which was monitored in Tokyo.</p>
<p>&quot;Our retaliation may be hundredfold or thousandfold. No matter what kind of retaliation we may make, the South Korean puppets will be wholly to blame,&quot; it said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
