<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83222" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korea kills another North agent as threats fly.</title>
<headline>S.Korea kills another North agent as threats fly.</headline>
<byline>Yeom Yoon-jeong</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops hunted down and killed the second-in-command of a grounded North Korean submarine on Saturday after the two Koreas traded angry words at the United Nations over the armed incursion.</p>
<p>The incident brings to 21 the number of North Koreans killed since they came ashore from the submarine last week, a defence ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>He said the man shot dead in a gun battle on Saturday was identified as 38-year-old Yu Rim, deputy commander of the submarine.</p>
<p>Hours earlier, South Korean Foreign Minister Gong Ro-myung told the U.N. General Assembly the communist North may be planning more commando-style raids.</p>
<p>North Korea's U.N. ambassador countered by repeating Pyongyang's demand that the submarine be returned along with its surviving and dead crew. North Korea maintains the vessel drifted south after developing engine trouble while on a training mission.</p>
<p>&quot;We cannot remain a victim for an indefinite period ... Time is not unlimited,&quot; Park Soo Gil told the assembly.</p>
<p>The heated exchanges continued an escalating war of words between the two Koreas.</p>
<p>North Korea has threatened to retaliate &quot;a hundredfold or a thousandfold&quot; if the vessel is not handed back. South Korea has branded Pyongyang's explanation for the incursion as an &quot;evildoer's audacity&quot;.</p>
<p>Threats and counter-threats regularly fly across the inter-Korean border, site of one of the heaviest concentrations of opposing troops anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>But the latest verbal salvoes, following one of the most serious Northern military incursions since the early Cold War, have come at a particularly critical time. South Korea and the United States are trying to lure North Korea to join them at the peace table, along with China.</p>
<p>In his speech to the United Nations, Gong made clear the offer of talks still stood. Seoul and Washington are seeking a peace treaty to replace an armistice that ended the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
<p>But Gong denounced what he called a &quot;brazen act of military provocation&quot; that showed Pyongyang &quot;seeks Korean unification by any means including force&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigtion is still under way to find out the purpose of the infiltration ... but the findings to date present a strong possibility that last week's infiltration is part of a larger-scale infiltration operation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The infiltrator killed on Saturday was one of five still thought to be on the run after the submarine foundered on an east cost reef on Wednesday last week.</p>
<p>A defence ministry official later said the dead man was wearing South Korean military uniform and carried an M-16 rifle, standard issue for Southern troops.</p>
<p>Of the 26 infiltrators throught to have landed, 10 have been hunted down and killed by Southern troops, 11 were found shot dead -- possibly killed by their own colleagues -- and one was captured alive.</p>
<p>Adding to the tension was a report on Friday of another North Korean arriving in the South in search of asylum.</p>
<p>Lee Jong-hyon, 28, arrived in the southwestern port city of Inchon on Thursday from an unidentified third country, the domestic Yonhap news agency reported. He is the latest of about 30 North Koreans who have defected this year.</p>
<p>Many of the defectors have been spurred to flee by food shortages following disastrous floods. South Korea has been preparing for a possible refugee crisis.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
