<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83765" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: N.Korea spies sent to prepare provocation - Seoul.</title>
<headline>N.Korea spies sent to prepare provocation - Seoul.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea said on Sunday the recent infiltration by armed North Korean agents was aimed at spying out military facilities in the South as part of Pyongyang's preparations for a large-scale provocation.</p>
<p>In a statement on the outcome of preliminary probes into the incident, the defence ministry said evidence seized from the Northern infiltrators, whom it branded as &quot;armed guerrillas&quot;, showed that their aim was to reconnoitre Southern airports, radar bases and major military facilities.</p>
<p>&quot;The findings prove that the infiltration was part of the North's combat-style reconnaissance activities in preparation for a large-scale provocation,&quot; the statement said, referring to detailed maps of expressways and other routes leading to the runways at an airport in the east coast city of Kangnung.</p>
<p>It said the seized evidence also included &quot;panoramic&quot; photographs taken of the area surrounding the Kangnung airport.</p>
<p>It added that South Korean investigators have seized a total of 2,160 items from the infiltrators, including one recoilless gun, four Soviet-made AK rifles, two M-16 rifles, six pistols, hundreds of bullets, Southern army uniforms and other equipment used for infiltration and espionage missions.</p>
<p>An official at the Joint Chiefs of Staff (JCS) said the intrusion by the heavily-armed agents, all of whom had been identified as military officers, was regarded as Pyongyang's &quot;planned&quot; activity required to help revise or supplement its strategy for invasion of the South.</p>
<p>On September 18, an estimated 26 Northern agents came ashore from a submarine grounded on a reef on a beach near Kangnung.</p>
<p>Of them, 11 have been hunted down and killed by Southern troops, 11 others were found shot dead -- possibly killed by their own colleagues -- and one was captured alive.</p>
<p>The 11th killing by South Korean forces took place on Saturday when the submarine's deputy commander was shot dead. The JCS official alleged that the submarine had been built in the North for the purpose of special infiltration missions.</p>
<p>South Korea's Yonhap news agency quoted officials at the Joint Chiefs of Staff on Sunday as saying that for the first time since the infiltration came to light, a reconnaissance helicopter of the U.S. forces in South Korea joined Southern troops' massive manhunt for the other four Northern fugitives.</p>
<p>Yonhap said the OH-58 helicopter has an advanced detector capable of distinguishing humans from animals in the darkness.</p>
<p>Comments from both South Korean and U.S. officials were not immediately available.</p>
<p>On Friday, South Korean Foreign Minister Gong Ro-myung told the U.N. General Assembly that the communist North may be planning more commando-style raids, denouncing what he called a &quot;brazen act of military provocation&quot; that showed Pyongyang &quot;seeks Korean unification by any means including force&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation is still under way to find out the purpose of the infiltration...but the findings to date present a strong possibility that last week's infiltration is part of a larger-scale infiltration operation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>North Korea's U.N. ambassador Park Soo Gil countered by repeating Pyongyang's demand that the submarine be returned along with its surviving and dead crew.</p>
<p>The North maintains the vessel drifted south after developing engine trouble while on a training mission and has threatened to retaliate &quot;a hundredfold or a thousandfold&quot; if the vessel is not returned.</p>
<p>Seoul has branded Pyongyang's explanation for the incursion as an &quot;evildoer's audacity&quot;.</p>
<p>South Korea's 655,000 troops, bolstered by about 37,000 U.S. forces, confront the North's 1.1 million-strong army across the Cold War border which was set up at the end of the 1950-53 Korean War ended only with a truce treaty.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
