<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85099" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korea troops kill another N.Korean in gunfight.</title>
<headline>S.Korea troops kill another N.Korean in gunfight.</headline>
<byline>Shim Sung-won</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean troops killed another North Korean infiltrator on Monday, bringing to 22 the number of Pyongyang agents shot dead after coming ashore from a submarine nearly two weeks ago, the defence ministry said.</p>
<p>A spokesman also said a South Korean soldier, 21-year-old army sergeant Han Dae-sung, was gunned down by his colleagues who mistook him for an infiltrator on Sunday.</p>
<p>Five Southern soldiers have now been killed during the manhunt for an estimated 26 intruders thought to have landed on September 18. One civilian was also accidentally shot by South Korean forces.</p>
<p>Separately, a deputy defence minister said Seoul still intended to pursue with Washington the idea of reactivating joint U.S.-South Korean war games.</p>
<p>The massive Team Spirit exercises were suspended as an inducement to Pyongyang to freeze its suspected nuclear weapons programme. North Korea and the United States signed a landmark nuclear accord in 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very interested in staging the Team Spirit exercises,&quot; Park Yong-ok told a news conference. &quot;For the military itself, a large-scale exercise like Team Spirit is very important.&quot;</p>
<p>The defence ministry first proposed the idea last week, but foreign minister Gong Ro-myung later said no decision had been made at a government level.</p>
<p>Restarting the exercises, which Pyongyang condemned as preparation for an invasion, would dim any hopes for a peace plan put forward by U.S. President Bill Clinton and South Korean head of state Kim Young-sam.</p>
<p>The plan calls for four-way talks, including China, to replace an armistice that ended the 1950-53 Korean War with a permanent peace arrangement.</p>
<p>Park said Seoul has not officially approached Washington about reviving Team Spirit, but it would be on the agenda at annual security talks with the United States this month or early next month.</p>
<p>&quot;We have never said we will permanently stop Team Spirit,&quot; Park stressed. &quot;Whether or not Team Spirit will be held depends on North Korea's behavior.&quot;</p>
<p>Pyongyang maintains the submarine drifted into Southern waters after developing engine trouble on a training exercise. It has threatened unspecified retaliation if the vessel is not returned along with the surviving and dead crew.</p>
<p>Park again refuted the explanation, saying Seoul &quot;shall expose North Korea's false claims and resolutely respond in such a way that North Korea cannot help but pay for its irrational behaviour&quot;.</p>
<p>On Sunday the defence ministry portrayed the incursion as a spying mission in preparation for a wider military provocation.</p>
<p>The latest infiltrator to die was killed in a gunbattle with South Korean troops, the defence ministry spokesman said. He was armed with a pistol and wore civilian clothes.</p>
<p>So far 11 infiltrators have been killed by Southern forces, 11 were found dead -- possibly executed by their own colleagues -- and one has been captured alive. Another three are believed to be still on the run.</p>
<p>An official at the Joint Chiefs of Staff said South Korean security forces were expanding the search area up to the border with North Korea.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that the remaining North Koreans are still within our net,&quot; the official told reporters. &quot;But we cannot rule out the possibility they have already escaped it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
