<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86326" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: N.Korea says &quot;infiltrators&quot; killed in cold blood.</title>
<headline>N.Korea says &quot;infiltrators&quot; killed in cold blood.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea accused South Korea on Monday of cold-blooded murder of soldiers and crew members of a submarine from the North which went aground earlier this month off the South's coast.</p>
<p>In a statement issued through its mission in Geneva, Pyongyang also charged that Seoul was using the incident to distract attention from problems at home and from difficulties in its relationship with the United States and Japan.</p>
<p>&quot;The soldiers from the North side (on board the submarine) should have been rescued and protected because they were in danger after an accident in the sea while engaging in training,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>But, it added, the South Korean authorities mobilised tens of thousands of troops, police and reservists to hunt down and kill the soldiers and the submarine's crew who, it said, &quot;had no self-defence arms&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;In the course of this, nearly 20 soldiers of the North side were killed in cold blood,&quot; the North Korean statement said.</p>
<p>South Korea says that many of the North Koreans were agents or &quot;armed guerrillas&quot; brought south to spy on military facilities as part of preparations &quot;for a large-scale provocation&quot;.</p>
<p>A defence ministry statement in Seoul at the weekend said evidence gathered from the bodies of the men killed in the search operation over the past two weeks showed they were on an infiltration and espionage mission.</p>
<p>South Korea also says 11 of the North Koreans -- including crew members of the submarine -- were killed by their escaping comrades. South Korean troops have hunted down and killed 11 others, the latest at the weekend.</p>
<p>The North Korean statement said that while the South accepted from the start of the incident that the submarine was stranded and that the men on board had no choice but to go ashore, it used the incident for &quot;sinister political purposes&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;To the consternation of the people, the soldiers of the North side were branded by the South Korean authorities as &quot;armed spies' and &quot;armed communist bandits',&quot; it declared.</p>
<p>&quot;There were no grounds or conditions for them to become the target of gun firing,&quot; the English-language statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;They had no arms and equipment needed for intrusion or destruction. Moreover, those who were killed were the crewmen, including the captain, the chief engineer and the navigator....</p>
<p>&quot;What could they do on land after abandoning the boat?&quot; the statement asked.</p>
<p>It said the soldiers on the stricken vessels had left on board the personal arms they used in training and on land &quot;did not attack or destroy anything or hurt anyone&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The South Korean authorities are aggravating tension by using the accident, which could have been settled peacefully, for the purpose of inter-Korean confrontation,&quot; it declared.</p>
<p>The statement said the South Korean response was due to &quot;a serious political and economic crisis&quot; facing President Kim Young-sam -- who has bitterly denounced Pyongyang over the affair.</p>
<p>&quot;They (the South) are extremely worried as they might lose patronage from the United States and Japan,&quot; the North Korean statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The South Korean authorities seek a way out of this crisis in aggravating tension by slandering their fellow-countrymen and firing guns on the Korean peninsula.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
