<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="21110" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Mad cow cull cuts global warming, report says.</title>
<headline>Mad cow cull cuts global warming, report says.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>The environment may indirectly benefit from the current scare over mad cow disease, New Scientist magazine reported on Thursday.</p>
<p>It quoted British scientists as saying reductions in British cattle herds because of the epidemic would cut emissions of methane, a greenhouse gas that contributes to global warming.</p>
<p>&quot;Beef is a greenhouse-intensive food,&quot; the magazine quoted Susan Subak of University College London as saying.</p>
<p>She estimates that, if British cattle herds are cut in half as a result of the epidemic, methane emissions from their belches would decline by up to three percent.</p>
<p>Cattle have long been blamed as contributors to global warming. They belch and fart methane, estimated at an average of 48 kilograms (105 lb) a year per cow.</p>
<p>In addition, fossil fuels are burned to produce fertiliser used on the crops fed to cattle. Fossil fuels send carbon dioxide, another greenhouse gas, into the atmosphere.</p>
<p>Britain is currently planning to cull 147,000 cows because of fears about Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE or mad cow disease). This is a small percentage of the 11 million national cattle herd.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
