<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30182" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Euro-MPs charge EU did not protect public from BSE.</title>
<headline>Euro-MPs charge EU did not protect public from BSE.</headline>
<byline>Chris White</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission and Council of Ministers were accused on Tuesday of failing to protect consumers from the dangers of mad cow disease and of putting market forces ahead of human health.</p>
<p>Members of the European Parliament made the charges as they launched a special inquiry into the 15-nation bloc's handling of the disease -- bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE) -- and its possible link to a deadly human equivalent.</p>
<p>Farm Commissioner Franz Fischer and the Irish EU presidency strongly denied the accusations, saying actions taken over the past six years to combat BSE were appropriate given the scientific evidence available.</p>
<p>&quot;The (EU's) veterinary legislation is among the most stringent in the world, and some third countries have even criticised it for being too restrictive,&quot; Irish Farm Minister Ivan Yates told the panel.</p>
<p>But clearly sceptical members of the committee indicated they believed the Commission and EU member states had not been open about the risks of the disease.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been told lies and we have been told lies for years. We now realise what the dangers are that meat eaters are subject to,&quot; Belgian Socialist Euro-MP Jose Happart said.</p>
<p>Others accused the Commission of taking &quot;mimimalist action&quot;.</p>
<p>Nineteen Euro-MPs, sitting as a temporary committee of inquiry, will consider whether the Commission and certain EU states correctly informed the public about alleged dangers from BSE.</p>
<p>They will also investigate whether the EU is efficiently monitoring its global ban on exports of British beef and adopting adequate measures for protecting public health and restoring the smooth operation of the beef market.</p>
<p>They have been asked to issue a report by November 17.</p>
<p>Fischler and Yates, the first to appear before the panel, offered robust defences of the actions of both the Commission and the EU's Council of Ministers.</p>
<p>Yates said EU member states had acted on the basis of two principles since worries about the disease first arose -- that human health must be protected, and that all measures taken must be based on the most recent scientific findings.</p>
<p>&quot;(Measures taken) could reasonably be considered to guarantee consumers the level of protection which they have a right to expect, he said.</p>
<p>He accused some committee members of using hindsight and of making up their minds &quot;in advance of hearing the evidence&quot;.</p>
<p>Fischler also defended the Commission's openness on BSE. &quot;I know of no disinformation campaign by the Commission,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The French daily newspaper Liberation reported on Monday that a senior Commission official had suggested in a 1993 memorandum that EU veterinary experts should avoid discussing the risk to humans posed by the disease.</p>
<p>It was the second such accusation concerning Commission policy. The Commission has denied trying to cover up any BSE dangers, pointing as proof to its speedy banning of British beef in March after evidence of a possible link between BSE and Creutzfeld-Jakob disease.</p>
<p>Fischler said that any new scientific information tended to take a long long time. &quot;My approach is to get the best independent advice on which to base legislation.&quot;</p>
<p>The parliament's power to investigate comes courtesy of the Maastricht Treaty, which gave the EU assembly the right to probe alleged violations or maladministration of European Union law.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
