<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="37729" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU scientists to study mad cow data further.</title>
<headline>EU scientists to study mad cow data further.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Scientific Veterinary Committee reviewed evidence on Friday that mad cow disease can be transmitted from cow to calves and decided to study the issue further, delegates said.</p>
<p>A British study recently confirmed scientists' warnings that the fatal brain wasting disease could be passed to calves, dealing a fresh blow to the British beef industry and raising German fears about the safety of British milk.</p>
<p>&quot;We discussed transmissibility all day and we did not reach any conclusions,&quot; a Belgian veterinary scientist said after the meeting.</p>
<p>Two sub-groups were set up to examine over the next few weeks the British research and implications for safety of milk.</p>
<p>A German scientist hinted that more calves may have to be killed to stamp out mad cow disease, known as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE).</p>
<p>&quot;Maternal transmission is a fact and in my opinion calves of all infected animals will have to be killed,' said Walter Heeschen, Director of the Federal Dairy Research Centre in Keele, Germany.</p>
<p>But he added that the human health risk from milk was remote.</p>
<p>&quot;In my opinion milk is safe as far as our scientific knowledge goes at the moment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Commission agriculture spokesman Gerard Kiely said that the consensus seemed to be that BSE was transmitted through the placenta.</p>
<p>Kiely said earlier that the transmission issue will be discussed further next week by the Standing Veterinary Committee and the week after by a multi-disciplinary committee of experts on food, human and animal health safety.</p>
<p>The British study on BSE transmission found that only one percent of British calves passed on the disease to their calves, but did not examine how the disease was transmitted.</p>
<p>The Commission said on August 6 that there was no scientific evidence that milk carries mad cow disease but this could not be ruled out completely.</p>
<p>Several member states have demanded further research.</p>
<p>The scientists said they were handed a new report by Oxford scientists, raising doubts about a scheme to slaughter British cattle most at risk from mad cow disease.</p>
<p>It was not discussed.</p>
<p>But the scientists recommended more research into the heat processing of the beef by-product, gelatine, so as to ensure that it is completely BSE free, Kiely said.</p>
<p>On sheepmeat, the scientists adopted a report from a sub-group recommending three options:</p>
<p>- No action</p>
<p>- Removing all BSE suspect tissues in sheep</p>
<p>- Banning all specified bovine offals (SBOs) from sheep and cattle.</p>
<p>Kiely said the BSE risk would be assessed for each country and the appropriate option chosen.</p>
<p>Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler proposed in July to ban sheep brains, spleens and spinal cords from the human and animal food chains to protect human health.</p>
<p>Fischler proposed EU measures after reports from Britain and France that sheep could catch Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), or mad cow disease, under laboratory conditions.</p>
<p>But some members of the EU's Standing Veterinary Committee questioned if such widespread and costly action was justified as there was only a slight risk to human health.</p>
<p>In a separate move to restore consumer confidence, the European Commission is preparing a proposal for an EU voluntary beef labelling scheme.</p>
<p>&quot;It should be ready later this month,&quot; Kiely said, adding it would be in the interests of all member states to have labels showing where the meat came from and how it was produced.</p>
<p>Austria, Belgium and the Netherlands already have national schemes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
