<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47015" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU vets discuss mad cow disease, slaughter plans.</title>
<headline>EU vets discuss mad cow disease, slaughter plans.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union veterinary officials met on Wednesday to discuss the latest data on mad cow disease, including selective slaughter programmes and the safety of milk.</p>
<p>The EU's Standing Veterinary Committee was due on the second day of a regular meeting to examine a British study which found that mad cow disease -- known as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE) -- could be passed to calves.</p>
<p>The study raised the possibility that more animals would have to be slaughtered to stamp out BSE, but said that only one percent of British cows passed on the disease to their calves.  </p>
<p>The officials were also expected to discuss a report by Oxford University scientists which disagreed about the need for a mass cull, predicting that mad cow disease would be over by 2001 even without such action.</p>
<p>&quot;It's quite possible the Oxford report will be discussed even though it wasn't on the agenda,&quot; a Commission official said before the meeting.</p>
<p>In London, British officials played down media reports on Wednesday that the government might abandon the planned slaughter of 147,000 cattle to eliminate the disease, saying no decision had been taken.</p>
<p>In Brussels, European Commission and British officials said they did not expect any decisions or conclusions to come out of the EU veterinary meeting.</p>
<p>Also on the agenda were the Commission's latest BSE inspection visits to Britain and Portugal as well as a French plan to eradicate the disease, including EU aid for farmers.</p>
<p>Measures to stop the fatal brain wasting disease spreading to sheep were also due to be considered.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
