<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="47078" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU warns Britain on mad cow cull review.</title>
<headline>EU warns Britain on mad cow cull review.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission said on Wednesday that a British programme to slaughter cattle most at risk from mad cow disease was an essential part of an agreement to gradually lift a worldwide ban on British beef.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Major said British ministers would review on Thursday the planned cull of 147,000 cattle most at risk of developing the fatal brain wasting disease, setting the scene for another clash with the European Union.</p>
<p>&quot;The selective slaughter plan is an integral part of the Florence agreement on a step by step lifting of the export ban,&quot; Commission agriculture spokesman Gerard Kiely told a news briefing.</p>
<p>EU leaders agreed at the Florence European Council in June to lift progressively the ban on exports of British beef and products as Britain implemented a series of tough measures, including the slaughter of affected cattle and those most at risk.</p>
<p>The deal defused a crisis which broke when the ban was imposed on March 27 after Britain said that the disease, known medically as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), could be transmitted to humans who ate infected beef.</p>
<p>Britain retaliated against the ban, which it said was disproportionate and unfair, by blocking EU business for many weeks.</p>
<p>It has now seized on a report by Oxford University scientists last month predicting that mad cow disease would disappear by 2001, even without the cull.</p>
<p>But the Commission noted an earlier British study which found that cows can pass mad cow disease to calves and raised the possibility that more animals would have to be killed.</p>
<p>The study, released on August 1, said that 10 percent of calves born within six months of their mothers showing signs of BSE, developed the fatal disease. This translated into a one percent overall rate of transmission.</p>
<p>It prompted Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler to write to British Agriculture Minister Douglas Hogg warning that the selective slaughter programme should be reviewed.</p>
<p>The confirmation of maternal transmission of the disease, even though at a very low level, also made it unlikely that Major's objective of ending the ban in November would be met.</p>
<p>The Commission, which stresses that consumer safety should be given priority, said it did not intend being drawn into a battle of numbers.</p>
<p>&quot;We have never got into discussing numbers,&quot; Kiely told Reuters. &quot;Our approach is based on reducing BSE as quickly as possible with better guarantees for consumer safety.&quot;</p>
<p>Kiely noted that the Oxford report, published in the British scientific review &quot;Nature&quot;, was based on a computer model that might prove impractical because some 25,000 farms would have to be monitored.</p>
<p>British officials said that Britain would draw attention to the Oxford report at a meeting of senior EU veterinary officials on Wednesday but discussions would concentrate on maternal transmission of BSE.</p>
<p>Britain would not be pressing for any decisions.</p>
<p>&quot;We are in listening mode,&quot; a British official said, adding that it was likely to take some time before EU veterinary experts came to any conclusions.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
