<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53572" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Britain's Hogg to probe Farm Council on beef ban.</title>
<headline>Britain's Hogg to probe Farm Council on beef ban.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Farm Minister Douglas Hogg is set to sound out the Farm Council next week on prospects for easing a worldwide ban on British beef, arguing that Britain was meeting tough terms to eradicate mad cow disease.</p>
<p>British sources said on Friday that Hogg would brief EU farm ministers on British action to comply with an agreement at the EU summit in Florence in June to lift the ban gradually.</p>
<p>Hogg will also draw attention to new British scientific data that casts doubts on a special cull to eliminate cattle most at risk to the fatal brain-wasting disease, known medically as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE).</p>
<p>&quot;Britain will look for reactions from member states,&quot; said a British source.</p>
<p>But EU officials cautioned that there was little short-term likelihood of easing the British beef export ban, the first stage of which would affect grass-fed herds.</p>
<p>The European Commission added there was no request or proposal so far to proceed with the next step in lifting the ban, which was imposed in March after Britain triggered a massive health scare by admitting that BSE could be transmitted to humans.</p>
<p>Britain in July introduced a passport scheme for cattle so their origins and movements could be traced. It has banned meat and bone meal, believed to be the cause of BSE, in all farm animal feed, British sources said.</p>
<p>By the end of August around 450,000 older cattle, which might have eaten contaminated feed before it was banned, had been slaughtered although officials said there was still an unspecified backlog due to shortage of incineration capacity.</p>
<p>Hogg will also call for the EU to review a scheme intended to speed up the elimination of mad caw disease by slaughtering younger animals believed to be at risk.</p>
<p>British sources said the scheme involved around 127,000 cattle, or 20,000 less than earlier reported.</p>
<p>Two recent British reports show that the disease can be passed from cow to calf and that the epidemic would disappear within five years even without a cull.</p>
<p>In a statement on Thursday, the British government said the new evidence should be evaluated in the light of the Florence agreement that the British beef ban should be lifted &quot;on the basis of objective scientific criteria&quot;.</p>
<p>But the European Commission again warned on Friday that the selective slaughter programme was essential.</p>
<p>&quot;It's an integral part of the Florence agreement,&quot; Commission agriculture spokesman Gerard Kiely told a news briefing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
