<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54315" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU ministers set to argue argue over beef crisis.</title>
<headline>EU ministers set to argue argue over beef crisis.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>European farm ministers are heading for a stormy meeting on Monday over whether cereals farmers should be paid less so that beef farmers can get more help in coping with the mad cow crisis.</p>
<p>Most countries argue that cereals farmers, who have been reaping bumper profits due to record world prices, could soon be confronted with falling prices as production rises.</p>
<p>&quot;It's unfair to make a permanent cut in aid after what may prove to be a temporary windfall,&quot; said one official.</p>
<p>Some, such as Germany, say that savings could be made within the farm budget to find the 1.3 billion Ecus ($1.7 billion) needed in 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;The discussion is likely to be long and heated but without any decisions,&quot; said an official.</p>
<p>With mainland Europe preoccupied with repairing the damage caused by the public health scare over mad cow disease, Britain is unlikely to receive any signal of a possible easing of a worldwide ban on its beef exports, EU officials said.</p>
<p>They said that Britain, which prompted the crisis in March by announcing that the fatal brain wasting disease can be passed to people who eat infected beef, is expected to present new data at Tuesday's session for easing a ban on its beef.</p>
<p>Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler proposed measures in July to curb a mounting beef mountain caused by an average 11 percent fall in EU demand due to consumer panic over the disease, known as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE).</p>
<p>Short-term action would include buying 720,000 tonnes of unwanted beef and extending British and Portuguese calf slaughter schemes to all EU states.</p>
<p>But Germany and other countries have condemned the so-called &quot;Herod premium&quot; to kill calves of a few days old, saying it would infuriate animal rights groups and stir public outrage.</p>
<p>British Farm Minister Douglas Hogg is due to sound out EU farm ministers on Tuesday, arguing that Britain was meeting tough terms to eradicate mad cow disease under an agreement at the EU summit in Florence in June to lift the ban in stages.</p>
<p>Hogg will also highlight new scientific data that casts doubt on a special cull to eliminate cattle most at risk to BSE.</p>
<p>Oxford University scientists reported last month that the disease would disappear within five years even without the cull.</p>
<p>&quot;Britain will look for reactions from member states,&quot; said a British source.</p>
<p>Another team of EU inspectors is due to visit Britain at the end of September and the British data still has to be examined by various EU scientific committees.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be very difficult,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>As British hopes fade of lifting the ban by the November deadline set by Prime Minister John Major, there is growing pressure from farmers and Eurosceptics to abandon the unnpopular selective slaughter scheme.</p>
<p>But the European Commission, while ready to review the British data, has warned that the selective slaughter programme is an integral part of the Florence agreement for a gradual lifting of the worldwide ban.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
