<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="57866" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British MPs say they could force BSE cull halt.</title>
<headline>British MPs say they could force BSE cull halt.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>British politicians, angered by other European Union countries' stand over mad cow disease, predicted on Tuesday that the government could tear up an agreement with its partners on tackling the crisis.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman in Prime Minister John Major's office said the government would &quot;announce its intentions shortly&quot; about whether a massive cattle cull Major agreed with fellow EU leaders in June would go ahead.</p>
<p>Britain insists the cull of up to 147,000 animals should be cut after new scientific evidence that the disease -- bovine spongiform encephalopathy -- will die out within five years.</p>
<p>But Britain's Douglas Hogg failed to persuade other EU farm ministers at a meeting on Tuesday to accept a cut the cull. The rejection sparked speculation in Britain that an accord Major agreed at an EU summit in Florence for lifting an export ban on British beef was about to unravel.</p>
<p>The EU introduced the ban in March after Britain said humans might catch the fatal Creuzfeldt-Jakob disease from eating BSE-infected beef.</p>
<p>The cull needs specific approval by the British parliament. Members of parliament warned they might not agree unless the EU gave hard-and-fast promises that the ban would be lifted progressively as the cull proceeded.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless we can get a cast-iron guarantee from the Europeans that they will lift the ban if we undertake this colossal slaughter, then what's the point of doing it,&quot; said Paul Marland, a Conservative member with a farming constituency.</p>
<p>&quot;We'd have to have a very, very good explanation as to why we should go ahead with that cull,&quot; he told BBC radio. &quot;I think that the minister (Hogg) could have very considerable difficulty with that.&quot;</p>
<p>Right-wing Conservatives have used the EU's actions during the BSE crisis to back up their campaign to prevent further integration with the bloc.</p>
<p>&quot;The Europeans are hypocritical and two-faced about this and won't change their attitude whatever we do,&quot; said Jerry Wiggin, Conservative chairman of parliament's agriculture committee.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless Mr Hogg has come back with an absolutely bankable guarantee...I cannot see it going through the House of Commons,&quot; said Paul Tyler, farming spokesman for the minority Liberal Democrats.</p>
<p>The vote is expected in October. Major has a one-seat majority in the 651-seat lower house.</p>
<p>A spokesman at the Agriculture Ministry said it was &quot;premature&quot; to speculate on the future of the agreement reached in Florence under which, Major has claimed, the export ban could be lifted by November.</p>
<p>He said Hogg was still discussing the cull with Britain's EU partners and in particular trying to persuade them to allow beef from herds certified free from BSE to be exported.</p>
<p>But the spokeswoman in Major's office said the government realised that farmers needed to be relieved of uncertainty about their future as quickly as possible and the government would therefore announce soon what it planned to do next.</p>
<p>Britain is relying on a report last month from Oxford University saying a cull would not hasten the end of BSE, although it might reduce the number of cattle getting the brain-rotting disease in the meantime.</p>
<p>But at the Brussels meeting, EU Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler insisted the cull must go ahead before any steps were taken to lift the export ban.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
