<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59561" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss defend mad cow cull denounced by farmers.</title>
<headline>Swiss defend mad cow cull denounced by farmers.</headline>
<byline>Marcus Kabel</byline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Switzerland's top farm official insisted on Tuesday that slaughtering 230,000 cows was the best way to curb mad cow disease although the plan has been denounced by many Swiss farmers and consumers.</p>
<p>Hans Burger, head of the Federal Agricultural Office, said the plan unveiled on Monday was the best way to restore confidence in Swiss beef damaged by being the second worst-afflicted country by mad cow disease after Britain.</p>
<p>The mass slaughter -- one in eight of the total Swiss herd -- will not affect two traditional Swiss exports, cheese and chocolate.</p>
<p>&quot;Swiss milk production creates such a big annual surplus that we are not afraid of a shortage,&quot; said Kurt Hunzinger, spokesman for the chocolate makers association Chocosuisse.</p>
<p>Burger rejected claims the programme wasted both tax money and healthy cattle and that it overshot calls from beef producers, who had suggested slaughtering up to 100,000 cows.</p>
<p>&quot;I am convinced that this is the best proposal,&quot; Burger said in an interview on Swiss public radio DRS.</p>
<p>Farmers, consumer groups and Swiss newspapers broadly condemned the plan, which must still be approved by parliament and could be trimmed down there.</p>
<p>Critics quickly attacked the proposal after it was unveiled on Monday by Federal President Jean-Pascal Delamuraz following a cabinet meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;Once again, consumers and taxpayers are the losers. Once again, the man in the street has to pay for the mistakes of farmers and agricultural bureacrats,&quot; the tabloid Blick complained about the price tag of 320 million Swiss francs ($260 million).</p>
<p>The Swiss move has put extra pressure on Britain to proceed with a scheme to kill an extra 147,000 animals most at risk.</p>
<p>Burger said the scope of the Swiss plan, under which 230,000 of Switzerland's 750,000 adult cows would be culled from an overall cattle population of 1.7 million, was the only way to combine three important goals.</p>
<p>These were easing supply to a glutted beef market, eradicating mad cow disease and regaining consumer confidence at home and in the European Union, where neighbours Germany and Italy have barred or severely restricted imports of Swiss beef cattle.</p>
<p>&quot;Mad cow disease&quot;, or Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), is a brain-wasting disease that scientists say may be linked to a human equivalent, Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease.</p>
<p>Switzerland is the second most-afflicted country after Britain, with 223 BSE cases from 1990 through this September as against 160,000 cases reported in Britain over 10 years.</p>
<p>The Swiss Farmers' Association (SBV) said the mass slaughter was only one alternative for stamping out BSE and rejected plans to help finance 60 million Swiss francs of the 320 million franc bill by trimming federal subsidies to milk producers.</p>
<p>The Association of Small and Medium-sized Farms was more critical, calling the programme a &quot;pointless waste of millions in tax money&quot;.</p>
<p>The association echoed complaints heard from dozens of farmers in television and newspaper interviews who said the slaughter would take away too many healthy animals.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not going to give up a single cow, even if they use force against me,&quot; organic farmer Andreas Ineichen told the newspaper Basler Zeitung.</p>
<p>Organic farmers, a small but growing sector, were especially angry that their cows were to be included in the round-up even though they had had never been fed on meal from cow carcasses.</p>
<p>The government plan is to slaughter cows born before December 1, 1990, the year Switzerland banned feeding them beef bone and remains which could help spread the disease.</p>
<p>It would also slaughter direct offspring of BSE infected cows. ($1=1.2403 Swiss Franc)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
