<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59577" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU rejects British bid to cut BSE cull.</title>
<headline>EU rejects British bid to cut BSE cull.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union's pact for ending the beef crisis with Britain looked like unravelling on Tuesday when EU countries rejected plans floated by London for reducing a cull of cattle most at risk from mad cow disease.</p>
<p>Britain's Douglas Hogg told other EU farm ministers London was fulfilling an agreement at a bloc summit in June to end the disease but that new scientific data showed an extra cull agreed at the meeting was unnecessary.</p>
<p>Germany said it would not permit British beef, banned around the world over health fears from mad cow disease, to be sold there until the risk was gone.</p>
<p>Belgium suggested that if Britain did not stick to the agreement made at the summit in Florence for combating the disease the EU might stop funds it has promised to help farmers overcome the crisis.</p>
<p>EU Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler stressed the extra British cull was an essential part of the Florence agreement for a staged lifting of the ban.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a pre-condition before any specific steps can be taken (to lift the ban),&quot; Fischler told a news conference after a two-dy meeting of farm ministers.</p>
<p>Germany, driven by consumer fears over the disease -- bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE) -- has taken the toughest stance against British beef.</p>
<p>&quot;We will have to keep the borders shut against imports as long as there is any risk,&quot; German Secretary of State for Agriculture Franz-Josef Feiter told reporters.</p>
<p>Belgium also took a hard line.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not see there can be any easing of the ban unless the British government goes ahead with it (the extra cull),&quot; Belgian Farm Minister Karel Pinxten said, warning that otherwise the EU would not provide any BSE financial aid.</p>
<p>For its part, Britain said its EU partners were not honouring their side of the Florence agreement, which was to work towards a step-by-step lifting of the ban on British beef exports.</p>
<p>&quot;We are rather disturbed by a number of steps taken by some countries which go beyond EU rules,&quot; Hogg said, raising speculation that London may soon decide to go it alone and cut the size of the cull.</p>
<p>Hogg was referring to recent German legislation banning imports of British bull semen and French measures against British cosmetics which he said were unjustified.</p>
<p>He said such action by Britain's EU partners would make it extremely difficult to get the slaughter scheme approved by the British parliament.</p>
<p>Europe has been battling a crisis of confidence in beef since March when the British government said BSE could be transmitted to humans.</p>
<p>Switzerland announced plans on Monday to slaughter up to 230,000 cattle, one in eight of its total herd, to curb the fatal disease.</p>
<p>The Swiss move put extra pressure on Britain to proceed with the scheme to kill an extra 147,000 animals most at risk.</p>
<p>But Hogg told reporters that Switzerland was only copying a British scheme to take out older cattle from the food chain.</p>
<p>&quot;The Swiss are following our example,&quot; Hogg said before the second day of the farm ministers' meeting.</p>
<p>Fischler played down a report last month by Oxford University that BSE would die out within five years even without a cull, saying it was widely recognised that the epidemic would disappear early next century if eradication measures were implemented.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
