<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60709" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EU presses Britain to stick to mad cow cull.</title>
<headline>EU presses Britain to stick to mad cow cull.</headline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG, France 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Commission President Jacques Santer kept up the pressure on Britain to fulfil a pledge to cull up to 147,000 extra cattle to eliminate mad cow disease more quickly.</p>
<p>At an EU summit in Florence in June, Britain reluctantly agreed to a package of measures, including culling cattle most at risk from the deadly disease, in return for a gradual lifting of a worldwide ban on its beef exports.</p>
<p>&quot;I do think we should stick to that agreement as formulated by EU leaders,&quot; Santer told a news conference at the European Parliament.</p>
<p>Britain now believes that new scientific data has thrown doubt on the effectiveness of the cull, which would supplement a scheme to slaughter annually around one million cattle over the age of 30 months and to destroy the meat.</p>
<p>An Oxford University report last month suggested that the disease, known medically as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE) would disappear within five years without the necessity of an extra cull.</p>
<p>But Santer said the agreed measures should be implemented.</p>
<p>&quot;We should be taking all the necessary steps to eradicate this disease in order to restore consumer confidence and then stabilise markets. Our over-riding concern is the protection of public health,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Irish Prime Minister John Bruton stressed the Irish EU Presidency was committed to ending the beef crisis, which he believed could only be done through joint European action.</p>
<p>&quot;What is clear is that the matter must be solved...on a European basis. The place to do that is at a European Council (summit) and not unilaterally,&quot; he told the news conference.</p>
<p>But Britain increasingly believes that the ban is unlikely to be lifted soon, even if the cull is carried out.</p>
<p>British Prime Minister John Major said on Wednesday Britain had made no firm decision yet about scrapping or reducing it.</p>
<p>&quot;I can tell you we will not delay a decision and when we take the decision we will take it on the basis of public health, on the basis of common sense and in the interests of the beef farmer but there are still discussions to be had before that decision can be finalised,&quot; Major said on BBC radio.</p>
<p>British Agriculture Minister Douglas Hogg failed on Tuesday to persuade other farm ministers or the European Commission to reduce the selective slaughter scheme.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Hogg warned in London that the British parliament would strongly oppose the scheme, which needs parliamentary approval, unless the EU agreed &quot;rapidly and substantially&quot; to proceed with lifting the ban.</p>
<p>The EU banned British beef exports in March after Britain said that there could be a link between BSE and Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease, the deadly human equivalent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
