<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62056" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain edges toward scrapping EU mad cow deal.</title>
<headline>Britain edges toward scrapping EU mad cow deal.</headline>
<byline>Alan Wheatley</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain set the stage on Wednesday for pulling out of a hard-won deal with its European Union partners designed to end the crisis over mad cow disease.</p>
<p>Agriculture Minister Douglas Hogg said there would be huge parliamentary opposition to a proposed cull of up to 147,000 cattle most at risk of the disease unless the EU agreed &quot;rapidly and substantially&quot; to lift a ban on British beef sales.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Major said no decision had been taken on whether to proceed with the selective cull -- key to a deal he struck at June's EU summit in Florence -- but Hogg's remarks reinforced speculation that it would be scrapped or reduced.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to be able to go the House of Commons, if I'm going to seek authority for a cull, and say that in my considered view member states are likely rapidly and substantially to lift the ban,&quot; Hogg told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;If I can do that honestly, then I think that there would be a reasonable prospect of the House of Commons being prepared to authorise a cull -- and if not, I fancy not.&quot;</p>
<p>In June, Major had said he expected the EU to start lifting the ban within five months but this confident prediction found little backing among other countries in the bloc.</p>
<p>Hogg did not say so explicitly, but officials said he returned from talks with EU farm ministers in Brussels on Tuesday convinced they would not lift the ban any time soon.</p>
<p>In Brussels Hogg failed to persuade Britain's partners to scale back the mass slaughter in light of a prediction by scientists from Oxford University that mad cow disease -- Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE) -- would die out within five years even without a cull.</p>
<p>The EU banned British beef sales worldwide after Britain acknowledged in March there could be a link between BSE and Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease, the human equivalent of the brain-wasting illness.</p>
<p>The cabinet committee handling the BSE crisis meets on Thursday. One of the options Hogg is expected to put forward is a reduced cull of about 22,000 animals at high risk of catching mad cow disease from their mothers.</p>
<p>Reducing the selective cull would go down well with British beef farmers and members of the ruling Conservative Party, who insist it is unnecessary.</p>
<p>But by effectively scuppering the Florence agreement, it could put fresh strain on Britain's ties with the EU.</p>
<p>Foreign Secretary Malcolm Rifkind underscored Britain's awkward relationship with the EU on Wednesday by warning that plans for a single currency could split the bloc in two.</p>
<p>&quot;Such a divided European Union was not what the founding fathes had in mind,&quot; he said in a speech in Zurich.</p>
<p>Commentators say Major is hoping that scepticism towards closer EU integration and a willingness to tear up the pact on mad cow disease will go down well with voters at the coming general election, now no more than eight months away.</p>
<p>In an interview with BBC radio, he was critical of Britain's partners and the European Commission, the EU executive, for the failure of the Brussels meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the Commission and the European Union are on very shaky scientific ground in the way they are behaving at the moment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tony Blair, leader of the main opposition Labour Party, said the government's policy was a &quot;confused shambles&quot;.</p>
<p>He said the prime minister would have to answer to parliament if the beef ban was not now going to be lifted -- as Major had indicated as part of the Florence deal -- by late November.</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't the faintest idea what their policy now is.&quot; Blair said. &quot;It's desperately important that they stop playing around with this issue and get a firm line and stick to it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
