<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64742" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU says no U-turn on mad cow cull.</title>
<headline>EU says no U-turn on mad cow cull.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union is sticking to its demand that Britain carry out an agreed plan to slaughter up to 147,000 cows most at risk of developing mad cow disease, a European Commission spokesman said on Thursday.</p>
<p>He was commenting on British media reports that the EU's executive had backtracked on Wednesday by asking scientists to look at a British study suggesting the cull was unnecessary because the epidemic would die out by the turn of the century regardless.</p>
<p>&quot;Suggestions in the British press today that there has been a U-turn by the Commission...are not true,&quot; agriculture spokesman Gerard Kiely told a news briefing.</p>
<p>The British reports said the request, which followed the intervention of Britain's senior EU Commissioner Sir Leon Brittan, contradicted the stony reception the Oxford University study received from EU Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler and farm ministers at a meeting on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Fischler had said he was disappointed that Britain was planning to revise the selective cull and at the lack of progress in stamping out the disease.</p>
<p>He said the report contained nothing new in that people knew that the disease would die out early next century.</p>
<p>Kiely said the Oxford evidence on the disease, known properly as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), had been passed to the EU's scientific veterinary committee 10 days ago and it should not serve as an excuse to delay the cull.</p>
<p>But some EU officials say that only a summary of the Oxford study published in Nature magazine had been circulated.</p>
<p>The committee is expected to report back later this month after which the Commission will decide if any action is needed.</p>
<p>The Commission decision to refer the report to the committee, which gave Britain a breathing space, showed that the EU's executive was anxious not to precipitate another crisis between London and European capitals.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Major, afraid that the controversial cull would be rejected by the British parliament, had been expected to go it alone and reduce the number of cattle to be slaughtered and was discussing the possibility with ministers on Thursday.</p>
<p>But this would have broken an agreement reached between Major and other EU leaders in Florence in June under which Britain was to impose the cull and other measures to eradicate BSE in return for a gradual lifting of the ban on British beef exports.</p>
<p>But at the same time the Commission did not want to be seen to be faltering in its efforts to stamp out the disease which threatens to bring the European beef industry to its knees.</p>
<p>The export ban was imposed in March after Britain admitted a possible link between BSE and Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease, a deadly human equivalent.</p>
<p>The Commission's chief spokesman, Nikolaus van der Pas, stressed on Thursday that the Florence agreement remained in force.</p>
<p>&quot;The Commission stated very clearly...that for the time being there was nothing new. We have the Florence decision which is being put into effect and it remains in effect,&quot; he told the news briefing.</p>
<p>&quot;So it's business as usual and nothing will change until further notice,&quot; Van der Pas said, adding however that if there was new scientific advice it was only normal that experts in the member states should look at it.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
