<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65477" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU Commission says no U-turn on mad cow cull.</title>
<headline>EU Commission says no U-turn on mad cow cull.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission said on Thursday that it had not changed its policy on a plan to kill up to 147,000 cows in Britain most at risk of developing mad cow disease.</p>
<p>&quot;Suggestions in the British press today that there has been a U-turn by the Commission...are not true,&quot; Commission agriculture spokesman Gerard Kiely told a news briefing.</p>
<p>The European Commission eased pressure slightly on Britain by agreeing on Wednesday to examine the new evidence, based on computer studies, showing mad cow disease -- Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy or BSE -- would die out naturally in five years.</p>
<p>But Kiely said the evidence by Oxford University scientists had been passed to the EU's scientific veterinary committee 10 days ago.</p>
<p>He added that the report would be studied but should not be used as an excuse for delaying the cull.</p>
<p>On Tuesday EU Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler told a meeting of EU farm ministers that he was disappointed that Britain was planning to revise the selective slaughter plan and at the lack of progress since the Florence EU summit in June.</p>
<p>The report contained nothing new in that people knew the disease would die out early next century, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;That aspect of the information...is not new and is irrelevant to the purpose of the selective slaughter programme, which was never intended by itself to eradicate the disease,&quot; Fischler told the ministers.</p>
<p>&quot;Its aim is to remove those animals most likely to develop BSE as quickly as possible thus sending an important signal to consumers that we are taking effective measures to protect their health and to restore their confidence in British beef,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The ministers rejected a British bid to reduce the number of cattle to be killed.</p>
<p>Europe has been battling to restore confidence in beef since March when the British government created a massive health scare by saying that BSE could be transmitted to humans.</p>
<p>British ministers were meeting on Thursday to consider whether to stick with the cull programme or scale it back.</p>
<p>Fearing a parliamentary rebellion from ruling party members opposed to the full cull, Prime Minister John Major and his colleagues were expected to cut back on the slaughter programme or introduce measures to protect the domestic beef market.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
