<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67787" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germans slam British for scrapping cattle cull.</title>
<headline>Germans slam British for scrapping cattle cull.</headline>
<byline>Douglas Busvine</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>German leaders, consumer groups and farmers threw their weight behind the European Commission on Friday to oppose lifting a ban on British beef exports after London abandoned a cull of cattle at risk from mad cow disease.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said the British decision was &quot;not acceptable&quot;, while the head of the European Parliament -- a German -- said it would be better for Britain to quit the EU altogether if it would not respect joint decisions.</p>
<p>Britain decided to ignore a vote by EU farm ministers this week and abandon a commitment made in June to slaughter 147,000 cattle at risk from Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE).</p>
<p>That move has aroused anger in Germany, one of the first European countries to slap a unilateral block on British beef last spring after scientists found a link between BSE and a fatal human brain-wasting disease.</p>
<p>&quot;The main priority is the health of the consumer. The ban on importing British cattle, beef and other products will remain in force,&quot; Kinkel said in a statement released in Bonn.</p>
<p>European Parliament President Klaus Haensch went further.</p>
<p>&quot;If the British abandon the Union's internal solidarity, when they don't respect decisions taken together, then they do not belong in the Union,&quot; he told Saarland radio.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be better if such a member state left the Union.&quot;</p>
<p>Britain based its decision on a new study by scientists from Oxford University which showed the cull was unnecessary because BSE would die out naturally within five years.</p>
<p>But Commission President Jacques Santer and Agriculture Commissioner Franz Fischler both said on Friday Britain was still bound by its promise to cull the cattle as part of a step-by-step plan to lift the ban.</p>
<p>Germany's Farmers Association in Bonn joined the chorus of criticism, saying it was &quot;outraged&quot; by Britain's decision.</p>
<p>&quot;We call on the government and all other member states to exclude Britain from the European beef market until it fulfils its commitments to the European Union,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>Germany's 300,000 beef farmers have been hit by a slide of nearly half in beef consumption in the past five years linked to the BSE scare. Price falls since 1994 mean they now get 400 marks ($270) less for each bull sold, a spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Germany has also been swept by consumer health fears that humans could contract the deadly Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease (CJD) from dairy produce after it was found that cows could pass BSE on to their calves through their milk.</p>
<p>Consumer groups also said they backed Brussels' position.</p>
<p>&quot;We must stick to this strict export ban until the whole slaughter is complete,&quot; Susanne Hampel-Masfeld of the Bonn-based Consumer Initiative group told Reuters.</p>
<p>Hampel-Masfeld said her group was advising consumers not to buy imported milk or cheese until the produce is given a clean bill of health. &quot;We think that this whole problem is so unclear that we should be careful,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The umbrella organisation of German consumer associations also slammed the British decision as irresponsible. It said the move could have waited until a meeting in October of Commission science committees to review the findings of the Oxford study.</p>
<p>&quot;Germany's consumer associations see no reason to give the all-clear,&quot; a statement said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
