<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69536" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRELAND: Britain in dock over BSE at EU farm meeting.</title>
<headline>Britain in dock over BSE at EU farm meeting.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>KILLARNEY, Ireland 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain came under renewed attack from its European Union partners on Sunday for failing to carry out in full a cattle cull that was supposed to end the beef crisis over mad cow disease.</p>
<p>&quot;I always try to be friendly to everyone, but they (the British) cause us problems,&quot; French Agriculture Minister Philippe Vasseur told reporters on arrival for a three-day informal meeting of EU agriculture ministers.</p>
<p>Other EU ministers criticised Britain for announcing last week that it was suspending the slaughter of up to 147,000 cattle, agreed at an EU summit in Florence to stamp out mad cow disease so that a ban on British beef exports could be lifted.</p>
<p>Asked if he was angry at Britain, Austria's Wilhelm Molterer replied: &quot;Yes, of course. There was a solution in Florence. My position is clear. This agreement has to be held to.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked the same question, Belgium's Karel Pinxten said: &quot;Yes, indeed. I think they (Britain) took the wrong decision. We feel that the crisis started in Britain but we suffer a lot from it.&quot;</p>
<p>Britain says it will slaughter around one million older cattle a year but it said last week new scientific research indicated the destruction of younger cows would not hasten the end of mad cow disease (BSE).</p>
<p>Other European countries regarded its decision as a surrender to a powerful and traditionally pro-Conservative party farm lobby and a gesture towards right-wing anti-Europeans in the ruling Conservative party.</p>
<p>British Agriculture Minister Douglas Hogg tried to play down media speculation that an EU verbal onslaught awaited him at the meeting in the southern Irish town of Killarney.</p>
<p>&quot;I am sure that beef and BSE will be discussed but we will be primarily dwelling on the long-term strategic requirements for addressing the problem of the beef industry in Europe,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Irish farmers gathered at the gates of the Killarney conference centre hotel to protest at a slump in beef prices since Britain said in March there was a possible a link between Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE) and a fatal brain-wasing disease in humans.</p>
<p>Irish Agriculture Miniser Ivan Yates said earlier he would do everything possible to defuse the dispute but he laid the onus on Britain and said it had to carry out the Florence plan.</p>
<p>Irish officials said they did not want the meeting, which includes visits to model farms and informal working sessions, to turn into a &quot;BSE summit.&quot; They hope it will focus on steps to restore consumer confidence across Europe in beef.</p>
<p>Britain's statement in March caused a crash in beef prices and the EU imposed a worldwide ban on British beef exports six months ago to try to &quot;ring fence&quot; what it saw as a mainly British problem.</p>
<p>Britain subsequently declared a policy of non-cooperation in Europe, blocking dozens of EU decisions, until the Florence summit agreed on a phased lifting of the ban subject to Britain carrying out the cull and other measures.</p>
<p>&quot;There was an agreement in Florence,&quot; said Sweden's minister, Annika Ahnberg. &quot;So (Britain's decision) is not very good.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KILLARNEY, Ireland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
