<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82540" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - British cattlemen keep stiff upper lip over BSE.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - British cattlemen keep stiff upper lip over BSE.</headline>
<byline>Dale Faulken</byline>
<dateline>HAILSHAM, England 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dairy farmer Phil Hook has been raising cattle all his life and would normally sell 20 cows at auction every week.</p>
<p>But Hook no longer bothers taking his cattle to market. The mad cow crisis has all but finished him.</p>
<p>It is six months since the British government admitted that eating beef could give people the fatal brain disease CJD (Creuzfeldt-Jacob Disease) and it has been a time of painful change for the beef industry.</p>
<p>The impact of a worldwide ban on beef exports imposed by the European Union on March 27 can be plainly seen at the livestock market in Hailsham, 50 miles (80 km) south of London.</p>
<p>On a normal day 145 cattle used to be sold. But Hailsham's daily average is now around 95 as fewer traders and retailers come to the auction because of the slump in demand.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm having a real cash flow problem. I have to feed cattle I can't sell,&quot; Hook said. Next week he will go to his local bank manager and ask for an increase in his overdraft.</p>
<p>&quot;It's terribly frustrating. British beef is the safest and the best in the world but it's all about politics not science,&quot; said Peter Saunders, a beef exporter and owner of one of southern England's largest abattoirs.</p>
<p>Saunders believes European politicians are using the BSE crisis as a political lever to force the British government to toe the line on closer European monetary integration.</p>
<p>&quot;If we agreed to join the common currency with Germany and France the ban would be lifted within a week,&quot; he said before bidding 1.00 pound ($1.55) a kg (2.2 lb) for a prime Sussex steer.</p>
<p>Saunders, who used to pay 1.40 pound a kg before the scare, has seen his meat export business plunge by 90 percent since March. He has managed to survive only through a government compensation scheme and with money earned by his participation in the cull of cattle over the age of 30 months.</p>
<p>But the cull, aimed to revive consumer confidence in beef, has hit serious problems, both political and structural.</p>
<p>Last week, the British government put on hold a separate cull of up to 147,000 younger cattle most at risk from bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE) because of new evidence from researchers that the disease would die out in five years.</p>
<p>The European Union (EU) said the decision to suspend the additional cull ruled out for now the lifting of their ban.</p>
<p>Saunders, whose abattoir deals with 500 cattle a week, said the government had little choice but to suspend the additional cull because of the huge buildup of cattle from the rolling programme.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a serious backlog of older cattle. I think there are a lot more cattle than even the government realises.&quot;</p>
<p>Abattoirs could process twice as many cattle but the renderers who dispose of the carcasses cannot cope, Saunders said. He expects the backlog to increase when abattoirs and renderers start processing sheep in the autumn.</p>
<p>Around 550,000 older cattle have been slaughtered since the cull began, according to the Intervention Board for Agricultural Produce (IBAP), the government agency coordinating the operation.</p>
<p>Over the next three years IBAP expects to kill three million cattle at a cost to the taxpayer of around 1.65 billion pounds ($2.56 billion). The EU has promised to reimburse Britain 70 percent of the cost but that still leaves the Treasury with a large shortfall.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Major said in June that the total cost to the British taxpayer was expected to be around two billion pounds ($3.1 billion) over the next three years.</p>
<p>The cull has been criticised by right-wing &quot;Euro-sceptic&quot; members of Major's ruling Conservative party who already believe the EU has too much influence on British domestic policies.</p>
<p>Major has a majority of just one in parliament and the ban on British beef has made the task of keeping his government from unravelling ahead of the next election -- due by May next year -- all the more difficult.</p>
<p>&quot;In the light of the government's problems here with its own party, they had to be sure that Europe were going to properly look at all of the scientific evidence,&quot; said Sir David Naish, president of the National Farmers Union.</p>
<p>Political posturing &quot;has not been helpful&quot; according to Hook, who like most dairy and cattle farmers, grazes his herd on grass in summer but must buy costly feed for the coming winter.</p>
<p>&quot;Small tenant farmers like myself all across the country just cannot afford to keep going on indefinitely. Politicians need to stop talking and sort this problem out,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>British beef is still being sold in Britain but trade is well below their pre-crisis levels. Alex Mofitt, who owns two local butchers' shops, would normally buy six beasts a week at Hailsham but now only bids on one.</p>
<p>&quot;Beef sales in my shops are down by 80 percent. I can't give away mince or stewing steak,&quot; Mofitt said. He has had to lay off staff because of the downturn. &quot; People will come back to beef but it will take time -- a long time.&quot;</p>
<p>Time is something that many beef farmers across Britain do not have, according to the auctioneer at Hailsham market, Roger Waters.  &quot;At the moment we are not like the French. It's just not cricket to go and block the roads so we have been very English -- keeping a stiff upper lip,&quot; said Waters.</p>
<p>But he believes this could change as farmers like Hook are forced to buy expensive feed for cattle that cannot be culled because of a growing backlog. Frustration will grow along with their debts.</p>
<p>&quot;I think when the autumn comes the farmers could take action and march on Downing Street (Major's official residence) and cause problems for the government like the French farmer does.&quot; (1 pound = $1.55)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAILSHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
