<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="12874" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Conrad Black turns 52, Canadian Press gets present.</title>
<headline>Conrad Black turns 52, Canadian Press gets present.</headline>
<byline>Sarah Edmonds</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Newspaper magnate Conrad Black celebrated his 52nd birthday on Sunday in the unfamiliar role of white knight after galloping in last week to grant a reprieve to the Canadian press.</p>
<p>One of Black's trusted managers, Sterling Newspapers chairman Michael Sifton, took over on Wednesday as chairman of the 79-year-old news service, which was endangered earlier this year when Southam Inc., its biggest-circulation member, threatened to pull out of the cooperative.</p>
<p>Black's Hollinger Inc. bought control of Southam, Canada's best-respected newspaper chain, in May. Two months later Southam's chief executive, William Ardell, who wanted to revamp Southam's news service to compete with CP, quit.</p>
<p>Despite Black's recent acquisition of the lion's share of the newspaper industry in his native Canada and the appointment of a close lieutenant to run CP, Hollinger disputes that it has an iron grip on Canada's press.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not, absolutely not, a Hollinger ... coup,&quot; David Radler, Hollinger's president and chief operating officer, said of Sifton's appointment to head CP.</p>
<p>Black, who turned 52 on Sunday, is the youngest of the current breed of global newspaper magnates. Like Rupert Murdoch, he is not often seen as a hero by the media.</p>
<p>Black began with a C$500 ($365) investment in two tiny Canadian newspapers, and with a little help from a multimillion-dollar family inheritance, he parlayed that into the Hollinger empire, which now spans three continents.</p>
<p>Southam is the newest addition to Black's media toy chest, which includes the Daily and Sunday Telegraph in London, the Chicago Sun-Times, the Jerusalem Post and a 25 percent stake in John Fairfax Holdings Inc., which publishes the Sydney Morning Herald and the Australian Financial Review.</p>
<p>Black has candidly confessed his delight at the respect and deference granted newspaper proprietors and admitted he likes hobnobbing with the rich, famous and powerful. His long-standing love affair with newspapers does not extend to the journalists he employs, however.</p>
<p>Before a government commission on mass media in 1969, Black dismissed reporters as &quot;ignorant, lazy, opinionated, intellectually dishonest and inadequately supervised&quot; and slammed what he called an abdication of responsibility by many editors, publishers and newspaper owners.</p>
<p>There is no reason to think he has changed his mind since. After a strike at the Telegraph forced management to step successfully into the breach for 36 hours, Black said &quot;one of the greatest myths in the industry&quot; was that journalists were required to produce a newspaper.</p>
<p>Black said he was virtually forced to buy out Southam to protect his investment. Irritated with a group of independent directors who he said thwarted all efforts to reverse Southam's losses, Black bumped his stake up to 41 percent from 19.5 percent by buying out Power Corp. of Canada.</p>
<p>His move on Southam seems to be classic Black. He usually starts with a small shareholding, ups it to a controlling interest and eventually acquires the entire business.</p>
<p>This is how Black won the Telegraph and, earlier, acquired Argus Corp., a company where his father had been an executive and one he had reportedly coveted since childhood.</p>
<p>Black's managers and board representatives are fast replacing those who opposed him at Southam. Defections emptied Southam's executive suite last week. Black is now chairman and chief executive of Southam, and Radler is deputy chairman.</p>
<p>The young Black was apparently riveted by the character of Napoleon, &quot;A Life in Progress,&quot; whom he describes in his autobiography as an accomplished &quot;aphorist, swashbuckler and self-mythologist.&quot; He might have been describing himself.</p>
<p>Black's tough approach to business once led Bob Rae, the left-wing former premier of the province of Ontario, to describe him as &quot;a symbol of bloated capitalism at its worst.&quot;</p>
<p>Even his friends admit he tends toward narcissism. &quot;I think you have to have a certain arrogance to aspire to this sort of thing ... and to push it through. I don't think you do that with the humility which Jesus has commanded on us -- He said the meek will inherit the earth, not own the earth,&quot; Stephen Jarislowsky, a friend and business associate who sits on many Hollinger company boards, said in a recent interview.</p>
<p>Black &quot;fell profoundly in love&quot; with London Sunday Times political columnist Barbara Amiel and married her in 1992.</p>
<p>Amiel, vice president of editorial at Hollinger, is a sought-after party guest in London, and British society magazines Harper's and Queen and Tatler have both named her one of history's most alluring women.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
