<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15628" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: United News to sell some local newspapers.</title>
<headline>United News to sell some local newspapers.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>United News &amp; Media said its regional newspaper division had decided to divest its newspaper holdings in Wales and the South East of England.  </p>
<p>United News said the decision was prompted by the desire to focus on its primary areas in the north of England.</p>
<p>&quot;The proposed divestment will allow us to concentrate on and develop our local media interests in the North, where we already have a strong portfolio of titles,&quot; said United News chief executive Clive Hollick.</p>
<p>United Provincial Newspapers (UPN), the UK regional newspaper division of United News, is the third largest regional publisher in the UK. It had operating profits of 28.6 million stg in 1995 on revenue of 184.4 million stg, the bulk of which was generated from its northern titles.  </p>
<p>Up for sale are UPN South East and UPN South Wales.</p>
<p>UPN South East includes 28 separate free weekly newspapers in London and the surrounding area. UPN South Wales has a portfolio of 19 free and paid-for titles including the daily South Wales Argus.</p>
<p>UPN's main titles include the Yorkshire Post, Yorkshire Evening Post and the Sheffield Star plus the Lancashire Evening Post. It also operates one of the north's leading newspaper printing centres at Broughton near Preston.</p>
<p>United News recently merged with media and financial services group MAI Plc.  </p>
<p>The group publishes national newspapers The Daily Express, Sunday Express and Daily Star and operates the commercial ITV television franchises for southern and eastern England.</p>
<p>The planned divestments are the latest in a series of sales of UK local newspaper groups.</p>
<p>Earlier this month Pearson sold its Westminster Press local newspaper unit to Newsquest Media Group for 305 million stg.</p>
<p>In June, EMAP sold its UK regional newspapers to Johnston Press for 211 million stg.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
