<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26681" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: TVB banking on pick up in holiday shoppers.</title>
<headline>TVB banking on pick up in holiday shoppers.</headline>
<byline>Kathleen Kearney</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's Television Broadcasts Ltd (TVB) is hoping for a pickup in consumer spending from October to boost second-half earnings, after its interim results fell short of expectations.</p>
<p>&quot;The broadcast media, like the print media, is tied to trends in advertising spending,&quot; said Alex Ying, general manager for corporate affairs at TVB.</p>
<p>&quot;Our viewership increased, but the advertising market declined.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts said the company's earnings performance was tied directly to trends in advertising spending which in turn are tied to consumer spending habits.</p>
<p>TVB surprised the market with interim results last week showing a downturn in earnings when most analysts were expecting a healthy rise. The company reported profit attributable to shareholders of HK$177.96 million, against HK$189.01 million a year earlier.</p>
<p>This represented a decline of 5.8 percent, while the market was expecting a rise of 20 percent.</p>
<p>The results of the territory's major newspaper publishing companies have been fairly dismal. Oriental Press Group Ltd , publisher of the Chinese-language Oriental Daily which has the largest circulation in Hong Kong, showed a 94 percent fall in earnings for the year to March 31, 1996.</p>
<p>Sing Tao Holdings Ltd, another major newspaper publisher, had a net loss of HK$146.40 million for the period.</p>
<p>&quot;Compared to other media stocks, these (TVB) results were the best,&quot; said SBC Warburg Ltd media analyst Andrew Farrant. He is forecasting a double-digit percentage decline in earnings for South China Morning Post (Holdings) Ltd, whose financial year ended on June 30.</p>
<p>However, TVB's earnings results still have analysts baffled. While the bottom line showed a decline, turnover was HK$1.33 billion versus HK$1.195 billion, a rise of 11 percent.</p>
<p>Robert Fong, media analyst at HSBC James Capel Asia Ltd, said TVB's interim results showed a sharp, unexpected downturn in the company's pre-tax profitability.</p>
<p>&quot;Operating profit margins fell to 15.9 percent from 19.4 percent during the first six months,&quot; Fong said. &quot;TVB is usually fairly good at keeping costs under control, so this large shift is surprising,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Analysts said this could indicate the premiums paid for prime time, which the company never clearly discloses, fell substantially.</p>
<p>Ying said indirect costs were kept below the level of inflation. However, he said direct costs associated with the production of more expensive programmes boosted overall costs.</p>
<p>In addition, TVB, which is now competing with regional broadcasters including Star TV and the territory's new cable TV service, Wharf Cable Ltd, spent more on computer facilities.</p>
<p>In the second half, advertising and sponsorship revenue generated from the Atlanta Olympics would give a boost to earnings, but analysts said more was required.</p>
<p>Consumer spending patterns in the territory follow Western holiday spending practices, with sometimes as much as 50 percent of a retailer's income derived from Christmas sales.</p>
<p>&quot;If we see a drop in consumer spending during the holiday period (the fourth quarter), then we will have poorer prices (for advertising time),&quot; Ying said.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
