<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38305" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FORECAST - Newsprint, TV costs to hit Mirror.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - Newsprint, TV costs to hit Mirror.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Higher newsprint costs and continuing losses from its LIVE TV cable television venture are likely to depress first half results from Mirror Group, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts are forecasting pre-tax profit in a range of 32.5-41.0 million stg when Mirror reports on Wednesday. Pre-tax, pre-exceptional profit totalled 39.0 million in the same period a year ago.</p>
<p>Panmure Gordon's Anthony de Larrinaga said that a 40 percent increase in newsprint prices is likely to add some 20 million stg to costs.  </p>
<p>He expects most of the shortfall to be made up by an increase of around 12 million stg in circulation revenue and growth of around five million stg in advertising income.</p>
<p>The group increased the price of its flagship Daily Mirror by 2p to 30p in March, as it sought to offset higher costs.</p>
<p>&quot;The performance should rebound in the second half because of falling newsprint prices and an improvement on the advertising side,&quot; de Larrinaga said.</p>
<p>He forecasts first half profit of 32.5 million stg but is expecting the full-year to total 87.6 million.  </p>
<p>The first half figures are likely to include some six million stg in losses from LIVE TV, Mirror's local cable television network launched last year.</p>
<p>The company has said it expects LIVE to break even within three years after total start-up costs of 25 million stg.</p>
<p>Mirror Group also owns a 46 percent stake in The Independent broadsheet, which lost a total of 18.9 million stg last year.  </p>
<p>De Larrinaga forecasts that Mirror's share of Indepedent losses will be around 2.5 million stg in the first half but said this should be virtually cancelled out by a profit contribution from Scottish TV.</p>
<p>Mirror Group has a holding of almost 20 percent in commercial (ITV) channel Scottish.</p>
<p>-- Keith Weir, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8793</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
