<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="42697" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China sacks president of outspoken newspaper.</title>
<headline>China sacks president of outspoken newspaper.</headline>
<byline>Benjamin Kang Lim</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's powerful Propaganda Department has decided to remove the president of the most outspoken newspaper in China's capital after it reported a poisoning case that caused a plunge in sales of a state-owned beverage manufacturer.</p>
<p>The Propaganda Department of the ruling Communist Party had decided to remove Cui Enqing as president of the liberal Beijing Youth Daily, Chinese sources familiar with the case said.</p>
<p>Chen Xing, a deputy editor-in-chief of the rival and conservative Beijing Daily, would replace Cui, an official of Chen's newspaper told Reuters by telephone.</p>
<p>Cui and Chen could not be reached for comment.</p>
<p>Distribution of the Beijing Youth Daily, the capital's most popular morning newspaper, was delayed until the afternoon on Tuesday. The post office, which distributes subscriptions to all publications in China, did not receive the edition until after lunch.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Beijing Youth Daily said the newspaper's Tuesday edition had been printed as usual and the name of the president had yet to be removed from the masthead. The newspaper is run by the Beijing branch of the Communist Youth League.</p>
<p>The Chinese sources said the Beijing Youth Daily came under fire from state-owned beverage manufacturer Hangzhou Wahaha Group for reporting last June that some children in the central province of Anhui had died after drinking the company's products.</p>
<p>Sales of the group -- among China's most profitable state firms -- plunged, prompting enraged executives to take their case to China's propaganda tsars, said the sources, who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>Wahaha's best-selling product is a yoghurt health drink for children. It had earlier said that sales should rise 20 percent in 1996 and 50 percent in 1997, and forecast a fivefold rise in sales by 2000.</p>
<p>Wahaha is a state firm that has seven joint ventures with foreign companies, including one with French food giant Danone.</p>
<p>The company argued that Chinese brand names should receive government protection because it was so difficult for state-owned enterprises to make money, the sources said. About 40 percent of China's state enterprises are in the red.</p>
<p>Wahaha officials reached by telephone in the eastern city of Hangzhou refused to comment.</p>
<p>Angry government officials had wanted to close down the Beijing Youth Daily, but Wei Jianxing, the municipal Communist Party chief of Beijing, had delayed closure plans pending an investigation, the sources said.</p>
<p>However, Cui was still sacked to serve as a warning to the liberal newspaper, the sources said.</p>
<p>It was not the first time the outspoken Beijing Youth Daily has run afoul of authorities. Chen Yi was removed as the newspaper's editor in chief two years ago.</p>
<p>The market-oriented Beijing Youth Daily, which woos readers with racier fare than its almost universally dull competitors, has seen circulation jump 30 percent this year. It has published sensational accounts of disastrous accidents and dared to report bad news.</p>
<p>All Chinese mass media are tightly controlled by the state, which wields them as tools of ideological propaganda.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
