<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="42824" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: FORECAST-Irish growth to lift Independent.</title>
<headline>FORECAST-Irish growth to lift Independent.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Marshall</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irish-based media group Independent Newspapers Plc is expected to post strong first-half results on Wednesday, with its Irish profits boosted by buoyant economic conditions and the demise of a major competitor.</p>
<p>Analysts said losses in the UK, where the company holds a stake in loss-making British broadsheet The Independent, would make a dent in the first-half figures, but other regions had all made progress over the period.</p>
<p>They forecast pre-tax profits of around 24 million Irish pounds, compared with 20.37 million in the first half last year.</p>
<p>Interim results have already been released by Independent's operations in New Zealand, Australia and South Africa, so attention will be focused on the performance of Ireland and Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;Ireland will be the main focus of attention,&quot; Riada Stockbrokers analysts John Clarke said. &quot;People are expecting quite a big jump in profitability in Ireland, and I don't think they'll disappoint on that front.&quot;</p>
<p>Clarke said the demise of the rival Irish Press newspaper group, which collapsed in mid-1995, would have boosted profits.</p>
<p>&quot;Recent circulation figures showed the Independent group had been the biggest beneficiary of the demise of the Irish Press,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ireland's buoyant economic conditions should also have lifted profits in Ireland, analysts said, with growing advertising volumes and sales offsetting newsprint price increases.</p>
<p>Goodbody analyst Joan Garahy forecast pre-tax profits of 24.7 million punts. &quot;We're looking for a strong performance in Ireland based on economic growth. Advertising should be strong and the demise of the Press Group should have helped,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>In Britain, losses from the company's 46-percent stake in The Independent newspaper are expected to continue, although analysts believe there may be some improvement.</p>
<p>&quot;The indication is that it is beginning to stabilise and circulation figures are beginning to pick up again,&quot; Clarke said.</p>
<p>Aside from the figures, any comments on Independent's acquisitions strategy will be closely scrutinised. A joint bid by Independent and Mirror Group to buy UK regional newspaper group Westminster Press in August was unsuccessful, and analysts are waiting for Independent's next move.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a lot of talk about them missing Westminster Press, and whether they are keen to do something in the UK or not, and people will be looking out for any comment on that,&quot; Garahy said.</p>
<p>-- Dublin Newsroom +353 1 660 3377</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
