<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46991" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ireland's Independent Newspapers says profit jumps.</title>
<headline>Ireland's Independent Newspapers says profit jumps.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN, Ireland</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland's Independent Newspapers Plc said Wednesday that a strong performance from all its businesses helped boost first half pre-tax profit by 28 percent to a record 26.02 million Irish punts ($41.8 million).</p>
<p>The media group, flagship company of Irish businessman and H.J. Heinz Co. Chief Executive Tony O'Reilly, has operations in Ireland, Britain, France, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa.</p>
<p>Independent, which prints and publishes more than 12 million newspapers a week, saw half-year revenues rise by nine percent to 182.5 million punts ($294 million) .</p>
<p>&quot;We are very, very pleased with the results,&quot; Independent Chief Executive Liam Healy said in an interview.</p>
<p>The group's Irish operations, which recorded a 35 percent rise in operating profit, benefited from circulation gains and strong advertising income.</p>
<p>In Britain, the results of Newspaper Publishing were broadly in line with expectations and represented a significant improvement on 1995, Independent said in a statement.</p>
<p>Independent and Mirror Group each hold a 46 percent stake in Newspaper Publishing which reported a loss of 7 million pounds ($11 million) in the first half.</p>
<p>The Irish group said it hoped to see Newspaper Publishing, publisher of Britain's Independent and Independent on Sunday, return to profitability before the end of 1997.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN, Ireland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
