<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="48085" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Independent sees improved full-yr results.</title>
<headline>Independent sees improved full-yr results.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irish-based media group Independent Newspapers Plc said on Wednesday that full-year results are expected to show an improvement over 1995.</p>
<p>The group said in a statement that its strategy was to continue to expand and develop its products in print, electronic media and outdoor advertising throughout the world.</p>
<p>&quot;Our aim remains to provide our shareholders with a stake in a range of dynamic and expanding economies where shareholder value can be built over the long term,&quot; Independent said.  </p>
<p>Independent, which has operations in Ireland, Britain, Australia, New Zealand, South Africa and Portugal, reported a 28 percent rise in half-year pre-tax profit to 26.02 million Irish pounds and said it saw strong performances from all of its businesses.</p>
<p>In Ireland, the first half saw strong gains in advertising and circulation income, the company said. Each of its five leading titles made significant circulation gains over the same period of 1995 while the strength of the Irish economy was reflected in the increase in advertising income in the group's Irish publishing operations.  </p>
<p>The Irish operations contributed a first-half operating profit of 16.29 million on turnover of 83.66 million.</p>
<p>In Britain, the results of Newspaper Publishing, in which Independent has a 46 percent stake, were broadly in line with expectations and represented a significant improvement on 1995.</p>
<p>Circulation on the daily UK Independent averaged 280,000 in the first half and more than 303,000 on the Independent on Sunday.</p>
<p>But Newspaper Publishing accounted for the bulk of the loss from Independent's associated undertakings in the UK. This rose to 2.94 million from 0.72 million in the first half of 1995.  </p>
<p>Finance director James Parkinson noted that this year's figure takes in six months of the Newspaper Publishing loss compared with just one month the previous year.</p>
<p>Independent Newspapers (UK), the largest paid for group of London regional newspapers, and Independent Magazines (UK) which operates a range of recruitment and sporting magazine titles, recorded significantly improved performances. Outdoor advertiser Buspak (UK) moved into profit during the second quarter and Independent increased its shareholding in it to 51 percent.</p>
<p>Overall UK operating profits rose to 1.61 million from 0.82 million with turnover up at 12.55 million from 8.41 million.  </p>
<p>In France outdoor advertising business Sirocco saw operating profits rise by 44 percent to 1.01 million against a background of continued sluggish economic growth.</p>
<p>The group's South African operations contributed 8.23 million to operating profits, up from 6.96 million last year.</p>
<p>Independent's associated undertakings in Australia and New Zealand, which include Australian Provincial Newspapers Holdings Ltd and Wilson and Horton Ltd slipped to 3.51 from 3.61 million last year.</p>
<p>Cable television company Princes Holdings saw its net income, boosted by premium subscriptions, improve by 53 percent over the same period of 1995.</p>
<p>-- Dublin Newsroom +353 1 676 9779</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
