<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66425" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New York Times names Lewis president, COO.</title>
<headline>New York Times names Lewis president, COO.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York Times Co said on Friday that Lance Primis had resigned as president and chief operating officer and would be succeeded by Russell Lewis, president and general manager of the New York Times newspaper.  </p>
<p>Janet Robinson, senior vice president-advertising of the newspaper, will replace Lewis as newspaper president and general manager, New York Times Co said.</p>
<p>Chairman and Chief Executive Officer Arthur Ochs Sulzberger made the announcement after a regular meeting the company's board.</p>
<p>&quot;Lance wanted to be free to seek a more certain opportunity to run an enterprise and thought it would be appropriate to relinquish his responsibilities,&quot; Sulzberger was quoted as saying.  </p>
<p>Sulzberger will still have overall responsibility for the newspaper's news and business operations, the company said.</p>
<p>Daniel Cohen, vice president of advertising sales for the newspaper, will succeed Robinson, the company said.</p>
<p>About Lewis, Sulzberger said, &quot;I have known Russ Lewis for 30 years and look forward to a strong partnership as we continue to implement and build our growth strategy.&quot;</p>
<p>Lewis, 49, has been responsible for the newspaper's business functions, including production, circulation, advertising, financial and planning, the company said.  </p>
<p>He joined The Times in 1966 as a copy boy.</p>
<p>Sulzberger said the changes would help the company achieve its strategy of investing in core businesses, increasing its holdings in traditional and new media, and focusing on reengineering and revenue building.</p>
<p>-- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
