<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70379" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK's SCMP survives tough yr relatively unscathed.</title>
<headline>HK's SCMP survives tough yr relatively unscathed.</headline>
<byline>Tan Ee Lyn</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong newspaper publisher South China Morning Post (Holdings) Ltd on Monday posted a 20 percent increase in 1995/96 net profit with the help of gains from the sale of its old headquarters building.</p>
<p>SCMP's operating profits shrank during a trying year for publishers, but the company said it saw a better year ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect an improvement in the Hong Kong economy in the coming year largely due to positive signs in the retail and property market, a lower unemployment figure, and an anticipated increase of visitors to Hong Kong,&quot; company said.</p>
<p>Together with an expected drop in newsprint costs and improved results from its new subsidiary TVE (Holdings) Ltd, that would provide for a &quot;rewarding year ahead&quot;, it said.</p>
<p>SCMP announced a 20 percent jump in net profit to HK$695.87 million (US$90 million) in the year to June 30, helped by an exceptional gain of HK$181 million from sale of its old headquarters building in Hong Kong's Quarry Bay district.</p>
<p>But prior to exceptionals and contribution from associates, operating profit fell to HK$602.34 million from HK$692.71 million.</p>
<p>Analysts said SCMP, which publishes the English-language South China Morning Post daily in Hong Kong, rode through a difficult year relatively unscathed, and added it was likely to turn in better results in the coming year.</p>
<p>&quot;In light of the difficult conditions, SCMP has done fairly well and better than the market expected,&quot; said Robert Fong, a media analyst with James Capel.</p>
<p>Analysts said Hong Kong newspapers faced an extraordinarily trying 1995/96 due to steep rises in newsprint costs, a downturn in advertising and an aggressive newspaper price war.</p>
<p>The tough times were seen in the closure of several Chinese language newspapers, while the Oriental Press Group shut down its English-language daily Eastern Express in June.</p>
<p>In August, Oriental Press reported a 94 percent drop in net profit to HK$25.08 million for the year to March 31, while publisher Ming Pao Enterprise Corp Ltd plunged into the red by HK$9.39 million for the same period.</p>
<p>&quot;I would say the (SCMP) results are better than what many expected...I'm sure the Chinese press would have liked to have come out with only a 15-20 percent downturn in operating profit,&quot; said another analyst, who declined to be named.</p>
<p>Analysts also expected the group to turn in better results in the coming year with the turnaround in advertising spending and lower newsprint costs.</p>
<p>(US$1=HK$7.73)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
