<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78018" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Analysts see U.S. newsprint price bottom in 1997.</title>
<headline>Analysts see U.S. newsprint price bottom in 1997.</headline>
<byline>Robert Melnbardis</byline>
<dateline>MONTREAL 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Analysts say North American newsprint commodity prices are likely to head lower over the next few months and reach bottom in early 1997.</p>
<p>Newsprint is currently being sold to core customers in the eastern United States at $500 to $570 a metric ton, a precipitous slide from the price cycle peak of $740 a tonne in March.</p>
<p>Analysts expect the price to decline further in the coming months, possibly eroding to $500 a tonne and below.  </p>
<p>&quot;We will see $550-540 (a tonne) for October and then I will expect $500 before the end of the year and $450 bottom sometime early next year,&quot; said Richard Kelertas, of Bunting Warburg Inc.</p>
<p>Kelertas is one of the most bearish analysts on the outlook for newsprint prices, but others agree that the North American newsprint industry, including the big Canadian producers such as Abitibi-Price Inc, Stone-Consolidated Corp and Avenor Inc, are in for a rough ride in the months ahead.  </p>
<p>The main problem is that the industry is burdened by producer and consumer inventory surpluses that are heading toward historic highs.</p>
<p>Preliminary figures for August show that North American producer and consumer newsprint inventories (excluding Canadian consumers) were at roughly 2 million tonnes, well above the 1.6 million tonne norm expected for this period.  </p>
<p>Most analysts are now negative on the newsprint sector and expect to stay that way until sometime in 1997.</p>
<p>The Toronto Stock Exchange's paper and forest products index is down 22 percent from its 1995 peak and analysts say it could slip another three to five percent. Newsprint makers' stock prices could slip below their 52-week lows.</p>
<p>&quot;Things may bottom and stay at the bottom for some time,&quot; said independent analyst John Duncanson.  </p>
<p>Newspapers struggling to maintain circulation and advertising revenues have been cutting back on their newsprint usage. Conservation measures, such as printing smaller and fewer newspaper pages, competition from electronic media and mergers and acquisitions in the publishing industry have also crimped newsprint consumption.</p>
<p>Newsprint makers have also been hurt by their own zeal in ramping up prices aggressively in 1994 and 1995. The price hikes hurt newspaper publisher profits just as the industry was coping with tough circulation and advertising markets.  </p>
<p>Ironically, some of those hardest hit, Abitibi-Price and Stone-Consolidated, have been North American leaders in taking downtime at their newsprint mills in an effort to redress inventory surplusses.</p>
<p>Since January, Stone-Consolidated has taken a total of 128,000 tonnes of downtime at its Canadian mills, including three weeks slated for its Kenora, Ontario mill in  October, which is traditionally the industry's biggest shipment month.  </p>
<p>Saucier estimates that to bring producer and consumer inventories back into line, the operating rate for all of the North America industry must decline to 90 percent. If U.S. newsprint makers do not lower their operating rate convincingly, Canadian producers would have to drop their rate to 84 percent, an unrealistically low rate, he said.</p>
<p>Jim Rowland, publisher of the newsletter Canadian Paper Analyst, said the lack of industry discipline means newprint commodity prices could decline to the cash-cost level of the sector's highest-cost producers.  </p>
<p>&quot;A lot of smaller and mid-size producers have been running flat out,&quot; Rowland said.</p>
<p>Still, there are some hopeful signs on the horizon. While newsprint prices may slip further, consumption levels may have already hit bottom, said Saucier.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we have hit bottom in terms of consumption, but the price declines show how powerful an inventory correction can be,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>But it may take several months to work through the inventory surplusses That situation will be exacerbated by an estimated 3-4 million tonnes of new newsprint production capacity coming on stream globally from mill start-ups and machine accelerations between 1995 and 1998, mainly in Asia.</p>
<p>Canadian newsprint producers already have been diverting newsprint from traditional Asian markets to Europe, where prices are higher than their North American counterparts but are also falling.</p>
<p>&quot;When you've got tonnage that you want to move, you tend to spot price it, or offer deals, and that brings prices down,&quot; Kelertas said.</p>
<p>U.S. newsprint producers have not done their part to curtail production in the face of declining shipments, said Richard Saucier, analyst at ScotiaMcLeod Inc.</p>
<p>&quot;Since the beginning of the year, the newsprint industry's operating rate in the United States has been 97 percent, while it has been 91 percent in Canada,&quot; Saucier said.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Montreal bureau (514) 985-2434</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MONTREAL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
