<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85067" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Third rise seen in ex-HK to Europe air cargo rates.</title>
<headline>Third rise seen in ex-HK to Europe air cargo rates.</headline>
<byline>Jim Gilchrist</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Air cargo rates have been increased on Hong Kong's main long-haul routes with the prospect of more to come as airlines and freight forwarders report heavy peak season demand for both trans-Pacific and European traffic, Reuters research shows.</p>
<p>Airline cargo managers complaining of a 30-40 percent drop in rates to Europe over the past year said they are trying to claw back some of their losses and raised Hong Kong to Europe rates on August 1 by HK$3 a kg. That will be followed on October 1 with another HK$2 a kg rise.</p>
<p>Some airlines are now threatening a third increase during October to compensate for an 18 percent rise in Singapore jet fuel prices and yields which continue to be painfully low, they said.</p>
<p>Trans-Pacific traffic from Hong Kong is also reported to be strong as the traditional peak season for exporters gets underway. How long it will last, is the key question for airlines.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is very strong which is normal for this time of year. But I'm not so optimistic on how long the peak period will last for,&quot; said Philippe Bour, regional cargo manager for Air France in China, Hong Kong, Macau, Taiwan and South Korea.</p>
<p>He said rates had dropped by about 35 per cent compared with December last year.</p>
<p>&quot;In May and June rates to Europe were about HK$15-16 compared to $22-23 last December. We had to recover and even with the rise on October the first we will still be under what the rate was last year,&quot; Bour said.</p>
<p>One of the biggest air cargo carriers from Hong Kong - Lufthansa Cargo - said it cannot supply the demand to Europe despite August's rate rise with another increase imminent.</p>
<p>&quot;Not a single Lufthansa plane has left Hong Kong with empty space since early July. It has been a dramatic improvement over the first half of the year. Demand is higher than capacity which no one was able to predict,&quot; said Frank Berweger, Lufthansa Cargo's general manager in Hong Kong, South China and Macau.</p>
<p>Lufthansa, which operates its Hong Kong to Frankfurt service in a joint venture with Cathay Pacific, increased the number of freighters from nine to 10 per week in September. An 11th freighter is being drafted onto the route at end-October due to the strong demand. Airlines say the market has accepted the HK$3 a kg rise on Hong Kong to Europe routes which was imposed in August after a meeting of the main carriers .</p>
<p>Market reaction for the further HK$2 a kg rise on European routes starting on October 1 will be studied closely by the airlines.</p>
<p>&quot;The first three months were very bad for the whole industry because yield dropped by more than 20 per cent, so we are still a long way from what we need to maintain a long term profitable operation in Hong Kong,&quot; Berweger added.</p>
<p>But with demand said to be very high, prices on those key routes are expected to remain bouyant. A well known freight forwarder in Hong Kong said there has been little space available on trans-Pacific flights during last two weeks of the September.</p>
<p>&quot;There's been a real space problem, it's been very very tight for forwarders because one major toy importer has block booked all available space to Los Angeles. Freighters to Europe have also been very busy and there is a backlog on most of the major carriers,&quot; he said. He reported little movement in intra-Asian rates.</p>
<p>Polar Air, the no-frills cargo operator which has a trans- Pacific Boeing 747 service from Hong Kong to either Columbus, Ohio or Chicago five times a week, said higher fuel prices were wiping out any benefit from peak season rates.</p>
<p>But Polar's vice-president Asia Peter Hansen. said he was happy to report that the market had &quot;very definitely&quot; picked up.</p>
<p>Ray Jewell, cargo marketing and sales manager for Cathay Pacific Cargo agreed. He said trans-Pacific and long haul routes to Europe are both doing well. That contrasts with a poor load factors both trans-Pacific and to Europe in the first half which caused Cathay to fall short of its profit target for 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Utilisation and load factors on both trans-Pacific and European routes has been very good for the last two weeks and the market has definitely turned up. The seasonal peak has been as strong as we had hoped. The question is, and it is crystal ball stuff, how long the peak will last? Traditionally we are looking at through November,&quot; Jewell said.</p>
<p>He also said the market had generally accepted rate rises in August, which have increased yields.</p>
<p>But China Airlines' Hong Kong cargo manager M.F.Lai complained about low yields and said trans-Pacific rates were &quot;ridiculously&quot; as low as U.S.$2 a kg. He said the average trans-Pacific rate to the U.S. east coast is U.S.$2.45 per kg compared with $2.70 last year.</p>
<p>&quot;That situation has developed because of over-capacity,&quot; he said highlighting new trans-Pacific services to New York by Cathay Pacific and to Chicago by all-cargo airline Air Hong Kong.</p>
<p>There has also been increased competition since August 1 on the Hong Kong to Taipei route with EVA Air flying 16 times per week using Boeing 747 Combis. Both EVA's main rivals on the route - Cathay Pacific and China Airlines said there has been no significant impact on cargo volumes.</p>
<p>But China Airlines said it is concerned about EVA cuttnng rates to try and attract more business which again is hurting yields. Statistics from Hong Kong's Civil Aviation Department show that the Taipei to Hong Kong route is the busiest. The latest figures available for July shows 7,619 tonnes of air cargo was unloaded at Kai Tak airport and 5,642 tonnes was flown to Taipei - much of it to and from China.</p>
<p>Lai also said the differential between European carriers flying cargo direct and regional carriers such as China Airlnnes which takes longer to fly European cargo through its Taipei hub has narrowed to around HK$2 a kilo.</p>
<p>Macau airport, which also benefits from being a stopover for Taiwanese bound traffic from China has had a successful month attracting two new scheduled air cargo operators to add to EVA Air and Scandinavian Airline System services.</p>
<p>South Korea's Asiana Airlines began linking Seoul with Macau and U.S.-based Gemini Air Cargo began a DC-10 freighter service from New York and Chicago. Both airlines say much of their cargo originates in or is destined for Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Anthony Fong, managing director of Hong Kong based air freight forwarder U-Freight Holdings said European has now caught up with the traditionally stronger trans-Pacific market.</p>
<p>&quot;For the past 30 years, the trans-Pacific market has always been stronger but now the tables have gradually turned and traffic to Europe is booming at the moment. There is a lot of cargo being shipped to Asia from the U.S. and China is contributing to that boost. 25 percent of air cargo from the U.S. is China-bound,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Competition is fierce because everyone is hungry but we are fortunate in that we are not relying on the trans-Pacific market as the main segment and have west bound revenue as well,&quot; Fong added.</p>
<p>One interesting change in Chinese trade patterns was reported during September by Northwest Airlines which says it has suffered a 26 percent drop in tonnage of fish shipments from Hong Kong to Japanese dining tables. Much of that fish used to be trucked to Hong Kong from southern China but now is nowit's being taken by train or lorry to growing domestic markets within China.</p>
<p>Rates from Hong Kong to the Gulf are said to be &quot;holding up firmly&quot; at around HK$15 a kg with several airlines serving the main cargo destination from the territory, Dubai. According to Hong Kong Civil Aviation Department statistics, 565,183 kgs of air freight was imported into Hong Kong from Dubai during July and 957,167 kgs exported. That compares with 760,578 kgs of exports and 1,002,586 of imports during June.</p>
<p>Other statistics released in September by the department show the territory's the total air cargo handled by country during July rose by 1.6 percent compared with the same month last year. Air cargo imports on both scheduled and non-scheduled flights reached 62,714 tonnes and 68,328</p>
<p>Inter Asian rates are said to be firm with little change. Thailand continued to be the biggest Asian exporter into Hong Kong with 7,851 tonnes being airfreighted in and 1,994 tonnes being exported to Thailand, mainly Bangkok.</p>
<p>Regionally, there were also increases in trade recorded with China up 5.3 percent, South Korea up 4.3 percent, Singapore up 9 percent, Taiwan up 6.1 per cent.</p>
<p>Falls in Asian trade were recorded during July with Japan down 6.8 percent, Malaysia  down 6.2 percent and the Philippines, down 2.7 percent. --Air Cargo Newsroom Tel+44 171 542 7706 Fax +44 171 542 5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
