<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15865" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.AFRICA'S STALS SPEECH - KEY EXTRACTS.</title>
<headline>S.AFRICA'S STALS SPEECH - KEY EXTRACTS.</headline>
<dateline>PRETORIA 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are key extracts from South African Reserve Bank Governor Chris Stals' address to the central bank's annual meeting On Tuesday:</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;From the middle of February 1996 to the middle of August 1996 the average weighted value of the rand against a basket of currencies of South Africa's major trading partners depreciated by 20 percent. At this juncture, it continues to need coolheadedness from both policy makers and currency traders to restore stability to the foreign exchange market.</p>
<p>Not only the external economic relations of South Africa, but also domestic economic activity changed significantly from 1995 to the first half of 1996. Although the rate of overall real economic expansion has been retained at last year's level of about 3.5 per cent, the primary sectors of production, and particularly agriculture and non-gold mining, have since replaced manufacturing and the services sectors as the prime movers of the economy.</p>
<p>The growth in overall expenditure, however, continues to outpace growth in total production with the result that large imports of goods and services are required to maintain equilibrium between overall demand and supply. The current account of the balance of payments therefore remains in deficit and, in light of the decline in the net capital now become a matter of concern from a macroeconomic policy point of view.</p>
<p>The maintenance of the expansion in domestic demand continues to depend heavily on the extension of more bank credit which not only contributes to an unacceptably high rate of increase in the money supply, but also leads the country towards an untenable debt positin where an unduly high share of the current income of both government and households will be claimed for debt servicing. This dangerous prospect holds a serious warning for the banking sector to apply greater caution in their lending operations. It also dictates the need to continue with a restrictive overall monetary policy. Despite growing pressure from different sources for the relaxation of monetary policy, the Reserve Bank, in the interests of medium-term financial stability and longer-term sustainable eonomic growth and development, must persist on its current course of responsible monetary restraint.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;In this, the fourth year of the current economic upswing, there are clear signals of a cyclical slow down in the rate of economic growth. Although the rate of expansion in the country's gross domestic product is still set on course to achieve about 3 per cent growth for 1996, the main impetus for growth is now being provided by a recovery in the agricultural sector, following the adverse climatic conditions during the 1994/95 season. At the same time, steady growth in the output of the non-gold mining indusry continues to lend support to the overall growth rate. In contrast, the real value added by the manufacturing sector which expanded by nearly 11 per cent in the first half of 1995, increased by only 2 per cent in the second half of last year, before declining by about 1 per cent during the first half of 1996. The contribution of the services sector to growth has likewise slowed down with its total real value added increasing by less than 2 per cent in the first half of 1996, compared with 4.5 per cent during the second half of last year.</p>
<p>Total domestic expenditure continued to show erratic changes from quarter to quarter, but generally it increased at a rate higher than the increase in total domestic production. After 5.5 per cent growth in 1995, total real gross domestic expenditure increased at a lower average annualised rate of 3.5 per cent in the first half of 1996. Some slowdown in the rate of expansion of private consumption expenditure and smaller additions to inventories were partly offset by an acceleration in the rate of increase in consumption expenditure by general government, which rose by 3 per cent in the first half of 1996. Real gross domestic fixed investment did not maintain its relatively high rate of expansion of more than 10 per cent last year. Nevertheless, it still increased by 6 per cent in the first half of 1996. </p>
<p>&quot;Two major structural deficiencies of the South African economy were again tellingly exposed by the developments of the past year. Firstly, gross domestic saving continued to decline to a level of only 16.5 percent of gross domestic product. This was clearly not sufficient to finance in a non-inflationary way gross domestic investment equal to 19 per cent of gross domestic product, which in itself was still inadequate to sustain more rapid econmic growth. The decline in the net inflow of foreign capital during the first half of 1996, which made less funds available for financing real investment, provided a strong reminder of the urgent need for a significant improvement in the propensity of the economy to save. Similarly, with domestic saving at a low level compared to many other countries at the same stage of economic development, the present deficit on the budget of the Government of about 5 percent of gross domestic product also becomes unsustainable.</p>
<p>Secondly, despite the better economic growth performance over the past three years, very few additional job opportunities were created. In 1995 total employment in the formal non_agricultural sectors of the economy rose by only 0,6 per cent. Taking account of the growth in the labour force of more than 2.5 per cent per annum, the total number of unemployed people increased by some 280,000 last year. Unemployment remains the most intractable economic problem of South Africa, and drastic measures are needed to raise the labour absorption capacity of the economy. This problem, reflecting a serious structural weakness, cannot be solved by means of normal periodic cyclical economic recoveries, nor by any artificial stimulation of the economic growth rate. The Government's recently announced macroeconomic policy strategy contains encouraging prospects to make some progress in containing the growing number of unemployed over time.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;Triggered by an unfortunate combination of certain changes in the international financial markets, particularly in the United States of America, and several economic and political developments in South Africa that were construed to be unfavourable, the maket in foreign exchange displayed unexpected turmoil starting in February 1996.</p>
<p>An initial depreciation in the weighted exchange rate of the rand of 9 per cent from 13 February 1996 up to the end of March 1996 could still be justified in terms of underlying economic fundamentals such as inflation differentials, purchasing power parity, a weakening of South Africa's competitiveness in the international markets, and the growing deficit in the current account of the balance of payments. The subsequent further depreciation of 11 per cent from the end of March 1996 up to the end of July, however, could hardly be explained or justified in terms of these basic economic fundamentals. Unfounded rumours, speculative transactions and negative viws of the South African socio_political situation, forced the exchange rate of the rand to a value which now surely does not reflect the true economic potential of the country.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;It was fortunate that the depreciation of the rand occurred at a time when the Reserve Bank had no foreign liabilities outstanding, while it had also succeeded in reducing its net oversold foreign exchange position from over US$20 billion at one stage to only $8.1 billion at the end of February 1996. Thus, the net losses reflected in the forward foreign exchange position of the Bank were restricted to a smaller amount than would have been the case with a similar depreciatn at any other stage during the pst three years. This net oversold position has, however, increased again to over $15 billion as the Bank intervened in the forward foreign exchange market at the sliding exchange rate, mainly to enable importers to cover future commitments and to make use f available foreign financing facilities. It is true that an increase in the net oversold foreign exchange position of the Reserve Bank inevitably increases the risk of possible losses from future exchange rate changes. Such losses will eventually become ecoverable from taxpayers. This risk must, however, be measured against the costs to the taxpayers in general of a further fall in the exchange rate with accompanying higher interest and inflation rates. There is no costless way to adjust the  economy downwards in a situation where the inflow of capital from abroad has fallen so abruptly as was the case in South Africa earlier this year.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The excessive rate of increase in bank credit extended to the private sector...remains a matter of concern, not only because of its effect on the money supply, but also because of the rising levels of indebtedness of private houseolds. As pointed out in the Annual Economic Report, accumulated household debt has now risen to more than 66 per cent of personal disposable income. The stage has been reached where the average South African household has to earmark almost six weeks' of is annual income for the sole purpose of servicing the cost of its debt.</p>
<p>This situation also casts some doubt on the quality of the loan book of banking institutions. Controlling the amount of credit extension in an economy, when it has developed to the state in which South Africa now finds itself, cannot entirely rely on interest rates. Many of the more recent participants in the market economy remain relatively insensitive to interest rate changes since they base their applications for loans almost entirel on disposable income. Borrowers and lenders must become more aware of the inherent dangers involved in the extension of credit beyond the capacity to service debt on a sustained basis. Many South African households have already moved beyond these limits and may be heading towards a debt trap.</p>
<p>For good reason, interest rates in South Africa remain high. The level of interest rates cannot be dictated by the needs of borrowers alone, just as they cannot be fixed solely by the demands of lenders. In the final analysis, interest rates must be determined by the underlying demand for and supply of loanable funds. The huge demand for funds emanating from general government, the business sector and private households, must be matched with the limited amount of domestic saving plus an amount of medium and longer-term foreign investment funds that can reasonably be expected to flow into the country. This simplified macroeconomic truism confirms that South Africa, with its low savings and high consumption propensities, cannot have low interest rates for any length of time without running the risk of persistent high inflation. The upward pressure on interest rates is further exacerbated by the present overall balance of payments deficit.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;For monetary policy purpose it is of the utmost importance that the fiscal deficit and dissaving by government be reduced further. This will alleviate the burden on monetary policy to maintain financial stability,and thereby also allow for lower interest rates.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;Since February 1996, the net level of foreign caital inflows diminished, and a shortage of foreign exchange developed in the market because of the large deficit in the current account of the balance of payments. The Reserve Bank has had to provide some foreign exchange from its reserves to maintain liqidity in the foreign exchange market, and more particularly to enable importers to continue to meet their commitments in respect of goods already ordered some months before. The new situation of an overall deficit in the balance of payments is now effectively draining liquidity from the domestic money and capital markets, and exerting upward pressure on interest rates.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>&quot;Under current conditions, the monetary authorities must rely heavily on market forces to restore equilibrium.The disciplinary effects of these market forces are unfortunately not lways perceived to be supportive of the near-term macroeconomic objectives of government and of the expectations of businesses, private households and trade unions. Furthermore, since the relevant market forces needed to remedy an overall balance of paymets deficit invariably take time to show effect and are necessarily painful and costly, they understandably tend to be unpopular with the majority of the South African community. More particularly, a rise in interest rates at this stage, which forms one of he crucial elements in the market adjustment process, is widely regarded as unacceptable because of its adverse effect on domestic spending. This limited view, however,disregards the even more disastrous consequences for the economy of not correcting a non-sustainable deficit in the overall balance of payments.</p>
<p>As emphasised earlier on, the Reserve Bank is pursuing a policy which is partly intended to facilitate the arduous but inevitable adjustment process to restore a greater degree of overall balance of payments equilibrium. This means the economy must eventually adjust total domestic spending to a level that can be accommodated by the total of its production capacity plus imports. It must be possible,however, to finance total imports on a durable basis wih export proceeds together with a consistent inflow of longterm foreign investment funds. In order to make the inescapable adjustment more palatable, the Reserve Bank is, in the first instance, supporting the process by selling some foreign exchange from ts foreign reserves towards alleviating the market shortage. This policy action is being supplemented, also on a temporary basis, by allowing the Bank's net oversold forward book to increase again to a higher level. The Bank is at the same time deliberatey allowing market forces to work towards the required adjustment as reflected in the depreciation of the exchange rate of the rand, the decline in the amount of liquidity available in the financial markets, and the recent rise in interest rates. It follow that without or with less Reserve Bank assistance, the market adjustment processes will have to be stepped up, and the unpleasant adaptation executed with more vigour.</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank more than any other institution is aware of the adverse implications of high interest rates for many sectors of the economy. As part of its policy of gradual adjustment the Bank has nevertheless over the past twelve months allowed interes rates to rise, not only in nominal terms, but even more so in real terms. Monetary policy has indeed effectively been tightened as inflation declined while nominal interest rates were not lowered. Given South Africa's complex macroeconomic situation, the choice for monetary policy, however, is not only between higher or lower interest rates, but rather between high interest rates now or high inflation in the future.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - - </p>
<p>&quot;The present situation reflects many of the traditional constraints experienced in the past when the South African economy was at a similar stage of the business cycle.</p>
<p>Firstly, after more than three years of economic expansion, the domestic economy is now osing some of its vigour as reflected in a slowdown in the rate of expansion in manufacturing production as well as in the services sector, and also, as could have been expected, in most of the components of gross domestic expenditure.</p>
<p>Secondly, the overal balance of payments is in deficit because of large increases during the past two years in imports needed to supplement domestic production and to meet the requirements of large investments in both fixed capital and inventories, apart from the growing deand for consumer goods.</p>
<p>Thirdly both bank credit extension and the money supply are increasing at excessive rates, and they lag behind the slow down in the growth of real economic activity. This may reflect some distress borrowing, but may also be due to sructural changes in the South African economy. Over the medium term, however, the rates of increase in the monetary aggregates must be reduced and again brought more in line with the growth rate in nominal gross domestic product.</p>
<p>Fourthly, interest rates remain under upward pressure, and are placing an increasing burden on government, businesses and private households. The balance of payments deficit at its present level is obviously not sustainable, particularly after the substantal decline in the net capital inflow since February 1996. The challenge for macroeconomic policy at present is to assess whether the current slow down in economic growth will be sufficient to correct the external imbalance, and whether the current monetar policy stance is restrictive enough to underpin this unavoidable adjustment process. In this assessment, account must also be taken of the expected effects of the depreciation of the rand on imports and exports, which will only work through with some considerable time lag.The Reserve Bank's view is that, in the present situation, the Bank should provide some assistance to the market in foreign exchange by selling foreign currency from the official reserves, supplemented by available foreign credit facilites, if necessary. The Bank should also support the money market to assist banking institutions in bridging the period of transition to more stable conditions. In this way, the unavoidable but painful adjustments will become more tolerable. At the same time macroeconomic corrective market forces must not be impeded, but deliberately encouraged, where necessary, to restore balance of payments equilibrium with a minimum of disruption. Exporters have an important part to play in this adjustment process by taking advantage of the current favourable exchange rate. </p>
<p>The need for a downward adjustment in the rate of expansion in total economic activity will, of course, be reduced considerably if more long_term foreign investment funds can be attracted. The  effective implementation of the Government's Macroeconomic Strategy for Growth, Employment and Redistribution can make an important contribution towards creating a more friendly investment environment, for both foreign and South African investors. It also remains o crucial importance that the present wave of crime and violence be seen to be curtailed, and that greater confidence be gained in our determination as well as ability to achieve our longer-term economic goals in the interest of all the people of this country.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRETORIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
