<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="20760" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: PRESS DIGEST - Ireland - Wednesday August 28.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Ireland - Wednesday August 28.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the highlights of stories reported in the Irish press on Wednesday.</p>
<p>IRISH INDEPENDENT -</p>
<p>- Ireland's Prime Minister John Bruton on Tuesday offered talks at short notice to representatives of loyalist fringe parties following dire warnings that their ceasefire was on the brink of collapse.</p>
<p>- A man who was closely involved with the controversial All-Ireland Children's Hospice, which is being investigated by Irish police, is now involved in the organisation of a new charity for sick children.</p>
<p>- A woman prisoner has escaped from custody while on a day release from Mountjoy Jail in Dublin to visit her child at a health care centre.</p>
<p>- The auditor for one of the main trading companies in the Taylor and Associates Financial Services Group would not sign off the accounts of that company for the past six years meaning that accounts have not been filed with the Companies Office since 1989.</p>
<p>IRISH TIMES</p>
<p>- Irish political parties may receive one million Irish pounds a year less than they envisaged in State aid under the new Electoral Bill, if changes contemplated by the Minister for the Environment, Brendan Howlin, are adopted by the government.</p>
<p>- A file has been sent to the Director of Public Prosecutions about the alleged role of a Dublin solicitor in a car accident fraud network and 60 people are already facing charges.</p>
<p>- The Insurance Ombudsman of Ireland received 58 complaints relating to investment intermediaries in 1995, but could not act on them as they were outside her terms of reference.</p>
<p>- Future growth in the tourism industry could be jeopardised by a chronic recruitment crisis, according to CERT, the State tourism training agency.</p>
<p>- The outlook for mortgage lending remains bright, with the demand for new home loans expected to remain healthy for the rest of 1996.</p>
<p>-- Dublin Newsroom + 353-1-6603377</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
