<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="31404" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: BILL TABLED TO SET UP NEW S.AFRICAN TOURISM BODY.</title>
<headline>BILL TABLED TO SET UP NEW S.AFRICAN TOURISM BODY.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Attempts to upgrade tourism in South Africa took another step forward on Wednesday with the tabling of a bill to set up a new tourism authority, Tourism South Africa.</p>
<p>The new body will replace the existing South African Tourism Board, which was recently criticised in a tourism policy paper as being under-resourced and &quot;still associated with the old South Africa.&quot;</p>
<p>The Tourism Amendment Bill said that the aims of the new body would include promoting tourism to South Africa internationally and ensuring that services and facilities available &quot;comply with the highest attainable standards.&quot;</p>
<p>The tourism policy paper had said that there was &quot;a general culture of poor service in the tourism industry and related sectors&quot;.</p>
<p>It said that it was vital to &quot;develop inclusive, effective national, provincial and local structures for the development, management and promotion of the tourism sector in South Africa.&quot;</p>
<p>The policy paper also recommended the establishment of a fund to kick start a major tourism development thrust over the next three years and extensive training programmes to make South Africans more aware of tourism as a potential new source of growth.</p>
<p>&quot;Had its history been different, South Africa would probably have been one of the most visited places in the world,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Instead, the tourism industry had been &quot;woefully protected&quot; from foreign competition, international visitors and South Africans at large while catering for a small white elite.</p>
<p>As such, the potential of the industry to spawn entrepreneurship, create new services, drive other sectors of the economy, strengthen rural communities, generate foreign exchange and create employment had not been realised, the paper said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
