<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="31947" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Affluent Asians stimulate region's hotel industry.</title>
<headline>Affluent Asians stimulate region's hotel industry.</headline>
<byline>Mary Binks</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>The newly affluent in the burgeoning economies of Asia and a surge in visitors to the region are powering a boom in the Asia-Pacific hotel industry, travel industry analysts said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Tourism in the Asia-Pacific region is definitely growing, and not only from international traffic,&quot; said Rohan Dalziel, an investment analyst with Barings Securities.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the fastest growing areas is intra-region traffic.</p>
<p>&quot;People in Asia are riding the back of rising disposable incomes and, with the transition from some of the older Asian values to more relaxed Western work ethics, they're beginning to travel further afield,&quot; Dalziel said.</p>
<p>A new survey by PKF Consulting Ltd, a long-time follower of trends in the regional hotel industry, shows that in the first half of this year, the majority of markets saw increases both in occupancy and average daily room rates.</p>
<p>Hong Kong led the cities surveyed with the fullest hotels, posting a rate of 88 percent in June, up slightly from about 86 percent in the same period last year.</p>
<p>Sydney, up three percent from 77 percent, and Seoul, which maintained growth at 80 percent, followed Hong Kong with the highest half-year occupancy levels.</p>
<p>Bali and Jakarta showed the biggest growth in occupancy, and Seoul the largest increase in average room rates, which jumped 15 percent to $159 this year from US$138 last year.</p>
<p>Tokyo continued to lead the market with the most expensive average rate at US$178 for the first six months of this year, followed by Seoul and Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been an increase in the volume of tourists and business travellers to the region. Some markets such as Bali, Jakarta, Manila, and Tokyo, jumping substantially,&quot; said PKI's manager Susan Goodfellow.</p>
<p>&quot;In comparison to other regions, Asia has become the major focus of growth, and there's still a lot more potential for even further growth,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The World Tourism Organisation said in May the Asia-Pacific region was the biggest winner in the global tourism stakes. Its market share was expected to rise to 22 percent this year compared with 15 percent last year.</p>
<p>Hotel room occupancy in Beijing jumped to 85 percent in June -- the highest among cities surveyed -- from 60 percent in January.</p>
<p>More than 24 million overseas tourists visited China in the first six months of this year, up 11 percent on the same period last year, the official China Daily newspaper said recently.</p>
<p>&quot;China has become a focus for international tourism, and it's showing,&quot; Dalziel said.</p>
<p>In many countries around the region, the rise in disposable incomes was pushing the newly affluent further afield, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;What's happened in Asia is that very rapidly rising GDP (growth domestic product) is now filtering into the domestic populace in the form of better education, better welfare, and better exposure to information.</p>
<p>&quot;They now have the ability to travel, financially, and they now have the desire to travel,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Goodfellow said the British colony of Hong Kong, which reverts to Chinese sovereignty next year, remained the market leader in occupancy levels due mainly to its stopover role.</p>
<p>Hong Kong's Tourism Association says more than 10 million people visited last year, up from a record 9.3 million in 1994.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I66500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
