<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45168" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: FEATURE - Indonesia seeks further tourism boost.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Indonesia seeks further tourism boost.</headline>
<byline>Jim Della-Giacoma</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Looking at the map, tropical Indonesia can be as daunting to the tourist as it is alluring.</p>
<p>With more than 14,000 palm-fringed islands dotted with volcanoes, the only problem is chosing a location and figuring out how to get there.</p>
<p>Indonesia is the world's largest archipelago stretching more than 5,000 km (3,000 miles) in an arc between northern Australia and the Southeast Asian mainland, from the Indian Ocean to the Pacific.</p>
<p>Travellers have been lured to its seas for centuries and today the distances which have helped preserve its natural wonders and cultural mystique have also kept most of its picturesque islands from all but the most determined explorers.</p>
<p>But while this sounds good in the travel brochures, limits on accessibility are seen hampering the government's aim of doubling the number of tourists in the next decade.</p>
<p>&quot;The first need of tourism is accessibility. People now prefer to travel without taking too much time,&quot; says Andi Mappisameng, Indonesia's director-general of tourism.</p>
<p>This is particularly relevant because affluent Asians are increasingly looking at their own backyard for vacation spots.</p>
<p>Indonesia's answer is to build better airports and extend visa-free access to more nationalities.</p>
<p>Ten years ago, the airports of the capital Jakarta and the holiday island of Bali were the main entry and exit points. Now there are 21 designated gateways.</p>
<p>Five years ago, fewer than 20 overseas airlines served this nation of almost 200 million people. The number has now reached 38 and continues to climb.</p>
<p>Indonesia has also given visa-free access to 46 nations.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't mind as we need people to come to Indonesia and we have to facilitate them,&quot; Mappisameng says.</p>
<p>The strategy seems to be working. Last year, more than 4.3 million people visited Indonesia, 7.8 percent more than in 1994, and spent an estimated $5.2 billion.</p>
<p>Tourist arrivals for the first half of 1996 continued to grow, reaching 1.98 million compared to 1.69 million in the same period last year.</p>
<p>Mappisameng expects arrivals for the full year to reach five million.</p>
<p>The government has set a 10-year target to attract more than 11 million tourists a year by 2005. By then, Mappisameng says tourism will generate more than $15 billion, part of a strategy to diversify the nation's export base away from finite oil and gas resources.</p>
<p>&quot;In the last 25 years, we are the only country to have had an average annual growth in arrivals of more than 17 percent. It's incredible,&quot; he says.</p>
<p>Success has also caused problems.</p>
<p>New entry points in places such as Padang in West Sumatra, with stunning mountain lakes, or Manado in North Sulawesi with its world-renowned coral reef, are creating new markets rather than redirecting existing traffic that is threatening to swamp Bali.</p>
<p>While some worry about the environmental impact of the growing hordes of visitors, conservationists say greater threats come from over fishing, poaching or commercial exploitation.</p>
<p>Much of the impetus to preserve key natural assets is driven by their worth as tourist assets.</p>
<p>Mappisameng says the government will continue to encourage foreign investors to get involved with the tourism sector. Between 1988 and 1995, more than $6 billion was estimated to have been spent on improving tourism infrastructure, with three quarters of the total spent on hotels.</p>
<p>Indonesian tourism department officials said earlier this year there were 20,435 rooms in 43 international hotel chains in operation. Another 13,010 rooms were planned or being built.</p>
<p>National hotel chains have 10,636 rooms in operation, but only another 580 planned or under construction.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
