<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="45161" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore launches smile for tourists campaign.</title>
<headline>Singapore launches smile for tourists campaign.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1996-09-10</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore said on Tuesday it would launch a campaign to persuade people to smile for tourists and make welcome the tiny country's huge number of visitors.</p>
<p>The Singapore Tourist Promotion Board (STPB) said the campaign would kick off with &quot;Smile, Singapore&quot; television and newspaper advertisements and posters in underground trains and bus shelters.</p>
<p>It said in a statement those would be followed up with exhibitions and seminars to emphasise the importance of the tourist industry to Singapore, which earned almost Singapore $12 billion (US$8.5 billion) from seven million visitors last year.</p>
<p>The STPB said the aim of the campaign was to build up the image of an industry which &quot;does not enjoy the recognition it deserves among the population at large&quot;.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, the government, worried by slowing growth in the number of visitors to the country, said it would promote Singapore aggressively as a tourist hub for Southeast Asia.</p>
<p>That would be successful only if &quot;the man in the street understands how tourism impacts on his well-being, and displays a warm and positive attitude towards tourists&quot;, the STPB said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
