<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="48098" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: PRESS DIGEST - Ireland - September 11.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Ireland - September 11.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the highlights of stories reported in the Irish press on Wednesday.</p>
<p>IRISH INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>- Irish prime minister John Bruton last night gave a clear signal that a new IRA ceasefire is on the cards. He said he had received information &quot;that gives me ground for optimism&quot;.</p>
<p>- Union leaders last night backed a deal to end the strike at Irish retail chain Dunnes Stores, raising hopes that the company's 73 stores will be back in business next week.  </p>
<p>- The Revenue Commissioners are to begin investigating the names of investors and the amounts of undeclared money, if any, which was invested with Tony Taylor and Taylor Asset Managers.</p>
<p>- Matt Cooper, business editor of the Irish Independent, has been appointed editor of the Sunday Tribune.</p>
<p>IRISH TIMES</p>
<p>- Irish prime minister John Bruton has signalled that a new IRA ceasefire could be on the cards because of the progress being made by the Ulster Unionist Party and the SDLP in striking a deal on the decommissioning of arms.  </p>
<p>- Two Ukrainian women and their three children, who they claimed were victims of the Chernobyl nuclear explosin, were deported following refusal of their request for asylum in Ireland.</p>
<p>- The Irish Tourist Board, Bord Failte, is seeking up to five major corporate partners who will pay millions of pounds to promote their products alongside Irish tourism.</p>
<p>- Aer Lingus will begin negotiations with Aeroflot and Aer Rianta over the much-disputed rights to the Shannon-New York flight.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
