<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="55602" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAYMAN ISLANDS: Russian destroyer gets new role as dive site.</title>
<headline>Russian destroyer gets new role as dive site.</headline>
<dateline>GEORGE TOWN, Cayman Islands 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Russian destroyer mothballed in Cuba at the end of the Cold War was set to be sunk on Monday to become an undersea attraction for tropical fish and scuba divers.</p>
<p>The vessel was towed to Cayman Brac, one of the British islands off Cuba's south coast, on Friday from Cienfuegos. It will be sent to the bottom in an environmentally safe zone of sand in about 100 feet (30 meters) of water about 200 yards (180 meters) off the north coast of the island.</p>
<p>The Cayman Islands Tourism Ministry purchased the 330-foot (100-meter) frigate for $275,000 from the Russian embassy in Havana.</p>
<p>Russian officials said the end of the Cold War had made the Soviet fleet in Cuba obsolete, even though the ship cost $5 million to build in 1983 when it was commissioned.</p>
<p>The sinking, which had been scheduled for Saturday, was delayed pending a final inspection by the Cayman's Department of the Environment to ensure there would be minimal environmental damage.</p>
<p>The actual sinking of the ship, to be filmed by environmentalist and marine filmmaker Jean Michel Cousteau, will take about 24 hours while the vessel fills with water.</p>
<p>Tourism officials said they believed this was the first time such a dive site has been created in the Caribbean. Many ships have been sunk as artificial reefs off Florida's coast.</p>
<p>Soon after sinking, the ships become encrusted with marine life, offering food and shelter from predators for lobster, crabs and smaller fish.</p>
<p>The site is expected to boost tourism to Cayman Brac, the sister island to Grand Cayman, where the vast majority of the one million-plus annual visitors to this upscale western Caribbean British territory spend their time and money.</p>
<p>Cayman Brac, about 70 miles (110 km) east of Grand Cayman, has just two tourist hotels and a population of about 900 people, compared with the 32,000 people on Grand Cayman.</p>
<p>The ship -- called Russian destroyer 356 -- was renamed the &quot;Captain Keith Tibbetts&quot; after a local sea captain who was instrumental in the growth of the Caymans' tourism industry.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CAYI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GEORGE TOWN, Cayman Islands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAYMAN ISLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
