<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="57876" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>EU: REUTER EC REPORT LONG-TERM DIARY FOR SEPT 23 - DEC 31, 1997.</title>
<headline>REUTER EC REPORT LONG-TERM DIARY FOR SEPT 23 - DEC 31, 1997.</headline>
<text>
<p>****</p>
<p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
<p>****</p>
<p>DUBLIN - EU leaders hold special European Council (October 5).</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Inaugural World Trade Organisation (WTO) ministerial conference (December 9-13).</p>
<p>DUBLIN - Irish Presidency European Council of heads of state and government (December 13-14).</p>
<p>MONDAY, SEPTEMBER 23</p>
<p>PARIS (NEW ITEM) - Group of the Party of European Socialists present report on &quot;Public service television - the future of European television and cinema industry&quot; (1130/0930 GMT). Venue: Information office, 288, Blvd. St. Germain. Contact: Ambroise Perrin (322) 284 3062.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) holds seminar on &quot;World competition rules&quot; (1315/1115 GMT). Speaker is Karel Van Miert, member of the European Commission responsible for competition policy. Venue: Place du Congres 1. Contact: CEPS (322) 229 3911.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, SEPTEMBER 24</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Social Affairs Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision on the establishment of an employment and labour market policy committee.</p>
<p>- Modification of the &quot;carcinogens&quot; directive.</p>
<p>- Amendment of directive 86/378/EEC on equal treatment in occupational social security schemes.</p>
<p>- Council resolutions on equal opportunities between men and women and the European structural funds.</p>
<p>- Information and consultation of workers.</p>
<p>- Future of social dialogue.</p>
<p>- Joint report on employment.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - IGC Working Party of EU foreign ministers' representatives meets to continue review of EU treaties (To September 24). Topics include: issues on which proposals become available from delegations.</p>
<p>LONDON - European Commission hosts conference on &quot;Private security industry in society: a European perspective&quot; (To September 25). Topics include: vocational training, regulation, standards of service and employment. Venue: Forte Crest Hotel. Contact: Nigel Greaves Associates, Andrew Mackay (44) 1886 833 034.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Economic and Social Committee (ECOSOC) holds plenary session (To September 26).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - The European Aviation Club holds symposium on &quot;The impact of the third package&quot; (0915/0715 GMT). Speakers include: European Commissioner Kinnock Head of Cabinet Philip Lowe and Air Transport Policy Head of Unit frederik Sorensen. Venue: Amigo Hotel. Contact: the European Aviation Club (322) 647 0760.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) holds seminar on &quot;The inter-governmental conference&quot; (1315/1115 GMT). Speaker is Michael Patijn, State Secretary for Foreign Affairs, The Netherlands. Venue: Place du Congres 1. Contact: CEPS (322) 229 3911.</p>
<p>ROTTERDAM, The Netherlands - Royal Dutch Jaarbeurs holds conference on &quot;The European market for infrastructural projects - EMIP '96&quot; (1400/1200 GMT) (To September 26). Venue: Erasmus Expo and Congress Centre. Contact: Pieter Kannegieter (31) 30 2955 453.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, SEPTEMBER 25</p>
<p>GALWAY, Ireland - Informal Culture and Audiovisual Council (To September 26). Main discussions focus on developing a strategy for enhancing the position and role of culture in the EU and debate the importance of the cultural element in the EU's audiovisual policy, particularly in the context of the vital position of public service broadcasting services in EU member states. Venue: Galway University.</p>
<p>BERGEN, Norway - NATO defence ministers hold informal meeting (To September 26).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, SEPTEMBER 26</p>
<p>DUBLIN - Informal Justice and Home Affairs Council (To September 27). Discussions include the fight against drugs.</p>
<p>BERLIN - The Kangaroo Group in collaboration with the Fondation Europe et Societe host European Parliament and Commission conference on &quot;On the way to the European home market: the single currency&quot; (To September 28). Agenda includes: role of the single currency in the development of the EU; priorities of the Irish Presidency regarding the single currency; preparation for the move to the single currency; impact on the French banking system; impact on financial services and policy; impact on business; single currency and social aspects; relations between the single currency and the currencies which will join the EMU later; single currency and political union. Speakers include: MEPs Karl von Wogau, Giorgos Katiforis and Elmar Brok; Irish Finance Minister Ruairi Quinn; European Economy Commissioner Yves-Thibault de Silguy. Venue: Steigenberger Hotel. Contact: Kangaroo Group conference office (322) 284 4438.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (EXPANDED ITEM) - Forum Europe holds conference on behalf of DG XIII on &quot;Wide-screen television 16:9&quot; (0900/0700 GMT). Main topics discussed: Issues past, present and future; broadcasting beyond; the political challenges for 16:9. Speakers include: European Commissioner Bangemann. News conference at 1100/0900 GMT). Venue: Albert hall, 651 chaussee de Wavre. Contact: Forum Europe (322) 736 1430.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Club de Bruxelles hold conference on &quot;The future of Biotechnologies in Europe&quot; (To September 27). Topics include: development and role of biotechnology R&amp;D in the EU; innovation in health care: novel pharmaceutical products; new crops from plant biotechnology; the &quot;greening&quot; of industry: clean products and processes; biotechnology in Europe society: public perceptions; industrial competitiveness and biotechnological innovation. Contact: Club de Bruxelles (322) 743 1520.</p>
<p>DUESSELDORF, Germany - Euromanagement holds conference on &quot;The future of European thermal waste treatment - waste to energy&quot; (To September 27). Main topics include: how can you most benefit from the growing waste-energy market; how can you lower the costs of thermal waste treatment; strategic issues for waste to energy: opportunities v/ obstacles; the future of price policies for renewable energy across Europe; improving efficiency of waste power plants. Venue: Radisson SAS Hotel. Contact: Euromanagement, Michele Nichols (31) 40 2 974 944.</p>
<p>WARSAW - Euromoney Seminars holds third annual conference on &quot;The 1996 Polish investment forum&quot; (To September 27). Venue: Bristol Hotel. Contact: Euromoney Seminars (44) 171 7798793.</p>
<p>ROME - European Association of Advertising Agencies (EAAA) holds annual conference on &quot;The future of brand-building across borders&quot;. Contact: Paola di Discordia, EAAA (322) 280 1603.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, SEPTEMBER 27</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (EXPANDED ITEM) - Telecoms Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a European Parliament and Council directive on a common framework for general authorisations and individual licences in the field of telecommunications services COM(95)545.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a European Parliament and Council directive on common rules for the development of Community postal services and the improvement of quality of service COM(95)227.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a European Parliament and Council decision on action at Union level in the field of satellite personal communications services in the European Union COM(95)529.</p>
<p>- (NEW ITEM) Proposal for EP and Council directive on the application of Open Network Provision (ONP) to voice telephony COM(95)575.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) holds workshop on &quot;Completing the internal market for electricity: the meaning of the June 20th decision&quot; (1300/1100 GMT). Speakers include MEP Claude Desama. Venue: Place du Congres 1. Contact: CEPS (322) 229 3911.</p>
<p>MONDAY, SEPTEMBER 30</p>
<p>DUBLIN (NEW ITEM) - European Commission President Jacques Santer and Irish Prime Minister John Bruton meet Japanese Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto for the annual summit; to discuss EU-Japan relations and the international situation.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - IGC Working Party of EU foreign ministers' representatives meets to continue review of EU treaties. Topics include: flexibility, follow-up of specific issues in the light of first round of discussions.</p>
<p>DUBLIN - People First holds conference on &quot;Challenges of living and working in the European information society&quot; (0830/0630 GMT) (To October 1). Topics include: employment and economic structure in the information society; the future of work in the information society; labour market and learning in the information society; living in the information society. Venue: Dublin Castle. Contact: People First (353) 1 661 8904.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 1</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - General Affairs Council (To October 2).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Preparation for December WTO ministerial meeting.</p>
<p>- Mediterranean policy;</p>
<p>- MEDA regulation: adoption of the guidelines for the indicative programmes;</p>
<p>- Conclusion of negotiations with Jordan and Lebanon;</p>
<p>- West Bank and Gaza: Commission proposal for a negotiating mandate.</p>
<p>- Relations with Albania: approval of mandate to negotiate a new agreement.</p>
<p>- Former Yugoslavia:</p>
<p>- Follow-up to electoral process;</p>
<p>- Peace process;</p>
<p>- Medium/long-term strategy.</p>
<p>- Middle East.</p>
<p>- Mandate for negotiation of extension of steel agreements with the former USSR.</p>
<p>- Relations with central and eastern European countries; decisions of association councils.</p>
<p>- Approval to sign supplementary protocols to Baltic FTAs.</p>
<p>- India - Council conclusions on Commission communication.</p>
<p>- ASEAN - Council conclusions on Commission communication; protocol to ASEAN agreement to take account of Vietnam's accession.</p>
<p>- Preparation for SADC ministerial meeting on October 14-15.</p>
<p>- Food aid distribution regulation.</p>
<p>- Mid-term review of decisions on the association of overseas countries and territories.</p>
<p>- Draft joint action on anti-personnel landmines (possible adoption of further joint action).</p>
<p>- KEDO (Korean Peninsular Energy Development Organisation).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Preparation of the association council with Turkey.</p>
<p>- IGC ministerial session.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament, Regions and Local authorities hold joint conference designed to improve it's relations with Union's regional and local authorities and to discuss with them how to strenghten democracy and solidarity in the EU (To October 3). Contact: EP fax (352) 4300 2673.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Touchstone exhibitions and conferences hold conference on &quot;Managing economic transition in central and eastern Europe and central Asia&quot; (To October 3). Venue: Palais des Congres. Contact: Olga Arola, Touchstone exhibitions and conferences (44) 181 332 0044.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Agra Europe holds conference on &quot;CAP reform 1996-2000 and beyond&quot; (To October 2). Venue: Sheraton Hotel. Contact: Agra Europe (44) 1892 511 807.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 2</p>
<p>PARIS (NEW ITEM) - French Foreign Minister Herve de Charette and German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel meet ahead of October 5 special European Council in Dublin to discuss Franco-German position on inter-governmental conference.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (NEW ITEM) - European Aluminium Association holds annual international conference (1045/0845 GMT). Venue: Hotel Renaissance. Contact: Strategic Communications (322) 387 2191.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (EXPANDED ITEM) - European Trade Union Confederation (ETUC) holds conference on &quot;European Works Councils and the Europeanisations of industrial relations&quot; (1330/1130 GMT) (To October 4). Main topics discussed: European Works Council, an incitement social dialogue; the EP and the directive; voluntary agreements: developments from 1995 to 1996; specific aspects and experiences of existing agreements; advisory needs and training for European Works Councils; the transposition of the directive: the present situation; strategies at the sectoral level for application of the directive; EWC: a non-European point of view; role of EWC-Europeanisation of industrial relations. Venue: ITUH, Auditorium 155 Blvd Emile Jacqmain. Contact: ETUC (322) 224 0411.</p>
<p>NOVEMBER</p>
<p>- Irish presidency hosts conference on &quot;Local employment initiatives&quot;. Date and venue to be announced.</p>
<p>VENICE, Italy - Conference on fish management in the Mediterranean. Date to be confirmed.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, NOVEMBER 1</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - EU institutions closed for All Saints Day holiday.</p>
<p>MONDAY, NOVEMBER 4</p>
<p>EUROPEAN UNION - 1996 European Telework week begins (To November 11). The aim is to raise awareness of the business and work opportunities presented by telework and to provide opportunities to understand and use telework technologies. Contact: Horace Mitchell (44) 1 635 253 802.</p>
<p>VIENNA - Third European assembly on telework and new ways to work (To November 6). Main topics discussed are: getting people to work; training for life in the information society and working towards sustainability. Contact: Josef Hochgerner (43) 1 4950 442 42.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, NOVEMBER 5</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (NEW ITEM) - IBC Legal Studies and Services Ltd. hold third annual conference on &quot;EC Competition law&quot; (0845/0645 GMT) (To November 6). Venue: Radisson SAS Hotel. Contact: Holly Barton, IBC Legal Studies and Services Ltd. (44) 171 637 4383.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Transport Safety Council (ETSC) holds conference on &quot;Low-cost/high-return engineering measures for road accident reduction&quot;. Contact: ETSC (322) 230 4106.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - CENELEC holds conference on &quot;Standards on trial: case studies in European standardisation&quot; (To November 6). Venue: Sheraton Hotel. Contact: Annick Colman, CENELEC (322) 519 6889.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 7</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Culture Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Debate on European funds promoting cinema and television production.</p>
<p>- Directive amending the television without frontiers directive.</p>
<p>- Decision establishing an audiovisual guarantee fund.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a directive harmonising rules on media concentrations.</p>
<p>- Decision on Ariane programme.</p>
<p>- Decision on Raphael programme.</p>
<p>- First Commission report on consideration of cultural aspects of EU action.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision on rules concerning the European city of culture after the year 2000.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Green paper on new audiovisual services.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a directive amending directive 93/7/EEC concerning the return of cultural objects unlawfully removed from the territory of a member state.</p>
<p>CORK, Ireland - European Commission hosts European conference on &quot;Rural development&quot; (To November 9). Discussions will focus on the future perspectives for the Union's rural development policy. This policy seeks to address the challenges faced by rural areas in a way that considers all economic sectors and aspects of rural life and builds on their strengths.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (NEW ITEM) - European Voice holds conference on &quot;What future for industrial liberalisation in Europe?&quot; (0915/0815 GMT). Main topics discussed: European Commissioner Van Miert addresses on &quot;The future of competition policy in Europe&quot;; Commissioner Bonino addresses on &quot;Implications of liberalisation for consumers&quot;; discussions on how companies are facing up to a liberalised single market and debate on industrial liberalisation and competition. Venue: SAS Radisson Hotel. Contact: IBC technical Services (44) 171 453 2700.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Trade Union Confederation (ETUC) holds conference on &quot;Social protection&quot; (To November 8). Contact: ETUC (322) 224 0411.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, NOVEMBER 8</p>
<p>CHICAGO - Transatlantic Business Dialogue (TABD NEWS) holds conference (To November 9) to discuss transatlantic trade relations and develop creative solutions to remaining barriers to transatlantic trade. Speakers are: US Commerce Secretary Mickey Kantor, European Trade Commissioner Sir Leon Brittan and European Industry Commissioner Martin Bangemann. Contact: Stephen Johnston, EU Contact Point (322) 548 0693.</p>
<p>MONDAY, NOVEMBER 11</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Preparation for December 13-14 Dublin European Council:</p>
<p>- EMU;</p>
<p>- Employment;</p>
<p>- Report on taxation;</p>
<p>- (possibly) Banking and financial directives;</p>
<p>- Taxation issues.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament plenary session (To November 15).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, NOVEMBER 12</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Health Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for an EP and Council decision adopting a programme of Community action on the prevention of drug dependence within the framework for action in the field of public health.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision adopting a programme of Community action on health monitoring in the context of the framework for action in the field of public health.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive on the approximation of the laws, regulations and administrative provisions of the member states relating to the advertising of tobacco products.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council creating a network for the epidemiological surveillance and control of communicable diseases in the European Community.</p>
<p>- Setting-up of an EU-U.S. task force to develop and implement a global early warning system and response network for communicable diseases.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Transmissible Spongiform Encephalopathies (TSE).</p>
<p>- Blood safety/self sufficiency.</p>
<p>- State of health in the EU.</p>
<p>- Health protection requirements in Community policies.</p>
<p>- European health card.</p>
<p>- Pollution-related diseases:</p>
<p>- Rare diseases;</p>
<p>- Accidents/injuries.</p>
<p>- Statement by presidency on Alzheimers Disease conference (November 21-22, 1996).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, NOVEMBER 13</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Committee of the Regions holds plenary session (To November 14).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - EuroCommerce launches the business of adding value, an analysis of European retail and distribution based on a study by London economics, and the EuroCommerce recommendations for future policy in recognition of the vital importance of this sector to th European economy (1030/0930 GMT). Venue: International Press Centre (IPC). Contact: Catherine Piana (322) 230 5 874.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Agra Europe holds third annual European grain conference (To November 14). Contact: Agra Europe (44) 1892 511 807.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 14</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Industry Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes</p>
<p>- Steel:</p>
<p>a) State aids code;</p>
<p>b) Sixth monitoring report on state aids in steel sector;</p>
<p>c) (possibly) Future of ECSC Treaty.</p>
<p>- Competition:</p>
<p>a) State aids;</p>
<p>b) Merger regulation;</p>
<p>c) Agreement with Canada.</p>
<p>- Shipbuilding:</p>
<p>- (possibly) State of ratification procedure - OECD agreement.</p>
<p>- SMEs:</p>
<p>a) Proposal for a Council decision on a third multiannual programme for small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs) in the European Union (1997-2000);</p>
<p>b) Report on integrated programme.</p>
<p>- Competitiveness policy:</p>
<p>a) Commission's first report on the competitiveness of European industry;</p>
<p>b) A European policy for quality promotion;</p>
<p>c) Benchmarking;</p>
<p>d) Standards.</p>
<p>- Merger regulation:</p>
<p>- Review of regulation 4064/89 on the control of concentrations between undertakings.</p>
<p>- Automobile industry.</p>
<p>- Chemicals industry.</p>
<p>- Textiles:</p>
<p>- Communication from the Commission on the competitiveness of subcontracting in the textile and clothing industry in the European Union.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Recycling industry and environmental technology.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Space industry.</p>
<p>- (possbly) Cooperation with third countries.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - EuroCommerce holds conference on &quot;The business of adding value - European retailing and distribution&quot;. Main discussions focus on commerce in the cashless society and the challenges of multimedia. European Commission President Jacques Santer attends. Contact: Catherine Piana (322) 230 5874.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, NOVEMBER 17</p>
<p>QATAR - European Commission DG XVII and the Cooperation Council for the Arab States of the Gulf (GCC) hold joint conference on &quot;EU-GCC: extending the partnership to natural gas&quot; (and 18/11).</p>
<p>MONDAY, NOVEMBER 18</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To November 19).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, NOVEMBER 19</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Budget Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Draft Community budget for 1997 (second reading).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Euro-Mediterranean Committee for the Barcelona process meets (To November 20).</p>
<p>LONDON - Agra Europe holds ninth annual European and international dairy conference &quot;Dairy '96&quot; (To November 20). Contact: Agra Europe (44) 1892 511 807.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Forum Europe, UNICE, the European Round Table of Industrialists (ERT), Eurochambres, the EU Committee of AmCham, the European Automobile Manufacturers Association (ACEA) and the European Chemical Industry Council (CEFIC) hold one-day conference (0930/0830 GMT) on &quot;Europe's competitive edge&quot;. Main topic is: assessing the state of EU competitiveness, an agenda for future action. Main speaker is Martin Bangemann, Member of the European Commission with responsibility for Industrial Affairs, Information and Telecommunications technologies. Venue: Concert Noble, rue d'Arlon 82, 1040 Brussels. Contact: Clare Richardson, Forum Europe (322) 736 1430.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 21</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Education/Youth Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision on TEMPUS II.</p>
<p>- Conclusions on school effectiveness.</p>
<p>- European year of lifelong learning.</p>
<p>- Green paper on obstacles to mobility in higher education.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a recommendation concerning the assessment of quality in higher education.</p>
<p>- White paper on teaching and learning: towards the learning society.</p>
<p>- In-career development for teachers.</p>
<p>- (possibly) &quot;SOCRATES&quot; programme: draft decision amending the Socrates decision.</p>
<p>- Quality of higher education.</p>
<p>- General assessment of first and second level education systems.</p>
<p>- Commission proposal for a Council recommendation on the transferability of grants.</p>
<p>- Preparation of the structured dialogue with counterparts from central and eastern European countries.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, NOVEMBER 22</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Development Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- First ministerial exchange of views on ACP/EU relations post-Lome IV (Commission green paper).</p>
<p>- Further exchange of views on relief, rehabilitation and development.</p>
<p>- Resolution on the forestry sector.</p>
<p>- Adoption of a common position on the regulation on north/south cooperation in the fight against drugs.</p>
<p>- Adoption of a common position on the regulation on aid for population policies and programmes.</p>
<p>- Approval after EP second reading of the regulations on rehabilitation and construction in developing countries, refugees in Asia and Latin America, environmental measures in developing countries and HIV/AIDS related operations in developing countries.</p>
<p>- Horizon 2000 - coherence, complementarity and coordination.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Fisheries Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council regulations (EC) fixing:</p>
<p>- The guide prices for the fishery products listed in Annex I (A), (D) and (E) of Regulation (EEC) No. 3759/92 for the 1997 fishing year;</p>
<p>- The guide prices for the fishery products listed in Annex H to Regulation (EEC) No. 3759/92 for the 1997 fishing year;</p>
<p>- The Community producer price for tuna intended for the industrial manufacture of products falling within CN code 1604 for the 1997 fishing year.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation (EC) temporarily suspending totally or partially the autonomous duties of the Common Customs Tariff for certain fishery products (1997).</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Proposal for a Council Regulation laying down (new) technical measures for the conservation of fishery resources.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Proposal for a Council decision on MAGP IV.</p>
<p>- Commission report on third countries' activities in Community waters.</p>
<p>- Proposals for a Council regulation on the conclusion of the protocol establishing the fisheries rights and financial compensation provided in the agreement between the European Economic Community and the government of Senegal.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Conclusion of new fisheries agreements with:</p>
<p>a) Certain countries of South America;</p>
<p>b) South Africa;</p>
<p>c) Namibia;</p>
<p>d) Mozambique.</p>
<p>MONDAY, DECEMBER 9</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Inaugural World Trade Organisation (WTO) ministerial conference (To December 13).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- European Commissioner Brittan presents report on integrating multilateral clothing and textile pacts under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.</p>
<p>- Review of the implementation of Uruguay Round commitments.</p>
<p>- Endorsement of results of negotiations on services.</p>
<p>- Report from the committee on trade and environment.</p>
<p>- Any other trade-related issues.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Environment Council (To December 10).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council on the review of the European Community programme of policy and action in relation to the environment and sustainable development &quot;Towards sustainability&quot;.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive amending directive 90/219/EEC on the contained use of genetically modified micro-organisms.</p>
<p>- Auto oil:</p>
<p>a) Draft directive relating to the quality of petrol and diesel fuels;</p>
<p>b) Draft directive on measures against air pollution by emissions from motor vehicules - amendment of directives 70/229//EEC and 70/156/EEC.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive concerning the quality of water intended for human consumption.</p>
<p>- Commission communication on waste policy.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council regulation (EEC) No 3254/91 prohibiting the use of leghold traps in the Community and the introduction into the Community of pelts and manufactured goods of certain wild animal species originating in countries which catch them by means of leghold traps or trapping methods which do not meet international humane trapping standards.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation establishing common rules and procedures to apply to the shipments to certain non-OECD countries of certain types of waste.</p>
<p>- Follow-up to the conference on climate change.</p>
<p>- Fifth session of the Commission on sustainable development.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament plenary session (To December 13).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, DECEMBER 12</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Transport Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- External relations:</p>
<p>- Relations with the United States in the field of air transport.</p>
<p>- Recommendation for a Council decision authorising the Commission to open negotiations on air transport agreements between the Community and Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Poland, Romania and Slovakia.</p>
<p>- Negotiations between the European Community and Switzerland on land and air transport.</p>
<p>- Other measures:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to green paper on the citizens' network.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to green paper on internalisation of external costs.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for an European Parliament and Council directive on summertime arrangements.</p>
<p>- Surface transport:</p>
<p>a) Rail transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to the white paper on the future of the railways.</p>
<p>b) Road transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Access to the road haulage profession.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Taxation of goods vehicles to replace directive 93/89/EEC.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation laying down the conditions under which non-resident carriers may operate national road passenger transport services within a member state.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council directive and regulation on recording equipment in road transport.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation (EEC) No 684/92 on common rules for the international carriage of passengers by coach and bus.</p>
<p>- Air transport:</p>
<p>- Follow-up to white paper on air traffic management.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to high level group on air safety.</p>
<p>- Proposal for the establishment of a single European authority for air safety.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal on airport charges.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation on air carrier liability in case of accidents.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Revision of regulation on slot allocation.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposals to update rules on denied boarding compensation and passenger protection.</p>
<p>- Maritime transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Licensing regime for roll-on roll-off ferry operations.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Compiling lists of passengers on roll-on roll-off ferries.</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council directive setting up a harmonised safety regime for fishing vessels of 24 metres in length and over.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission strategic document.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal to amend Council directive 94/58/EC on the minimum level of training of seafarers.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal to amend Council directive 93/75/EEC concerning minimum requirements for vessels bound for or leaving Community ports and carrying dangerous or polluting goods.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Shipping agreements with third countries, especially China and India.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Report on competition in the multimodal sector.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, DECEMBER 13</p>
<p>DUBLIN - Irish presidency hosts European Council of heads of state and government (To December 14).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Council report on the development of tax systems within the Union, taking into account the need to create a tax environment that stimulates business and the creation of jobs and promotes a more efficient environmental policy.</p>
<p>- Commission and European Monetary Institute (EMI) report on progress in stage three of European Monetary Union (EMU).</p>
<p>- Commission report on subsidiarity.</p>
<p>- Presentation of draft revision of the treaties, addressing in particular:</p>
<p>* Bringing th and enlarging the scope of the Union's common foreign and security policy;</p>
<p>* Assuring, in view of enlargement, the proper functioning of the institutions while respecting their balance of powers and the efficiency of the decision-making process;</p>
<p>* Simplification of the treaties.</p>
<p>- Commission report on appropriate initiatives for reinforcing regional cooperation in Europe.</p>
<p>- Report on the evolution of the trade policies and the preferential agreements of the Community in relation to the World Trade Organisation (WTO).</p>
<p>- Final European Commission report on the mutually beneficial effects of greater coordination of the Union's economic and structural policies.</p>
<p>- Review of December 1995 Madrid summit recommendations on fighting unemployment and on application of multiannual employment programmes.</p>
<p>- Joint ECOFIN/Social Affairs Council annual employment monitoring report.</p>
<p>- Review of progress in application of Madrid December 1995 drug experts group report on the fight against drugs.</p>
<p>- Territorial pacts for employment within the framework of the confidence pact for employment.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 3</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Transport Council (To October 4).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- External relations:</p>
<p>- Recommendation for a Council decision authorising the Commission to open negotiations on air transport agreements between the Community and Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Poland, Romania and Slovakia.</p>
<p>- Relationship with central and eastern European countries.</p>
<p>- Negotiations between the EU and Switzerland on land and air transport.</p>
<p>- Other measures:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a European Parliament and Council directive on summertime arrangements.</p>
<p>- Surface transport:</p>
<p>a) Road transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Access to the road haulage profession.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Taxation of goods vehicles to replace directive 93/89/EEC.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation laying down the conditions under which non-resident carriers may operate national road passenger transport services within a member state.</p>
<p>- Proposal for the modification of Council regulation (EEC) No 684/92 on common rules for the international carriage of passengers by coach and bus.</p>
<p>b) Rail transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) White paper on the future of the railways.</p>
<p>- Air transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to white paper on air traffic management.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation on air carrier liabilities in case of accidents.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending regulation EEC/3922/91 on the harmonisation of technical requirements and administrative procedures in the field of civil aviation.</p>
<p>- Maritime transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal on the compilation of lists of passengers on roll-on roll-off ferries.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive setting up a harmonised safety regime for fishing vessels of 24 metres or more in length.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council directive amending Council directive 93/75/EEC concerning minimum requirements for vessels bound for or leaving Community ports and carrying dangerous or polluting goods.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council directive amending directive 94/58/EEC on the minimum level of training for seafarers.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (NEW ITEM) - European Centre for Advanced research in Economics (ECARE) holds lunchtime seminar on &quot;Competition policy in central Euro</p>
<p>pe: facilitating transition and preparing for EU integration&quot; (1330/1130 GMT). Venue: ECARE, 39 avenue Franklin Roosevelt. Contact: Nancy De Munck (322) 650 3075.</p>
<p>LIEGE, Belgium - European Institute for Legal Studies &quot;Fernand Dehousse&quot; holds conference on &quot;Regional trade agreements and multilateral rules after the Uruguay Round: convergence, divergence and interaction&quot; (To October 5). Venue: Palais des Congres. Contact: Xavier Denoel, Liege University (32) 41 66 3156.</p>
<p>SATURDAY, OCTOBER 5</p>
<p>DUBLIN - European Union leaders hold special summit to discuss a wide range of issues including trade, drugs and the EU's future. Agenda likely to include the IGC, employment and social protection, the fight against drugs, and preparations for the December ministerial meeting of the World Trade Organisation in Singapore.</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 7</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Research Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Financial supplement to the fourth framework programme/task forces.</p>
<p>- Follow-up to the green paper on innovation.</p>
<p>- International cooperation in the research and technological (RTD) development field:</p>
<p>- Science and technology cooperation strategy with Mediterranean countries;</p>
<p>- (possibly) Bilateral science and technology agreements with several third countries.</p>
<p>- Joint Research Centre (JRC): Commission report on progress in the implementation of Council conclusions of April 21, 1994 on the role of the JRC.</p>
<p>- Fifth RTD framework programme.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Evaluation of Community RTD activities.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Environmental Bureau (EEB) holds conference on &quot;Agrisystems for sustainability&quot; - the EU contribution to the global food security conference and the restructuring of the EU agricultural budget (0900/0700 GMT). Venue: Auditorium of the Credit Communal de Belgique, 2 rue de Ligne. Contact: EEB (322) 539 0037.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 8</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Industry Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Implications of the information society for EU policies.</p>
<p>- Review of the action plan &quot;Europe's way to the information society&quot;.</p>
<p>- Member state experiences.</p>
<p>- The information society and services for industry.</p>
<p>- Standardisation and the information society.</p>
<p>- Information society and the citizen.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Multilingual information society.</p>
<p>- The information society and space.</p>
<p>- Green paper on the social aspects of the information society.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Euro-Mediterranean committee for the Barcelona process meets (To October 9).</p>
<p>GALICIA, Spain - European Commission's DG XVI, Committee of the Regions and Galicia hold seminar on land-use planning in the Atlantic Arc region.</p>
<p>LONDON - Agra Europe holds third annual European meat industry conference &quot;Meat '96&quot;. Topics include: EU policy for meat and livestock; EU policy, European meat production and trade - perspectives from UK and Germany; market outlook for beef, sheepmeat, pigmeat and poultry; BSE and the effects on European meat consumption; rebuilding the image of meat; regaining consumer confidence. Venue: Copthorne Tara Hotel. Contact: Agra Europe (44) 1892 51 18 07.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 10</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Cogen Europe holds third annual conference on &quot;Europe's cogeneration markets of the future: prospects and challenges&quot; (To October 11). Venue: Sheraton Hotel. Contact: Cogen Europe (322) 772 8290.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, OCTOBER 11</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Institute for Asian Studies (EIAS) holds conference on &quot;APEC and the EU&quot;. Main discussions focus on what APEC is, what it actually does and what it means for EU policy makers and business. Contact: EIAS, Kerstin Bergloef (322) 230 81 22.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, OCTOBER 13</p>
<p>AUSTRIA - Austria holds its first elections to the European Parliament, electing 21 deputies.</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 14</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- EMU third stage: preparation for Dublin European Council.</p>
<p>- European Investment Bank (EIB) loans to third countries:</p>
<p>- New guarantee system;</p>
<p>- Renewal of envelopes for eastern Europe, the Mediterranean and ALA.</p>
<p>- Protection of the Community's financial interests: regulation on on-the-spot checks and inspections (final adoption).</p>
<p>- Fight against fraud: transit sector.</p>
<p>- Taxation issues.</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Fisheries Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation laying down (new) technical measures for the conservation of fishery resources.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation on logbooks and landing declarations.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission report on direct landing of fish.</p>
<p>- Commission report on fishing and responsible marketing.</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council regulation fixing the conditions of access to waters and resources of the Baltic Sea.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council decision on Multi-Annual Guidance Programme (MAGP) IV.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation on the fixing of management objectives and strategies for certain fisheries for the period 1994-1997.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation amending for the sixteenth time regulation (EEC) No. 3094/86 laying down certain technical measures for the conservation of fishery resources (drift-nets).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation amending previous Council regulations opening and providing for the administration of autonomous Community tariff quotas for certain fishery products (1996) or for tariff suspensions (1996).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation (EC) amending regulation (EEC) No. 2847/93 establishing a control system applicable to the common fisheries policy (establishment of a Community catch-reporting database).</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation (EC) laying down common marketing standards for certain fishery products.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation introducing transitional measures into regulation (EC) No 1624/94 laying down certain technical measures for the conservation of fishery resources in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation (EC) amending regulation (EEC) No. 2847/93 establishing a control system applicable to the common fisheries policy (satellite monitoring).</p>
<p>- Commission report on the application of the basic regulation (No. 3760/92).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for Council regulation (EC) amending for the fourth time regulation (EEC) No 3699/93 laying down the criteria and conditions for Community structural funding in the fishing and aquaculture sector as well as the processing and marketing of their products.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission report on control operations in 1995.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission report on MAGP III.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Conclusion of new fisheries agreements with:</p>
<p>a) Estonia;</p>
<p>b) Latvia;</p>
<p>c) Lithuania.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Venice conference on marine management in the Mediterranean, November 1996 - final arrangements.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Negotiating mandate for future South Atlantic Fisheries Organisation (SAFO).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for Council decisions on the conclusion of the agreement in the form of an exchange of letters concerning the provisional application of the protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the agreements between the European Economic Community and:</p>
<p>a) Angola;</p>
<p>b) Sao Tome;</p>
<p>c) Gambia;</p>
<p>d) Mauritius.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposals for the conclusion of a new fisheries agreement with Mauritania.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Conclusion of fisheries agreements with Russia on behalf of:</p>
<p>a) Sweden;</p>
<p>b) Finland.</p>
<p>- Recommendations for a Council decision authorising the Commission to negotiate fisheries agreements with certain Mediterranean countries.</p>
<p>- Commission report on third countries' activities in Community waters.</p>
<p>LILLE, France - European Commission (DG VII-transport, XI-environment, XVII-energy) and Nord-Pas de Calais Region organise congress (To October 16) on &quot;City and mobility; moving ideas around!&quot;. Venue: Alteris, avenue de la Creativite 3, 59650 Villeneuve d'Ascq. Contact: Marianne Ryckewaert (33) 20 67 08 21)</p>
<p>CYPRUS - Experts on the implementation of the multiannual rolling work programme for maritime transport in the Mediterranean hold their first meeting.</p>
<p>WINDHOEK, Namibia - EU/Southern Africa Development Council ministerial meeting (To October 15).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 15</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Environment Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council on the review of the European Community programme of policy and action in relation to the environment and sustainable development &quot;Towards sustainability&quot;.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council regulation (EEC) No 3254/91 prohibiting the use of leghold traps in the Community and the introduction into the Community of pelts and manufactured goods of certain wild animal species originating in countries which catch them by means of leghold traps or trapping methods which do not meet international humane trapping standards.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up of the conference on climate change and preparation of EU position for protocol negociations.</p>
<p>- Preparation for the conference on biodiversity.</p>
<p>- Preparation for the eighth meeting of the parties to the Montreal protocol on substances that deplete the ozone layer.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission communication on waste strategy.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive amending directive 90/219/EEC on the continued use of genetically modified micro-organisms.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive concerning the quality of water intended for human consumption.</p>
<p>- Auto oil:</p>
<p>a) Draft directive relating to the quality of petrol and diesel fuels;</p>
<p>b) Draft directive on measures against air pollution by emissions from motor vehicules - amendment of directives 70/229/EEC and 70/156/EEC.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 16</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) holds seminar on &quot;Water, politics and security in the Mediterranean Region&quot; (0915/0715 GMT). Venue: Place du Congres 1. Contact: Shireen Hunter, CEPS (322) 229 3911.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 17</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Executive committee of Schengen group on free movement of people meets at ministerial level under Luxembourg presidency. Venue: Kirchberg conference centre. Luxembourg is hoping to achieve admittance of Nordic countries to Schengen accord during its presidency of the group, with signature of accession protocols for Denmark, Finland and Sweden and association protocols for Iceland and Norway at December 19 meeting.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, OCTOBER 20</p>
<p>FINLAND - Finland holds municipal elections and the first elections to the European Parliament on the same day.</p>
<p>VILNIUS - Parliamentary elections in Lithuania.</p>
<p>TIRANA - Albania holds local elections; all parties, including those which withdrew from the controversial general election, have agreed to participate in the local vote.</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 21</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament plenary session (To October 25).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 22</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - The European Aviation Club lunchtime meeting with British Airways Chief Executive Bob Ayling (1230/1030 GMT). Venue: Amigo Hotel. Contact: The European Aviation Club (322) 647 0760.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - Confederation of European Paper Industries (CEPI) holds conference on &quot;Forest management and paper: growing cooperation&quot;. Contact: CEPI (322) 627 4911.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 24</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Tourism Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Commission report on the evaluation of the Community's action plan to assist tourism (1993-1995).</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council decision on a first multiannual programme to assist European tourism (1997-2000) &quot;PHILOXENIA&quot;.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Report by the Commission on the situation regarding travel guides and ski instructors in the EU.</p>
<p>MADRID - European Investment Bank (EIB) holds forum on &quot;The Mediterranean: a space for partnership&quot; (1500/1300 GMT) (To October 25).</p>
<p>Agenda includes:</p>
<p>- The Mediterranean, a common destiny:</p>
<p>- The EU's Mediterranean policy: from cooperation to partnership;</p>
<p>- The sea, water and cities: preserving a common heritage.</p>
<p>- An area for joint development:</p>
<p>- The dynamic role of trans-national projects;</p>
<p>- The banking sector and north-south partnership.</p>
<p>Speakers include: EIB President Sir Brian Unwin; European Commissioner for Relations with the Mediterranean Manuel Marin; MEP Willy de Clercq; Egyptian Minister of State for Economic Affairs Youssef Boutros-Ghali; Greek Deputy Foreign Minister George Romeos; Jordanian Planning Minister Rima Khalaf; Barcelona Mayor and EU Committee of the Regions President Pasqual Maragall. Contact: Yvonne Berghorst, EIB (352) 4379 3154.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, OCTOBER 25</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Internal Market Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Operation of the internal market:</p>
<p>- Oral report of the Commission including progress report on the SLIM initiative;</p>
<p>- Administrative cooperation;</p>
<p>- Transposition.</p>
<p>- Citizens first.</p>
<p>- Preparation for structured dialogue with central and eastern European countries:</p>
<p>- White paper on approximation of the laws of central and eastern European countries in the field of the internal market.</p>
<p>- Three proposed directives concerning the free movement of persons:</p>
<p>a) elimination of controls on persons crossing internal frontiers;</p>
<p>b) abolition of restrictions on movement and residence within the Community;</p>
<p>c) (possibly) the right of third-country nationals to travel in the Community.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a directive on pluralism and media concentration.</p>
<p>- The &quot;Robert Schuman&quot; action.</p>
<p>- Transparency mechanism for national regulations concerning the information society.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, OCTOBER 27</p>
<p>- European summer time ends - Central European time changes from GMT +2 to GMT +1.</p>
<p>SOFIA - Bulgaria holds its second post-communist presidential election.</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 28</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - General Affairs Council (To October 29).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Preparation for December WTO ministerial meeting.</p>
<p>- Mediterranean policy:</p>
<p>- Status report on negotiations with Egypt and Algeria;</p>
<p>- Decision on signature of agreements with Jordan and Lebanon;</p>
<p>- Preparation for EU political profile at Cairo Summit (November 12-14).</p>
<p>- Middle East.</p>
<p>- Former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>- Ukraine action plan.</p>
<p>- OSCE - Proposed guidelines for review and summit.</p>
<p>- Determination of EU's position for structured dialogue with central and eastern European countries.</p>
<p>- Commission presentation of green paper on post-Lome scenario.</p>
<p>- Relations with South Africa; state of negotiations.</p>
<p>- Relations with Switzerland.</p>
<p>- Interpretation and implementation of European Council common criteria to be applied to arms exports.</p>
<p>- Status of negotiations on framework agreement with Australia.</p>
<p>- Structured dialogue with central and eastern European countries.</p>
<p>- Signature of new partnership accords with Jordan and Lebanon.</p>
<p>- Signature of a framework accord with Korea.</p>
<p>- IGC ministerial session (first day).</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Farm Council (To October 29).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Second European forum for social partners on services of general interest (To October 29). Agenda includes: role and missions of services of general interest in achieving the goals of the EU and guaranteeing the fundamental rights of its residents and citizens; role of the actors (public authorities, operators, consumers, employees); subsidiarity, regulation, control, evaluation; globalisation and European strategy towards third countries. Venue: Palais des Congres. Contact: First &amp; Top Travel - L'Universelle Travel Group (322) 647 4935.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 29</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Economic and Social Committee (ECOSOC) holds plenary session (To October 31).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 30</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - EU senior officials meet in the framework of the Euro-Mediterranean partnership on political and security questions (To October 31).</p>
<p>PARIS - Euroforum holds conference on &quot;Gas and electricity '96 - deregulation: what is the impact?&quot; (To October 31). Venue: Pavillon Royal, Bois de Boulogne. Contact: Alexandra Galeza (33) 1 44 88 14 98.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 31</p>
<p>MARRAKESH, Morocco - Prometheus-Europe holds conference on &quot;Articulate the Euro-Mediterranean partnership and decentralised cooperation&quot; (To November 1). Topics include: the objectives of the Euro-Mediterranean partnership; the functioning of the EMP - circuits of decision-making, financial control and the MEDA regulation; the functioning of Euro-Mediterranean programmes in the context of decentralised cooperation. Contact: Euro-Med (33) 1 43 43 03 07.</p>
<p>MONDAY, NOVEMBER 25</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - General Affairs Council (To November 26). In margins of the Council, EU/African Unity Organisation ministerial meeting.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Preparation for Dublin European Council.</p>
<p>- Transatlantic relations.</p>
<p>- Preparation for December WTO ministerial meeting.</p>
<p>- Middle East.</p>
<p>- Mediterranean policy:</p>
<p>- Status report on contacts with Syria;</p>
<p>- Middle East (post-Cairo summit).</p>
<p>- Albania: decision to sign a new accord.</p>
<p>- Relations with Turkey.</p>
<p>- Former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>- Decision to sign trade and cooperation agreement with FYROM.</p>
<p>- Nigeria: renewal of sanctions.</p>
<p>- Biological and toxin weapons convention: approval of statement on the opening of the fourth review conference.</p>
<p>- Ratification of chemical weapons convention: statement welcoming ratification.</p>
<p>- Determination of EU position for structured dialogue with Cyprus and Malta.</p>
<p>- Conclusion of negotiations on framework agreement with Australia.</p>
<p>- Relations with central and eastern European countries:</p>
<p>- Approval of conclusion of Europe agreements with Baltic States;</p>
<p>- Approval of interim protocols to Europe agreements.</p>
<p>- Russia: review of action plan.</p>
<p>- Food aid for Central Asian Republics.</p>
<p>- Status of negotiations with South Africa.</p>
<p>- Preparation for OSCE conference, Lisbon.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Consumers Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Commission proposal on access to justice (injunctions).</p>
<p>- Commission communication on access to justice (settlement).</p>
<p>- Directive amending existing consumer credit directives.</p>
<p>- Commission green paper on commercial communications in the internal market.</p>
<p>- Commission green paper on financial services meeting consumers' expectations.</p>
<p>- Guarantees and after sales services.</p>
<p>- Consumer protection within the information society.</p>
<p>- Protection of vulnerable and disadvantaged consumers.</p>
<p>- Continuation of consumer education theme.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS (NEW ITEM) - European Commission hosts conference on &quot;Investment and trade cooperation between India and the EU&quot; (To November 26). Speakers include: European Commissioner Marin. Venue: Sheraton Hotel. Contact: Euro Synergy Network (322) 510 2463.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Brussels institute for management of the environment (IBGE), European federation of regional energy and environment agencies (FEDARENE) and Eurocities hold joint conference on &quot;Plans and strategies for waste management on regional and local level&quot; (0900/0800 GMT). Venue: General de Banque auditorium. Contact: IBGE by fax (322) 775 7679.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, NOVEMBER 26</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Internal Market Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- (possibly) 1996 study of the impact and effectiveness of single market legislation.</p>
<p>- Simpler legislation for the internal market (SLIM).</p>
<p>- Directive on legal protection of designs and industrial models.</p>
<p>- (possibly) 16th amendment of the directive 76/769/EEC on the marketing and use of certain dangerous substances and preparations.</p>
<p>- Citizens First initiative.</p>
<p>- Directive concerning the free movement of lawyers.</p>
<p>- European company statute.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Directive concerning the free movement of doctors.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a directive amending directive 93/7/EEC concerning the return of cultural objects unlawfully removed from the territory of a member state.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a directive on the supplementary supervision of insurance undertakings in an insurance group.</p>
<p>- Amendments to directive 89/398/EEC - dietary foods:</p>
<p>a) Vertical directives;</p>
<p>b) Temporary authorization;</p>
<p>- Amendments to directive 2/95/EEC - miscellaneous additives:</p>
<p>a) Prohibition of use in traditional products;</p>
<p>b) Classification of processed euchema seaweed.</p>
<p>- Amendment to sweeteners directive 94/35/EEC.</p>
<p>- In-vitro medical diagnostic devices.</p>
<p>- Amending public procurement directives following the adoption of G.P.A.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Green paper on public procurement.</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - European Commission DG XI hosts standing conference on &quot;Health and safety in the nuclear age: informing the public on European radiation standards&quot; (1030/0930 GMT) (and 27/11). Topics include: major changes in the Euratom basic safety standards directive. Venue: Jean Monnet building, room M6. Contact: Mrs Eisen, DG IX (352) 4301 33 164.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Economic and Social Committee (ECOSOC) holds plenary session (to 28/11).</p>
<p>DUBLIN - European Finance Convention holds tenth anniversary meeting (to 30/11). Contact: (44) 171 381 9291.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, NOVEMBER 27</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament mini-session (To November 28).</p>
<p>VENICE - Second ministerial conference on the management of fish stocks in the Mediterranean (To November 29).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 28</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Justice and Internal Affairs Council (To November 29).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Telecoms Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Telecommunications terminal and satellite earth station equipment.</p>
<p>- TENs: Proposal for a European Parliament and Council decision on a series of guidelines for trans-European telecommunications networks.</p>
<p>- Data protection: modified proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the processing of personal data and the protection of privacy in the telecommunications sectors, in particular in the integrated services digital network (ISDN).</p>
<p>- (possibly) Numbering.</p>
<p>- (possibly) ONP voice telephony.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council decision on inter-administration telematic networks for statistics relating to the trading of goods between member states (EDICOM).</p>
<p>- Proposal for a European Parliament and Council directive on interconnection in telecommunications.</p>
<p>- Update of framework and leased lines directives on open network provision (ONP).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Commission and the Indian government hold joint forum on trade and investment in India.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Institute for Asian Studies (EIAS) hold conference on &quot;EU-Asia cooperation in the WTO context&quot; (To November 29). Main discussions focus on how and to what extent Asians and Europeans can cooperate in opening up markets within the WTO. Speakers include: European Commissioner Sir Leon Brittan. Contact: EIAS, Kerstin Bergloef (322) 230 8122.</p>
<p>BRUGES, Belgium - European Society of Transport Institutes (ESTI) holds conference on &quot;The citizens' network&quot; (and 29/11). Topics discussed include: the implications of external costs principles on urban transport; the network benefits principles; the modernising of the regulatory framework in public transport. Venue: Castle Prinsenhof. Contact: Laetitia Hoste, ESTI (322) 230 0514.</p>
<p>LEIPZIG, Germany - Verband Saechssicher Bildungsinstitute hold conference on &quot;Education 2000&quot; (To November 30). Topics include: the European education market; training in the latest skills; multimedia ability for both suppliers and users; innovation through personal development. Contact: Verband Saechssicher Bildungsinstitute, Dieter Webner (49) 341 490 5910.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
