<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59244" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Popular Banks sees Cyprus economic slowdown.</title>
<headline>Popular Banks sees Cyprus economic slowdown.</headline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cyprus's economy is showing discouraging signs of stunted growth over the next year, mainly because of a downturn in tourism, a leading banker said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;It is probably the first time in recent years that so many economic indicators are simultaneously recording a slowdown,&quot; said Kikis Lazarides, chairman of the Cyprus Popular Bank, Cyprus's second largest banking group.</p>
<p>&quot;In the sector of industry, agriculture, manufacturing and tourism negative developments have been noted, with unemployment rising as a consequence,&quot; he told a news conference.</p>
<p>The Popular Bank released its six monthly results showing an increase in pre-tax profit of 13.2 percent to 18.20 million pounds ($39.5 million) compared to 16.08 million last year. HSBC Holdings Plc owns a 22 percent stake in the bank.</p>
<p>Lazarides said the results were &quot;especially satisfying&quot; in view of the prevailing economic conditions.</p>
<p>Commercial banks were forced to curtail their credit expansion early in the year to percentages set by the Central Bank, which expressed concern at a widening deficit in the current account.</p>
<p>The account deficit reached 88 million pounds in 1995 after a surplus of 32 million in 1994. Official forecasts put the deficit at 135 million pounds in 1996.</p>
<p>The rate of GDP growth, according to official estimates, is expected to reach 3.5 to four percent in 1996 compared to a growth rate of five percent in 1995.</p>
<p>A clampdown on credit expansion and a decline in tourism arrivals had an impact on banking operations, Lazarides said.</p>
<p>&quot;Cyprus is a single-product economy. It relies on tourism and this is definitely wrong because it has shown a slowdown. Some people speak about a decline of between three and 12 percent,&quot; he said. &quot;We think there will be a decline of between three and five percent.&quot;</p>
<p>An estimated two million tourists a year earn for Cyprus about 810 million Cyprus pounds - representing 21 percent of the island's gross domestic product.</p>
<p>By mid-August figures showed tourism arrivals down by four percent this year compared with last year, official sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are clear indications that there will be problems in tourism in 1997, and that will have an impact on the economy. We hope we will be proven wrong,&quot; said Lazarides.</p>
<p>Lazarides said the bank planned to continue its expansion abroad by increasing the number of branches in Greece, where it is known as the European Popular Bank. It also has branches in Britain and representative offices in Australia, South Africa and Canada.</p>
<p>Last month the bank announced cooperation with Fidelity Investments, becoming the only Cypriot institution with the right to market Fidelity Funds locally.</p>
<p>&quot;This agreement will provide the customer base of the Popular Bank with investment opportunities in the world's capital and money markets satisfying the diverse risk profiles of both individual and institutional investors,&quot; Lazarides said. ($ = 0.46 pound)</p>
<p>-- Michele Kambas, Nicosia newsroom 357 2 365089 --</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
