<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67411" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: British Air files to dismiss USAir suit.</title>
<headline>British Air files to dismiss USAir suit.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Airways Plc. said it filed a motion in Manhattan federal court Friday asking the judge to dismiss an antitrust suit brought by USAir Group Inc. over the British carrier's proposed alliance with American Airlines.</p>
<p>USAir has &quot;been unable to identify a single substantive provision of the 1993 agreement (between USAir and British Airways) that Brtish Airways has purportedly broken.&quot;</p>
<p>British Airways' motion to dismiss claims that USAir has &quot;a case of corporate amnesia&quot; and that it &quot;forgets&quot; its previous chairman calling the deal &quot;perfectly acceptable.&quot;</p>
<p>Arlington, Va.-based USAir, British Airways' existing trans-Atlantic partner, filed suit in July saying the proposed alliance between British Airways and American Airlines would monopolise air travel between the United States and Britain.</p>
<p>It also charged the new alliance would undermine its own relationship with British Airways.</p>
<p>British Airways said it believed the suit was a tactic by USAir to rengotiate that agreement.</p>
<p>USAir said British Airways' motion to dismiss, a standard tactic in lawsuit, was &quot;posturing.&quot;</p>
<p>The USAir suit alleged that British Airways forced it to relinquish three routes, but British Airways countered in its motion that a consent decree with the U.S. Deparment of Justice compelled the move for anti-trust concerns.</p>
<p>The motion claimed that the suit was based on the &quot;frustration&quot; of USAir management that British Airways has a new partner. &quot;Disappointment and frustration, however, do not give rise to recognisable legal claims,&quot; the filing said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
