<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75282" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: S&amp;P sees moderate growth outlook for NZ tourism.</title>
<headline>S&amp;P sees moderate growth outlook for NZ tourism.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>International tourism growth in New Zealand is likely to settle at seven to eight percent per annum through to the end of the decade, somewhat below the record growth of the early 1990s, Standard and Poor's said in a report on the sector.</p>
<p>S&amp;P said the growth outlook was moderate and largely dependent on risk factors outside the control of New Zealand operators, such as world and domestic economic conditions, relative costs, exchange rates and air access.  </p>
<p>But the defence of the America's Cup yachting trophy and the Sydney Olympic Games, both in 2000, will generate a strong spurt in international tourism at the turn of the decade, it said.</p>
<p>Tourism contributed about 10 percent of Gross Domestic Product in fiscal 1996 and earned about NZ$4.8 billion or 19 percent of export earnings. It provides some 200,000 fulltime equivalent jobs.</p>
<p>S&amp;P said the industry was highly fragmented between many firms of all sizes, and seasonality of demand was a negative factor. Margins and profits were highly volatile and variable. It maintained its industry ranking for the sector at C.  </p>
<p>S&amp;P said it expected the accommodation sector to come under significant pressure in the next two years due to increased room supply and slowing growth rates. Some 1,500 extra rooms have come on the market since mid-1995, with 820 more to open by mid-1997.</p>
<p>&quot;By making such a large incremental addition to capacity within the industry in a period of relative weak growth, operators are placing themselves under pressure to cut rates to maintain economical occupancy levels. However, lowering room rates creates expectations that are very difficult to readjust,&quot; the report said.  </p>
<p>New Zealand's main listed companies in the tourism sector are Air New Zealand Ltd, CDL Hotels NZ Ltd, the Helicopter Line, Shotover Jet Ltd and Sky City Ltd.</p>
<p>S&amp;P said the ownership of the country's three main airports was likely to gravitate towards private investors, depending on the government's willingness to sell down its stakes. It holds 51.6 percent of Auckland, 25 percent of Christchurch and 66 percent of Wellington airports.</p>
<p>-- Wellington newsroom 64 4 473-4746</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I66500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I72603">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
