<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="77936" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain sets 1995 tourism record, problems remain.</title>
<headline>Britain sets 1995 tourism record, problems remain.</headline>
<byline>David Ljunggren</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>A record 23.7 million foreign tourists visited Britain in 1995 but the figures disguised the fact that the country's hotel industry has problems and needs shaking up, senior industry officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The British Tourist Authority (BTA) said the visitors -- an increase of 13 percent on 1994 -- spent 11.9 billion pounds ($18.5 billion), up 20 percent from the previous year.</p>
<p>&quot;We have consolidated our recovery in global market share which we started to build two years ago, when Britain hit a record low of 4.4 percent. Today the figure is five percent,&quot; BTA chairman Anthony Sell told a news conference.</p>
<p>Sell said the authority now was selling Britain as an fashionable country enjoying a major cultural renaissance.</p>
<p>&quot;We've managed to recreate the image of Britain as an exciting, stylish and contemporary destination,&quot; he said, adding that preliminary figures for the first half of 1996 showed visitor numbers up 12 percent and spending up six percent.</p>
<p>&quot;We are seeing growth three times the world average. Most of our competitors are seeing slower rates of growth and some are experiencing significant losses,&quot; Sell said.</p>
<p>The figures conceal continuing problems in the hotel sector but BTA chairman David Quarmby said these were being tackled.</p>
<p>A study carried out last year for the Department of National Heritage showed significant numbers of foreign visitors were unhappy with the quality and cost of their hotel rooms, especially in London.</p>
<p>&quot;We are aware that research shows some visitors were not wholly satisfied with the quality of accommodation. We are working with the London Tourist Board and the hotel industry to address questions of quality,&quot; Quarmby said in an interview.</p>
<p>He said 10,000 more hotel rooms would be needed in London by the turn of the century and he called for an increase in budget hotels of the kind found in France, where a family room costs around 35 pounds ($55).</p>
<p>Tourists are also confused by five separate hotel classification schemes operating in Britain. Quarmby said talks were being held to merge the five into a single body, although he admitted progress had not been easy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
