<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79950" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Northern Ireland politics grim but economy thrives.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Northern Ireland politics grim but economy thrives.</headline>
<byline>Carmel Linnane</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Northern Ireland's peace process is faltering. But, tourism aside, its economy is thriving.</p>
<p>&quot;The basic story is really quiet good with strong growth prospects,&quot; Graham Gudgin, director of the Northern Ireland Economic Research Centre told Reuters.</p>
<p>He was speaking on the eve of resumed peace talks in Belfast after a summer of violent unrest and sectarian tension which blackened the province's image as a tourist destination but has failed to blemish its overall economic performance.</p>
<p>Gudgin said the main victim of political unrest was tourism but this represented only a minute part of overall Gross Domestic Product (GDP), contributing about two percent per annum to a 12 billion pound ($18.79 billion) annual take.</p>
<p>Other sectors of the economy, especially local manufacturing, had proved resilient to the 25-year &quot;Troubles&quot; and were now performing exceptionally well, he said.</p>
<p>The region has been the fastest growing in Britain for some time. &quot;It has been a much more successful economy in growth terms then most people realise,&quot; said Gudgin.</p>
<p>The economy, which had grown steadily during the past decade, blossomed when twin guerrilla ceasefires in late 1994 gave a 17-month respite to 25 years of bloodshed.</p>
<p>Tourism was one of the main beneficiaries of the ceasefires and the Northern Ireland Tourist Board (NITB) said visitors to the province reached record levels.</p>
<p>The number of holiday visitors in 1995 showed a 67 percent increase over the previous year and the total visitor spend reached 214 million pounds, an increase of 17 percent on 1994, official figures show.</p>
<p>But a ceasefire by the Irish Republican Army, which wants a united Ireland, collapsed in early 1996 with an IRA bomb in London.</p>
<p>Tension in Northern Ireland soared when Protestant demonstrations forced police to reverse a ban on a July 12 march through a Roman Catholic area of the town of Portadown from a church at Drumcree, igniting Catholic anger instead.</p>
<p>&quot;The events of the summer of 1996 did more damage to tourism than the whole of the troubles. It just shows what a sensitive and volatile business tourism is. Some (smaller) tourist venues were empty in August for the first time ever,&quot; Gudgin said.</p>
<p>Other areas of the economy are not so sensitive to the province's political turmoil. &quot;Ninety eight percent of the economy, outside tourism, is really not very much affected either by ceasefires or lack of them,&quot; Gudgin said.</p>
<p>A Confederation of British Industry (CBI) regional trends survey, published in August, showed manufacturers' confidence in Northern Ireland the most buoyant of all British regions.</p>
<p>&quot;Our latest survey on the manufacturing industry found Northern Ireland the most optimistic region in the UK and that was reflected in the higher growth they had seen in their orders and output than the rest of the UK,&quot; Sudhir Junankar, CBI associate director for economics, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Northern Ireland manufacturing exports grew by 21 percent to 2.6 billion pounds in the year ending in March 1995 and by 48 percent over the most recently measured four year period, compared to a growth rate of 30 percent for the British manufacturing industry as a whole, official figures show.</p>
<p>&quot;The economy itself is doing well, particularly manufacturing and within that indigenous manufacturing has done well in comparison to most other parts of the UK,&quot; Gudgin said.</p>
<p>Its manufacturing export includes clothes, electrical goods and computer parts as well as traditional industries in the ship-building and aerospace sector.</p>
<p>&quot;The externally (foreign) owned sector, some of which have been here for 30 years, is about 50 percent of the total but it is the locally owned sector which is growing fastest and is the main success story and does much better than the equivalent in the (Irish) Republic or mainland Britain,&quot; said Gudgin.</p>
<p>Belfast-based management consultants BDO Stoy Hayward said a recent confidence survey on the Northern Ireland hotel industry confirmed the &quot;severe&quot; negative impact current political uncertainty had on tourism.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been conducting surveys for over two years now and recorded growing confidence over that period as a result of opportunities that peace had brought,&quot; said Shaun Kelly, Stoy Hayward's partner in charge of tourism services.</p>
<p>&quot;We conducted a survey in March after the Canary Wharf (London) bomb and had seen some decline in confidence but this survey has showed a more marked decline,&quot; Kelly added. ($1=.6385 Stg)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
