<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86459" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Boycott bites into Northern Irish business.</title>
<headline>Boycott bites into Northern Irish business.</headline>
<byline>Martin Cowley</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>A summer of sectarian strife in Northern Ireland has spilled onto the shop counters of a divided province. Catholics and Protestants have gone on a trade war.</p>
<p>They are boycotting each others' businesses in many areas to score political points after a summer of strife which has left the British province more polarised than ever.</p>
<p>&quot;They're showing their faces but they're not buying,&quot; said a small-town Protestant shopkeeper about Catholics who now shun him and buy their goods elsewhere.</p>
<p>The practice of boycotting, perfected by impoverished Irish land agitators a century ago and named after its first victim, Captain Charles Boycott, has returned to haunt the search for Northern Irish peace.</p>
<p>One hundred years ago Irish citizens used it as a weapon against English estate owners. Now it is setting neighbour against neighbour in rural communities in Northern Ireland and could spill over the border into the Irish Republic.</p>
<p>Threatening letters have been sent to Protestant businessmen. Posters have gone up in some Protestant areas telling residents to boycott Catholics.</p>
<p>Stop-go talks supposed to reconcile the 60 percent pro-British Protestant majority and 40 percent pro-Irish Catholic minority have gone nowhere since opening in June.</p>
<p>But the latest manifestations of bitterness have destroyed any middle ground between ordinary Catholics and Protestants.</p>
<p>Alan Field, leader of a pro-British business group, reckons that more than a hundred Protestant traders have been victimised. &quot;My latest reports suggest it is not easing at all.&quot;</p>
<p>The Irish News, published in Belfast, quoted a Catholic trader in County Fermanagh as saying Protestant hardliners had been boycotting him for a year.</p>
<p>&quot;The Protestants are trying to make out that the Catholics started these boycotts, but that is simply not true,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Northern Ireland has been spared a return to violence since twin ceasefires by the Irish Republican Army (IRA) and Protestant &quot;Loyalist&quot; guerrillas in 1994. The Catholic-backed IRA has not struck the province since resuming its war against British rule in February.</p>
<p>But communal strife and economic warfare are casting a pall over Anglo-Irish attemps to establish a lasting, real peace and a political agreement to underpin it.</p>
<p>&quot;Exhuming the legacy of Captain Charles Boycott as an economic or political weapon today simply turns the clock back 100 years,&quot; according to hotel chain owner Billy Hastings.</p>
<p>&quot;It did nothing to create mutual understanding and economic well-being then and it will do even less now.&quot;</p>
<p>The bitterness is a spillover from a summer of sectarian hatred which erupted when police banned a pro-British Protestant Orange Order march through a Catholic area of Portadown.</p>
<p>Protestants demonstrated against the banning of what they saw as a traditional right. The ban was lifted, and Catholic anger was ignited instead in days of riots province-wide.</p>
<p>Since then church property has been attacked. Catholics were forced from their homes in north Belfast. Protestants in a south County Londonderry village said they were being intimidated.</p>
<p>Militant Protestants blockaded a church and jeered Catholics going into religious services in County Antrim.</p>
<p>Protestants blame Sinn Fein and its IRA military ally for the boycott, accusing them of economic &quot;ethnic cleansing&quot; to force Protestants from Catholic zones.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein denies organising the campaign. It says individual Catholics are hitting back at businessmen who took part in triumphalist parades through Irish nationalist enclaves at the height the annual summer Protestant &quot;marching season&quot;.</p>
<p>Catholic clerics have united with Protestant leaders in condemning boycotts. Field insists the majority of victims had no connection with parades or demonstrations.</p>
<p>In Pomeroy, a strongly Irish nationalist town, Victor Ramsey's heating oil firm has been hit after an unfounded rumour spread that he had taken part in a Protestant parade.</p>
<p>His delivery lorry was set alight on July 13 and then he was sent letters telling to stay out of Catholic areas. He is convinced some of his former customers have been pressurised.</p>
<p>&quot;We have only done one Catholic run in the past 11 days. We (previously) could have done 70 to 80 Catholic runs every week,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>A Catholic pensioner suffered for trading with him, Ramsey said.  His tank was sabotaged and half its contents spilled out.</p>
<p>Field, head of the 75-member Business and Professional People for the Union (with Britain) group, opposes boycotts.</p>
<p>But he says some business people might stop bringing in goods from the Irish Republic as a reprisal.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been approached by a group of (Protestant) wholesalers and distributors who have indicated that if the boycott continues until the end of this month, they will start a boycott of goods from the Republic of Ireland,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
