<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="20159" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: FOCUS - Stena Line sinks in Channel.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Stena Line sinks in Channel.</headline>
<byline>Paul de Bendern</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedish ferry operator Stena Line AB on Wednesday forecast profits would sink throughout 1996 after a poor first half due to competition from the Channel Tunnel and the late delivery of ferries.</p>
<p>For the six months to June 30, the company posted a loss of 560 million crowns ($84.55 million) against a 350 million crown loss a year ago when the tunnel between Britain and France first began to hit revenues.</p>
<p>Managing director Bo Lerenius said Stena Line was likely to talk about a joint offensive with rival English Channel operator, Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Co (P&amp;O), but this would not save this year's figures.</p>
<p>&quot;On the short-sea route, where the tunnel went for halving its price, we had to follow that to keep our market share,&quot; Lerenius said in an interview. &quot;That has cost us a lot on all our ferry routes.&quot;</p>
<p>The ferry line's performance picked up in July due to the heavy summer holiday traffic and for the seven months to the end of July the company reported a loss of 340 million crowns.</p>
<p>But Lerenius forecast Stena Line would end the year 450 million crowns in the red compared with a profit of 201 million crowns in calendar 1995.</p>
<p>The statement sent Stena's share price tumbling from a high of 31.00 crowns to a low of 28.50 crowns. It recovered to 30.50 crowns in afternoon trade.</p>
<p>Although Stena's passenger volumes increased by eight percent in the first half and cars transported by 10 percent, the price war with the Channel Tunnel cut its turnover by seven percent to 3.97 billion crowns against 4.27 billion a year ago.</p>
<p>Passenger volumes on Stena's British lines rose by nine percent and car traffic by 12 percent in the first half due to higher demand on the Dover-Calais route.</p>
<p>But the share of cross-Channel traffic captured by the tunnel -- operated by Eurotunnel -- rose to 44 percent in July from 40 percent in early 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Volume growth and price levels have not been strong enough to compensate for increasing capacity and market costs,&quot; Stena said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;The introduction of our new ferries has been delayed, causing us enormous amounts of problems in planning and ship change...costing us millions of crowns,&quot; Lerenius added.</p>
<p>He said the company was taking action to redress its falling profits. Stena expects to enter talks with P&amp;O after the British government last month agreed to remove restrictions on cross-Channel ferry operators making pooling arrangements.</p>
<p>&quot;We will have to stabilise the situation and after the authorities have said there are no restriction anymore we can talk about virtually any way of stabilising.&quot;</p>
<p>Lerenius said the two ferry lines needed to cooperate, although Stena earlier ruled out a merger.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a financial situation which does not really make this a survival issue but of course it is never very good to lose a lot of money,&quot; Lerenius said. ($1=6.623 Swedish Crown)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
