<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26644" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: FEATURE - Families wait in vain for Bangladesh fishermen.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Families wait in vain for Bangladesh fishermen.</headline>
<byline>Anis Ahmed</byline>
<dateline>MAHESHKHALI, Bangladesh 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mohsina Begum consoled her weeping four-year-old daughter, telling her that her father will come home soon.</p>
<p>Sharea Khatoon looked far out to sea, breast-feeding her 18-month-old son who is still too young to be aware of the tragedy that has befallen the family.</p>
<p>Mohsina and Sharea are among hundreds of women who rush to the sea shores at Maheshkhali island, seven kilometres (four miles) from Cox's Bazar resort town, at least once a day.</p>
<p>At water's edge, they wait and hope for their loved ones, missing fishermen, to appear.</p>
<p>Fishing is the main livelihood of the many small Bangladeshi islands dotting the Bay of Bengal and it is a tough, hard life that has taken heavy toll on the people.</p>
<p>&quot;He has been lost in the sea,&quot; Mohsina said of her husband, struggling to hold back her tears. &quot;But I don't know if he is dead.&quot;</p>
<p>A few people walked past but hardly noticed as Sharea spoke to Reuters. &quot;Tragedies have struck almost every house on this island,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;I am keeping an endless vigil, for years. My conscience is divided -- one says he is dead but the other would not agree,&quot; said Mohsina. Her husband Abdul Barek, a fisherman, has been lost in the Bay of Bengal since a storm struck his boat more than three years ago.</p>
<p>Sharea's husband, Mohammad Mohiuddin, went fishing eight months ago but has not returned. The bodies of a few of his colleagues were collected on the beach days after the island was battered by strong winds but Mohiuddin remains unaccounted for.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe the sea will return my husband -- dead or alive,&quot; said the young mother.</p>
<p>Her neighbours believe otherwise.</p>
<p>&quot;She is too shocked to accept he will never return. They had a sweet family full of hopes. Now everything has been shattered,&quot; one neighbour said.</p>
<p>People on the islands and the coast say they have no statistics on those  killed by storms and other accidents at sea.</p>
<p>&quot;It's impossible to keep track. Some people are known to have died immediately after a disaster. Others, presumed dead, sometimes come back months after they had been reported missing or killed,&quot; said Shafiqur Rahman, a fishing community leader.</p>
<p>Boats sometimes drift into Indian waters, some towards Burma and some even farther. &quot;We also rescue fishermen from Sri Lanka, India and other countries. So it happens to our fishermen too,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Fishing vessel owners offer up to 20,000 taka ($500) to families of each crew killed, but there is no compensation for families of those missing.</p>
<p>&quot;This is an unwritten law. We try to honour it,&quot; one leader said.</p>
<p>The greatest number of fishermen died in 1991, when a cyclone killed more than 138,000 people.</p>
<p>Shamsu Miah, a Maheshkhali trawler crewman and veteran of many storms in his 26 years of fishing, estimated nearly 1,500 fishermen are still missing from that cyclone.</p>
<p>About 12,000 people died on Kutubdia island alone, 12 km (eight miles) from Maheshkhali, local officials said. Many survivors have managed to resume their lives, get new boats and moved back to the sea.</p>
<p>&quot;But the women and children rendered widows and orphans have been thrown into a totally uncertain future,&quot; said Mohammad Kamal, who described himself as a social worker.</p>
<p>Sharea has found shelter in her parents' home, but they are too poor to provide her with two square meals a day.</p>
<p>She works in Cox's Bazar at a fish processing house owned by a local vessel owner.</p>
<p>&quot;I will live for my son only. I have no hopes except for him,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Clad in a torn sari, Sharea recalls her brief married life and sheds silent tears.</p>
<p>&quot;The marriage was built on years of love. People in our community are conservative about love and free choice... but we managed to. Perhaps Allah did not approve of it,&quot; she said, referring to her marriage not being arranged by her family.</p>
<p>Islanders insist that the sareng (pilot) and the crew on fishing vessels, which sail up to 160 km (100 miles) or more into the Bay, are highly skilled though not formally trained.</p>
<p>&quot;Knowing by practice makes one more efficient,&quot; said 70-year-old fisherman Hamid Ali.</p>
<p>&quot;Tragedies are mainly to blame on inadequate warning, lack of life-saving gear onboard and the indomitable lure for big catch.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MAHESHKHALI, Bangladesh"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
