<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27426" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Estonia sinking due to sloppy repairs, experts say.</title>
<headline>Estonia sinking due to sloppy repairs, experts say.</headline>
<dateline>HAMBURG, Germany 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>A panel of experts has determined that poor maintenance and sloppy repair work on the Estonia were responsible for the ferry sinking in 1994 when 852 people drowned, an investigator said on Monday.</p>
<p>Werner Hummel, who led a four-member team of researchers hired by the ship's builder, said their 20-month study had concluded the ship was in good seaworthy condition when it was first delivered by the Meyer Werft shipyard in 1979.</p>
<p>The blame for the disaster, he said, lay not with the ship's construction or design but with the ship's operator, because repair work on the ship had been improperly carried out.</p>
<p>The operator, Estline of Tallinn, has denied any fault.</p>
<p>&quot;We were able to prove that there were substantial deficits such as bad maintenance and very poorly performed repairs,&quot; Hummel said in a telephone interview with Reuters.</p>
<p>The panel of independent German experts presented excerpts of their findings to two groups of friends and relatives of the ship's victims at a meeting last week in Hamburg.</p>
<p>The report fills four thick folders and comprises several hundred pages. The experts plan to release a summary of their findings within the next four weeks.</p>
<p>Only 137 people survived when the Estonia sank in the Baltic Sea on September 28, 1994.</p>
<p>Other investigations into the disaster have unearthed a series of errors which contributed to the fatalities, including weaknesses in the structure of the ship and basic design flaws that allowed all the water to run to one side of the car deck, causing the list.</p>
<p>The huge car and passenger ferry sank off the coast of Finland during a vicious autumn squall. The bow visor of the roll-on, roll-off ferry worked loose and fell off, allowing water to flood in to the ship's cavernous car deck.</p>
<p>With thousands of tonnes of water flooding the car deck, stability was impossible and the ship keeled over before sinking rapidly to the bottom of the Baltic Sea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAMBURG, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
