<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="31472" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Tourists to be evacuated from Arctic cruise.</title>
<headline>Tourists to be evacuated from Arctic cruise.</headline>
<dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>About 150 tourists stranded for nearly a week on a German cruise ship that ran aground in Canada's Arctic will be evacuated, the cruise line and Canadian Coast Guard said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The luxury ship the Hanseatic ran aground on a gravel bar near King William Island in Canada's Northwest Passage last Thursday. No one was hurt but attempts to refloat the vessel have failed, officials said.</p>
<p>They said 120 of the mostly American and German passengers on board would be transferred to another ship, the Russian ice-breaker Kaptain Dranitsyn, and continue their voyage on Thursday. The remaining passengers have decided to cut short their voyage and return home.</p>
<p>The Coast Guard said there were 153 passengers on the ship. Cruise operator Hanseatic Tours of Hamburg said there were 149 passengers. The ship has a crew of about 115 people.</p>
<p>A Canadian Coast Guard spokesman said the Dranitsyn was headed toward the Hanseatic from nearby Resolute Bay. A Coast Guard vessel was standing by alongside the cruise ship.</p>
<p>The timing of the passenger transfer depended on weather conditions but was planned for Thursday. Food and supplies will also be switched from the Hanseatic so the cruise could continue through the Arctic.</p>
<p>Hanseatic Tours said in a statement that the ship had run into sandy ground about half a mile (one km) south of the King William island on Aug. 29. &quot;Those are very difficult, tricky waters to navigate,&quot; Canadian Coast Guard spokesman Andries Blouw said. Thick ice and high winds in the area tend to cause the shoals and gravel bars to shift.</p>
<p>The passengers have passed the time with expeditions to the nearby island, where they held barbecues, the cruise company said. &quot;The atmosphere on board is very good,&quot; it said. &quot;The temperature outdoors is four degrees (39 Fahrenheit).&quot;</p>
<p>The 404-foot (123-metre) long ship, built in 1993 to the highest international standards for ice-going passenger vessels, also has a theater for lectures on the ecology of the North, the Canadian Press news agency said.</p>
<p>Amenities on board include several lounges and dining rooms, exercise facilities, sauna and massage, duty-free shopping, a swimming pool and a library.</p>
<p>Those passengers who are returning home will be taken by small boats to a nearby air strip and will be flown to Cambridge Bay where they will catch other planes.</p>
<p>Three tow boats were on their way to try to pull the Hanseatic free of the sand barge, the operator added. The Coast Guard said it would probe the cause of the incident.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VANCOUVER, British Columbia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
