<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="42847" id="root" date="1996-09-10" xml:lang="en">
<title>EU: REUTER EC REPORT LONG-TERM DIARY FOR SEPT 16 - DEC 31, 1997.</title>
<headline>REUTER EC REPORT LONG-TERM DIARY FOR SEPT 16 - DEC 31, 1997.</headline>
<text>
<p>- Adoption of common position on U.N. register of conventional arms.</p>
<p>- Former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>- Middle East.</p>
<p>- Mediterranean policy:</p>
<p>- Report on the follow-up to the Barcelona Conference;</p>
<p>- Algeria and Egypt: decision to sign agreements;</p>
<p>- Syria: Commission proposal for a negotiating mandate.</p>
<p>- Preparation of EEA ministerial council.</p>
<p>- Internal financial regulation on ACP.</p>
<p>- Radiation protection of persons undergoing medical examination or treatment.</p>
<p>- Negotiating directives for a nuclear cooperation agreement between EURATOM and Japan.</p>
<p>- Approval of mandate to negotiate an agreement on wine with Slovakia, Slovenia and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>- Agreement on steel with central and eastern European countries.</p>
<p>- Approval of negotiating mandate for a partnership and cooperation agreement with Turkmenistan.</p>
<p>- Asia:</p>
<p>- Decision to sign a protocol relating to the accession of Vietnam to ASEAN;</p>
<p>- Preparation for EU-ASEAN ministerial (February 1997);</p>
<p>- Follow-up to Bangkok ASEM and preparation for Singapore ministerial.</p>
<p>- Decision to sign framework agreement with Australia.</p>
<p>- Decision to sign mutual recognition agreements with Australia and New Zealand.</p>
<p>- Decision on signature of free trade agreement with South Africa.</p>
<p>MONDAY, DECEMBER 9</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Inaugural World Trade Organisation (WTO) ministerial conference (To December 13).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- European Commissioner Brittan presents report on integrating multilateral clothing and textile pacts under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.</p>
<p>- Review of the implementation of Uruguay Round commitments.</p>
<p>- Endorsement of results of negotiations on services.</p>
<p>- Report from the committee on trade and environment.</p>
<p>- Any other trade-related issues.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Environment Council (To December 10).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council on the review of the European Community programme of policy and action in relation to the environment and sustainable development &quot;Towards sustainability&quot;.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive amending directive 90/219/EEC on the contained use of genetically modified micro-organisms.</p>
<p>- Auto oil:</p>
<p>a) Draft directive relating to the quality of petrol and diesel fuels;</p>
<p>b) Draft directive on measures against air pollution by emissions from motor vehicules - amendment of directives 70/229//EEC and 70/156/EEC.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council directive concerning the quality of water intended for human consumption.</p>
<p>- Commission communication on waste policy.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council regulation (EEC) No 3254/91 prohibiting the use of leghold traps in the Community and the introduction into the Community of pelts and manufactured goods of certain wild animal species originating in countries which catch them by means of leghold traps or trapping methods which do not meet international humane trapping standards.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation establishing common rules and procedures to apply to the shipments to certain non-OECD countries of certain types of waste.</p>
<p>- Follow-up to the conference on climate change.</p>
<p>- Fifth session of the Commission on sustainable development.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament plenary session (To December 13).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, DECEMBER 12</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Transport Council.</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- External relations:</p>
<p>- Relations with the United States in the field of air transport.</p>
<p>- Recommendation for a Council decision authorising the Commission to open negotiations on air transport agreements between the Community and Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Poland, Romania and Slovakia.</p>
<p>- Negotiations between the European Community and Switzerland on land and air transport.</p>
<p>- Other measures:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to green paper on the citizens' network.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to green paper on internalisation of external costs.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for an European Parliament and Council directive on summertime arrangements.</p>
<p>- Surface transport:</p>
<p>a) Rail transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to the white paper on the future of the railways.</p>
<p>b) Road transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Access to the road haulage profession.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Taxation of goods vehicles to replace directive 93/89/EEC.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation laying down the conditions under which non-resident carriers may operate national road passenger transport services within a member state.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council directive and regulation on recording equipment in road transport.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation (EEC) No 684/92 on common rules for the international carriage of passengers by coach and bus.</p>
<p>- Air transport:</p>
<p>- Follow-up to white paper on air traffic management.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Follow-up to high level group on air safety.</p>
<p>- Proposal for the establishment of a single European authority for air safety.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal on airport charges.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation on air carrier liability in case of accidents.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Revision of regulation on slot allocation.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposals to update rules on denied boarding compensation and passenger protection.</p>
<p>- Maritime transport:</p>
<p>- (possibly) Licensing regime for roll-on roll-off ferry operations.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Compiling lists of passengers on roll-on roll-off ferries.</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council directive setting up a harmonised safety regime for fishing vessels of 24 metres in length and over.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Commission strategic document.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal to amend Council directive 94/58/EC on the minimum level of training of seafarers.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal to amend Council directive 93/75/EEC concerning minimum requirements for vessels bound for or leaving Community ports and carrying dangerous or polluting goods.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Shipping agreements with third countries, especially China and India.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Report on competition in the multimodal sector.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, DECEMBER 13</p>
<p>DUBLIN - Irish presidency hosts European Council of heads of state and government (To December 14).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Council report on the development of tax systems within the Union, taking into account the need to create a tax environment that stimulates business and the creation of jobs and promotes a more efficient environmental policy.</p>
<p>- Commission and European Monetary Institute (EMI) report on progress in stage three of European Monetary Union (EMU).</p>
<p>- Commission report on subsidiarity.</p>
<p>- Presentation of draft revision of the treaties, addressing in particular:</p>
<p>* Bringing the Union closer to its citizens;</p>
<p>* Strengthening and enlarging the scope of the Union's common foreign and security policy;</p>
<p>* Assuring, in view of enlargement, the proper functioning of the institutions while respecting their balance of powers and the efficiency of the decision-making process;</p>
<p>* Simplification of the treaties.</p>
<p>- Commission report on appropriate initiatives for reinforcing regional cooperation in Europe.</p>
<p>- Report on the evolution of the trade policies and the preferential agreements of the Community in relation to the World Trade Organisation (WTO).</p>
<p>- Final European Commission report on the mutually beneficial effects of greater coordination of the Union's economic and structural policies.</p>
<p>- Review of December 1995 Madrid summit recommendations on fighting unemployment and on application of multiannual employment programmes.</p>
<p>- Joint ECOFIN/Social Affairs Council annual employment monitoring report.</p>
<p>- Review of progress in application of Madrid December 1995 drug experts group report on the fight against drugs.</p>
<p>- Territorial pacts for employment within the framework of the confidence pact for employment.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, DECEMBER 15</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - Council of Europe holds symposium on &quot;Medically-assisted procreation and the protection of the human embryo&quot; (To December 18).</p>
<p>MONDAY, DECEMBER 16</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To December 17).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, DECEMBER 17</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Economic and Social Committee (ECOSOC) holds plenary session (To December 19).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, DECEMBER 19</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Fisheries Council (To December 20).</p>
<p>Provisional agenda includes:</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation fixing, for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, the total allowable catches for 1997 and certain conditions under which they may be fished.</p>
<p>- (possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation amending Council regulation (EC) No. 3074/95 fixing, for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, the total allowable catches for 1996 and certain conditions under which they may be fished.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation laying down certain rules for the access to Community waters of research vessels for scientific purposes.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Commission proposal on the financing of collection of scientific data.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Proposal for a Council regulation (EC) amending regulation (EEC) No. 2847/93 establishing a control system applicable to the common fisheries policy (establishment of a Community catch-reporting data-base).</p>
<p>- (Possibly) Proposal for a Council decision on MAGP IV.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council regulations</p>
<p>a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of Norway;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, certain catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in the Norwegian exclusive zone and the fishing zone around Jan Mayen.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council regulations:</p>
<p>a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of the Faroes;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, certain catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Faroese waters.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation allocating, for 1997, Community catch quotas in Greenland waters.</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council regulation allocating, for 1997, certain catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Icelandic waters.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council regulations:</p>
<p>a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of Estonia;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Estonian waters.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council regulations:</p>
<p>a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of Latvia;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Latvian waters.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council regulations</p>
<p>a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of Lithuania;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Lithuanian waters.</p>
<p>- a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of Poland;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Polish waters.</p>
<p>- a) laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of the Russian Federation;</p>
<p>b) allocating, for 1997, catch quotas between member states for vessels fishing in Russian waters.</p>
<p>- Proposal for Council regulation laying down, for 1997, certain conservation and management measures for fishery resources in the regulatory area as defined in the Convention on future multilateral cooperation in the North West Atlantic Fisheries.</p>
<p>- Proposal for a Council regulation laying down, for 1997, certain measures for the conservation and management of fishery resources applicable to vessels flying the flag of certain non-member countries in the 200-nautical-mile zone off the coast of the French Department of Guiana.</p>
<p>- (Possibly) NAFO: New STACFAC regulations.</p>
<p>- Proposals for Council decisions:</p>
<p>a) Authorising the Kingdom of Spain to extend the agreement on mutual fishery relations with the Republic of South Africa;</p>
<p>b) Authorizing the Portuguese Republic to extend the agreement on mutual fishery relations with the Republic of South Africa.</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Executive committee of Schengen group on free movement of people meets at ministerial level under Luxembourg presidency. Venue: Kirchberg conference centre. Luxembourg is hoping to achieve admittance of Nordic countries to Schengen accord during its presidency of the group, with signature of accession protocols for Denmark, Finland and Sweden and association protocols for Iceland and Norway at the meeting.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, DECEMBER 23</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - EU institutions closed for Christmas holidays until January 2.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, DECEMBER 31</p>
<p>- Irish EU presidency ends. The Netherlands takes over to June 30, 1997.</p>
<p>EARLY 1997 (NEW ITEM) - NATO holds summit to formally decide new members and approve a charter defining the alliance relationship with Russia - date to be set later.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JANUARY 13</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To January 17).</p>
<p>MONDAY, JANUARY 20</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - General Affairs Council (To January 21).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To January 21).</p>
<p>MONDAY, JANUARY 27</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - (possibly) ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, JANUARY 29</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To January 30).</p>
<p>FRIDAY, JANUARY 31</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - Informal Transport Council (To February 1).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 5</p>
<p>NOORDWIJK, The Netherlands - Informal Justice and Home Affairs Council (To February 6).</p>
<p>FRIDAY, FEBRUARY 14</p>
<p>ROTTERDAM - Informal Social Affairs Council (To February 15).</p>
<p>MONDAY, FEBRUARY 17</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To February 18).</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To February 21).</p>
<p>MONDAY, FEBRUARY 24</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - General Affairs Council (To February 25).</p>
<p>FRIDAY, FEBRUARY 28</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - Informal Development Council (To March 2).</p>
<p>MONDAY, MARCH 3</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Environment Council (To March 4).</p>
<p>ROTTERDAM - Informal Education Council.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, MARCH 6</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Telecoms Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, MARCH 10</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Internal Market Council.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To March 14).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, MARCH 11</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Transport Council (To March 12).</p>
<p>SATURDAY, MARCH 15</p>
<p>APELDOORN, The Netherland - Informal General Affairs Council (To March 16).</p>
<p>MONDAY, MARCH 17</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To March 19).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, MARCH 18</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Justice and Home Affairs Council (To March 19).</p>
<p>MONDAY, MARCH 24</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - General Affairs Council (To March 25).</p>
<p>FRIDAY, APRIL 4</p>
<p>NOORDWIJK, The Netherlands - Informal ECOFIN Council (To April 6).</p>
<p>MONDAY, APRIL 7</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To April 11).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, APRIL 10</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Consumers Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, APRIL 14</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Fisheries Council (To April 15).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, APRIL 17</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Social Affairs Council.</p>
<p>FRIDAY, APRIL 18</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - Informal Environment Council (To April 20).</p>
<p>MONDAY, APRIL 21</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Farm Council (To April 22).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, APRIL 23</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - ACP-EU Council (To April 24).</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To April 24).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, APRIL 29</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - General Affairs Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, MAY 5</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - (possibly) General Affairs Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, MAY 12</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Farm Council (To May 13).</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To May 16).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, MAY 14</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Research Council (To May 15).</p>
<p>TUESDAY, MAY 20</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Internal Market Council.</p>
<p>SUNDAY, MAY 25</p>
<p>VENUE TO BE CONFIRMED - EU foreign ministers hold Inter-governmental conference (IGC) conclave ahead of European summit (To May 26).</p>
<p>DOMBURG, The Netherlands - Informal Farm Council (To May 27).</p>
<p>MONDAY, MAY 26</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Energy Council.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, MAY 27</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Justice and Home Affairs Council (to May 28).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, MAY 28</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To May 29).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, MAY 29</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Telecoms Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JUNE 2</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - General Affairs Council (To June 3).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, JUNE 5</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Health Council.</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Development Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JUNE 9</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Farm Council (To June 10).</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To June 13).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, JUNE 12</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Social Affairs Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JUNE 16</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - Dutch presidency hosts European Council of heads of state and government (To June 17).</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Transport Council (To June 18).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, JUNE 19</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Fisheries Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JUNE 23</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Environment Council (To June 24).</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - (possibly) ECOFIN Council.</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, JUNE 25</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Paliament holds mini session (To June 26).</p>
<p>THURSDAY, JUNE 26</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Education Council.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JUNE 30</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - General Affairs Council.</p>
<p>LUXEMBOURG - Culture Council.</p>
<p>- Dutch EU presidency ends. Luxembourg takes over to December 31, 1997.</p>
<p>MONDAY, JULY 14</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (to July 18).</p>
<p>MONDAY, SEPTEMBER 15</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To September 19).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 1</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To October 2).</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 20</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliamnt holds plenary session (To October 24).</p>
<p>WEDENESDAY, NOVEMBER 5</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To November 6).</p>
<p>MONDAY, NOVEMBER 17</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To November 21).</p>
<p>WEDNESDAY, DECEMBER 3</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - European Parliament holds mini session (To December 4).</p>
<p>MONDAY, DECEMBER 15</p>
<p>STRASBOURG - European Parliament holds plenary session (To December 19).</p>
<p>If you have items for inclusion in the Reuter European</p>
<p>Community diary, please contact:</p>
<p>Telephone: Cynthia Simpson (322) 287 6851</p>
<p>Fax: (322) 230 5573</p>
<p>For technical queries regarding</p>
<p>the service, please call (322) 287 6666</p>
<p>- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -</p>
<p>EC Report (C)opyright Reuters Limited.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-10"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-10"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
