<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59459" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Families start legal action over Estonia disaster.</title>
<headline>Families start legal action over Estonia disaster.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Relatives of the Estonia ferry victims began legal action in Paris on Tuesday against the ship's German builder and French and Swedish inspectors to try to pinpoint blame for the deaths of 852 people two years ago.</p>
<p>In Europe's worst peacetime maritime disaster, the Estonia sank in the Baltic Sea off the coast of Finland on September 28, 1994, during a heavy storm.</p>
<p>Gunnar Bendreus of the International Estonia Support Group (ISG), which represents victims' relatives, said the action, lodged on the eve of the second anniversary of the sinking, was not motivated by a desire for financial compensation.</p>
<p>&quot;We just want the truth,&quot; said Bendreus, who lost both his parents-in-law when the car and passenger ferry sank on the way from Estonia to Sweden.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to know who was guilty, and to what extent, so steps can be taken to make sure this never happens again. This is the only way to ensure sea safety in the future.&quot;</p>
<p>The Estonia went down after heavy seas ripped off the car deck's outer bow door which allowed water to flood the ship's cavernous car deck, causing it to list and then sink.</p>
<p>Last year victims' relatives and the vessel's 137 survivors received a package of about 600 million crowns ($90 million) from ship owner Estline and insurer Assuranceforeningen Skuld.</p>
<p>The maker of the Estonia, German shipyard Meyer Werft, which delivered the vessel in 1979, France's classification society Bureau Veritas, which approved the ferry for traffic, and Sweden's National Maritime Administration, which inspected the ship for safety, have denied any blame.</p>
<p>The ISG, representing 1,304 relatives, filed a summons application in Paris on Tuesday against all three bodies.</p>
<p>ISG lawyer Henning Witte said the French judge would appoint an expert to investigate the disaster and report back.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the first step to establish liability and it could lead to a damages claim for between five and 10 million crowns in a year or two,&quot; Witte told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We had to act now as this type of action may not be possible more than two years after the accident and it is the two-year anniversary this month.&quot;</p>
<p>Witte said the action was lodged in France because the relatives hoped the case would be treated without bias there.</p>
<p>He said the ISG wanted to avoid any influence from an international commission set up to investigate the accident.</p>
<p>The commission, comprising representatives from Sweden, Finland and Estonia, has been in disarray in recent months with its chairman resigning amid allegations of cover-ups.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't think any truth will come out of that investigation,&quot; Witte said.</p>
<p>The commission's problems followed a long row in Sweden over whether to lay a concrete shell over the sunken wreck which lies 55-88 metres (180-270 feet) down on the Baltic seabed about 100 km (60 miles) off southwest Finland.</p>
<p>Relatives have complained that the entombment would deny the 700 people thought to remain in the wreck a decent burial and have called for attempts to salvage the vessel.</p>
<p>The decision has now been postponed until after the commission tables its final report.</p>
<p>&quot;At least 90 percent of the relatives don't want this to go ahead so why waste money on it,&quot; said Bendreus. ($1=6.62 Swedish crowns)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
