<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61141" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 18.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 18.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Wednesday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Siiri Oviir from the Centre Party and Tunne Kelam from the right-wing Pro Patria have agreed to stand at the presidential elections.</p>
<p>- Editor of a culture magazine, Juri Estam, and MPs Eldur Parder and Villu Muuripeal have turned to Tallinn City Court to argue their case that President Lennart Meri lied when he took his presidential oath.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- An interview with presidential candidate Tunne Kelam focusses on the forthcoming election. He said he is convinced he has a good chance to win the election and that Meri is the president for today while Estonia needs a president for tommorrow.</p>
<p>- A 200 hectare peat field is burning near the northeast Estonian town of Johvi, some 160 kms from Tallinn.</p>
<p>- The crew of the ferry Estonia are to receive offers of compensation this week, their lawyers said.</p>
<p>- An article highlights the alleged links of Lennart Meri with the KGB, allegations which have dogged the president for a long time.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- The government has approved the 1997 draft budget of 22.8 billion kroons and a 1996 supplementary budget of 33 million kroons.</p>
<p>- The government has granted residence permits to 11,224 aliens, most of them Russian-speaking inhabitants. Three of them were dead when the document was issued.</p>
<p>- Justice Minister Paul Varul drove his car into a roadside post on Monday. The car, a government service vehicle, was damaged but the minister was unhurt.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- The support group for the victims of the Estonia ferry disaster started a court case in France against the shipping yard that built the vessel, the Veritas certification bureau and the Swedish maritime department.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- The 1997 draft budget foresees three percent growth of gross domestic product (GDP) and 14 percent inflation.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7 22 66 93</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
