<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="66866" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 20.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 20.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Friday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Tiit Madison, charged with attempted treason and planning a coup, claims to have attempted to scare authorities to get them to allocate more funds to Defence League.</p>
<p>- Tallinn City Court threw out case against Lennart Meri, accused of perjury when taking the oath of conscience; court said the case was beyond its competence.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- The new chairman of the 'Estonia' disaster inquiry expected to be elected next Tuesday; Interior Minister Mart Rask recommended an experienced seaman.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- Presidential candidates were passive in TV debate and avoided personal attacks.</p>
<p>- An outbreak of bacterial disease tularaemia has been confirmed in the small island of Prangli; authorities say there is no reason for panic.</p>
<p>- Estonian feature film &quot;I am tired of hating&quot; won special prize at Alexandria Film Festival in Egypt.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- Fire in Aware peat field continues, but situation is described as stable.</p>
<p>- Compensation agreed for crew members of sunken ferry 'Estonia' and relatives of the dead; a law office declared the amounts no lower than those for passengers and their families.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- Hotel management firm Finest Hotel Group is recovering from recent losses; plans to build hotels in Narva and Otepaa.</p>
<p>- Presidential officer claims 1.2 million kroons in compensation from travel agency, which organized tour in U.S. and Mexico last year and failed to meet some requirements.</p>
<p>- Estonia's admission to WTO will be postponed -- bilateral negotiations with members cannot be completed in time for congress to be held in December.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7226693</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
