<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="70200" id="root" date="1996-09-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 23.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Monday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Estonian peace-keeping company will leave for Norway for training before a mission in Lebanon.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- President Lennart Meri has sent a plan to increase Estonia's security to Washington, which includes a call for a security partnership.</p>
<p>- An Estonian-Finnish visa-free travel agreement will probably be postponed since Finland is presenting more requirements, a foreign ministry official said.</p>
<p>- Estonian investment opportunities are excellent, British Foreign Trade Council chairman Martin Laing said after a visit to Estonia last week.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- Estonia sold its only marine research vessel to Swedish Navy, allegedly below its true value.</p>
<p>- U.S. State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns commented on the re-election of Lennart Meri, described him as a democrat and an inspiring leader.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- The Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) will open its office in Tallin early next year and two agents will be assigned to the U.S. Embassy.</p>
<p>- The fire in the Oru peat fields in northeast Estonia continues for the second week and fire-fighters fear that wind may increase the burning area.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- The inactive chemical plant project Ceosil received 18 million kroon credit from the U.S., which will enable to pay debts and purchase raw material. The firm will produce washing powder.</p>
<p>- Estonia's largest food concern, ETFC, has decided to support the EKSEKO pig farm to prevent its bankruptcy, which could lead to the collapse of meat production in Estonia.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7 22 66 93</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
