<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72569" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 24.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 24.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Delegations from Estonia and Finland approved in Helsinki a draft agreement on visa-free travel. The deadlines for signing and the implementation of the proposals were left undecided.</p>
<p>- Central bank president Vahur Kraft dismissed in parliament yesterday the doubts of opposition Centre Party members of parliament about the central bank's actions.</p>
<p>- The government has been successful in checking illegal arms deals in Estonia and there is no legal vaccuum in that sphere anymore, Prime Minister Tiit Vaehi told parliament.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- Forged documents, proving proficiency in the Estonian language can be bought at markets for 500 kroons, officials from the language department discovered. Part of the process for Russian-speakers to be naturalised as an Estonian citizen is the need to know and prove they can speak the language.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- The education ministry asked for 50 million kroons but was promised only 35.5 million kroons in the 1997 budget for new technology, dubbed the &quot;tiger leap&quot; into the future by President Lennart Meri. Students of Tartu University say the computer project should be called &quot;the lying tiger&quot;.</p>
<p>- A Latvian vessel was found trawling in Estonian waters on September 19, violating the recent sea border agreement.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- Estonia's leading heart surgeon Toomas Sulling said operating on Russian President Boris Yeltsin has been left too late and no great success can be expected.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- The re-election of Lennart Meri will ensure that investments to Estonia will continue, foreign experts said.</p>
<p>- IMF resident representative Basil Zavoico believes that inflation in Estonia in 1997 will remain at the current level or even grow whereas Vaehi's advisor Heido Vitsur believes inflation will fall.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7 22 66 93</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
