<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75108" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 25.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 25.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Wednesday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- A real estate firm evicted a family from their apartment without a court order.</p>
<p>- Oil terminal owner Endel Siff accused the foreign ministry of unwillingness to improve relations with Russia. The ministry rejected the accusations and explained that Russia does not want better relations.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- Swedish police prevented an attempt to smuggle 14 Indians to Sweden in the luggage compartment of a tour bus.</p>
<p>- Justice Minister Paul Varul declared that the abolition of capital punishment as demanded by the EU can take place in two years but not earlier.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- Estonia is the third country in Eastern/Central Europe in terms of the level of foreign investment, Foreign Investments Agency director Juri Sakkeus announced.</p>
<p>- The President of the International Red Cross Committee, Cornelio Sommaruga, is visiting Estonia. He held a lecture on humanitarian law in Tartu University and stated that the Red Cross will have to restore its reputation after Soviet occupation.</p>
<p>- The fire in the Oru peat fields in northeastern Estonia has been reduced from 250 to 150 hectares, but winds may still spread the fire.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- The first parties have begun their election campaign for the local councils and the Reform Party intends to use 1.5 million kroons for campaigning.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Tiit Vaehi opened a new cargo ferry line between Tallin and Kiel yesterday.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7 22 66 93</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
