<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81463" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Egypt divers find 14 bodies in Nile ferry accident.</title>
<headline>Egypt divers find 14 bodies in Nile ferry accident.</headline>
<dateline>MINYA, Egypt 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Divers combing the Nile River on Friday recovered 14 bodies and are looking for at least 40 more after a ferry capsized with 75 people on board off a southern Egyptian village, security sources said.</p>
<p>Nineteen people were rescued on Thursday night after the ferry sank while carrying the villagers home from a funeral.</p>
<p>&quot;When I saw the boat sinking I screamed at the top of my lungs...I only saw the people for a flash and then it went under,&quot; said grocer Zaghloul Fares of the Sheikh Tamy village.</p>
<p>The interior ministry said the boat, a four-metre (13 foot) long sailing vessel, was grossly overloaded. Security sources and survivors said it hit a barge, listed and sank.</p>
<p>Cairo newspapers published in their Saturday editions stories of distraught survivors.</p>
<p>&quot;While we were on the way back, I noticed the very young son of the captain was holding the rudder. I warned him to let go but his father scolded me,&quot; survivor Mohammed Khalifa told the Al-Akhbar newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;Shortly after, the boat veered and hit a barge and we all were tipped to one side and jumped off. I managed to hang onto the barge and was saved in the nick of time.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I also managed to pull up 10 others onto the barge but I could not save my best friend Yasser and I saw him drown in front of my eyes,&quot; Khalifa, 21, added.</p>
<p>The accident happened near the ancient tombs at Beni Hassan, in Minya province about 260 km (160 miles) south of Cairo, after a funeral on the west bank of the river.</p>
<p>The river is several hundred metres (yards) wide at that point and the current is strong.</p>
<p>Police have detained the ferry captain, 59-year-old Ahmed Mohammed Munir, for questioning and ordered a widescale investigation into the facilities of other ferry boats.</p>
<p>Anxious families were lining the river bank, waiting for bodies to float up and diving themselves to look for their kin. Women doused themselves in dust in an age-old mourning tradition and distraught elders cried for missing relatives.</p>
<p>Divers will continue their search until Sunday but have broken off until dawn. A wire net has been erected to prevent any bodies floating downstream.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINYA, Egypt"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
