<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83370" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Two years on, Estonia disaster still a puzzle.</title>
<headline>Two years on, Estonia disaster still a puzzle.</headline>
<byline>Abigail Schmelz</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedes and Estonians lit candles on Saturday in memory of the 852 people killed when the Estonia ferry sank, but two years after Europe's worst peacetime maritime disaster major question marks remain.</p>
<p>Delays in the investigation and government indecision about what to do with the wreck, thought to contain hundreds of bodies on the Baltic Sea floor where it lies, have left relatives of victims not knowing what, or who, was to blame for the accident.</p>
<p>The ship went down about 100 km (60 miles) off the Finnish coast on its way from Estonia to Sweden after heavy seas tore the ship's bow door off and water flooded the cavernous car deck, causing the vessel to list and sink in a few minutes.</p>
<p>More than 500 of the victims were Swedes, trapped on board as the ferry wallowed through a vicious autumn squall. Estonians made up the second largest group.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course it's a concern to the government that we are not ready,&quot; said Olof Forssberg, the Swedish chairman of the international commission set up to investigate the accident.</p>
<p>&quot;We are three countries without a common language,&quot; Forssberg said about the committee, which has representatives from Sweden, Finland and Estonia.</p>
<p>&quot;New details that we have to investigate have emerged. We now have enough information to establish a cause for the accident,&quot; Forssberg said, adding he hoped the much delayed final report would be completed by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The commission has been in disarray in recent months following the resignation of Estonian chairman Andi Meister amid allegations of cover-ups over a video of the wreck which was said to reveal who was on the bridge when the accident occurred.</p>
<p>One of the 137 survivors, Kent Harstedt, has called for an investigation into how Swedish authorities handled the disaster.</p>
<p>Harstedt made headlines at the time of the calamity after making a pact with a woman as the ship was sinking that if they survived they would have dinner together. The woman also lived.</p>
<p>&quot;Two years after the accident we have no accident report and no national memorial,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Many countries are looking to see how Sweden, which is good at helping out with catastrophes in developing countries, copes with its own disaster,&quot; Harstedt said.</p>
<p>A panel of experts hired by the ship's German builder Meyer Werft earlier this month accused the ship's operator, Estline of Tallinn, of poor vessel maintenance and sloppy repair work.</p>
<p>Estline has denied any fault.</p>
<p>Other investigations into the disaster have unearthed a series of errors which contributed to the fatalities, including weaknesses in the basic design of roll-on, roll-off ferries.</p>
<p>Relatives of victims of the disaster filed a legal action in Paris this month against the ship's German builder and French and Swedish inspectors to try to pinpoint blame for the accident, rather than for financial compensation, they said.</p>
<p>The Swedish government has shelved plans to encase the sunken wreck, which lies 55-88 metres (180-270 feet) down on the Baltic seabed, in a concrete shell in order to protect it from graveyard plundering.</p>
<p>Relatives have complained the entombment would deny victims a decent burial and have called for the wreck to be salvaged, a project which would cost around 1.5 billion crowns ($230 million).</p>
<p>&quot;The Swedish government is the only one that has declared the site of a catastrophe a burial place,&quot; said Orjan Norlin, who lost his wife in the accident.</p>
<p>&quot;The TWA plane outside New York was salvaged within a few weeks, but not the Estonia,&quot; Norlin said.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know for example where my wife is. Is she inside the Estonia, or was she, and now she's been washed away?&quot; said Norlin, a police officer whose wife was part of a group of civilian police employees onboard the ill-fated Estonia.</p>
<p>At least one private dive has been made by a man in an attempt to recover the body of his wife.</p>
<p>As a consequence of the accident European nations decided to toughen ferry safety requirements, increasing the amount of water a damaged ship must be able to hold before capsizing. ($1=6.6175 Swedish crowns)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
