<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="84873" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 30.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - Sept 30.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Monday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- The presidents of the Baltic states in a joint statement vowed to make efforts to upgrade their defence capabilities to NATO standards and get entry into the alliance as soon as possible after U.S. Defence Secretary William Perry on Friday said the Balts were not yet ready for NATO.</p>
<p>- President Lennart Meri said at the opening of the monument to the Estonia ferry disaster in Tallinn that he would give his full support to finding out the reasons for the disaster.</p>
<p>- The fire at the Oru peat field in northeastern Estonia may spread from 150 hectares to a 500 hectare area after winds picked up over the weekend although a downpour of rain is expected to help the rescue services.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- The former chairman of the European Parliament Egon Klepsch said at a roundtable meeting in Tallinn that no prognosis could be made on European Union expansion.</p>
<p>- Estonian Foreign Minister Siim Kallas said he would ask NATO member countries to explain further the statement by Perry in the Norwegian town of Bergen.</p>
<p>- The prosecutor's office said that detaining former defence forces chief Aleksander Einseln for questioning was legal.</p>
<p>- A Bangkok court eased a prison sentence for three Estonian drug smugglers.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- Kallas said a statement by Prime Minister Tiit Vaehi's foreign policy advisor Sirje Ender that there was no eastern foreign policy to speak of was provocative coming at a time when complicated talks were being held with Russia.</p>
<p>- Police in Harju county arrested two policemen, suspected to beating to death a 16-year-old boy.</p>
<p>- Russian nationalist Pyotr Rozhok was granted a nine-day visa to Estonia to allow him to attend a trial over his deportation, due to begin on October 1.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- A member of the central Bank of Estonia council Ardo Hansson warned that the Estonian economy was in danger of over-heating and that bankers and businessmen were too confident.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 7 22 66 93</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
