<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85889" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Eurotunnel seen winning battle for business.</title>
<headline>Eurotunnel seen winning battle for business.</headline>
<byline>Edna Fernandes</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Anglo-French cross-Channel operator Eurotunnel Plc was locked in talks with banks over its debts on Monday but analysts say it is winning its battle for business with the ferry companies.</p>
<p>Eurotunnel has seen its market share soar to 45 percent of the cross-Channel market since slashing prices for its Le Shuttle services in May. Analysts say it is set to raise that share further in 1997.</p>
<p>In its bid to secure the position of market leader, Eurotunnel ignited a new and more vicious price war, reducing economy vehicle fares through the tunnel by more than 50 percent earlier this year.</p>
<p>Passenger numbers were also boosted by a changeover in ownership of the British arm of the Eurostar passenger trains. This has marketed the service more aggressively as an alternative not only to ferries but also to short-haul continental flights.</p>
<p>The moves led to further haemorrhaging of sales at the ferry operators, with casualties including Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Co (P&amp;O) and Sweden's Stena.</p>
<p>Eurotunnel shares were suspended on Monday. A source in Paris close to the discussions said negotiations with banks over the firm's huge $14 billion debts were advancing and the positions getting closer.</p>
<p>Analysts say Eurotunnel's marketing strategy had been a success and expect further gains in market share next year.</p>
<p>Michael Cohen, analyst at Salomon Brothers, said: &quot;I think we may see a further improvement -- perhaps close to 60 percent. But Eurotunnel will have to reach a balance on sales and prices.&quot;</p>
<p>Selwyn Jones, analyst at Credit Lyonnais Laing, agreed that although Eurotunnel could edge volumes a little higher, it would have to raise prices, too, as the current bargain-basement level was unsustainable.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices cannot possibly go on at this level,&quot; he said. &quot;The cross-Channel market of 1997 will be very different to 1996. Prices at Eurotunnel and the ferry companies will have to move higher.&quot;</p>
<p>But he added that the tunnel operator was unlikely to restore fares to the full 1995 level and might instead seek a rate between this and 1996 price-war levels.</p>
<p>Ferry companies have said they are looking at link-ups to cut excess capacity and allow room for higher prices.</p>
<p>The price war has seriously eroded results at big companies such as P&amp;O and Stena, leading to calls for the freedom to establish alliances. Last week, Belgian state-owned group RMT said it would pull out of the Channel market completely.</p>
<p>Jones said the prospect of a ferry alliance was &quot;no threat (to Eurotunnel) in the short term&quot;.</p>
<p>Cohen said the ferry companies had no choice but to link up, commenting: &quot;The tunnel is there and they can't change its effect.&quot; A link-up is an inevitable prospect, he added.</p>
<p>In a related move, P&amp;O is to buy out Dutch partner Nedlloyd's 50 percent stake in North Sea Ferries, which operates large passenger and freight ferries between Britain and the Netherlands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C313">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
