<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14501" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Hijacked Sudanese plane flies towards London.</title>
<headline>Hijacked Sudanese plane flies towards London.</headline>
<dateline>LARNACA, Cyprus 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>A hijacked Sudan Airways plane with 199 passengers and crew on board was flying early on Tuesday towards London where its armed hijackers intend to surrender and seek political asylum, police said in Cyprus where the plane refuelled.</p>
<p>The Airbus 310 Flight 150 was hijacked on its way from Khartoum to the Jordanian capital Amman on Monday evening and landed at Larnaca airport in Cyprus after it ran low on fuel.</p>
<p>One hijacker was apparently armed with grenades and TNT and had threatened to blow the plane up unless it was refuelled and they were taken to London where they wanted political asylum, police spokesman Glafcos Xenos said.</p>
<p>&quot;They will surrender the passengers there and surrender themselves,&quot; Xenos told reporters at Larnaca airport.</p>
<p>He said the foreign minister of Cyprus had contacted the High Commission in Nicosia to inform British authorities that the plane would fly to London's Heathrow airport.</p>
<p>The flight was expected to take about 4-1/2 hours with the plane due to reach London at around 03.15 GMT.</p>
<p>Cypriot authorities tried to negotiate through the pilot with one of the hijackers, asking him to release all women and children on board before refuelling.</p>
<p>But he refused and was quoted as saying: &quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>The police spokesman defended the decision by Cypriot authorities to refuel the plane and let it fly to London, saying they could not risk the lives of those on board.</p>
<p>&quot;They ordered us to refuel the plane otherwise they were going to blow it up...They had hand grenades,&quot; Xenos said.</p>
<p>&quot;All possible measures were taken but the hijackers refused to negotiate. We tried our best,&quot; Xenos said.</p>
<p>The identity and number of the hijackers was not known. One of them negotiated through the pilot in English. The pilot said several hijackers appeared to be placed around the plane.</p>
<p>Cyprus initially refused permission for the plane to land but allowed it to touch down when the pilot said he was running out of fuel. Egypt had earlier stopped it from landing, Cypriot officials said. They sent a message to Khartoum asking for a passenger list but got no reply, police said.</p>
<p>The plane was believed to have 186 passengers and 13 crew on board. There were no reports of injuries, Xenos said.</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner.</p>
<p>On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew was hijacked to Eritrea. The two Sudanese hijackers who seized the plane on an internal flight sought political asylum in Eritrea. They surrendered to Eritrean authorities on reaching Asmara, the Eritrean capital.</p>
<p>Sudan's Islamist military government has a broad array of political opponents and is waging a bitter war against separatist rebels in the mainly Christian and animist south. The United States accuses the Khartoum government of sponsoring &quot;state terrorism&quot;.</p>
<p>The Sudanese army on Saturday denied an opposition report that 11 military officers were executed on charges of taking part in a conspiracy to blow up government targets in Port Sudan.</p>
<p>But army spokesman General Mohamed Sanousi Ahmed told the Sudan News Agency (SUNA) that up to 25 people had been arrested, including 17 military men, in connection with the plot to attack vital installations in the Red Sea port and disrupt Sudan's foreign trade.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LARNACA, Cyprus"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
