<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14512" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Hijacked Sudan plane refuelled in Cyprus for UK.</title>
<headline>Hijacked Sudan plane refuelled in Cyprus for UK.</headline>
<dateline>LARNACA, Cyprus 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cypriot authorities ordered the refuelling early on Tuesday of a hijacked Sudanese Airbus 310 parked at Larnaca airport after armed men threatened to blow it up unless they were flown to London, a police spokesman said.</p>
<p>The Sudan Airways plane was hijcked on Monday night en route from Khartoum to Amman in Jordan with 186 passengers and 13 crew on board.</p>
<p>Police said they believed there was more than one hijacker and at least one was armed with grenades and TNT. They wanted political asylum in Britain, police said.</p>
<p>Cypriot authorities negotiated through the pilot with one of the hijackers for him to release all women and children on board before refuelling but he refused and was quoted as saying:</p>
<p>&quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>He later said he would release all passengers on arrival in London, the police spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are making every effort to get the passengers free,&quot; Xenos told reporters.</p>
<p>Refuelling began and was expected to take about 20 minutes. The plane would then leave for London, Xenos said.</p>
<p>The identity of the hijackers was not known. One of them negotiated through the pilot in English, police said.</p>
<p>The Airbus 310 was parked at the western edge of Larnaca's coastal airport and was ringed by police. Anti-terrorist police arrived.</p>
<p>Cyprus initially refused permission for the plane to land but allowed it to touch down when the pilot said he was running out of fuel, Cypriot officials said.</p>
<p>Cairo airport sources said earlier the plane was hijacked about 20 minutes after it took off from Khartoum airport.</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner.</p>
<p>On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew was hijacked to Eritrea.</p>
<p>The two Sudanese hijackers who seized the plane on an internal flight sought political asylum in Eritrea. They surrendered to Eritrean authorities immediately after reaching Asmara, the Eritrean capital.</p>
<p>Sudan's Islamist military government has a broad array of political opponents and is waging a bitter war against separatist rebels in the mainly Christian and animist south</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LARNACA, Cyprus"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
