<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14673" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Plot to bomb 12 jets was real, U.S. says.</title>
<headline>Plot to bomb 12 jets was real, U.S. says.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, U.S. Law Correspondent</p>
<p>A plot by three militant Moslems to bomb 12 U.S. passenger jets last year was very real and the defendants had the know-how and will to carry it out, a federal prosecutor said on Monday.</p>
<p>In closing arguments at the trial of the three accused plotters, Assistant U.S. Attorney Dietrich Snell told a Manhattan federal jury that if a fire had not broken out in the Philippine apartment being used to make the bombs, the scheme would have been executed.</p>
<p>&quot;The defendants' plan was very real. They had the material, they had the knowhow and they had the determination to carry out the plan with deadly precision,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The three have been on trial since May for their alleged plan to destroy the planes within a 48-hour period last year and kill about 4,000 passengers as they returned to the United States from the Far East.</p>
<p>The government's presentation of evidence entered a crucial phase last month at about the same time as the fatal TWA explosion over Long Island, New York. All 230 passengers and crew on board were killed.</p>
<p>Reports speculating that the defendants might have some connection to the explosion caused U.S. District Judge Kevin Duffy to question jurors as to whether their judgment had been affected by the disaster.</p>
<p>The government's evidence included a laptop computer seized from a Manila apartment shared by two of the defendants that held files calling the scheme &quot;Bojinka.&quot;</p>
<p>It contained flight schedules and code names for the defendants who would carry out the bombings aboard Delta, Northwest and United planes bound for the United States from the Far East. The schedules were for flights with stopovers before they reached the United States.</p>
<p>A letter in the computer said the purpose of the attacks was to punish the United States for its support of Israel.</p>
<p>Snell said the word &quot;Bojinka&quot; should have become part of the jurors' vocabulary, &quot;synonymous with one of the most hideous crimes ... ever conceived.&quot;</p>
<p>The alleged ringleader of the airline bombing scheme is Ramzi Ahmed Yousef, who will be tried again this year on charges that he masterminded the 1993 World Trade Centre bombing that killed six people and injured more than 1,000.</p>
<p>&quot;He was the architect of the whole scheme. He was the chief recruiter,&quot; Snell said.</p>
<p>The other defendants are Abdul Hakim Murad and Wali Khan Amin Shah.</p>
<p>Yousef is also charged with placing a bomb on a Philippine Airlines flight from Manila to Tokyo on Dec. 11, 1994, as a trial run. The bomb exploded under the seat of a Japanese passenger, killing him and injuring 10 other people.</p>
<p>The flight originated in Manila and Yousef allegedly left the plane during a stopover. Prosecutors alleged that he mixed the bomb in a restroom during the first leg of the flight and placed it under his seat with the timer set to detonate the bomb after the plane left for Toyko.</p>
<p>The plot to bomb the airliners was uncovered on Jan. 6, 1995, when a fire broke out in a Manila apartment where Yousef and Murad were mixing chemicals. Philippine police found the laptop computer during their search of the apartment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
