<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16169" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British police arrest seven as hijack ends quietly.</title>
<headline>British police arrest seven as hijack ends quietly.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>STANSTED, England 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Armed Iraqis who hijacked a Sudanese airliner carrying 199 passengers and crew released all their hostages and surrendered in London on Tuesday after several hours of tense negotiations, police said.</p>
<p>Seven suspected hijackers were arrested and police in black commando-style overalls boarded the plane to search for weapons.</p>
<p>Police said they were still not sure what the men wanted, but said they had apparently asked for political asylum. Several had brought their families along, including children, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think they saw (Britain) possibly as a safe haven and somewhere that they would be received,&quot; Essex police chief John Burrow told a news conference.</p>
<p>Burrow said the hostage-takers had agreed to surrender after an Iraqi exile became involved in the negotiations.</p>
<p>The hijack started when Sudan Airways flight 150 left Khartoum for Amman on Monday night. The hijackers told the crew they had grenades and other explosives and threatened to blow up the plane if they were not taken to London, police said.</p>
<p>The Airbus 310 airliner refuelled at Larnaca, Cyprus and landed at London's Stansted airport in the early hours of Tuesday after circling overhead for about an hour, Burrow said.</p>
<p>Five hundred police, many armed, were deployed at the airport 30 miles (50 km) northeast of the capital.</p>
<p>Negotiations began within an hour via radio and tired-looking passengers, many of them women carrying small children, trickled off the aircraft.</p>
<p>Most of the passengers were Sudanese with an unknown number of Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Syrians and Saudis.</p>
<p>Burrow said the hijackers demanded to speak to Iraqi exile Saddiq Sadda and asked that United Nations and International Committee of the Red Cross observers come to the airport.</p>
<p>Sadda was brought to Stansted after a frantic police search. Burrow said his presence immediately defused the situation.</p>
<p>&quot;When we assured them 'Saddiq is here and he is prepared to witness the coming off from the aeroplane along with the United Nations and the Red Cross' they said 'Well, all right, that's enough for us',&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Burrow described the hijackers as &quot;firm and disciplined&quot; but denied they made any threats while in London.</p>
<p>Police said passengers were calm despite their ordeal. Three men overcome by stress were taken to hospital in ambulances but police said they had not been ill-treated by the hijackers.</p>
<p>Burrow said it would take several days to interview the passengers and hijackers, many of whom did not speak English, and piece together exactly what happened.</p>
<p>Iraqi exiles condemned the hijacking. &quot;The Iraqi National Congress is unequivocally opposed to hijacking and violence against innocent civilians,&quot; the London-based group said.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation under (Iraqi leader) Saddam Hussein's regime may lead some Iraqis to take desperate measures,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is possible the hijackers would prefer to live in a British jail than in Saddam's Iraq, but all Iraqis who believe in democracy and human rights would condemn terrorism and hostage-taking under any circumstances.&quot;</p>
<p>The Iraqi National Congress said it believed an Iraqi diplomat was on the plane, but could not say if he was a passenger or a hijacker.</p>
<p>Another group opposing Saddam, the Supreme Council of Islamic Resistance in Iraq (SCIRI), also attacked the hijackers. &quot;However we think the internal situation in Iraq might push Iraqis to seek refugee status by wrong methods as they try to get out of the hell under Saddam's regime in Iraq.&quot;</p>
<p>Members of Saddam's family defected to Jordan last year. Iraqi news media reported in February two of Saddam's sons-in-law were murdered by relatives days after returning home to a pardon from the Iraqi leader.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STANSTED, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
