<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17361" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SUDAN: Sudanese plane hijackers release 160 hostages.</title>
<headline>Sudanese plane hijackers release 160 hostages.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>STANSTED, England 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Sudanese aircraft on a flight from Khartoum to Amman was hijacked to London on Tuesday where armed hostage-takers, believed to be from the Middle East, released some 160 of 199 passengers and crew.</p>
<p>Hundreds of armed police were deployed at Stansted airport, where the Sudanese Airways Airbus landed in the early hours after being forced to divert to Cyprus for refueling. At Larnaca the hijackers had at one point threatened to blow up the jet. Some police stood as close as 50 metres from the aircraft, while dozens of police vans waited about 1.5 miles (two km) across the tarmac along with firefighters and ambulances.</p>
<p>Meanwile, negotiations were conducted by radio.</p>
<p>Police said some of the hijackers may be Iraqi nationals. An Iraqi exile group said the hostage-takers wanted to contact one of its members.</p>
<p>They said over 160 hostages had been released in batches of 10 and expressed the hope others would soon be freed.</p>
<p>The six or seven hijackers, who have said they want to seek asylum in Britain, are believed to be armed with grenades and possibly other explosives, according to police.</p>
<p>&quot;All I can say is, negotiations are going on between themselves (the hijackers) and members of the Iraqi Community Association,&quot; said police spokeswoman Kim White.</p>
<p>An official at the Iraqi Community Association said they believed the hijackers were trying to contact an Iraqi named Sadik Sadah.</p>
<p>Sadah is a former member of the Association's executive committee who now works as a volunteer. The official was unable to say whether Sadah had made contact with the hijackers.</p>
<p>Police were unable to comment on speculation that the Iraqis were diplomats based in Khartoum who were seeking to defect rather than return to Baghdad.</p>
<p>The plane was hijacked on Monday evening soon after it left Khartoum for the Jordanian capital Amman.</p>
<p>The hijackers started to release captives about two hours after the Airbus 310 airliner arrived at Stansted from Larnaca in Cyprus, where it was refuelled, at 4.30 a.m. (0330 GMT).</p>
<p>Police said the passengers who disembarked, led by the elderly and mothers with small children, were very calm and collected despite their ordeal.</p>
<p>Two sick passengers were taken away in ambulances, but police said their illnesses were not related to the way they had been treated by the hijackers.</p>
<p>Sanctions imposed on the government of Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein mean international flights do not land in Baghdad. Travellers can fly to Amman and proceed overland.</p>
<p>Members of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's family defected to Jordan last year. Iraqi news media reported in February that the two top-level defectors, who were Saddam's sons-in-law, were murdered by relatives days after returning home to a pardon from the Iraqi leader.</p>
<p>During the stop in Cyprus, the hijackers told police they wanted to claim political asylum in Britain and would release the passengers once they landed in London.</p>
<p>Those who were released were being interviewed by police who were attempting to gather information about the hijackers.</p>
<p>Specially trained British negotiators established telephone contact via the airliner's captain within an hour of the aircraft touching down at Stansted, which is about 30 miles (50 km) northeast of the capital.</p>
<p>The plane was parked at a remote part of the airport two miles (three km) from the main terminal.</p>
<p>White said that most of the passengers were Sudanese but that there were also an unknown number of Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Syrians and Saudis.</p>
<p>The Cypriot authorities tried to negotiate through the pilot with one of the hijackers, asking him to release all women and children on board before refuelling.</p>
<p>But he refused and said only: &quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner. On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew on an internal flight was hijacked to Asmara, the Eritrean capital, where the two Sudanese hijackers surrendered and sought political asylum.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STANSTED, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SUDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
