<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17648" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sudan airliner hijackers begin release of hostages.</title>
<headline>Sudan airliner hijackers begin release of hostages.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>STANSTED, England 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hijackers began to release hostages on Tuesday from a Sudan Airways plane carrying 199 passengers and crew that landed at London's Stansted airport.</p>
<p>Police said 40 passengers, mostly women and children, had been freed from the Airbus 310 airliner in a &quot;controlled release&quot; by 7.30 a.m. (0630 GMT), three hours after it arrived from Cyprus.</p>
<p>Two sick passengers were taken away in ambulances, but police said their illnesses were not related to the way they had been treated by the hijackers.</p>
<p>One woman appeared to collapse in the aircraft doorway before picking herself up and walking down the steps. Two elderly passengers were helped down the steps by a crew member.</p>
<p>The plane was hijacked on Monday evening soon after it left Khartoum for the Jordanian capital Amman.</p>
<p>British police said there were six or seven hijackers on board armed with grenades and possibly other explosives.</p>
<p>During a refuelling stop in Cyprus, the unidentified hijackers told police they wanted to claim political asylum in Britain and would release the passengers once they landed in London.</p>
<p>However, British police said the hijackers, thought to be from Sudan or the Middle East and to have their whole families with them on board the plane, had issued just one demand -- that they be allowed to speak to an unidentified fellow countryman who is based in London.</p>
<p>They had not asked for food or water.</p>
<p>&quot;The only demand that they have made so far is to speak to this fellow countryman,&quot; said Kim White, a spokeswoman for Essex police, the force with responsibility for Stansted.</p>
<p>&quot;They have given us a name and we are making efforts to contact the man. Everyone seems calm and collected, considering the circumstances.&quot;</p>
<p>Released passengers were being interviewed by police who were attempting to gather information about the hijackers.</p>
<p>Specially trained British negotiators established telephone contact via the airliner's captain within an hour of the aircraft touching down at Stansted, which is about 30 miles (50 km) northeast of the capital.</p>
<p>The plane was parked at a remote part of the airport two miles (three km) from the main terminal.</p>
<p>White said that most of the passengers were Sudanese but that there were also an unknown number of Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Syrians and Saudis.</p>
<p>Sudan's Islamist military government, which the United States has accused of sponsoring &quot;state terrorism&quot;, has a broad array of political opponents and is waging a bitter war against separatist rebels in the mainly Christian and animist south.</p>
<p>Police in Cyprus said that at least one of the hijackers had apparently been armed with grenades and TNT and threatened to blow the aircraft up unless it flew to Britain so they could claim political asylum.</p>
<p>The Cypriot authorities tried to negotiate through the pilot with one of the hijackers, asking him to release all women and children on board before refuelling.</p>
<p>But he refused and said only: &quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner.</p>
<p>On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew on an internal flight was hijacked to Asmara, the Eritrean capital, where the two Sudanese hijackers surrendered and sought political asylum.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STANSTED, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
