<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17647" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sudanese plane hijackers release 140 hostages.</title>
<headline>Sudanese plane hijackers release 140 hostages.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>STANSTED, England 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Armed hijackers, believed to be Iraqis, freed 140 of the 199 passengers and crew aboard a Sudan Airways plane on Tuesday after it was seized on a flight from Khartoum to Amman and diverted to Britain.</p>
<p>Police at Stansted airport near London spoke of a &quot;controlled release&quot; of hostages in batches of 10 at a time and said they hoped the rest would soon be freed.</p>
<p>The six or seven hijackers, who have said they seek asylum in Britain, are Iraqi nationals believed to be armed with grenades and possibly other explosives, according to police.</p>
<p>The hijackers, who were still on board, earlier threatened to blow up the aircraft during a refuelling stop in Cyprus.</p>
<p>&quot;They're definitely Iraqi,&quot; police spokeswoman Kim White told reporters. They also had their families with them.</p>
<p>A police commander, Roger Grimwade, said the captors had made various requests of police negotiators but stepped back from reports conveyed by other police spokesman that they had demanded to meet a leader of the Iraqi Community Association in London named as Mr Sadiki.</p>
<p>Grimwade was also unable to comment on speculation that the Iraqis were diplomats based in Khartoum who were seeking to defect rather than return to Baghdad.</p>
<p>The hijackers started to release their captives about two hours after the Airbus 310 airliner arrived at Stansted from Cyprus, where it was refuelled, at 4.30 a.m. (0330 GMT).</p>
<p>Police said the passengers who disembarked, led by the elderly and mothers with small children, were very calm and collected despite their ordeal.</p>
<p>Two sick passengers were taken away in ambulances, but police said their illnesses were not related to the way they had been treated by the hijackers.</p>
<p>The plane was hijacked on Monday evening soon after it left Khartoum for the Jordanian capital Amman.</p>
<p>During the stop in Cyprus, the hijackers told police they wanted to claim political asylum in Britain and would release the passengers once they landed in London.</p>
<p>Those who were released were being interviewed by police who were attempting to gather information about the hijackers.</p>
<p>Specially trained British negotiators established telephone contact via the airliner's captain within an hour of the aircraft touching down at Stansted, which is about 30 miles (50 km) northeast of the capital.</p>
<p>The plane was parked at a remote part of the airport two miles (three km) from the main terminal.</p>
<p>White said that most of the passengers were Sudanese but that there were also an unknown number of Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Syrians and Saudis.</p>
<p>Sudan's Islamist military government, which the United States has accused of sponsoring &quot;state terrorism&quot;, has a broad array of political opponents and is waging a bitter war against separatist rebels in the mainly Christian and animist south.</p>
<p>The Cypriot authorities tried to negotiate through the pilot with one of the hijackers, asking him to release all women and children on board before refuelling.</p>
<p>But he refused and said only: &quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner.</p>
<p>On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew on an internal flight was hijacked to Asmara, the Eritrean capital, where the two Sudanese hijackers surrendered and sought political asylum.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STANSTED, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
