<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17652" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Police make contact with Sudanese plane hijackers.</title>
<headline>Police make contact with Sudanese plane hijackers.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>STANSTED, England 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>British police began negotiating early on Tuesday with hijackers who diverted a Sudan Airways plane with 199 passengers and crew on board to London and who were reported to want political asylum in Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody is calm and there is nothing untoward on the plane,&quot; police Chief Inspector Roger Grimwade told reporters. &quot;We would hope to have reached a peaceful conclusion within two or three hours.&quot;</p>
<p>The passengers, said by the police to be Sudanese and from Middle Eastern countries, were on their way from Khartoum to the Jordanian capital Amman on Monday when the plane was diverted to Cyprus for refuelling and then to London.</p>
<p>Specially trained negotiators established telephone contact with the unidentified hijackers within an hour of the Airbus 310 Flight 150 touching down at London's Stansted airport at 4.30 a.m. (0330 GMT) after a flight from Cyprus.</p>
<p>&quot;Negotiations have begun or are certainly in the process of being established,&quot; Kim White, a spokeswoman for Essex police, the force with responsibility for Stansted, said as dawn broke.</p>
<p>A forward door was opened on the plane, which was parked at a remote part of the airport two miles (three km) from the main terminal, and reporters on the scene could see figures moving in the doorway.</p>
<p>White said that most of the passengers were Sudanese but that there were also an unknown number of Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Syrians and Saudis.</p>
<p>Two buses stood by in the hope that the hijackers would make good on their promise, reported earlier by police in Cyprus, to release the passengers once they landed in London.</p>
<p>Police in Cyprus, where the plane took on fuel, said earlier that at least one of the hijackers was apparently armed with grenades and TNT and had threatened to blow the aircraft up unless it flew to Britain so they could claim political asylum.</p>
<p>&quot;They will surrender the passengers there and surrender themselves,&quot; police spokesman Glafcos Xenos told reporters at Larnaca airport.</p>
<p>Armed police kept watch on the plane, but White said there were no plans to call in the army or members of Britain's crack SAS special forces.</p>
<p>There was no immediate word on the motives or even the number of the hijackers. White said police only knew for sure of one hijacker, who was armed.</p>
<p>Sudan's Islamist military government, which the United States has accused of sponsoring &quot;state terrorism&quot;, has a broad array of political opponents and is waging a bitter war against separatist rebels in the mainly Christian and animist south.</p>
<p>Earlier, Cypriot authorities tried to negotiate through the pilot with one of the hijackers, asking him to release all women and children on board before refuelling.</p>
<p>But he refused and was quoted as saying: &quot;I will blow the plane up.&quot;</p>
<p>The hijackers had wanted to fly to Heathrow, London's main airport, but the British authorities directed the plane instead to Stansted, about 30 miles (50 km) northeast of the capital.</p>
<p>Stansted is the preferred option for handling hijackings in southern England because it is more remote than Heathrow and Gatwick, London's other main airport, and handles less traffic.</p>
<p>It was the second hijacking this year involving a Sudanese airliner.</p>
<p>On March 24, a Sudan Airways Airbus A320 plane carrying 40 passengers and crew on an internal flight was hijacked to Asmara, the Eritrean capital, where the two Sudanese hijackers surrendered and sought political asylum.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STANSTED, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
