<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17689" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: List of major and recent world hijacks.</title>
<headline>List of major and recent world hijacks.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a list of some of the world's most noteworthy and most recent hijackings:</p>
<p>February, 1931 -- The first recorded hijacking of an airliner took place in Peru.</p>
<p>July, 1948 -- First hijacking in Asia, when a Cathay Pacific Catalina plane from Macao to Hong Kong was boarded by four Chinese hijackers. The pilot and co-pilot were killed and the plane crashed into the sea killing 25 aboard.</p>
<p>April, 1958 -- Start of the &quot;Cuban shuttle&quot;. A Cubana airlines plane was flown to Mexico starting a two-way flow of hijacked planes between Cuba, the United States and Mexico.</p>
<p>August, 1960 -- First reported hijacking in the Soviet Union. Details were not released as Soviet data was secret.</p>
<p>July, 1968 - First Arab-Israeli incident and first in a series of political hijackings when three Arabs seized an El-Al Israeli plane in Rome and forced it to fly to Algiers.</p>
<p>September, 1970 - Palestinian guerrillas seized three Western airliners, forcing them to land in Jordan where the planes were blown up. All hostages were released in exchange for Palestinian prisoners.</p>
<p>September, 1974 - An Air Vietnam plane was hijacked leaving Danang by a lone man demanding to go to Hanoi. He detonated two hand grenades and all 70 aboard were killed in the crash.</p>
<p>July, 1976 - Two Palestinians and two Europeans hijacked an Air France Airbus with 244 passengers and 12 crew to Uganda. They released 153 non-Jewish passengers and Israeli commandos rescued the others in a long-range operation.</p>
<p>February, 1978 - Two Arab guerrillas seized an airliner at Larnaca, Cyprus. Egyptian commandos flew in uninvited to try to storm the plane during negotiations. Cyprus National Guardsmen resisted them and 15 Egyptians died in a 45-minute battle.</p>
<p>August, 1980 - A total of 168 hijackers seized a Braniff airliner in Peru demanding to fly to Miami. After they gave up the United States agreed to expedite their emigration papers.</p>
<p>June, 1985 - Two Lebanese Shi'ite gunmen hijacked a TWA flight out of Athens with 153 aboard. The hijack ended 16 days later at Beirut airport with one killed and 39 Americans freed.</p>
<p>November, 1985 - Palestinians hijacked an Egyptair plane to Malta. Egyptian commandos stormed the plane and 59 people died.</p>
<p>September 5, 1986 - Twenty-two people died when Pakistani security forces stormed a Pan Am Boeing 747 carrying 400 passengers and crew to end a 16-hour siege which began after four Palestinian hijackers slipped on board at Karachi.</p>
<p>March 8, 1988 - Two Siberians pulled shotguns from musical instrument cases and demanded to be flown to London. The Tupolev 154 landed instead at a military airfield near Leningrad where nine people died when security forces stormed it.</p>
<p>April 5, 1988 - Arab gunmen seized a Kuwait Airways Boeing 747 carrying 115 passengers and killed two Kuwaitis. The hijack was abandoned on April 20 in Algiers.</p>
<p>January 26, 1990 - Four gunmen tried to hijack an Iran Air Boeing 727 but were killed by security guards in a mid-air shootout over southern Iran.</p>
<p>August 20, 1990 - Eleven Soviet convicts surrendered to security forces after overpowering their guards and forcing an Aeroflot Tu-154 with 101 passengers and crew to fly to Karachi.</p>
<p>October 2, 1990 - Hijackers seized a Chinese Airways Boeing 737 aircraft with 94 passengers and 10 crew after it left Xiamen but it crashed as it tried to land in Canton, killing 128.</p>
<p>October 10, 1990 - Two Burmese youths surrendered at Calcutta airport after hijacking a Thai Airbus with 204 passengers and 17 crew to press demands for an end to military rule in their country.</p>
<p>March, 1991 - Four Pakistanis seized a Singaporean Airbus on a flight to Singapore to demand the release of Benazir Bhutto's husband. Singaporean commandos stormed the plane with 114 passengers and nine crew and shot dead all four hijackers.</p>
<p>March 18, 1993 - Security forces stormed a hijacked Ethiopian Airlines plane at Dire Dawa in eastern Ethiopia, killing two of four hijackers and a woman passenger.</p>
<p>October 25, 1993 - A Nigerian Airbus 310 was hijacked on an internal flight and forced to fly to Niamey, Niger, where 129 of the 149 passengers and crew were released. Niger security forces stormed the plane, freeing the passengers but killing a crewman.</p>
<p>October 25, 1994 - An armed men seized a Yak-40 with 27 passengers on a flight to Rostov. Thirteen passengers were freed after it landed in Dagestan and the remainder once Russian authorities had paid a ransom of $2.3 million. One hijacker blew himself up when police commandos stormed the plane.</p>
<p>November 13, 1994 - Three Algerians armed with hammers diverted an internal flight with 42 people on board to Majorca, where they asked for asylum.</p>
<p>November 24, 1994 - A 36-year-old man from Russia's far north took control of a Tu-134 on a flight from Syktyvkar to Minsk and diverted it to Estonia. He threatened to blow up the plane but released the 69 passengers and crew unharmed.</p>
<p>December 24, 1994 - A French Airbus A-300 was hijacked at Algiers airport by four men demanding the release of jailed opposition leaders. French elite police stormed it in Marseille, killing the hijackers. Three passengers also died.</p>
<p>September 19, 1995 - An airline steward used a gun and explosives to divert an Iranian internal flight to Israel, where he asked for asylum in the United States. All 176 passengers and crew were returned to Iran.</p>
<p>March 8, 1996 - A 20-year-old Turkish waiter diverted a plane on a northern Cyprus-Istanbul flight with 147 passengers and crew to Munich to gain sympathy for the cause of Chechen independence. He was armed with only a toy pistol.</p>
<p>March 24, 1996 - A Sudanese Airbus A320 carrying 40 passengers and crew was hijacked to Eritrea. The two Sudanese hijackers sought political asylum in Eritrea.</p>
<p>March 27, 1996 - Three Egyptians with Molotov cocktails forced an EgyptAir Airbus 320 leaving Luxor with 147 passengers and crew to fly to Libya, saying they had a divine message for world leaders. They surrendered five hours later in Libya.</p>
<p>July 26, 1996 - An Iberia DC-10 was hijacked en route from Madrid to Havana carrying 231 passengers and crew. It landed in Miami and a man was later accused of using a fake bomb and a makeshift knife to hijack it.</p>
<p>August 16, 1996 - Three Cubans used a knife to force the pilot of a small plane to fly to Florida, where the aircraft crashed into the Gulf of Mexico. All four Cubans were rescued.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
