<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27378" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Man arrested at Tampa with bags full of weapons.</title>
<headline>Man arrested at Tampa with bags full of weapons.</headline>
<dateline>TAMPA, Fla. 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>A seminary student was arrested at the Tampa International Airport after officials searched his duffel bag and knapsack and found a virtual arsenal inside, Tampa police said on Monday.</p>
<p>Roman Regman, a student at St. Tikhon's Seminary in northeastern Pennsylvania, tried to board a USAir flight on Saturday with two carry-on bags that were so full the airport X-ray machine could not detect their contents.</p>
<p>Airport officials searched the bags by hand and found a 9 mm pistol, two hand grenades, six military-style knives, 181 rounds of ammunition and a ski mask and homemade handcuffs, police said.</p>
<p>Tampa police charged Regman with 14 state weapons and explosives charges. Regman, who was being held at the Hillsborough County jail, also faces a federal investigation by the FBI, authorities said. An FBI spokesman could not be immediately reached for comment.</p>
<p>A third-year student at the Orthodox Church in America seminary, Regman studied the Bible but also subscribed to military magazines and dressed like a soldier, neighbours said. The Romanian native was studying to become a monk.</p>
<p>Police said Regman had bought a round-trip plane ticket to Pennsylvania and had a reservation for an immediate return to the Tampa area. Classes at the seminary were scheduled to resume on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A neighbour in the Tampa suburb of Hernando said she often saw Regman wearing shorts, a pressed shirt, a military-style hat and black leather gloves. &quot;I couldn't imagine why anyone would be wearing black leather gloves all the time. Especially in Florida,&quot; she told the Tampa Tribune.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Tampa airport police said they had no idea what Regman intended to do with the weapons inside his carry-on bags. He had no checked luggage.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAMPA, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
