<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33155" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>NORWAY: Palestinian hijacker was seeking peace in Norway.</title>
<headline>Palestinian hijacker was seeking peace in Norway.</headline>
<byline>Rolf Soderlind</byline>
<dateline>OSLO 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Palestinian who hijacked a Bulgarian charter plane to Oslo to seek political asylum has told his lawyer he wants to live in Norway because it is so peaceful compared to the Middle East.</p>
<p>Norwegian officials doubted, however, that he would get his wish given Norway's strict policy on air pirates. The hijacker was expected to be remanded in custody at a court hearing later on Wednesday (1100 GMT).</p>
<p>Tuesday's hijacking was the third to end in Norway since the Scandinavian state helped to broker the landmark 1993 Israel-PLO peace pact, leading some experts to suggest Oslo's profile as a peacemaker had made it an attractive destination for hijackers.</p>
<p>The 23-year-old Palestinian commandeered the Tupolev TU-154 on a flight from Beirut to Varna airport near Bulgaria's Black Sea coast. He released all 150 passengers before ordering the crew of eight to take off on the three-hour flight to Oslo.</p>
<p>About 45 minutes after the plane landed at Oslo's Gardermoen airport, the man gave himself up. No one was hurt and a bomb with which he had threatened the crew turned out to be a fake, police said.</p>
<p>Police have refused to identify the hijacker, in keeping with Norwegian legal practice.</p>
<p>Bulgarian officials had earlier named him as Nadir Abdulah, but he introduced himself to Norwegian police as Nazem Abdulah, according to a transcript of the radio conversation during the brief standoff published by daily VG.</p>
<p>&quot;He has declared he wants to live in peace in Norway and not at war in his own country,&quot; lawyer Jan Schjatvedt told reporters. &quot;He wants to gain political asylum in Norway because he regards Norway as a peaceful country.&quot;</p>
<p>Norway's secret mediation between Israel and the Palestine Liberation Organisation -- the so-called Oslo channel -- put Oslo at the centre stage of international diplomacy.</p>
<p>&quot;The Oslo channel made people aware of what Norway stands for,&quot; said Kari Karame, a researcher at the Norwegian Institute for International Affairs (NUPI).</p>
<p>&quot;Maybe hijackers feel that Norway is a country that should do something for them because it advocates human rights so much,&quot; she told Reuters. &quot;They know they get good treatment while they are here.&quot;</p>
<p>Three Iranians commandeered a Russian Aeroflot airliner on a domestic flight to Oslo in September 1993 -- after Norway's role in the Middle East peace process became known -- to protest against human rights abuses in Iran. They were sent back to Russia 16 months later.</p>
<p>A Bosnian Moslem hijacked a domestic Norwegian flight in November 1994 to Oslo in a bid to seek more international aid for his war-ravaged country. He was later sentenced to four years in prison by an Oslo court.</p>
<p>The only previous hijacking involving the normally quiet Scandinavian state was in 1985 when a drunken Norwegian brandishing an air pistol hijacked a domestic flight only to give himself up in return for a six-pack of cold beer. He was later jailed for three years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OSLO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NORWAY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
