<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33759" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. District judge approves airline settlement.</title>
<headline>U.S. District judge approves airline settlement.</headline>
<dateline>MINNEAPOLIS 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>A federal judge granted preliminary approval Thursday to a settlement in which the nation's five largest airlines will pay $81.8 million to an estimated 33,000 travel agents.</p>
<p>The settlement agreement, approved by U.S. District Judge James Rosenbaum, is one of three reached between lawyers representing travel agents and seven airlines they sued in February 1995.</p>
<p>Their suit claimed the airlines conspired to unfairly cap travel agent commissions at $25 for one-way plane tickets and $50 for round-trip.</p>
<p>The airlines and the amounts they agreed to pay in Thursday's settlement are: American Airlines, $21.3 million; Delta Air Lines Inc., $20.3 million; Northwest Airlines, $10.9 million; United Airlines, $19.5 million; and USAir, $9.8 million.</p>
<p>USAir had previously reached a settlement with the travel agents, and that agreement was merged into the one before Judge Rosenbaum at Thursday's hearing.</p>
<p>Also named in the suit were Continental Airlines Inc. and Trans World Airlines Inc.</p>
<p>Continental said earlier this week it had reached a separate settlement agreement in which it would pay $5 million. TWA settled with the travel agents in May 1995.</p>
<p>None of the airlines admitted wrongdoing, and only TWA has dropped the commission-capping policy.</p>
<p>A final hearing is scheduled for Nov. 15.</p>
<p>The settlement involving American, Delta, Northwest, United and USAir does not prohibit the carriers from using the current travel agent commission structures. Continental said earlier it planned to continue using the cap.</p>
<p>Lawyers representing the airlines said earlier that all the settlements combined would award the plaintiffs $86 million.</p>
<p>With filings made during Thursday's hearing, all but TWA's dollar amount have been made public. Some $4.2 million remains to be paid, but attorneys for TWA said the carrier has yet to determine how much it will pay.</p>
<p>The airlines that agreed to make payments have 10 days to do so.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINNEAPOLIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
