<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36575" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria fires striking air traffic controllers.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria fires striking air traffic controllers.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria's air traffic service fired 40 air traffic controllers on the grounds that they refused to do their job after a local court ruled that their strike planned for this week was illegal.</p>
<p>The director general of the air traffic service Valentin Valkov told a news conference on Friday that he had fired 40 air traffic controllers &quot;for violating work discipline&quot;.</p>
<p>Bulgaria's association of air traffic controllers (Bulatka) announced one-hour warning strikes on Tuesday but cancelled it after a Bulgarian charter plane on a flight from Beirut was hijacked on the same day 15 minutes before landing at Varna airport to refuel and continue for Oslo.</p>
<p>Valkov said that since then traffic controllers at airports in Sofia, Varna and Bourgas did not show up at work regularly simulating sickness. They were replaced by their chiefs and air traffic control instructors.</p>
<p>&quot;Flights in Bulgaria are not endangered,&quot; said Valkov.</p>
<p>The controllers demanded the monthly wage be increased from some $230 to some $1,000 per month, as well as the resignation of the air traffic service's management.</p>
<p>They also demanded the financial separation of the 350 air controllers from the technical staff.</p>
<p>Valkov said their claims were immoral.</p>
<p>Bulatka's chief Stefan Raichev said that they were prepared to resume negotiations with their employers. But Bulatka had not yet decided whether they would drop their demands, he added.</p>
<p>More than 1,500 planes per 24 hours fly over Bulgaria.</p>
<p>-- Sofia Newsroom, 359-2-84561</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
