<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41461" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. airlines raise most domestic fares by 2.5 pct.</title>
<headline>U.S. airlines raise most domestic fares by 2.5 pct.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Major airlines except Southwest Airlines Co said Monday they raised their fares by 2.5 percent because of strong passenger demand for seating.</p>
<p>The airlines said the fare increase applied to domestic flights in most routes which do not compete with Southwest and matched a 2.5 percent increase initiated by Continental Airlines Inc.</p>
<p>The fare hikes come on top of the 10 percent federal passenger excise tax reinstated in August, which had prompted some airlines to increase their fares 10 percent.  </p>
<p>Airlines that said they raised their fares include Trans World Airlines Inc, UAL Corp, parent of United Airlines, Northwest Airlines Corp and Delta Air Lines Inc and USAir Group Inc.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen a tremendous demand this summer and our advanced bookings for the fall are looking strong,&quot; said Jackie Pate, a Delta spokesperson specializing in pricing.</p>
<p>Pate said Delta's load factor for the calendar year through July was 70.14 percent, compared with 65.13 percent over the same period last year.  </p>
<p>&quot;Traditionally after Labor Day travel tends to slacken. That is occuring, but we are still seeing strong demand,&quot; said American Airlines spokesman John Hotard.  American Air is an AMR Corp subsidiary.  Hotard said this year's bookings are up &quot;a couple of percentage points&quot; compared with last year's.</p>
<p>The airlines gave other reasons for the fare increases, including rising fuel costs and the cost of greater security measures.</p>
<p>In August some airlines raised their fares by 10 percent to cover the excise tax, but the fare hike did not stick because it wasn't uniformly matched by all carriers.</p>
<p>Southwest said it absorbed the cost of the tax on most of its routes, except for longer flights, and has so far chosen not to make additional fare increases.</p>
<p>&quot;It was just a business decision.  We are the low-fare airline,&quot; said Southwest spokesperson Linda Rutherford, adding &quot;We know that the resumption of the (excise) tax will definitely impact profits, but we don't know by how much yet.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
