<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54291" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Northwest official sees problems for Asia airlines.</title>
<headline>Northwest official sees problems for Asia airlines.</headline>
<byline>Ajoy Sen</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asia's healthy airline industry could face problems in filling passenger seats and cargo space in the longer term, Northwest Airlines regional managing director James Reinnoldt said on Sunday.</p>
<p>Demand for passenger seats and cargo space was growing at eight percent a year, while airlines were increasing their fleets by 10 percent a year, he told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The capacity now is a little ahead of the demand,&quot; he said, adding that Asian airlines had placed large orders with Boeing Co and Airbus Industrie for new planes in 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;With these new orders for planes maturing, the supply could exceed demand for cargo and passenger seats. It's a longer-term growing concern,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Yields will be increasingly under pressure if capacity outstrips demand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Reinnoldt could not give any figure for new planes ordered by Asian airlines.</p>
<p>But just one airline, Singapore Airlines (SIA), announced a huge order for 77 new Boeing 777-200 medium-range planes in November last year. The planes are to be delivered between 1997 and 2004.</p>
<p>Some regional carriers are expanding fleets through the cheaper option of buying used aircraft.</p>
<p>Air Philippines, for example, said on Sunday it had agreed to buy 15 Boeing 737 airplanes from United Airlines over the next two years for US$90 million as part of a massive expansion plan.</p>
<p>Higher operating costs were another area of concern, Reinnoldt said. Growing fuel prices, accounting for almost 15 percent of an airline's operating costs, were not controllable.</p>
<p>There is also pressure on wages, accounting for about 20 percent of costs, as the regional economy expands and parts of Asia suffer from labour shortages, Reinnoldt said.</p>
<p>Analysts say wage inflation is running at more than 10 percent annually in Hong Kong and Singapore.</p>
<p>Reinnoldt said distribution costs, accounting for 20 percent of an airline's operating expenditure, also weighed on the Asian airline industry. Such costs include facilities for reservations, tickets, commission for travel agents and computer reservation systems.</p>
<p>Distribution costs could be controlled through measures adopted by Northwest and other North American airlines, he said. These include booking through the Internet, ticketless travel or electronic ticketing and encouraging customers to buy directly from the airline instead of through a travel agent.</p>
<p>The measures, some involving high technology, had helped some U.S. airlines reduce operating costs sharply. They could be introduced in Asia too, he said.</p>
<p>The U.S. airlines had some of the lowest unit costs in the industry, he said. &quot;We are trying to extend electronic ticketing to Asia. Singapore provides one of the potential markets to electronic ticketing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Electronic ticketing allows a customer to phone an airline and be given a number to hand over at the check-in counter. By doing away with a ticket, the airline saves about US$6 per passenger journey, he said.</p>
<p>Reinnoldt said last month 71 airlines in the United States offered electronic or paperless ticketing. Most major U.S. airlines had also imposed a cap on commissions by encouraging passengers to book directly with the airline.</p>
<p>&quot;If customers buy directly from the airline office, the airline can save on the nine percent commission paid to a travel agent,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
