<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68048" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: From the Flightdeck - The Air Cargo Week in Review.</title>
<headline>From the Flightdeck - The Air Cargo Week in Review.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON, O 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>This is Reuters' look back at the major developments in the global air cargo industry in the week September 16 - September 2O.</p>
<p>**SEPTEMBER 16**</p>
<p>CANBERRA - Department of transportation figures show Qantas maintained its market lead in the country's domestic aviation market in the year to June 30, 1996.</p>
<p>LONDON - BA company spokesman says it intends to make a progress report to staff on progress for its ambitious &quot;step change&quot; efficiency drive aimed at cutting a billion stg from its annual cost base before the year 2000.</p>
<p>LONDON - Singapore Airlines UK cargo manager, Barry Gibson says it is launching a weekly Boeing 747-400 freighter service to Dublin.</p>
<p>PARIS - Air France says its global cargo traffic, last month, was up 8.4 percent on August 1995 at 382.2 million FTK.</p>
<p>VIENNA - Austrian Airlines supervisory board chief Rudolf Streicher says it was likely to report a pre-tax profit for the full year despite having suffered a heavy loss in the first half.</p>
<p>OSLO - Industry sources says cargo insurance rates are under downward pressure because of increased competition and an abundance of reinsurance capacity.</p>
<p>MACAU - A travel official says North Korea will open its skies to overflights by world airlines in October, two months earlier than previously expected.</p>
<p>HONG KONG - Hong Kong Air Terminals Ltd says it has ruled out increases in its air cargo fees for next year despite a 50 percent hike in the Consumer Price Index over the past five years.</p>
<p>STOCKHOLM - Sweden's civil aviation administration t says Swedish airports handled 25 percent more cargo in August 1996 compared to August 1995.</p>
<p>PARIS - Turkish Airlines says its current Boeing 727-200F service between Maastricht and Istanbul will be unaffected by its new Istanbul-Paris 727F feeder service to be launched later this week in partnership with Air France.</p>
<p>ISLAMABAD - A government statement says the Pakistani cabinet decided to allow 50 percent rebate in aeronautical charges for one year to attract new airlines to use Pakistan's airports.</p>
<p>SOFIA - A transport ministry spokewoman says British consultancy firm KPMG will help Bulgaria's troubled national carrier Balkan Airline to work out a programme aimed at stabilising its finances.</p>
<p>KIEV - A top company official was quoted as saying Ukraine's Antonov airline designer and manufacturer is to complete work on models of its latest AN-70 and AN-140 transport aircraft by the year-end.</p>
<p>PARIS - Air France Cargo says it planned to increase weekly frequencies Boeing 747-200F freighter on its Paris-Singapore service from three to four due to strong demand.</p>
<p>* Air France says its Boeing 747-200 freighter fleet will be flying to Madras three times weekly from the end of October compared to twice-weekly currently.</p>
<p>BRUSSELS - Sabena says it had reached initial agreement with trade unions on a range of measures aimed at bringing the company back into profit from 1998.</p>
<p>PALMA DE MALLORCA - Airport figures show cargo traffic at Palma de Mallorca airport slipped to 1,960 tonnes in August from 2,032 in July.</p>
<p>RIO DE JANEIRO - Brazilian airport administrator Infraero says construction work on a new airport in Rio Branco in Brazil's Northwest state of Acre will speed up and conclude in 1997.</p>
<p>FOSTER CITY, California - InVision Technologies, a maker of airport bomb detection systems says the British Airport Authority has purchase three InVision CTX5000 units for London's Heathrow airport.</p>
<p>MEMPHIS - FedEx says that it will acquire 36 used DC-10-10 aircraft from UAL Corp's United Airlines in exchange for 59 727-200 heavyweight engine hushkits.</p>
<p>MONTREAL - Air Canada says it flew 10.2 percent more revenue passenger miles in August 1996 than in the same month of 1995.</p>
<p>MEMPHIS - FedEx says that lower international airfreight yields and higher fuel prices hurt it earnings for the first quarter of the fiscal year.</p>
<p>* FedEx chief financial officer says a weak international non-express airfreight market that helped dampen fiscal first-quarter earnings will likely continue for the rest of the fiscal year.</p>
<p>NEW YORK - The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey says it plans to tighten security by using everything from more bomb-sniffing dogs to high-tech computer operated machines.</p>
<p>LONDON - The Guardian newspaper says American airlines chairman Robert Crandall has threatened to pull out of a proposed alliance with BA if Anglo-American talks on an &quot;open skies&quot; agreement dragged on much longer.</p>
<p>**SEPTEMBER 17**</p>
<p>ANCHORAGE, Alaska - Airport officials says a new federal policy will allow foreign airlines the authority to sort, store and redirect cargo in Alaska, promising a possible cargo boom at the Anchorage and Fairbanks international airports.</p>
<p>TOKYO - Japan Airlines says it and Myanmar Airlines International are planning to jointly operate non-stop flights between Japan and Rangoon in the future.</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - The Washington Post say USAir Group chairman Stephen Wolf said there was no room for USAir in the proposed international marketing agreement between American Airlines and BA.</p>
<p>CALGARY - Canadian Air Cargo says it will introduce a new international, flight-specific express product with a money-back guarantee on October 1.</p>
<p>DUBAI - Sharjah airport says cargo volumes rose year-on-year 14.5 percent in August to almost 28,398 tonnes from 24,810 tonnes in August 1995.</p>
<p>MADRID - Airlines and freight forwarders says air cargo rates ex-Madrid are steady -- the downward pressure on North Atlantic prices appears to have abated and tariffs could actually rise on some routes in the coming peak months.</p>
<p>HANOI - Official media reports says the airport at Vietnam's northern port city of Haiphong has reopened after more than a year of repairs and upgrading.</p>
<p>DUBAI - Dubai cargo village figures show Dubai airport cargo volumes rose five percent in August to 27,843 tonnes from 26,482 tonnes in the same month last year.</p>
<p>MOSCOW - Private Russian carrier Transaero says that it had launched thrice-weekly non-stop flights between Moscow and Krasnoyarsk, in Eastern Siberia.</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Industry sources says Asian Airlines are unfazed by the 18 percent rise in benchmark Singapore jet fuel prices so far this year.</p>
<p>GENEVA - Airport authority figures show Geneva's Cointrin airport handled 5,253 tonnes of air cargo traffic in July, a decrease of 5.6 percent on the same month in 1995.</p>
<p>OSLO - A marine insurance industry report says thefts of computer parts and memory chips have soared, leaving insurers around the world stuck for a solution to rising claims -- substantial increases in thefts and non-delivery of shipments, mostly from air and overland routes, have been reported by cargo insurance associations around the world.</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - Airline spokesman Udo Buys says Martinair is to increase the number of freighter flights between Schiphol and Nairobi to four weekly from the previous single flight.</p>
<p>BARCELONA - Airport authority figures show cargo traffic at Barcelona airport was 12.3 percent higher in August at 5,184 tonnes against 4,617 tonnes in August 1995.</p>
<p>MOSCOW -  Russian private cargo airline Volga-Dnepr says it will buy an Antonov-124-100 heavy freighter before the end of this year, increasing its fleet of such planes to seven aircraft.</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Singapore Airlines says it plans to expand cargo co-operation with Lufthansa Cargo AG by increasing the frequency of their joint freighter service between Frankfurt and Singapore.</p>
<p>MOSCOW - Russian's private Transaero company spokesman says airlines passenger traffic and cargo increased sharply in the first eight months on year-ago levels.</p>
<p>ROME - Italian carrier Air One it was launching two new routes - Turin-Rome and Naples-Milan - as part of its expansion strategy.</p>
<p>LISBON - A government minister says loss-making Portuguese state airline TAP-Air Portugal must conclude its restructuring plan before forming any strategic alliance with foreign airlines.</p>
<p>CALGARY - WestJet Airlines says all of its flights were grounded after a maintenance dispute with Transport Canada.</p>
<p>AMSTERDAM - A spokesman for Martinair says its planned twice-weekly service to Guangzhou in southern China, planned for October 1, is being delayed due to &quot;administration problems&quot;.</p>
<p>GATWICK - Orient Airlines Association commercial director Carlos Chua says the phenomenal growth of air transport experienced by Asia-Pacific airlines is increasingly driven by an upsurge in intra-regional trade.</p>
<p>BASLE - Airport authority figures show global cargo traffic handled at Basle-Mulhouse-Freigburg airport, in the first eight months of 1996, totalled 58,019 tonnes, an increase of 15 percent on the same period last year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON, O"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
