<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86381" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: ValuJet set to return to U.S. skies Monday.</title>
<headline>ValuJet set to return to U.S. skies Monday.</headline>
<byline>David Morgan</byline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>ValuJet Inc., the discount carrier that was once a darling on Wall Street but the bane of other airlines, was scheduled to return to the skies Monday for the first time since its grounding three months ago.</p>
<p>With an aggressive weekend marketing campaign, the airline sought to lure passengers back to its no-frills service by offering one-way fares of just $19 for flights between Atlanta and four other U.S. cities, including Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>The authorities grounded the fledgling airline in mid-June -- just over a month after Flight 592 crashed into the Florida Evergrades, killing all 110 passengers and crew on board.</p>
<p>The last time ValuJet planes flew from their Atlanta hub, the carrier had grown in just 2-1/2 years from a tiny startup airline to a regional operation with 320 daily flights to 31 cities and had a payroll of about 4,000 employees.</p>
<p>ValuJet was being relaunched with a fleet of only five DC-9s and staff of 400. After 15-weeks spent in one of the intensive overhauls in U.S. airline history, ValuJet executives have shown nothing but fiery enthusiasm.</p>
<p>&quot;We've done our homework. We have prepared for Game Day. Game Day is here. We're ready for the whistle to blow and we'll be out there doing a great job,&quot; ValuJet President Lewis Jordan told reporters after announcing the carrier's return.</p>
<p>The maiden voyage was set to get under way with a departure gate party featuring a jazz band and a news conference with top management that was sure to provide plenty of colourful quotes for the local press.</p>
<p>&quot;We're going to have a nice party out there,&quot; said ValuJet spokesman Gregg Kenyon.</p>
<p>At 12:30 p.m. EDT  (1630 GMT), a fully booked DC-9 with 113 passengers on board was scheduled to take off for Washington's Dulles airport, carrying a group of VIPs including a U.S. senator and Congressman from Georgia as well as Jordan and ValuJet Chairman Robert Priddy.</p>
<p>The return of ValuJet promised far more fanfare than its birth in October 1993, which transpired without notice.</p>
<p>Rival airlines braced for the onset of ultra-low fares. On Friday, Atlanta-based Delta Air Lines Inc. said it would match the $19 introductory ValuJet fares, which run through Thursday. Kiwi International Air Lines said it also would adopt a similar strategy.</p>
<p>ValuJet came under intense scrutiny from the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) after the May 11 crash. A cause has not yet been determined, but investigators think oxygen generators that were improperly stored in the plane's cargo hold by a subcontractor may have ignited, causing a fire that led to the crash.</p>
<p>After the disaster, FAA inspectors also found widespread maintenance problems at ValuJet, and in mid-June forced the airline to ground its fleet of 51 planes. An intensive 15-week project to overhaul the airline's operations ensued.</p>
<p>The U.S. Department of Transportation (DOT) finally declared ValuJet fit to fly again last Thursday. By midday on Friday, the airline had rung up about 7,000 bookings.</p>
<p>Initially, the carrier also will fly to Orlando, Tampa and Fort Lauderdale, Florida. Plans call for the addition of another 12 destinations by Oct. 24, by which time its one-way fares will have risen to $49.</p>
<p>A union for airline flight attendants was still trying to halt ValuJet's rebirth in federal court.</p>
<p>On Friday, the Association of Flight Attendants asked the U.S. Court of Appeals in Washington to block the airline's return pending a union appeal to have Jordan and Priddy ousted from management.</p>
<p>The union, which accuses the two men of putting profits ahead of safety during the months preceding the Everglades crash, has launched an appeal of the DOT's approval.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
