<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="23408" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Child sex campaigner asks travel industry to help.</title>
<headline>Child sex campaigner asks travel industry to help.</headline>
<byline>Trevor Datson</byline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1996-08-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of a global anti-sex- tourism pressure group on Wednesday demanded that the travel industry play a part in combating the sexual exploitation of children.</p>
<p>A conference in Stockholm has heard the child sex trade is worth billions of dollars a year and that at least a million new children every year are forced into child prostitution, sold for sexual purposes or used in pornography, according to estimates by the U.N. children's agency UNICEF.</p>
<p>Officials say that sex tourism is an important source of sexual abuse of children in Asian countries.</p>
<p>Amihan Abueva, executive secretary of End Child Prostitution in Asian Tourism (ECPAT), targeted the travel and tourism industry in an interview with Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It's irresponsible for people who are indirectly earning millions of dollars from the child sex trade to say they have no responsibility in this area,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the type of industry where self-regulation is absolutely essential. But if we recognise that legal systems are lagging behind, then it's time to try and find ways of catching up,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Such action must not be limited to governments and bodies such as ECPAT, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;I do feel that the private sector is one of the most important groups to reach. The tourism industry, and airlines should all be held more responsible, and if they bring their resources to bear then we can tackle the problem.&quot;</p>
<p>Key customer groups for child prostitutes such as seamen and business travellers can also be prevented by employers from supporting the child sex trade, she said.</p>
<p>ECPAT was one of a handful of groups that took the initiative for the Stockholm congress that opened on Tuesday with over 1,000 delegates from 130 countries discussing ways of tackling the growing problem of the child sex trade.</p>
<p>The conference has been given added impetus by the revelations in Belgium's ongoing child sex scandal, in which the bodies of two children, abducted by a paedophile ring, have been found and two more children are missing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
