<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25590" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: FEATURE - Asians increasingly prefer to holiday close to home.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Asians increasingly prefer to holiday close to home.</headline>
<byline>Jim Della-Giacoma</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Affluent Asian consumers are more and more looking to vacation spots in their own backyard when they venture abroad for rest and recreation, tourism authorities say.</p>
<p>The lure of Europe and the United States, while still strong for some countries, is fading.</p>
<p>Increasingly, Asians are holidaying in the Orient, or mixing business and pleasure as they travel in neighbouring countries.</p>
<p>Whether it's trekking in Nepal, diving in the Indonesian archipelago or seeking unique health therapies in Indonchina, the lure of the East is proving stronger.</p>
<p>&quot;People in this region are wealthier now and they prefer to travel without wasting too much time,&quot; Indonesia's director-general of tourism, Andi Mappissammeng, told Reuters in a recent interview.</p>
<p>&quot;If you travel to Europe from Singapore it will take you more than 10 hours, but it's only 1-1/2 hours to Bali,&quot; Mappissamneng said.</p>
<p>&quot;In the last 10 years there has been an evolutionary switching of the source of our tourists from Europe to the Asia-Pacific region, with the biggest market being the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) countries,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Last year, Indonesia received 4.3 million international visitors, with around 62 percent from seven Asian countries. Neighbouring Singapore, with a population of about three million, accounted for just over one million of these visits.</p>
<p>Around 30 percent of all visitors are businesspeople taking advantage of their visit to add a few days' holiday onto a working trip or conference.</p>
<p>In Singapore, about 70 percent of its 7.14 million visitors in 1995 were from other countries in Asia.</p>
<p>The pattern is repeated in Thailand, where its seven million foreign visitors in 1995 have made tourism the country's top revenue earner.</p>
<p>&quot;The largest number of tourists visiting Thailand are from East Asia comprising ASEAN members, China, Hong Kong, Japan, South Korea and Taiwan,&quot; said Charun Chuennaitham, chief of the state-run Tourism Authority of Thailand's statistic section.</p>
<p>Tourist numbers from North America and Europe are still substantial, particularly where there are former colonial ties.</p>
<p>While 43 percent of tourists visiting the Philippines are from East Asia, the largest single group is from the United States, which accounts for 19 percent of all visitors. In India, British tourists are the largest single group, accounting for 15 percent of holidaymakers.</p>
<p>But not everybody prefers to holiday close to home.</p>
<p>With a strong yen, Japanese have increasingly travelled abroad in recent years, and figures from the Japan National Tourist Organisation show a majority of the 15.3 million Japanese who travelled overseas in 1995 preferred to go to the United States.</p>
<p>Korea, Hong Kong, China, Taiwan, Australia, Singapore and Thailand, in that order, are the next most popular destinations.</p>
<p>However, data from Visa International shows the top four destinations for Japanese credit card use are the U.S., Hong Kong, Italy and France.</p>
<p>While shopping is the priority of tourists in Singapore and Hong Kong, other countries are trying to develop different approaches to lengthen average stays and daily expenditure.</p>
<p>Malaysia is developing itself as an eco-tourist destination. The World Wide Fund (WWF) for Nature office there says these types of destinations are proving more popular with tourists, particularly specialist visitors like birdwatchers, from the U.S. and Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;They are willing to pay to come and see these things which are of special interest to them,&quot; WWF conservation director in Malaysia, Geoffery Davidson, said.</p>
<p>Indonesia, promoting itself as a centre for marine-orientated tourism, has increased the number of international gateways from just the capital Jakarta and the holiday isle of Bali 10 years ago to 21 international airports.</p>
<p>In addition, Indonesias has sought an edge on its neighbours by unilaterally granting visa-free access to 46 countries as it aims to boost tourist numbers to more than 11 million by 2005.</p>
<p>Japanese travel agencies say they have to now come up with more unique tours to lure well-travelled customers.</p>
<p>The Japan Travel Bureau, one of the country's largest travel agencies, now organises tours of Asian countries offering rare health therapies such as special massages and herbal medicines.</p>
<p>Kinki Nippon Tourist, a rival agency, has its eye on countries off the beaten track such as Burma, Cambodia and Laos.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
