<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="25645" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Palestinians to protest at Jerusalem shrine.</title>
<headline>Palestinians to protest at Jerusalem shrine.</headline>
<byline>Danny Gur-arieh</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of Palestinians are expected to pray at a Jerusalem mosque on Friday in a protest against Israel's policy on the city which both Jews and Arabs call their capital.</p>
<p>Police ordered reinforcements into Jerusalem, a city holy to Jews, Moslems and Christians, after Palestinian President Yasser Arafat called on his people to converge on the  city for prayers at noon (0900 GMT) on Friday.</p>
<p>Restrictions Israel maintains over the West Bank and Gaza Strip will prevent most Palestinians from reaching the al-Aqsa Mosque, Islam's third holiest shrine perched on the ancient Jewish Temple Mount, but Palestinians in East Jerusalem are expected to flock to the site.</p>
<p>&quot;We intend to prevent any inflammatory elements from reaching the Temple Mount....If we have to use force, we will,&quot; said Internal Security Ministry official Avigdor Kahalani on Thursday.</p>
<p>Palestinian legislator Hanan Ashrawi said Arabs would hold massive prayer meetings at Israeli roadblocks if soldiers prevented them from reaching Jerusalem.</p>
<p>&quot;People are going to go to the checkposts and they have the right to go through and to reach the mosque. Should Israel prevent them, I am sure that there will be public prayers at the checkposts,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The protest was triggered by Israeli announcements this week on the expansion of Jewish West Bank settlements surrounding Jerusalem and the demolition of an Arab community centre in East Jerusalem which city officials said was being erected illegally.</p>
<p>Arafat said the moves by Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's government were tantamount to war.</p>
<p>&quot;What happened concerning continuous violations and crimes from this new Israeli leadership means they are declaring a state of war against the Palestinian people,&quot; he told legislators this week.</p>
<p>Palestinians observed a four-hour general strike in the West Bank and Gaza Strip on Thursday and then had their busiest day of contacts with Israel since Netanyahu, who opposed Israel-PLO peace deals, swept to power in May elections.</p>
<p>Leaders of an Israeli-Palestinian steering committee charged with monitoring implementation of Israel-PLO agreements met for the first time since Palestinian suicide bombings rocked Israel in February and March.</p>
<p>But after the meeting the two men had different views of peace prospects.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe after this meeting that we have the ability to advance all the issues that today are found at different levels of implementation,&quot; said Israeli negotiator Dan Shomron.</p>
<p>His Palestinian counterpart, Saeb Erekat said: &quot;It is not a secret that the status of peace is slipping like sand outside our fingers.&quot;</p>
<p>Later on Thursday, Netantyahu aide Dore Gold met senior PLO negotiator Mahmoud Abbas, better known as Abu Mazen. Palestinian officials said the U.S. ambassador to Israel, Martin Indyk, was mediating between the two sides and had met with Arafat.</p>
<p>Palestinians complain that settlement expansion in the West Bank and Gaza and Israel's policy on Jerusalem help tighten the Jewish state's grip over areas where Arafat hopes to create an independent Palestinian state.</p>
<p>Netanyahu rules out Palestinian statehood.</p>
<p>Israel captured East Jerusalem in the 1967 Middle East war and quickly annexed it. Israeli governments since then have all vowed to keep Jerusalem united as the Jewish state's eternal capital. Palestinians want East Jerusalem for the capital of their future state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
