<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="32982" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Rocky road led to Netanyahu-Arafat summit.</title>
<headline>Rocky road led to Netanyahu-Arafat summit.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Palestinian President Yasser Arafat held their first summit on Wednesday, a meeting which could jumpstart stalled Israel-PLO peace talks.</p>
<p>Following is a chronology of Israel-PLO contacts since Netanyahu took office:</p>
<p>June 18 - Netanyahu takes office promising to promote peace with Israel's Arab neighbours.</p>
<p>June 26 - Netanyahu aide Dore Gold holds secret meetings with senior PLO negotiator Mahmoud Abbas, better known as Abu Mazen.</p>
<p>June 28 - Gold and Netanyahu representative Yitzhak Molho meet Arafat in what senior PLO offical calls &quot;first official contact&quot; with the new Israeli government.</p>
<p>July 16 - PLO officials say Arafat, upset Netanyahu refuses to meet him, rejects Dore Gold request for meeting.</p>
<p>July 23 - Arafat meets Israeli Foreign Minister David Levy in Gaza in first open high-level meeting since Netanyahu took office.</p>
<p>Aug 2 - Netanyahu infuriates Palestinians by lifting a four-year freeze on West Bank Jewish settlement expansion imposed by the previous government.</p>
<p>Aug 9 - Israel says no progress on peace moves until Palestinian Authority (PA) shuts offices in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Aug 11 - Arafat threatens Israel with international arbitration if his peace goals are frustrated.</p>
<p>Aug 14 - Israeli-PLO talks on civilian affairs resume.</p>
<p>Aug 22 - Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak says he will cancel a Mideast economic conference if Israel stalls on peace; former Israeli Prime Minister Shimon Peres meets Arafat in Gaza, highlighting Netanyahu's continued refusal to meet the PLO leader.</p>
<p>Aug 25 - Israeli President Ezer Weizman says he will meet Arafat if Netanyahu will not; Palestinian Authority, bowing to Israeli demands, shuts two East Jerusalem offices.</p>
<p>Aug 27 - Israel hoists bulldozer over Jerusalem's Old City wall to demolish a Palestinian community centre it said was built without a permit; Palestinian Trade Minister Maher al-Masri meets Israeli Finance Minister Dan Meridor.</p>
<p>Aug 28 - Arafat says Israel declared war on Palestinians with settlement expansion.</p>
<p>Aug 29 - Palestinians hold first general strike in West Bank and Gaza in two years to protest against Israeli policy; Heads of Israeli-PLO steering committee on implemention of interim peace deals holds first meeting since Netanyahu took office.</p>
<p>Aug 30 - Dore Gold and Abu Mazen hold five hour talks to resolve crisis.</p>
<p>Sept 1 - Israeli and PLO negotiators launch marathon talks with Norwegian mediation aimed at Netanyahu-Arafat meeting.</p>
<p>Sept 4 - Netanyahu and Arafat hold their first summit, at Erez crossing between Israel and Gaza.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
