<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="38920" id="root" date="1996-09-06" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Britain loses credibility - Egyptian press.</title>
<headline>Britain loses credibility - Egyptian press.</headline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1996-09-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Egypt's main government newspaper said on Friday the British government had lost much of its crebibility because of its failure to prevent a &quot;Rally for Revival&quot; which Islamists are organising in London on Sunday.</p>
<p>Egypt has been campaigning to stop the conference on the grounds that many of the participants finance, organise or support acts of political violence in the Middle East.</p>
<p>The British embassy in Cairo, responding to a barrage of criticism in the Egyptian government press, has told newspaper editors that the British government has no legal grounds for banning the rally but police will watch it carefully.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody much believes any longer what British officials say, specifically on combating terrorism,&quot; the newspaper al-Ahram said in a front-page editorial by editor Ibrahim Nafie.</p>
<p>&quot;It is also difficult for anyone to be confident that the assurances they give on this subject are a solution,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>&quot;Britain is tending to become the first international base for supporting and sheltering the terrorist groups which are working against various parties in the Middle East and the rest of the world,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Nafie said the attitude of the British authorities towards the rally on Sunday was obviously incompatible with Britain's tough line on &quot;terrorism&quot; in international forums.</p>
<p>&quot;The British government is dealing with the issue (the rally) as though it were a law and order issue, as though they were dealing with a group of rowdy football fans,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But these meetings usually produce waves of extremist or terrorist activity here and there... Most waves of terrorism have been preceded by such meetings,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Egypt has suffered for several years from violence spawned by Islamic militants. About 1,000 people, mainly militants and policemen, have been killed in political violence in the country since 1992.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-06"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-06"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
