<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="41791" id="root" date="1996-09-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Jordan, Israel to boost tourism cooperation.</title>
<headline>Jordan, Israel to boost tourism cooperation.</headline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1996-09-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan and Israel agreed on Monday to market jointly their tourist attractions to tour operators in the United States, Europe and Japan to lure more travellers.</p>
<p>Israel's Tourism Minister Moshe Katsav and his Jordanian counterpart Saleh Irsheidat told a news conference they also looked into setting up a joint tourism park on the shores of the Dead Sea, the lowest point in the world.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe the 'Lowest Park on Earth' is a very attractive project for international tourists and we have serious intentions to develop it,&quot; Katsav said of the Dead Sea, part of which lies between Jordan and Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;It could be a symbol for peace,&quot; Irsheidat added.</p>
<p>The ministers said they formed a commission to follow up on tourism projects and joint marketing campaigns &quot;on the basis of equality and mutual benefits&quot;. The commission will hold its first meeting in Israel on October 22, they said.</p>
<p>Jordan and Israel signed a peace treaty in October 1994, ending a 46-year state of war between the two neighbours and encouraging them to boost tourism cooperation and tap world markets to lure tourists on joint package tours.</p>
<p>Tourism, a major hard currency earner in both countries, has shown the most visible gains from the treaty with more European and American guests visiting the region.</p>
<p>But it has suffered recently from uncertainty of future Middle East peace moves after the election of Israel's Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in May and U.S. air strikes against Iraq earlier this month.</p>
<p>&quot;Tourism was the first sector to harvest the fruits of peace by increasing tourism traffic in the region and laying the foundations for regional tourism,&quot; Irsheidat said.</p>
<p>&quot;But peace and stability are very important factors for promoting tourism in region.&quot;</p>
<p>Katsav, who became the first Israeli tourism minister to visit Jordan since both countries signed a cooperation pact in April 1995, said his government was committed to an overall Arab-Israeli settlement.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a very big potential, and through cooperation we can dramatically increase tourism to the region,&quot; Katsav said.</p>
<p>A total of 110,000 Israeli tourists visited Jordan in 1995 while 45,000 Jordanians crossed to the Jewish state during the same period last year, Irsheidat said.</p>
<p>Katsav promised to study concerns by many Jordanians who complain it takes weeks for the Israeli embassy in Amman to issue them visas to visit Israel because of security concerns.</p>
<p>Many have relatives in the Palestinian self-ruled Gaza Strip and parts of the West Bank and in what is now Israel -- formed after the 1948 war on parts of British-mandated Palestine.</p>
<p>Talks also covered ways to ease administrative measures and security checks along their border posts to facilitate the travel of tourists. Both plan to set up consulates in their twin Red Sea cities of Aqaba and Eilat to ease travel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
