<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46387" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Lebanon warned of even bigger conflict with Israel.</title>
<headline>Lebanon warned of even bigger conflict with Israel.</headline>
<dateline>MARJAYOUN, Lebanon 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Israel's proxy militia in south Lebanon warned Lebanese leaders on Wednesday of a possible widescale Israeli operation in Lebanon if serious violence flared on the Lebanon-Israel border.</p>
<p>General Antoine Lahd, commander of the South Lebanon Army (SLA), made the warning after urging the Lebanese leaders to reconsider an offer from Israel for a conditional withdrawal of its troops from the area which they had already rejected.</p>
<p>He said Lebanon faced two possibilities if it continued its futile attempts to get an unconditional Israeli pullout from the south: the limited Hizbollah-Israel tit-for-tat war or widescale Israeli retaliation if matters worsened.</p>
<p>&quot;There are two possibilities; the first is that things remain the same in the south as they are today until peace arrives, meaning absence of security and stability and limited sabotage operations (by guerrillas),&quot; Lahd told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;The second possibility is that matters would escalate in south Lebanon in a manner that leads to Israel undertaking a wide military operation which no one knows where it will stop this time,&quot; Lahd, who was speaking in the zone, added.</p>
<p>Israel launched a 17-day blitz in April against pro-Iranian Hizbollah guerrillas that killed 200 people and caused extensive damage. A U.S.-brokered ceasefire agreement ended the blitz, barring both sides from targeting civilian areas.</p>
<p>The pro-Iranian Hizbollah (Party of God) leads an Islamic Resistance against Israeli and SLA forces to force them out of the 15-km (nine-miles)-deep zone set up by Israel in 1985 to protect its northern settlements from guerrilla raids.</p>
<p>Israel said in July it was ready to pull out from south Lebanon under a &quot;Lebanon first&quot; deal to be negotiated with Syria, if Syrian troops left Lebanon and if Lebanon's army could ensure Israel's security against raids by Hizbollah guerrillas.</p>
<p>It was flatly rejected by Beirut and Damascus, Lebanon's main power broker with 35,000 troops over two-thirds of the country. Syria and Lebanon argued it was an Israeli ploy to separate the twin Syrian-Lebanese peace talk tracks with Israel.</p>
<p>Lahd, appealing to Lebanese President Elias Hrawi and other leaders to accept &quot;Lebanon first&quot;, said:</p>
<p>&quot;I hope they go back to their right minds and consciences so as not to spoil the chance to regain south Lebanon especially as regaining it does not necessitate under &quot;Lebanon first&quot; to sign a peace treaty with Israel nor shed an ounce of sovereignty.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SYRIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARJAYOUN, Lebanon"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
