<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56638" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel agrees to let Palestinians import more.</title>
<headline>Israel agrees to let Palestinians import more.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel has agreed to expand the list of goods the Palestinian Authority can import from other Arab countries, Finance Minister Dan Meridor said on Monday.</p>
<p>An agreement will be signed next week, Meridor told reporters after the first working meeting under the new Israeli government of the Israel-Palestinian Joint Economic Committee. He did not provide details of the agreement.</p>
<p>Israel and the Palestinian Authority have a customs union setting out the level of duties on imports from third countries. There is a separate list of goods the Palestinians can import from countries that do not trade with Israel and the two sides have agreed to expand this list.</p>
<p>Israel and the Palestinian Authority also agreed to set up committees to address a number of economic issues.</p>
<p>One committee will discuss increasing the number of permits for Palestinian businessmen seeking to enter Israel.</p>
<p>Another will examine the issue of taxes collected by Israel that must be transferred to the Palestinian Authority as well as debt owed by the Palestinian Authority to Israel, mainly to the phone and water companies and hospitals.</p>
<p>A third committee will examine Palestinian complaints that Israel has made it difficult for them to move goods into Israel and parts of the Palestinian self-ruled areas in the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Meridor confirmed Israel will increase the number of permits for Palestinian workers to enter Israel from 37,000 to 50,000. It has already issued 5,000 of these permits.</p>
<p>Meridor did not say when the remaining permits would be issued. But he added that 50,000 was an intermediary target and that Israel would seek to raise this number.</p>
<p>Israel has enforced a crippling ban on Palestinian workers entering the country following a spate of suicide bombings in February and March. The ban has been slightly eased recently.</p>
<p>&quot;It's our interest that there is less poverty there, more employment and more free trade,&quot; Meridor said.</p>
<p>Palestinian Trade Minister Maher al-Masri said he would only be satisfied when all the Palestinians who used to work in Israel are allowed back in.</p>
<p>&quot;We made our position very clear. Maintaining the closure is detrimental to the peace process,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Some 160,000 Palestinians worked in Israel but over the past few years many have been replaced by labour imported from countries like Romania, Thailand and China.</p>
<p>Israel and the Palestinians also decided to try and coordinate their positions ahead of November's meeting of the international committee that manages the flow of aid to the Palestinian Authority.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
