<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58418" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Palestinians say Israel orders Hebron confiscation.</title>
<headline>Palestinians say Israel orders Hebron confiscation.</headline>
<dateline>HEBRON, West Bank 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinians accused Israel on Tuesday, ahead of a pivotal meeting on the future of Hebron, of planning to destroy Arab houses in the West Bank city to build a road for Jews.</p>
<p>Israel said it expected Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai to meet Palestinian President Yasser Arafat on Wednesday. Palestinians said they would discuss Israel's long-delayed handover of parts of Hebron to self-rule.</p>
<p>Palestinians said the Israeli army delivered orders written in Arabic and signed by central region commander Major-General Uzi Dayan to Arab landowners in Hebron informing them of an order to confiscate a strip of land between the Kiryat Arba Jewish settlement and al-Ibrahimi mosque in Hebron.</p>
<p>The mosque is inside the traditional tomb of the biblical patriarchs holy to both Arabs and Jews. Hebron is the only West Bank city where both peoples live -- 400 Israelis among 100,000 Palestinians.</p>
<p>Israel occupied the West Bank in the 1967 Middle East war and later the settlers moved in. Israel began handing over parts of the West Bank to self-rule in 1994 under peace deals with Arafat's PLO.</p>
<p>The confiscation order did not mention plans to demolish houses, stating only that the land was being taken for &quot;military purposes&quot;. But Palestinians said the Israelis planned to build a road in the area that would cut through the ancient casbah quarter of Hebron, destroying a number of Arab-owned houses.</p>
<p>&quot;My house falls within the area they said they wanted to confiscate,&quot; said Nasser Daana, a 30-year-old Palestinian landowner.</p>
<p>&quot;I really see no justification for this road, especially since the Jews already use our city roads,&quot; Hebron's Palestinian mayor Mustafa al-Natshe said.</p>
<p>An Israeli army spokeswoman was checking the report.</p>
<p>Hebron is the last of the West Bank Arab cities due to be given self-rule. Under a 1995 peace deal Israel was supposed to hand over parts of the city last March while keeping parts that include the homes of the Jews.</p>
<p>A series of suicide bombings in Israel delayed the handover and the three-month-old right-wing government of Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has been demanding changes in the redeployment map it says are necessary to the settlers' safety.</p>
<p>Palestinians view Israeli redeployment in Hebron as a litmus test for Israel's commitment to the self-rule deals signed by the Israeli government that Netanyahu ousted in May.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HEBRON, West Bank"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
