<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61409" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Hariri says south Lebanon escalation not likely.</title>
<headline>Hariri says south Lebanon escalation not likely.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lebanese Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri said on Wednesday he does not expect increased Israeli military action in south Lebanon, the last active Arab-Israeli frontline.</p>
<p>&quot;According to our information and in our estimate, military escalation in south Lebanon is not likely,&quot; Hariri told a delegation from the Lebanese Publishers' Syndicate.</p>
<p>Hariri's remarks followed a warning last week by Israel's client militia in south Lebanon that Israel might launch wide retaliation if Moslem guerrillas step up raids on Israeli forces occupying a south Lebanon border strip.</p>
<p>The head of the South Lebanon Army (SLA) militia, General Antoine Lahd, termed the warning his own analysis, not a message from Israel. But it caused concern in Lebanon.</p>
<p>Israel launched a bloody 17-day blitz on Lebanon in April in a failed attempt to crush Hizbollah (Party of God) guerrillas after tit-for-tat bombardments of civilian areas by the two sides. Some 200 Lebanese, mostly civilians, were killed.</p>
<p>A U.S.-brokered ceasefire that ended the fighting barred both sides from targetting civilian areas but allowed guerrilla raids on Israeli forces in south Lebanon.</p>
<p>Hariri said success in peace talks between Lebanon and Israel depended on an Israeli troop pullout from the south.</p>
<p>&quot;The peace process depends on Israel...We hope for peace. Let Israel pull out and peace will take place,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Lebanon is moving hand-in-hand with Syria in peace talks with Israel, stalled on both tracks over the question of an Isreali withdrawal from south Lebanon and the Golan Heights.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
