<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64271" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Netanyahu says Syrian tensions under control.</title>
<headline>Netanyahu says Syrian tensions under control.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu tried on Thursday to ease tension with Syria over troop movements in Lebanon and reassure Palestinians he was committed to peace.</p>
<p>But his comments came against a backdrop of violence in south Lebanon, a fight in Jerusalem's Old City between Arabs and Jewish settlers and news that 2,000 new Jewish homes can be built in occupied West Bank areas.</p>
<p>In Marjayoun, south Lebanon, militia sources said two Israeli soldiers were killed and two wounded in an ambush by pro-Iranian guerrillas.</p>
<p>Hizbollah, which is fighting to oust Israel from a 15-km (nine-mile) -deep border occupation zone, said its fighters clashed with an Israeli force trying to advance out of the zone and into the Iqlim al-Toufah highlands near Sojoud.</p>
<p>Israeli warplanes pounded Hizbollah targets in response. Israel says Hizbollah is armed via Syria that it believes can rein in the Shi'ite fighters if it chooses.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, who met U.S. peace envoy Dennis Ross in Jerusalem, said relations with Damascus were &quot;under control&quot;.</p>
<p>He also said Israel was committed to implementing a stalled self-rule agreement with Palestinians in an attempt to dispel the impression in the Arab world that his right-wing government was backtracking on Middle East peace.</p>
<p>&quot;Calming messages were sent by one side to the other and I think that it's important that in this case the United States assisted,&quot; Netanyahu told reporters. &quot;For now, things are under control.&quot;</p>
<p>At a news conference later Netanyahu said he and Ross had discussed ways to revive peace talks with Damascus and the Palestinians.</p>
<p>Syria has redeployed up to 12,000 troops in Lebanon, moving some to within striking distance of a key Israeli position on the occupied Golan Heights, causing war jitters in the Jewish state.</p>
<p>Syrian President Hafez al-Assad, the main power broker in Lebanon, began the redeployment after Netanyahu visited south Lebanon last month and said Hizbollah attacks against Israeli soldiers were &quot;not good for Syria&quot;.</p>
<p>Netanyahu had said Syria was trying to pressure Israel into unilateral concessions on the Golan, a strategic plateau Israel seized in the 1967 Middle East war. Syria wants back all of the Golan in return for peace with Israel. The two countries have failed in five years of sporadic peace talks to agree.</p>
<p>&quot;The crucial question right now is what is Syria's intention vis-a-vis the talks. We are in any case watching the situation, we are proceeding with the Palestinians, it is now up to President Assad if he is interested or not interested in resuming peace talks,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, who ousted the centre-left Labour government of Shimon Peres in May, has angered Arab peace partners by rejecting the land-for-peace formula that provided the basis for previous talks.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there is a real effort on the part of Israel and the United States to resume the peace talks. I don't think anyone seriously expected the new Israeli government to assume the positions of the previous Israeli government especially since they were never cemented in written contracts,&quot; Netanyahu said of Labour's understandings on a Golan withdrawal.</p>
<p>He said, however, Israel would honour the Oslo self-rule agreement Labour signed with the Palestinians.</p>
<p>Palestinians fear Netanyahu wants to rewrite parts of the accord, citing as evidence his delay in redeploying Israeli troops in the West Bank town of Hebron as already agreed, and his decision to expand settlements.</p>
<p>Israel's military administration has approved plans to build about 2,000 new homes in Jewish settlements in occupied West Bank lands, a settler spokeswoman said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The decision, which was immediately condemned by Palestinian and Israeli peace activists, still needs approval from Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai, who has already approved another plan for 1,800 units.</p>
<p>Also on Thursday Jewish settlers briefly occupied an East Jerusalem house they said they had bought from its Arab owners, igniting fresh violence in the holy city.</p>
<p>Witnesses said guards hired by the Ateret Cohanim settlement group, which claimed to have bought the house for $5 million, broke into the house at dawn.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SYRIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
