<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68775" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel defends Lebanon attacks ahead of meeting.</title>
<headline>Israel defends Lebanon attacks ahead of meeting.</headline>
<byline>Daniel Sternoff</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel defended its air and ground attacks in south Lebanon, saying they were necessary retaliation against the Jewish state's guerrilla foes.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying in every possible way to lower the tension in the region,&quot; Israeli Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai said. &quot;We have no intention of taking extraordinary measures, but we have the obligation to take every necessary operation for the good of our forces working in Lebanon.&quot;</p>
<p>Israeli jets and artillery blasted Hizbollah targets in south Lebanon on Saturday after an Israeli officer was wounded in clashes with Moslem guerrillas there.</p>
<p>Hizbollah fighters, who have killed 20 Israelis this year in south Lebanon, are battling to oust Israel and allied forces from a 15-km (nine miles) zone Israel has occupied since 1982.</p>
<p>A five-nation committee monitoring a ceasefire understanding -- which ended a 17-day Israeli blitz on Lebanon in April -- is to meet on Sunday to look into Israeli and Lebanese complaints.</p>
<p>Lebanon has filed a complaint that Israel shelled civilian areas on Thursday. Israel said it would complain the guerrillas fired on its forces from inside three villages.</p>
<p>According to witnesses, some 50 shells slammed into the Lebanese villages of Ain Bouswar and Jba'a on Thursday, wounding a civilian woman in Jba'a.</p>
<p>Representatives of the United States, France, Syria, Lebanon and Israel will gather in the town of Naqoura, south Lebanon.</p>
<p>Some 200 Lebanese, mostly civilians, were killed in the April onslaught, dubbed by Israel &quot;Operation Grapes of Wrath&quot;, after tit-for-tat bombardments of civilian areas by both sides.</p>
<p>In Saturday's attacks, Lebanese security sources said Israeli jets fired several rockets in four attacks into Mlita hill and Jabal Safi in Iqlim al-Toufah ridge which is used by Shi'ite Moslem Hizbollah (Party of God) fighters to attack Israeli troops occupying a south Lebanon border zone.</p>
<p>The Israeli strikes followed attacks against two Israeli outposts at Sojoud and Beir Kallab and forces stationed nearby.</p>
<p>Israel's army said an officer was wounded in an attack by Hizbollah guerrillas and confirmed the air raids, saying pilots reported accurate hits.</p>
<p>In Beirut, Hizbollah claimed responsibility for the assault, saying its fighters hit a tank and attacked the Sojoud and Beir Kallab posts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
