<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="72796" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Netanyahu promises more West Bank building -TV.</title>
<headline>Netanyahu promises more West Bank building -TV.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has promised a partner in his coalition government that 780 more homes for Jews will be built in the West Bank, Israel's Channel Two television said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The report came as Palestinian President Yasser Arafat convened his cabinet in emergency session in the Gaza Strip to discuss Israel's opening a tourist tunnel in Jerusalem's Old City, a move Arafat called a &quot;crime&quot; against the religious status quo in the city.</p>
<p>Senior Palestinian officials warned Israel on Saturday its expansion of Jewish settlements was leading Jews and Arabs towards &quot;confrontation and disaster&quot;.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's director of communications, David Bar-Illan, said he could neither confirm nor deny the report since the prime minister was out of the country. Netanyahu was in London on the first leg of a European diplomatic tour.</p>
<p>The television said Netanyahu made the promise on Sunday after the ultra-Orthodox Agudat Israel party threatened to leave his government unless more homes were built for religious Jews.</p>
<p>It said Netanyahu promised to approve another 580 housing units at Kiryat Sefer settlement and 200 more at Beitar settlement.</p>
<p>The report was only the latest in a flurry on approvals under Netanyahu's government of thousands of housing units for Jews in the occupied West Bank.</p>
<p>On September 19, settlers said Israel's military administration had approved plans to build about 2,000 new homes in Jewish settlements in occupied West Bank lands. The decision still needs approval from Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai.</p>
<p>That announcement came a day after it emerged that Mordechai had approved another plan to expand a Jewish settlement in the West Bank by 1,800 units.</p>
<p>Palestinians want to establish an independent state in the West Bank and Gaza Strip with Arab East Jerusalem as its capital.</p>
<p>Interim peace deals the Palestinians cut with Israel's previous government, ousted by Netanyahu in May, gave them limited self-rule in parts of the territories.</p>
<p>Final status peace talks are to deal with these issues but have yet to resume under Netanyahu, who opposes a Palestinian state and says he will not discuss Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Israel captured the territories and East Jerusalem in the 1967 Middle East war. It annexed East Jerusalem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
