<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75429" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Fierce Israeli-PLO clashes over Jerusalem.</title>
<headline>Fierce Israeli-PLO clashes over Jerusalem.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot dead three Palestinian policemen and a civilian on Wednesday in the bloodiest clashes in the West Bank since PLO rule began two years ago.</p>
<p>Doctors said up to 300 were injured and they expected more deaths.</p>
<p>The fighting erupted during widespread Palestinian protests against Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's decison to open a tunnel in Jerusalem near Islam's third holiest shrine.</p>
<p>At the PLO-ruled enclave of Ramallah, Palestinians pelted Israeli soldiers with stones and bottles. Soldiers responded with live ammunition and Palestinian police soon joined the fray, fighting running gun battles with Israelis, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Gun battles between Israeli and Palestinian forces also erupted near Bethlehem, south of Jerusalem, witnesses said. Residents dived for cover when shooting broke out at Rachel's Tomb on the outskirts of the West Bank town.</p>
<p>The violence plunged relations between Palestinian President Yasser Arafat and Netanyahu's new right-wing government into crisis.</p>
<p>The United States, sponsor of the flagging Middle East peace process, urged all sides to stay calm.</p>
<p>The clashes outside Ramallah were reminiscent of the 1987-93 Palestinian uprising, or intifada, against Israel -- only now there are nearly 30,000 armed Palestinian police in self-rule areas.</p>
<p>Major-General Nasr Youssef, commander of the Palestinian security forces, told Reuters in self-ruled Gaza: &quot;Three Palestinian policemen were killed and seven other policemen were wounded.&quot;</p>
<p>He accused Israel of violating peace agreements and said he would convene a meeting of the high Palestinian security council on Wednesday night.</p>
<p>Ramallah hospital director Shawqi Harb told Israel Radio earlier that four people had been killed and about 200 wounded, most of them from rubber bullets or teargas inhalation.</p>
<p>But he added: &quot;The last four hours we've been getting M-16 gunshot wounds, mostly in the brain and the chest...We have at least six or seven very critical patients. Well, we expect some of them to die.&quot;</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers fired live ammunition and rubber bullets when they came under a hail of stones and bottles at a crossing to the Ramallah enclave, north of Jerusalem, witnesses said.</p>
<p>One angry Palestinian policeman grabbed a rifle and started shooting back at the Israelis, according to witnesses at the scene. Others from Arafat's Force 17 guard joined in, sparking the most serious gunfight between Israeli and Palestinian forces since Arafat returned to Gaza in July 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;Come on, shoot, show them what can be done,&quot; one youth jeered at a Palestinian policeman who was frantically shouting into his walkie-talkie and trying to calm demonstrators.</p>
<p>Youths initially cursed Palestinian police for not defending them when Israeli soldiers fired. But jeers turned to cheers when Palestinian paramilitary forces took up positions behind walls and houses to return fire.</p>
<p>&quot;When we saw there was a massacre and the Israeli soldiers were entering our area, we had to respond,&quot; one officer told Reuters after the clashes had subsided.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers entered the self-rule area for the first time to try to stop the fire and pick off stone-throwers. Palestinian police fired from behind walls and dashed from building to building, some doing combat-rolls.</p>
<p>At sundown, after more than five hours of clashes, two truckloads of Palestinian police arrived and tried to prevent protesters from attacking the Israeli post.</p>
<p>Hospital sources said up to 300 Palestinians were wounded, six from live ammunition, the rest from rubber bullets, beatings and teargas inhalation. The Israeli army said seven of its soldiers were lightly wounded.</p>
<p>Israeli authorities contacted Arafat in Gaza in an attempt to halt the protests, Israeli officials said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, who was visiting Paris, said he appealed in a telephone call to Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to help calm the violence. He defended his decision to open the tunnel, which had prompted Arafat to call the demonstrations and a strike.</p>
<p>&quot;The most important thing that we cannot accept is the Judaisation of Jerusalem. East Jerusalem is our capital and this has been occupied since 1967,&quot; Arafat told reporters in Gaza.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said he had merely implemented a previous Labour government decision to open a second entrance to a tunnel beside the Dome of the Rock and al-Aqsa mosque complex, saying it made an important archaeological site more accessible to tourists.</p>
<p>The underground tunnel, with its sensitivities for the whole Moslem world, provided a perfect vehicle to mobilise popular sentiment against Netanyahu's delay in implementing self-rule.</p>
<p>Arafat cancelled a meeting on Thursday of the Israeli-Palestinian steering committee overseeing implementation of the Oslo accord.</p>
<p>In Cairo, the Arab League said it would meet on Thursday at the request of the Palestinians to discuss the tunnel.</p>
<p>Palestinians charge that Israel is trying to turn Jerusalem into a wholly Jewish city. They say Israel allows Jews to build in the city but restricts Arabs from building. They also say most Palestinians are barred from entering Jerusalem -- the political, cultural and religious centre of Palestinian life -- by closures of the West Bank and Gaza.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
