<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75434" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Arabs say Netanyahu turned back clock in 100 days.</title>
<headline>Arabs say Netanyahu turned back clock in 100 days.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Wright</byline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>In his first 100 days in office, rightwing Israeli leader Benjamin Netanyahu has turned the Middle East clock back years, Arab leaders say.</p>
<p>He has infuriated most of his Arab neighbours, driven Palestinians to despair and helped bring the word &quot;war&quot; back into the political vocabulary of the region.</p>
<p>Gone is the goodwill which former prime minister Shimon Peres and his predecessor, assassinated leader Yitzhak Rabin, built up through three years of diplomatic footwork.</p>
<p>Gone is the vision of a common Middle East market where, after more than 40 years of Arab-Israeli conflict, barriers to trade and travel might come tumbling down.</p>
<p>An Israeli decision on Tuesday to open an archaeological tunnel in Jerusalem near Islam's third holiest shrine was, in Arab eyes, Netanyahu's latest provocation.</p>
<p>The move sparked the bloodiest day of clashes between Palestinians and Israeli soldiers in the West Bank since the Jewish state handed over parts of the area to the PLO in 1994, leaving at least three Palestinians dead and 300 wounded.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said in France he would telephone Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to try to ease tensions but did not think the violence warranted cutting short his European tour.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the big crisis between the Israelis and the Palestinians, and the Arabs, and the Moslems and the Christians,&quot; Palestinian President Yasser Arafat told reporters in the self-ruled Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>The Gulf state of Qatar has postponed plans to open a trade office in Tel Aviv, in one of the first overt steps away from normalising relations with the Jewish state.</p>
<p>When a Middle East economic conference meets in Cairo in November, it is likely to be a subdued affair, quite unlike the peace jamboree the Egyptian hosts had hoped to organise.</p>
<p>&quot;Back to square one&quot; is the phrase on the lips of many an Arab minister and in the columns of Arabic newspapers.</p>
<p>&quot;To come in 1996 with the same ideas as in the 30s, the 40s, the 50s and the 60s, that's dangerous... We cannot go along with it,&quot; said Egyptian Foreign Minister Amr Moussa.</p>
<p>In Arab eyes, the reason for the present sour and hostile mood in Arab-Israeli relations is simple -- Netanyahu has questioned the land-for-peace principle which has been at the heart of Middle East peace diplomacy since the 1970s, when Israel gave the Sinai peninsula back to Egypt.</p>
<p>The Madrid peace conference in 1991, at which Netanyahu's Likud party represented Israel, took place on the same understanding. In contacts with Syria, the previous Israeli government had agreed in principle to give back all the Golan Heights, Israeli and Egyptian officials say.</p>
<p>On top of that, the Arabs say, Netanyahu has failed to put into effect measures clearly agreed between Israel and the autonomous Palestinian Authority, such as redeploying its troops in the West Bank town of Hebron.</p>
<p>Mubarak, now firmly aligned with Syria in diplomatic confrontation with the Jewish state, has bluntly accused Netanyahu of reneging on commitments he made at their first meeting in July.</p>
<p>All parties have been anxious to play down the risk of a shooting war but Syria has raised eyebrows in Israel by redeploying its forces in Lebanon and Israelis asked questions about this month's big military manoeuvres by Egypt.</p>
<p>But short of war, an implausible course since they believe Israel has nuclear weapons, the Arabs have no easy options for persuading the new Israeli government to change its tune.</p>
<p>The United States, which twisted Israel's arm to bring it to the Madrid conference, is out of the picture because of the presidential elections in November.</p>
<p>Conventional wisdom is that U.S. presidential candidates dare not take on the influential pro-Israeli lobby.</p>
<p>Egypt has tried a war of words, hurling epithets such as arrogant, impudent and stupid at Israel's new rulers. Some Arabs have played on Netanyahu's name, the first two syllables of which mean putrid in Arabic.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not have a magic recipe,&quot; Moussa said in an interview this week. &quot;But a start to serious action would be for the Arabs to stand together...and reject this approach of Netanyahu's.&quot;</p>
<p>In June, Egypt organised the first Arab summit in five years, to coordinate the Arab response to the election of Netanyahu.</p>
<p>It ended with a warning to Israel that Arab states would have to reconsider the gestures they have made towards Israel if Israel tries to change the ground rules for the peace talks.</p>
<p>Arab foreign ministers met in Cairo again this month and recommended a course of action in a secret report to Mubarak.</p>
<p>For the past 10 days Mubarak has been contacting other Arab leaders, either by telephone or by written message, but diplomats say they do not expect any dramatic decision.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
