<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76441" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Highlights of Netanyahu's first 100 days.</title>
<headline>Highlights of Netanyahu's first 100 days.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Benjamin Netanyahu became Israel's prime minister 100 days ago on Thursday. Here are some highlights of his time in office:</p>
<p>June 18 - Netanyahu, the right-wing Likud leader who ousted Labour party Prime Minister Shimon Peres in May elections, takes office promising to promote peace with Israel's Arab neighbours while ensuring security.</p>
<p>June 28 - Netanyahu sends two representatives to meet Palestinian President Yasser Arafat in what senior PLO offical calls &quot;first official contact&quot; with new Israeli government.</p>
<p>July 7 - Netanyahu's government, which inherited a bloated public sector from the Labour government, approves steep cut in 1997 spending. Cuts still need parliamentary approval.</p>
<p>July 23 - Arafat meets Israeli Foreign Minister David Levy in Gaza in first high-level meeting since Netanyahu took office.</p>
<p>Aug 2 - Netanyahu infuriates Palestinians by lifting a four-year freeze on Jewish settlement expansion in occupied West Bank imposed by the previous government.</p>
<p>Aug 9 - Israel says no progress on peace moves until Palestinian Authority shuts offices in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Aug 11 - Arafat threatens Israel with international arbitration if his peace goals are frustrated.</p>
<p>Aug 22 - Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak warns could cancel Middle East economic conference in November if Israel stalls on peace.</p>
<p>Aug 25 - Bowing to Israeli demands, Arafat's Palestinian Authority shuts two East Jerusalem offices.</p>
<p>Aug 27 - Israel hoists bulldozer over Jerusalem's Old City wall to demolish Palestinian community centre it said was built without permit.</p>
<p>Aug 28 - Arafat says Israel declared war on Palestinians with settlement expansion.</p>
<p>Aug 29 - Palestinians hold first general strike in West Bank and Gaza in two years to protest at Israeli policy; Heads of Israeli-PLO steering committee on implemention of interim peace deals hold first meeting since Netanyahu took office.</p>
<p>Sept 1 - Israeli and PLO negotiators launch marathon talks with Norwegian mediation aimed at Netanyahu-Arafat meeting.</p>
<p>Sept 4 - Netanyahu and Arafat hold first summit, at Erez crossing between Israel and Gaza.</p>
<p>Sept 17 - Government-appointed committee proposes sweeping reform in Israel's capital markets. Netanyahu, faced with plunging stock and bond prices, had taken office promising to reform Israel's markets.</p>
<p>Sept 24 - Israeli government opens tourist tunnel near Islamic holy site, igniting protests reminiscent of 6-1/2-year Palestinian uprising and further souring relations with Arab states. Israeli government demands Egypt stop &quot;threatening&quot; it for taking slower approach to peace than its Labour-led predecessor.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
