<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78572" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Netanyahu tunnel undermines peace.</title>
<headline>Netanyahu tunnel undermines peace.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli troops killed 39 Palestinians and PLO police shot dead 11 Israelis on Thursday in gun battles and stone-throwing clashes that threatened to undermine five-years of U.S.-driven Middle East peacemaking.</p>
<p>Israel declared a state of emergency, deploying extra troops and sending in tanks and helicopters to quell the violence. It was the first time the Jewish state had used tanks in the West Bank since it captured the territory in 1967, Israel Radio said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, whose decision to open a tunnel in Israeli-annexed Arab East Jerusalem triggered the violence, cut short a European tour and asked for a meeting with Palestinian President Yasser Arafat.</p>
<p>PLO officials said they doubted a meeting would talk place on Thursday, adding that both sides were studying a proposal by Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak for a three-way summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Most probably the meeting will not take place tonight. President Mubarak has proposed a three-way summit in Cairo and both sides are studying it,&quot; one of the officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;It has not been settled up until now,&quot; Arafat told reporters during a visit to Shifa Hospital in Gaza.</p>
<p>Arafat called the violence &quot;a real massacre against the Palestinian people&quot;.</p>
<p>The United States, which has to balance being Israel's staunchest ally with its role as peace broker, called for a halt to the fighting and a resumption of peace talks.</p>
<p>&quot;I asked both sides to end this violence, to get back to the business of the peace ... to resolve their differences through negotiations,&quot; President Bill Clinton said in Washington.</p>
<p>U.S. diplomats in Israel were working intensively behind the scenes to arrange an Arafat-Netanyahu meeting.</p>
<p>The unprecedented clashes and gunfights between Arafat's paramilitary police and Israeli soliders still occupying parts of the West Bank and Gaza Strip have claimed 44 Palestinian and 11 Israeli lives in two days. More than 740 Arabs and more than 50 Jews were injured on Thursday.</p>
<p>PLO officials said Arafat, who returned to Gaza in July 1994 to lead the Palestinian self-rule Authority, wanted Netanyahu to commit himself to honouring peace deals signed with the previous Labour government and not just discuss an end to the violence.</p>
<p>The fighting looked like Beirut militia battles with Palestinian police letting off bursts of automatic rifle fire from behind concrete blocks at crouching Israeli soldiers.</p>
<p>Israeli helicopters fired at gunmen in apartment blocks in Ramallah, north of Jerusalem, and armoured personnel carriers tried to rescue Israelis trapped inside the Jewish shrine of Joseph's Tomb in the West Bank town of Nablus, where six of the 11 Israelis were killed.</p>
<p>World governments voiced alarm at the fighting and most, well beyond the Arab world, blamed Netanyahu for provoking a second intifada, or uprising.</p>
<p>Besides Washington, Russia, France and Britain all appealed for calm.</p>
<p>An Arab League meeting in Cairo hailed what it called &quot;the intifada of the Palestinian people&quot; and said the tunnel was part of a plot to destroy a Moslem shrine.</p>
<p>Arafat ordered his 30,000-strong police to shoot only if fired on. Palestinian policemen tried to hold back stone-throwers in Ramallah and Nablus after the worst of the fighting had subsided, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Fighting was strongest around Jewish settlements in Gaza, at the entrance to PLO-ruled Ramallah, and at Joseph's Tomb in Nablus where security sources said about 40 soldiers and settlers were besieged by stone-throwers. They were later evacuated.</p>
<p>Israel denied its opening of an archaeological tunnel adjacent to the al-Aqsa and Dome of the Rock mosque complex, Islam's third holiest shrine after Mecca and Medina, was an assault on Moslem sites.</p>
<p>But the move unleashed long pent-up Palestinian frustration with the self-rule agreement which Netanyahu has held up. In private, Western diplomats called the tunnel-opening the biggest political miscalculation of Netanyahu's 100-day-long term.</p>
<p>The French Foreign Ministry accused Israel of triggering the riots and said they were a worrying throwback to the 1987-93 intifada. Then, youths confronted Israeli troops with stones.</p>
<p>This week the youths urged their police -- armed under terms of a 1993 peace deal with Israel -- to protect them. In Gaza, when one Palestinian policmen fell wounded, a young boy picked up his rifle and shot at Israelis.</p>
<p>Two Israeli soldiers were killed when hundreds of Palestinians charged an army post near the isolated Netzarim Jewish settlement south of Gaza City, Israel Radio said.</p>
<p>Three branches of Arafat's police fired at Israeli jeeps from behind concrete blocks at a checkpoint near Kfar Darom settlement in the centre of the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>&quot;Stop throwing stones, this will not help now,&quot; a Palestinian officer shouted. His words were drowned out by the crackle of automatic rifle fire from members of Arafat's Preventive Security force and the Coast Guard.</p>
<p>Among others killed in Gaza was a girl aged 13, health officials said.</p>
<p>Protests in Jerusalem, which is cut off from the West Bank by an Israeli closure, were muted. Palestinians accuse Israel of trying to Judaise Arab East Jerusalem, captured by Israel in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
<p>Israeli Defence Minister Yizhak Mordechai questioned the decision to open the tunnel. &quot;I don't know whether to say with finality that...all considerations were taken into account,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
