<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78584" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel, PLO in bid to arrange peace summit.</title>
<headline>Israel, PLO in bid to arrange peace summit.</headline>
<byline>Howard Goller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel and the Palestinians tried to arrange a summit on Friday after more than 50 people died in gunbattles that threatened to undermine five years of Middle East peacemaking.</p>
<p>A senior Israeli official said Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu urgently wanted the meeting to stop two days of bloodshed triggered by his decision opening an archaeological tunnel near an Islamic shrine in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>But PLO officials said Palestinian President Yasser Arafat would have little success in quelling the violence unless assured the right-wing Israeli leader would commit at the meeting to implementing the peace deals of the government he ousted in May.</p>
<p>Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak tried to arrange a three-way meeting in Cairo, perhaps on Friday, and Netanyahu spoke with him by telephone from a security cabinet meeting in Jerusalem called by the Israeli leader to confront the emergency.</p>
<p>An Israeli statement quoted Netanyahu as telling Mubarak: &quot;The Palestinian Authority has an obligation to curb the violent activities and cease the incitement.&quot;</p>
<p>In New York, the United Nations said it would hold a formal meeting on Friday at 11 a.m. (1500 GMT) on the situation. Besides Washington, Russia, France and Britain all appealed for calm.</p>
<p>Facing international condemnation and having sent in tanks and helicopters to quell the violence, Netanyahu cut short a three-day trip to Europe on Thursday, returning home from Germany several hours earlier than planned.</p>
<p>It was the first time Israel had used tanks in the West Bank since the territory's capture in 1967, Israel Radio said.</p>
<p>Israeli troops braced for renewed violence on Friday when Palestinians planned to bury their dead and Moslems to attend Friday prayers. Israeli Arab leaders called a general strike in solidarity with Palestinians of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Arafat's health ministry said 39 Palestinians died on Thursday, raising to 44 the number killed in two days of gunfights unprecedented in the two years since he returned to run self-rule areas under peace deals with Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;What happened is a real massacre against the Palestinian people,&quot; Arafat told reporters during a hospital visit in Gaza.</p>
<p>The Israeli army said 11 of its soldiers were killed by gunfire on Thursday, six of them during a siege of the domed tomb of the biblical Joseph in the heart of Palestinian-ruled Nablus in the West Bank.</p>
<p>Officials said 1,085 Palestinians and about 65 Israelis were wounded in the two days of unrest.</p>
<p>Israelis voiced outrage in radio programmes that Palestinian police would turn on them with weapons provided under peace deals with Israel.</p>
<p>Washington, Israel's closest ally, asked Netanyahu to close down the tourist tunnel, but the Israeli leader seemed opposed, telling Secretary of States Warren Christopher in a phone call that it would reward violence, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, 46, had already angered Arab states and Palestinians by opposing the policy of swapping occupied land for peace which had been the basis of U.S.-brokered peace talks launched in Madrid in 1991.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to preserve this peace process and we really urge Mr Netanyahu to start implementing the agreements immediately,&quot; chief Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erekat told CNN television.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called for a halt to the fighting and a resumption of talks. U.S. diplomats in Israel were working intensively behind the scenes to arrange an Arafat-Netanyahu meeting.</p>
<p>The fighting looked like Beirut militia battles with Palestinian police letting off bursts of automatic rifle fire from behind concrete blocks at crouching Israeli soldiers.</p>
<p>Israeli helicopters fired at gunmen in apartment blocks in Ramallah, north of Jerusalem, and armoured personnel carriers tried to rescue Israelis trapped in Joseph's Tomb. Fighting was strongest in those areas and around Jewish settlements in Gaza.</p>
<p>Israel denied its opening of the archaeological tunnel adjacent to the al-Aqsa and Dome of the Rock mosque complex, Islam's third holiest shrine after Mecca and Medina, was an assault on Moslem sites.</p>
<p>But the move unleashed long pent-up Palestinian frustration with the self-rule agreement which Netanyahu has held up. In private, Western diplomats called the tunnel opening the biggest political miscalculation of Netanyahu's 100-day-long term.</p>
<p>Israeli Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai questioned the decision to open the tunnel. &quot;I don't know whether to say with finality that...all considerations were taken into account,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
