<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78595" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Lebanon condemns Israeli &quot;massacres&quot;.</title>
<headline>Lebanon condemns Israeli &quot;massacres&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lebanon's defence minister condemned on Thursday what he called Israel's &quot;massacres&quot; of civilians in the occupied territories and accused the Jewish state of ending the Middle East peace process.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Mohsen Dalloul issued a statement urging Arabs to take a firm unified stand after Israeli troops shot dead dozens of Palestinians in a second day of clashes in the West Bank and Gaza strip.</p>
<p>Five Israelis, including two soldiers, were killed.</p>
<p>&quot;What is needed is Arab action making the United States of America and the international community face up to their responsibilities with regard to the massacres committed in Palestine against the unarmed civilians, women and children,&quot; Dalloul said.</p>
<p>Referring to the 1987-1993 Palestinian uprising against Israeli rule, Dalloul said a &quot;new intifada&quot; was the answer to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's &quot;arrogance and Israeli stubborness and aggressiveness.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The Israeli enemy's prime minister is proving day after day and during the period of his criminality that not only his mandate is coming to an end and vanishing but also the whole peace process,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Sheikh Mohammed Rashid Qabbani, Lebanon's highest Sunni Moslem cleric, said &quot;violence and terrorism...used by the Zionist enemy against our sons in Arab Palestine will not pass without punishment&quot;.</p>
<p>Violence erupted on Wednesday after Israel offended Palestinian sensitivities by opening a tunnel near Islam's third holiest site in Arab East Jerusalem</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
