<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79578" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Mideast peace hope lost in blood and talk of war.</title>
<headline>Mideast peace hope lost in blood and talk of war.</headline>
<byline>Jack Redden</byline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>One hundred days into the new Israeli government of Benjamin Netanyahu, hopes for Arab-Israeli peace have been replaced by the old fears of Middle East war and the bloody suppression of Palestinian protests.</p>
<p>As the Palestinian death toll mounted on Thursday in clashes triggered by the Israeli prime minister's decision to open a tunnel in Jerusalem adjacent to Islam's third holiest site, the question shifted from the health of the peace process to whether it still exists.</p>
<p>Foreign governments appealed for a resumption of the peace talks begun five years ago but the violence racking the Palestinian lands occupied by Israel in 1967 looked eerily reminiscent of the intifada -- the Palestinian uprising against Israeli rule that began in 1987 and did not officially end for nearly six years.</p>
<p>&quot;Whoever is in a position of leadership...should calm passions and not inflame them. He should return to the negotiating table and not preach violence,&quot; Netanyahu said in France on Wednesday night as the toll grew.</p>
<p>The problem is what Netanyahu puts on the negotiating table is markedly less than what Arabs and Israelis were discussing under the Labour-led government that the Likud party leader defeated last May.</p>
<p>Palestinians see the opening of a second entrace to a tunnel in the Moslem quarter of Jerusalem's Old City during the night, as symbolic of his approach to negotiations. The previous government had bowed to Arab objections about a tunnel built to show the foundations of the wall around the Temple Mount -- the site 2,000 years ago of the Jewish temple but home for the past 1,300 years to the al-Aqsa mosque.</p>
<p>The tunnel, seen by the Arab world as a further tightening of Israel's grip over the city occupied in the 1967 Middle East war, was the fuse that ignited a power keg of other Palestinian grievances accumulated under Netanyahu.</p>
<p>Palestinians, abandoning their quixotic quest for regaining all of pre-Israel Palestine, joined the U.S.-driven peace talks in Madrid in 1991. Their gains under Israel's Labour government were modest, but they were driven on by the hope that the process would end in full independence with East Jerusalem as their capital.</p>
<p>Even before he took office in June, Netanyahu made clear that would never happen under him. Rather than begin &quot;final status&quot; talks to address those issues, he has failed to implement even agreements signed by the previous Israeli government. Jewish settlement of occupied Arab land has accelerated.</p>
<p>Instead of the economic gains they expected, Palestinians have seen unemployment and poverty soar as investment failed to materialise and Netanyahu kept severe restrictions on them reaching jobs inside Israel.</p>
<p>Palestinian leader Yasser Arafat, risking the support of his own people by cracking down on Palestinian opponents of peace with Israel, was ignored by Netanyahu until early this month. When the current violence erupted, Netanyahu first called Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, not Arafat.</p>
<p>Hopes for broader Arab-Israeli peace look no healthier. Even countries that moved closer to Israel in the five years of peace talks have grown increasingly critical of Netanyahu's policies, above all his rejection of the principle of trading occupied Arab land for peace that was the basis for the negotiations.</p>
<p>Arab governments, even in Jordan which signed a peace treaty with Israel in 1994 and has since become the Jewish state's closest Arab friend, know Netanyahu's 100 days in office is likely to have reinforced existing popular suspicions about Israeli goals in the peace process.</p>
<p>Israel-Syrian talks made little headway under the previous Israeli government, but the sporadic negotiations have now been replaced by warnings that the alternative to peace is another war. Both Syria and Lebanon have moved forces closer to Israeli troops occupying Syria's Golan Heights and a &quot;security zone&quot; inside Lebanon.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has rejected Syria's key demand for peace, withdrawing the previous government's offer to return at least part of the Golan Heights, which was captured along with the West Bank, East Jerusalem and the Gaza Strip in 1967.</p>
<p>As prospects for Middle East peace disintegrate, U.S. President Bill Clinton is under pressure to act despite his reluctance to alienate Netanyahu in the final weeks of a U.S. presidential election where he wants the Jewish vote.</p>
<p>That pressure is also reminiscent of an earlier time. The United States, after years of relative inactivity, was pushed back into seeking Middle East peace in the late 1980s by the bloody televised images of the intifada.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
