<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80280" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israelis, PLO in Gaza gunbattle, three dead.</title>
<headline>Israelis, PLO in Gaza gunbattle, three dead.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot dead five Arabs and fought fierce gun battles with Palestinian police on Thursday as bloody protests over Israel's policy on Jerusalem spread to the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Palestinians throwing stones marched on Jewish settlements in the Strip, prompting fire from Israeli soldiers.</p>
<p>Yasser Arafat's police then opened up with automatic fire in scenes reminiscent of militia battles in Beirut.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu cut short a visit to Germany to return home to handle the worst crisis of his 100 days in office.</p>
<p>The deaths raised to 10 the number of Palestinians killed in two days of clashes over Netanyahu's opening of a tunnel beside the Temple Mount in Jerusalem, the site of Islam's third holiest shrine.</p>
<p>Clashes erupted in the West Bank towns of Bethlehem, Ramallah, Halhoul near Hebron, Nablus, Jenin, and Qalqilya, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Palestinians called a strike and Israel tightened its closure on the West Bank and Gaza in an attempt to thwart protests called in Jerusalem over the killing of five Arabs in Ramallah on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Three branches of Arafat's paramilitary police fired at Israeli jeeps from behind concrete blocks at a checkpoint near Kfar Darom settlement in the centre of the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>&quot;Stop throwing stones, this will not help now,&quot; a Palestinian officer shouted. His words were drowned out by the crackle of automatic rifle fire from members of Arafat's Preventive Security force and the Coastguard.</p>
<p>At least one Palestinian policeman was killed and one wounded. Among the four killed in Gaza was a girl aged between 14 and 16 years, health officials said.</p>
<p>Hundreds of youths also stoned Israeli soldiers guarding nearby Netzarim settlement and the Gush Katif bloc of settlements in the south of the Strip.</p>
<p>The Israelis responded with live ammunition, rubber bullets and teargas.</p>
<p>Palestinian police then returned fire in a replay of the gunbattle in Ramallah in which three Palestinian police were killed on Wednesday. No Israelis were killed in that battle.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers abandoned their checkpoint near Netzarim under the hail of stones. Palestinians moved over fields to try to get near to the settlement fence. Netzarim is an isolated enclave south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>Israel handed Gaza over to the PLO in 1994 but some 3,000 Jews still live there in fortified enclaves on some 40 percent of the land. The army brought five armoured personnel carriers to the entrance of Netzarim and an army helicopter landed in the settlement.</p>
<p>The police came to bolster Arafat and ensure Israeli security after the PLO leader returned to Gaza in July 1994 at the start of a process that Palestinians hoped would lead to an independent state.</p>
<p>But Netanyahu's election victory thwarted that dream. The Likud leader is offering only functional Palestinian autonomy under overall Israeli control. Palestinian anger at Netanyahu's failure to extend self-rule in the West Bank and Gaza boiled over after his right-wing government decided to open a tunnel near the al-Aqsa and Dome of the Rock mosques.</p>
<p>Palestinians accuse Israel of trying to Judaise Arab East Jerusalem, which they consider to be illegally occupied by the Jewish state.</p>
<p>Israeli Defence Minister Yizhak Mordechai questioned the decision to open the tunnel. &quot;I don't know whether to say with finality that...all considerations were taken into account,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>The violence plunged relations between Arafat and Netanyahu into crisis. Netanyahu came to power exactly 100 days ago questioning the basis of the whole Middle East process -- that Israel should exchange captured Arab land for peace.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's aide, attorney Yitzhak Molho, met Arafat overnight to appeal for calm.</p>
<p>Israel's guardian ally Washington mounted a frantic diplomatic effort to defuse the confrontation. Secretary of State Warren Christopher expressed &quot;deep concern&quot; over the clashes and his spokesman urged the sides to avoid raising new issues that could scuttle fragile peace talks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
