<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="80283" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Shooting, protests spread in Gaza, West Bank.</title>
<headline>Shooting, protests spread in Gaza, West Bank.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gunbattles, stoning and demonstrations spread to the Gaza Strip on Thursday from the West Bank where Palestinians prepared to bury five Arabs killed by Israelis soldiers in protests over Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Two Palestinians were shot dead and more than 50 people were wounded, including an Israeli army officer, in clashes outside Jewish settlements in the PLO-ruled strip, hospital sources and the Israeli army said.</p>
<p>The death raised to six the number of Palestinians killed in two days of clashes over Israel's opening of a tunnel beside the Temple Mount in Jerusalem, the site of Islam's third holiest shrine.</p>
<p>Clashes also erupted in the West Bank towns of Bethlehem, Halhoul near Hebron, Jenin, and Qalqilya, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Palestinians called a strike and Israel tightened its closure on the West Bank and Gaza in an attempt to thwart protests called in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Hundreds of youths stoned Israeli soldiers guarding settlements in the Gush Katif bloc in the south of the Gaza Strip and at Netzarim and Kfar Darom in the centre.</p>
<p>The Israelis responded with live ammunition, rubber bullets and teargas. Palestinian police then returned fire in a replay of the gunbattle in the West Bank town of Ramallah in which three Palestinian police were killed on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers abandoned their checkpoint near Netzarim under the hail of stones. Palestinians moved over fields to try to get near to the settlement fence. Netzarim is an isolated enclave south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>Israel handed Gaza over to the PLO in 1994 but some 3,000 Jews still live there in fortified enclaves on some 40 percent of the land. The army brought five armoured personnel carriers to the entrance of Netzarim and an army helicopter landed in the settlement.</p>
<p>Shifa hospital in Gaza said Palestinians Hani Moussa, 18, and Rizk Hawajreh, 32, were shot dead in a clash near Kfar Darom. The Israeli army said the officer, a lieutenant-colonel, was moderately wounded by a gunshot in the clash. It was not immediately clear which side fired the shot that wounded the officer.</p>
<p>At Kfar Darom, gunfire could be heard in the background while Israel Radio broadcast a live interview with a woman settler there. She said the gunfire came from the Israeli side.</p>
<p>&quot;Stones were thrown into the settlement. What you are hearing is about 200 metres from the house. Our children are in the houses...We have two wounded. One was taken to hospital by helicopter. The second is being treated on the spot,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The serious problem is that the Palestinians are taking care of this...It doesn't work.&quot;</p>
<p>Palestinian anger at Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's failure to extend self-rule in the West Bank and Gaza boiled over after his right-wing government decided to open a tunnel near the al-Aqsa and Dome of the Rock mosques.</p>
<p>Palestinians accuse Israel of trying to Judaise Arab East Jerusalem, which they consider to be illegally occupied by the Jewish state.</p>
<p>Israeli Defence Minister Yizhak Mordechai questioned the decision to open the tunnel.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know whether to say with finality that...all considerations were taken into account,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>The violence plunged relations between Palestinian President Yasser Arafat and Netanyahu into crisis.</p>
<p>Netanyahu came to power exactly 100 days ago questioning the basis of the whole Middle East process -- that Israel should exchange captured Arab land for peace.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's aide, attorney Yitzhak Molho, met Arafat overnight to appeal for calm.</p>
<p>Israel's guardian ally Washington mounted a frantic diplomatic effort to defuse the confrontation. Secretary of State Warren Christopher expressed &quot;deep concern&quot; over the clashes and his spokesman urged the sides to avoid raising new issues that could scuttle fragile peace talks.</p>
<p>The stone-throwing and tyre-burning brought back memories of the 1987-93 uprising or intifada but with one difference -- the presence of 30,000 armed Palestinian police in self-rule areas.</p>
<p>The police came to bolster Arafat and ensure Israeli security after the PLO leader returned to Gaza in July 1994 at the start of a process that Palestinians hoped would lead to an independent state.</p>
<p>But Netanyahu's election victory thwarted that dream. The Likud leader is offering only functional Palestinian autonomy under overall Israeli control.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, on a European trip, told a rally of French supporters of his right-wing Likud party that Arafat &quot;should calm passions and not inflame them. He should return to the negotiating table and not preach violence.&quot;</p>
<p>Senior Israeli defence officials, meeting in emergency session in Netanyahu's absence, ordered the West Bank and Gaza Strip sealed off immediately and &quot;until further notice&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
