<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81474" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israelis kill 3 at al-Aqsa, Netanyahu unbending.</title>
<headline>Israelis kill 3 at al-Aqsa, Netanyahu unbending.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli forces killed three Palestinian protesters and wounded 50 at Jerusalem's al-Aqsa mosque on Friday in a third day of violence that threatens to derail Washington's Middle East peacemaking.</p>
<p>Gun battles and stone-throwing flared throughout the West Bank and Gaza Strip despite the efforts of Palestinian police to restrain demonstrators, and the presence of Israeli tanks and extra troops.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, at a combative news conference, blamed Palestinian President Yasser Arafat for the violence.</p>
<p>Palestinians, backed by Arab and widespread international opinion, accused the right-wing Israeli leader of triggering the unprecedented fighting by opening a tunnel near the mosque.</p>
<p>In New York, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher planned to meet Israeli, Egyptian and Syrian foreign ministers as the United States kept up furious telephone diplomacy to try to end the fighting which has killed 53 Palestinians and 14 Israeli soldiers.</p>
<p>The United Nations Security Council on Friday met to discuss the violence amid fears that Washington's five-year-old regional peace policy could collapse.</p>
<p>The leaders of France, Britain and Germany made an unprecedented joint appeal to Netanyahu and Arafat to meet immediately.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said he would consider an invitation from Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to meet Arafat in Cairo. Arafat has turned down Netanyahu's invitation to a one-to-one summit. Both men met for the first time earlier this month in Gaza.</p>
<p>But the Likud leader was unrepentant about his decision to open the archaeological tunnel that runs beneath the Wailing Wall, the Herodian retaining wall of the ruined Second Jewish Temple, now Islam's third holiest site.</p>
<p>Critics in Israel and abroad called it a miscalculation, given popular Palestinian frustration with the peace process that has brought few tangible political or economic benefits.</p>
<p>Netanyahu repeated his contention that Arafat &quot;cynically&quot; used the tunnel as an excuse to stir up Arab passions against Israel and force his government into peace concessions.</p>
<p>Western diplomats said they were dismayed at Netanyahu's strident tone and inflexibility at the news conference.</p>
<p>Netanyahu was flanked by army and intelligence chiefs, one of whom said Israel would use tanks if needed to quell unrest.</p>
<p>Witnesses reported stone-trowing and armed clashes at Rafah in the southern Gaza Strip and in the West Bank towns of Jenin, Bethlehem, Jericho and Tulkarm.</p>
<p>In Jerusalem's walled Old City, a focus of the 100-year-old Arab-Jewish conflict, Israeli paramilitary police stormed on to the Temple Mount to disperse stone-throwers with bullets and teargas. Israeli forces last fired at Arab protesters on the Temple Mount, known to Moslems as Haram al-Sharif, in October 1990, killing 17 Palestinians.</p>
<p>&quot;There was massive stone-throwing at our forces,&quot; Israeli police commissioner Assaf Hefetz said of the al-Aqsa clash in which five of his men were wounded by rocks. &quot;There was no choice but to finish dealing with the demonstrators.&quot;</p>
<p>At an entrance to the West Bank town of Tulkarm, two Israeli paramilitary policemen and a Palestinian were killed during a gun battle, Israeli security sources said.</p>
<p>Two Palestinian were killed and 11 wounded in PLO-ruled Jericho when they stormed an Israeli army post, witnesses said. Demonstrators also attacked the Israeli Nahal Oz checkpoint in the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Palestinian police seemed unable to control the protesters, witnesses said. The did, however, prevent youths from attacking an Israeli checkpoint at Ramallah, north of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>PLO sources said Netanyahu telephoned Arafat at U.S. prompting overnight before the Jerusalem violence. The two leaders agreed that they should try to calm the situation.</p>
<p>But they could not agree on a summit.</p>
<p>Arafat favours a meeting under Egyptian auspices in Cairo, but Netanyahu does not want a three-way summit, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Arafat has ordered his 30,000-strong paramilitary police to fire only in self-defence, but when Israeli soldiers fire at stone-throwers the police respond. Voice of Palestine Radio called on Palestinians to hold peaceful demonstrations on Friday but the situation quickly spun out of control.</p>
<p>Israel too put soldiers along its border with the West Bank, deployed 4,000 police in Jerusalem and sent more tanks to the outskirts of Palestinian towns.</p>
<p>PLO officials said Arafat would have little success in quelling the violence unless assured that Netanyahu would commit Israel at the meeting to implementing the peace deals of the government he ousted in May.</p>
<p>In almost identical letters to Netanyahu and Arafat on Friday President Jacques Chirac, Prime Minister John Major and Chancellor Helmut Kohl said: &quot;We are sending you a joint, solemn appeal to make the necessary calming gestures.&quot;</p>
<p>The three main west European powers called for &quot;an immediate resumption of negotiations at the highest level&quot; and the full implementation of agreements already reached between Israel and the PLO on extending self-rule in the West Bank and Gaza, and redeploying Israeli troops in Hebron</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
