<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82164" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israelis kill three Palestinians at al-Aqsa mosque.</title>
<headline>Israelis kill three Palestinians at al-Aqsa mosque.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli security forces stormed Jerusalem's al-Aqsa mosque complex to disperse stone-throwers on Friday, killing at least three Palestinians and wounding 50, witnesses and hospital sources said.</p>
<p>Violence also flared for a third straight day in the West Bank and Gaza in protest at Israel's opening of a tourist tunnel adjacent to al-Aqsa and the Dome of the Rock mosques, Islam's third holiest site.</p>
<p>Israeli forces last fired at Arab protesters on the Temple Mount in October 1990, killing 17 Palestinians.</p>
<p>The current fighting, an expression of Palestinians' deep frustration with Israel's new right-wing government, further undermined the entire Middle East peace process.</p>
<p>At an entrance to the West Bank town of Tulkarm, an Israeli paramilitary policeman was killed during a gun battle between Israelis and Palestinian police, Israeli security sources said.</p>
<p>One Palestinian was killed and 12 Arabs were wounded, two seriously, in PLO-ruled Jericho when they stormed an Israeli army post, witnesses said. Demonstrators also attacked the Israeli Nahal Oz checkpoint in the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Palestinian police seemed unable to control the protesters, witnesses said.</p>
<p>At least 50 Palestinians and 12 Israeli soldiers have been killed since Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu opened the tunnel on Tuesday. Netanyahu was elected in May on a promise to ensure greater security.</p>
<p>The United States has been working frantically to arrange a meeting between Netanyahu and Palestinian President Yasser Arafat to salvage its five-year-old Middle East peace drive.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has rebuffed U.S. suggestions he close the tunnel, which Palestinians and Moslems say is an attempt by Israel to tighten its grip on Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Netanyahu denies any political motivation behind the tunnel, which runs beneath the Wailing Wall, the Herodian retaining wall of the ruined Second Jewish Temple, now a Moslem site.</p>
<p>Each side blamed the other for the fighting. Israel has sent tanks and helicopters into the West Bank and declared a state of emergency there.</p>
<p>PLO sources said Netanyahu telephoned Arafat at U.S. prompting overnight before the Jerusalem violence. The two leaders agreed that they should try to calm the situation.</p>
<p>But they could not agree on a summit.</p>
<p>Arafat favours a meeting under Egyptian auspices in Cairo, but Netanyahu does not want a three-way summit, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Arafat has ordered his 30,000-strong paramilitary police to fire only in self-defence, but when Israeli soldiers fire at stone-throwers the police respond. Voice of Palestine Radio called on Palestinians to hold peaceful demonstrations on Friday but the situation quickly spun out of control.</p>
<p>Israel too put soldiers along its border with the West Bank, deployed 4,000 police in Jerusalem and sent more tanks to the outskirts of Palestinian towns.</p>
<p>PLO officials said Arafat would have little success in quelling the violence unless assured that Netanyahu would commit Israel at the meeting to implementing the peace deals of the government he ousted in May.</p>
<p>Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak tried to arrange a three-way meeting in Cairo and Netanyahu spoke with him twice by telephone from the security cabinet meeting in Jerusalem on Thursday night.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called for a halt to the fighting and a resumption of talks.</p>
<p>Palestinian peace negotiator Saeb Erekat urged Clinton to convene an international summit to save the peace process.</p>
<p>&quot;We call on all world nations to intervene. It's time for President Clinton, and this will not affect his election campaign, to call for a conference...to salvage the peace process and to stop the massacre of the Palestinian people,&quot; Erekat told Reuters.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, 46, had angered Arabs and Palestinians by opposing the policy of swapping occupied land for peace which had been the basis of U.S.-brokered peace talks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
