<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82907" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel readies for Palestinian protests.</title>
<headline>Israel readies for Palestinian protests.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel placed police and soldiers along its border with the West Bank and sent reinforcements to Jerusalem on Friday as Palestinians prepared to bury their dead from fighting that has undermined Middle East peace.</p>
<p>Israel blamed the Palestinian Authority for two days of gun battles in which more than 50 people died, while the two sides sought a summit to try to salvage five years of U.S.-driven peacemaking.</p>
<p>Palestinians accused Israel of provoking the bloodshed by opening a tunnel beside the Dome of the Rock and al-Aqsa mosque complex in Jerusalem's walled Old City.</p>
<p>Police closed roads around the Old City ahead of Moslem Friday prayers at the mosque.</p>
<p>&quot;We are ready for anything,&quot; Israel's Chief of Staff General Amnon Shahak said.</p>
<p>&quot;Today in every place that there are Palestinians with weapons, even if it starts with stone-throwing, it's pretty clear that it will end in shooting,&quot; Shahak told Israel Radio.</p>
<p>Thousands of Palestinians demonstrated in Khan Younis, in the south of the PLO-ruled Gaza Strip on Friday morning. Some fired into the air but there were no reports of clashes with Israelis guarding nearby Jewish settlements.</p>
<p>Arafat has ordered his 30,000-strong paramilitary police to fire only in self-defence. Palestinian protests could erupt after the funerals of the 39 Arabs killed on Thursday. Eleven Israel soldiers were also killed on Thursday.</p>
<p>Voice of Palestine Radio called on Palestinians to hold peaceful demonstrations on Friday.</p>
<p>Protests in Arab East Jerusalem, which includes the Old City, have been more muted than in the rest of the West Bank and Gaza Strip because Palestinians have been prevented from reaching the city by an Israeli closure. But police were on alert for disturbances after midday prayers. Arabs inside Israel also plan protests for Friday.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu telephoned Yasser Arafat after a marathon cabinet meeting early on Friday and blamed the Palestinian president for the bloodshed, Israel Radio said. Netanyahu told Arafat he bore &quot;full responsibility for the bloodshed and for the future of the political process.&quot;</p>
<p>PLO officials said Arafat would have little success in quelling the violence unless assured that Netanyahu would commit Israel at the meeting to implementing the peace deals of the government he ousted in May.</p>
<p>Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak tried to arrange a three-way meeting in Cairo and Netanyahu spoke with him twice by telephone from the security cabinet meeting in Jerusalem on Thursday night.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called for a halt to the fighting and a resumption of talks. U.S. diplomats in Israel were working intensively behind the scenes to arrange an Arafat-Netanyahu meeting.</p>
<p>Palestinian peace negotiator Saeb Erekat urged Clinton to convene an international summit to save the peace process.</p>
<p>&quot;We call on all world nations to intervene. It's time for President Clinton, and this will not affect his election campaign, to call for a conference...to salvage the peace process and to stop the massacre of the Palestinian people,&quot; Erekat told Reuters.</p>
<p>He urged Netanyahu to close the tunnel, which Palestinians view as an attempt by Israel to tighten its grip on occupied East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Washington, Israel's closest ally, has also asked Netanyahu to close the tunnel, but the Israeli leader seemed opposed, telling Secretary of State Warren Christopher in a phone call that it would reward violence, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, 46, had angered Arabs and Palestinians by opposing the policy of swapping occupied land for peace which had been the basis of U.S.-brokered peace talks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
