<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83264" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Diplomacy edges out violence in Gaza, West Bank.</title>
<headline>Diplomacy edges out violence in Gaza, West Bank.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinian police kept a lid on protests in most of the West Bank and Gaza on Saturday while U.S. and U.N. officials tried to organise a PLO-Israeli summit to prevent more violence from threatening Middle East peace.</p>
<p>Almost 70 people have been killed in four days of unrest sparked by the opening of a new entrance to an archaeological tunnel beside a Moslem holy site in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources said mediators were working on a seven-point plan, which included trying to arrange a meeting soon between Palestinian President Yasser Arafat and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.</p>
<p>A senior U.S. administration official in the United States said they were offering to host a summit in Washington between Arafat and Netanyahu. &quot;It's one of several ideas that have been presented,&quot; the official added.</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources said the plan was that first Arafat and Netanyahu would meet at an unspecified location, and then they would meet in Washington together with President Bill Clinton, Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak and King Hussein of Jordan.</p>
<p>The proposals, the details of which have not yet been agreed, deal with issues beyond the present Arafat-Netanyahu stand-off over the archaeological tunnel, the sources said.</p>
<p>The package would include an Israeli commitment to resume implementing Palestinian self-rule agreements and redeploy Israeli troops in Hebron.</p>
<p>The delay in self-rule stoked Palestinian anger, which boiled over into violence on Wednesday after the Israelis opened an entrance to the the tunnel in Jerusalem's Moslem Quarter.</p>
<p>On Saturday night Netanyahu vowed never to close the tunnel, telling cheering Christian supporters in Jerusalem: &quot;The tunnel has been around for 2,000 years...It will stay open. It will always be open.&quot;</p>
<p>He added: &quot;This tunnel is 250 metres (yards), a quarter of a kilometre, from the nearest mosque...We believe in the freedom of all three great faiths...That was, is and will always remain our policy.&quot;</p>
<p>In Tel Aviv, thousands of Israelis atttended a rally at the same time urging Netanyahu to pursue peace and Arafat to stop Palestinian police from firing on Israeli soldiers. Organisers estimated a crowd of 20,000 attended.</p>
<p>During the day Palestinian police in riot gear stopped hundreds of youths from marching on an Israeli checkpoint at Ramallah, north of Jerusalem, scene of some of the fiercest fighting in which nearly 70 people had killed in four days.</p>
<p>They also thwarted protests in the West Bank town of Qalqilya and at Rafah in the Gaza Strip, witnesses said.</p>
<p>U.S. Consul General in Jerusalem, Edward Abington, met Arafat in Gaza and urged him to meet Netanyahu. Terje Larsen, the U.N. coordinator in Gaza, also met Arafat and Netanyahu to work on the seven-point framework, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's spokesman Shai Bazak said the Israeli leader was ready in principle to meet Arafat but added: &quot;I don't know of any plan such as this.&quot;</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources said Netanyahu had rejected an offer by Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to host the summit in Cairo. Arafat will not meet Netanyahu alone without a prior guarantee that the tunnel entrance will be sealed. The tunnel is scheduled to reopen to the public on Sunday after the Jewish sabbath.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's decision to open the tunnel brought widespread international condemnation and raised eyebrows in the Clinton administration, which is usually supportive of Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;Our demands are clear. We want them to close the tunnel, put the peace process back on track, and immediately implement the Oslo accords,&quot; Arafat's aide Nabil Abu Rdainah said.</p>
<p>Smouldering Palestinian frustration with Netanyahu's foot-dragging on the 1993 Oslo self-rule agreement, which includes a partial Israeli troop withdrawal in Hebron, ignited by the tunnel controversy.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has accused Arafat of &quot;cynically&quot; exploiting the tunnel issue and instigating the violence. Palestinians called the tunnel's opening an assault on Islamic shrines and an Israeli attempt to &quot;Judaise&quot; Arab East Jerusalem, occupied by Israel in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
<p>&quot;Keeping the tunnel open means pushing the whole region towards irresponsible violence,&quot; the PLO said in the statement.</p>
<p>Arafat ordered his 30,000-strong paramilitary force to rein in demonstrators and not to shoot at Israelis unless fired upon.</p>
<p>Youths clashed, however, for a fourth straight day with Israeli troops. Palestinians said 30 people were wounded. Soldiers fired rubber-coated metal bullets and threw percussion grenades at stone-throwers at Kalandia refugee camp between Jerusalem and Ramallah.</p>
<p>In the villages of Halhoul and Beit Umar near Hebron soldiers fired teargas and rubber bullets at Palestinians who burned tyres and blocked roads.</p>
<p>Palestinian demonstrators came to the rescue of four Israeli police injured when their jeep overturned in East Jerusalem while on the way to quell an Arab protest in nearby Jabal al-Mukaber village, witnesses said.Palestinians gave the soldiers water and helped them to ambulances, they added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
