<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83267" id="root" date="1996-09-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Palestinian police rein in protesters.</title>
<headline>Palestinian police rein in protesters.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinian police kept a lid on protests in most of the West Bank and Gaza on Saturday while the United States tried to arrange a PLO-Israeli summit to prevent a resurgence of violence threatening Middle East peace.</p>
<p>Palestinian police in riot gear prevented hundreds of youths from marching on an Israeli checkpoint at Ramallah, north of Jerusalem, scene of some of the fiercest fighting in the past four days which has claimed nearly 70 lives.</p>
<p>They also thwarted protests in the West Bank town of Qalilia and at Rafah in the Gaza Strip, witnesses said.</p>
<p>U.S. diplomats met Palestinian President Yasser Arafat in Gaza urging him to meet Israel's right-wing Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.</p>
<p>The two leaders are locked in a stand-off over an archaeological tunnel near Moslem shrines in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's decision to open a second entrance to the tunnel from Jerusalem's Moslem Quarter sparked the violence, brought widespread international condemnation and raised eyebrows in the Clinton administration, which is usually supportive of Israel.</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources said Netanyahu had rejected an offer by Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to host the summit in Cairo. Arafat will not meet Netanyahu alone without a prior guarantee that the tunnel entrance will be sealed. The tunnel, which Israel closed on Friday citing security reasons, is scheduled to reopen on Sunday after the Jewish sabbath.</p>
<p>&quot;Our demands are clear. We want them to close the tunnel, put the peace process back on track, and immediately implement the Oslo accords,&quot; Arafat aide, Nabil Abu Rdainah said.</p>
<p>Smouldering Palestinian frustration with Netanyahu's foot-dragging on the Oslo self-rule agreement, which includes a partial Israeli troop withdrawal in Hebron, ignited when he opened the tunnel beside the al-Aqsa and Dome of the Rock mosques.</p>
<p>Since then U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher and his Middle East coordinator Dennis Ross have made dozens of phone calls to Netanyahu, Arafat, Mubarak and other key leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;The Israelis want a bilateral meeting, we welcome a three-way meeting in Cairo and the Americans are working hard to convene a meeting attended by either Christopher or Ross,&quot; Abu Rdainah added.</p>
<p>Arafat said the meeting would take place but did not specify a time.</p>
<p>&quot;I will meet him (Netanyahu) in Cairo,&quot; Arafat told reporters in self-ruled Gaza.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has accused Arafat of &quot;cynically&quot; exploiting the tunnel issue and instigating the violence. Palestinians called the tunnel's opening an assault on Islamic holy shrines and an Israeli attempt to &quot;Judaise&quot; Arab East Jerusalem, occupied by Israel in 1967.</p>
<p>&quot;Keeping the tunnel open means pushing the whole region towards irresponsible violence,&quot; the PLO said in the statement.</p>
<p>Arafat has ordered his 30,000-strong paramilitary force to rein in demonstrators and not to shoot at Israelis unless fired upon.</p>
<p>Youths clashed, however, for a fourth straight day with Israeli troops. Palestinians said 30 people were wounded. Soldiers fired rubber-coated metal bullets and threw percussion grenades at stone-throwers at Kalandia refugee camp between Jerusalem and Ramallah.</p>
<p>In the villages of Halhoul and Beit Umar near Hebron soldiers fired teargas and rubber bullets at Palestinians who burned tyres and blocked roads.</p>
<p>Palestinian demonstrators came to the rescue of four Israeli police injured when their jeep overturned in East Jerusalem while on the way to quell an Arab protest in nearby Jabal al-Mukaber village, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Palestinians gave the soldiers water and helped them to ambulances, they added.</p>
<p>Israeli security forces had earlier shot and wounded three Palestinians in Jabal al-Mukaber.</p>
<p>Palestinians in the West Bank observed a general strike to mourn the 54 victims killed in clashes. Fourteen Israeli soldiers have died.</p>
<p>The Palestinian health minister accused Israel of preventing medical personnel and supplies from reaching wounded Arabs.</p>
<p>Riyad al-Zaanoun compiled a list of incidents in which he said Israel had fired at Palestinian ambulances, blocked the evacuation of wounded and refused to allow medical supplies to pass through areas under Israeli control. He said one medic was killed and a number had been wounded while treating victims.</p>
<p>&quot;Israeli soldiers in Ramallah threw quantities of medical supplies in the street,&quot; Zaanoun told Reuters. &quot;These supplies were supposed to be distributed to West Bank hospitals and clinics.&quot; The Israeli army said it was checking the report.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
