<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="83804" id="root" date="1996-09-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Clinton calls PLO-Israeli meeting, tunnel reopens.</title>
<headline>Clinton calls PLO-Israeli meeting, tunnel reopens.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel agreed to President Bill Clinton's call on Sunday for a summit with Arab leaders in Washington to end violence but the tunnel in Jerusalem that sparked the fighting with the Palestinians was reopened.</p>
<p>Clinton, fearing his Middle East peace policy could unravel five weeks before the U.S. presidential election, announced the summit before receiving formal notice the Palestinians and Egyptians would attend.</p>
<p>Clinton said he had called Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Palestinian President Yasser Arafat to the meeting that U.S. officials said would be on Tuesday and would includ Jordan.</p>
<p>Diplomats said the United States had not secured agreement on the main issues to ensure that the summit would be a success.</p>
<p>Arafat was trying to convince Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to attend, PLO officials said. Arafat wants Egypt as a counterweight to the United States, Israel's ally.</p>
<p>&quot;Clinton has telephoned Arafat and invited him officially to Washington. Arafat insisted on the participation of Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak,&quot; a PLO official told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Clinton and Arafat agreed to continue contacts with Mubarak to convince him to attend. Arafat will leave for Cairo tomorrow for this purpose.&quot;</p>
<p>Egyptian Foreign Minister Amr Moussa said in Washington on Sunday Mubarak was reluctant to go unless there were clear goals and Israel was prepared to honour previous peace deals with the Palestinians.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said hoped the summit would lead to accelerated peace talks with the Palestinians.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to achieve two things in this meeting: a renewed commitment to end violence and renewed acceleration of the peace process,&quot; he told Israeli television stations.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's cabinet secretary, Danny Naveh, said no prior understandings were reached before Israel agreed to attend.</p>
<p>The U.S. diplomatic drive came against a backdrop of continued tension in the West Bank and Gaza Strip. Fifty-five Palestinians and 14 Israeli soldiers have died in clashes since Israel opened the tunnel last Tuesday.</p>
<p>Israeli officials have raised the spectre of disarming Palestinian police if gunbattles resumed. More Israeli tanks moved into positions around PLO-ruled areas of the West Bank and Gaza, witnesses said. Palestinian police said they were closely watching the Israeli moves which they saw as sabre-rattling.</p>
<p>Security sources said Israel had implemented the first phase of &quot;Operation Field of Thorns&quot;, a plan whose final third stage is the retaking of West Bank and Gaza areas handed over to Arafat under the 1993 Oslo self-rule agreement.</p>
<p>The sources said the army had no intention at present of implementing the final phase, which would amount to a war with Arafat's more than 30,000 lightly armed police.</p>
<p>Palestinian stone-throwers clashed with Israeli soldiers in sporadic unrest but the West Bank and Gaza were quieter than they have been since Netanyahu opened the archaeological tunnel which Palestinians see as an illegal act on occupied land and an assault on Moslem holy places.</p>
<p>Youths hurled stones when the tunnel's new second entrance from the Old City's Moslem Quarter was re-opened after the Jewish sabbath. The protests were quickly quelled by police.</p>
<p>Many foreign governments and the Israeli opposition parties have called Netanyahu's move a blunder that Arafat has exploited to shore up his standing among Palestinians, deeply frustrated with Oslo and Israeli foot-dragging on implementing self-rule.</p>
<p>The United States, however, has tried to shield its ally. It cast the lone abstention when the 14 other members of the U.N. Security Council called for ensuring the safety of Palestinian civilians and for the immediate resumption of the Middle East peace process on Saturday.</p>
<p>Netanyahu aide David Bar-Illan said Israel should consider disarming Palestinian police if fighting resumes.</p>
<p>&quot;For now we aren't thinking of that. But if such things will continue and such incidents will recur, we will have to think about that also,&quot; Bar-Illan told Israel Radio.</p>
<p>Bar-Illan said Israel would also have to rethink its long-delayed handover of parts of the West Bank city of Hebron to Palestinian rule in light of the gunfights that erupted between its soldiers and Palestinian police.</p>
<p>On the Tel Aviv Stock Exchange, shares continued to fall. &quot;Events had a very negative impact on investors and most of them are sitting on the fence,&quot; said a trader at Israel's Bank Leumi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
