<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85987" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Jordan's King off to Washington for Mideast summit.</title>
<headline>Jordan's King off to Washington for Mideast summit.</headline>
<byline>Rana Sabbagh</byline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan's King Hussein, the only Arab leader who has so far accepted a U.S. invitation to an Arab-Israeli summit, left for Washington on Monday to attend the meeting, sparked by bloody Palestinian-Israeli clashes.</p>
<p>He telephoned Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak and Palestinian leader Yasser Arafat late on Sunday to agree on a &quot;common outlook&quot; on the summit with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamion Netanyahu, planned for Tuesday and Wednesday, Jordanian officials said.</p>
<p>But there were strong doubts on whether Arafat and Mubarak would attend the summit.</p>
<p>Arafat flew to see Mubarak in Egypt and PLO officials said Arafat had asked U.S. President Bill Clinton to postpone the summit with Netanyhau until differences over the agenda were settled, including demands that Israel close a tunnel near Moslem holy sites in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Mubarak and Arafat have been reluctant to go, on suspicion that Clinton and Netanyahu will not give the Arabs credible guarantees that Israel will carry out old agreements.</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources in Cairo said that unless Netanyahu backed down on his refusal to reach any agreement before the summit, it was hard to see how Arafat and Mubarak could attend.</p>
<p>The Mubarak-Arafat stand amounts to a revolt against Washington unprecedented since the United States brought Israel and its Arab neighbours together at the 1991 Madrid conference.</p>
<p>Palestinian officials said an all-night meeting between Palestinians, Israelis, U.S. and U.N. officials failed to solve problems over what the summit would discuss.</p>
<p>Clinton called the summit to end unrest sparked by Israel's opening of the tunnel - which killed nearly 70 people and endangered five-years of U.S. Middle East peacemaking.</p>
<p>Jordanian officials said before the king left Amman, his Prime Minister Abdul-Karim al-Kabariti sent a &quot;strongly-worded letter&quot; to Netanyahu, blaming him for the unrest.</p>
<p>Kabariti, who handed the letter to Israel's ambassador to Jordan, accused Israel of not honouring articles in its 1994 peace treaty with Jordan which recognised Amman's &quot;special role&quot; in Moslem shrines in Arab East Jerusalem, the officials added.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr. Kabariti said that Jordan, which adheres to all articles of the treaty, expects likewise from the government of Israel, especially articles that talk of respecting Jordan's supervision of the holy Moslem sites in the Holy City,&quot; added a prime ministry statement faxed to Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;He also affirmed Jordan's long-held stand which rejects any unilateral Israeli actions that aim at changing the cultural, religious and demographic aspects of the (disputed) Holy City and that serve to crystallise Israel's allegations of sovereignty and control over Holy Jerusalem.&quot;</p>
<p>King Hussein ruled the West Bank and Arab Jerusalem from 1950 until losing it to Israel in the 1967 Middle East War. He still pays for the upkeep of Moslem shrines in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>A 1993 peace pact between Israel and the Palestinians said the fate of Jerusalem will be determined in final status negotiations, which were due to begin in May. The talks were put on hold after Netanyahu's election in May.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has ruled to make any concessions on Arab East Jerusalem to Palestinians, who regard the city as a capital for their future independent Palestinian state.</p>
<p>Kabariti urged Netanyahu to implement all past deals reached with the PLO, including the redeployment of Israeli troops from the West Bank town of Hebron, lifting a ban on the movement of Palestinians and stopping Jewish settlement expansion policies.</p>
<p>&quot;Lack of implementation of all these issues reflects negatively on the hopes of the people of this region towards achieving peace,&quot; said the prime ministry's statement.</p>
<p>Jordan, which has a population largely of Palestinian origin, became Israel's closest friend in the Arab world after making peace with the former Labour-led government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
