<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13217" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: FOCUS-Tenaga seen moving to non-gas power.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Tenaga seen moving to non-gas power.</headline>
<byline>Christina Pantin</byline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia's electric utility, bucking a trend in many other parts of the world, has decided to reduce its reliance on cleaner-burning natural gas after a major blackout, but analysts say any changes will be gradual.</p>
<p>Citing gas turbine plants as a key factor in the crippling 12-15 hour power outage in peninsula Malaysia on August 3, Tenaga Nasional Bhd has recommended that the proportion of electricity generated from such stations be cut.</p>
<p>The incident, the country's second major blackout in four years, triggered official outrage and embarrassment in the fast-growing country which is seeking more foreign investment.</p>
<p>Malaysia is hiring a foreign consultant to review the utility's operations and has replaced its executive chairman.</p>
<p>Prior to the blackout, gas turbines generated 62.9 percent or 3,622 MW of the 5,760 MW supplied to the national grid. Thermal power plants contributed 30.7 percent and hydro-electric power plants 6.4 percent.</p>
<p>Tenaga said in a report that a faulty component in a circuit breaker at a power station tripped a number of gas turbines and led to an automatic cut-off to the national transmission grid. The grid connects 23 power stations.  </p>
<p>&quot;The major concern to the utility, the industry and the nation with regards to the electricity supply system reliability is the high proportion of gas turbine generating units connected to the national grid,&quot; Tenaga said.</p>
<p>It added that the gas turbine units have &quot;unpredictable performance characterstics during system disturbance.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts said an effort to balance the mix of power generation has already begun, pointing to two coal-fired plants and the planned $5.5 billion 1,800 MW Bakun hydro-electric dam. All three are due to come on stream over the next few years.</p>
<p>&quot;The additions hereon are non-gas,&quot; said Azman Mokhtar, an analyst at UBS Research, noting that independent power producers like Powertek Bhd are looking also to upgrade their gas plants to combined cycle stations.</p>
<p>While Malaysia has been seeking to promote the use of gas as an abundant, clean and efficient energy source over the past decade, analysts note that the addition of Independent Power Producers (IPPs) in the past several years has boosted gas to 70 percent of the nation's fuel mix.</p>
<p>What Tenaga will probably do to de-emphasise its gas-heavy generation is to increase thermal and hydro power plants, said an analyst at a foreign research house.  </p>
<p>&quot;Coal fired plants are not as dirty as they used to be,&quot; he said. &quot;In the past where gas was only 20-30 percent (of capacity), they've suddenly jumped from that level very significantly.&quot;</p>
<p>But one industry analyst in Singapore said Tenaga seems to be blaming the gas and not the equipment for the blackout. He said it was surprising that gas turbines should be susceptible in Malaysia and not other countries.</p>
<p>&quot;I find it difficult to know what is going on given the fact that (Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad) about a month ago at the (Asia Oil &amp; Gas conference in Kuala Lumpur) said oil and gas demand was growing and how there was going to be a shift of Asian countries towards gas and presumably hydro.&quot;</p>
<p>Whether Tenaga can drastically change its operations may be out of its hands, analysts said.</p>
<p>Noting that the Malaysian government, as the majority shareholder, has a large say over the company's future, one Tenaga analyst said: &quot;The best Tenaga can do is to put in recommendations. The real crux is who is calling the shots.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
