<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="16007" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Columbia Gas looking at range of alliances.</title>
<headline>Columbia Gas looking at range of alliances.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Columbia Gas System, Inc is considering alliances or acquisitions covering a range of areas, including power generation, electricity marketing, natural gas transmission, and energy trading, CEO Oliver Richard said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We're probably looking at as many people as are looking at us,&quot; Richard said in an interview, declining to elaborate on which companies Columbia Gas was focusing on.</p>
<p>&quot;I've always said if you're not a combination company, you should act like one,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Restructuring of the electricity industry should offer new opportunities for building new natural gas-fired plants, acquiring existing plants or buying into a coal company.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very optimistic about whether or not there is a place for us in the unfolding electricity market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We might take an equity interest in new plants or plants we may buy into,&quot; he said, adding that the company could also set up its own energy commodity trading group or acquire a trading unit.  </p>
<p>Natural gas-fired power plants can be built more easily than other plants, which should give them an advantage in reacting to changes in power market demands, Richard said.</p>
<p>&quot;When they need that niche marketing, we can jump in,&quot; he said. &quot;I still think gas has a healthy upward on new load.&quot;</p>
<p>As electricity prices come down and competition increases from coal-fired power plant, Richard said that &quot;it might make sense for us to be a partner with a coal company.&quot;</p>
<p>Columbia Gas has no specific plans to enlarge transmission capacity beyond existing plans to expand its transportation and storage services by 500 million cubic feet a day.  </p>
<p>However, Richard said he would consider any opportunities that might arise with Trailblazer Pipeline in the Colorado area, which Columbia Gas co-owns with Enron Corp unit Northern Natural Gas Co and Occidental Petroleum Corp unit Natural Gas Pipeline Co of America.</p>
<p>Richard declined to predict how the company would do in the third quarter, when natural gas company earnings typically fall, except to say: &quot;I think we're shaping up OK.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
