<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17450" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. natgas demand could reach 30 Tcf in 2015 - GRI.</title>
<headline>U.S. natgas demand could reach 30 Tcf in 2015 - GRI.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Annual U.S. demand for natural gas should climb to 30.2 trillion cubic feet in 2015 from 21.6 Tcf in 1995, if technology for using natural gas continues to advance as it has over the last 20 years, the Gas Research Institute projected in a report released Tuesday.</p>
<p>While natural gas use is expected to grow in homes, offices, industry and utilities, demand from power generators is expected to grow the most, followed by industrial demand.</p>
<p>Gas demand for electric generation is seen rising to 6.4 Tcf by 2015, making up 21 percent of the gas market, from 3.4 Tcf or 16 percent of the market in 1995.  </p>
<p>Natural gas is expected to make up 27 percent of the total U.S. energy market in 2015 from 24 percent in 1995, but well below its peak of 32 percent in 1971.</p>
<p>In the unlikely event that technology failed to improve over the next twenty years, consumption of natural gas would fall to 19 percent of the total energy market, GRI projected.</p>
<p>&quot;If the investment levels fall off in research, particularly on the supply side ... then in fact we some concern in meeting what I see as an opportunity for the industry in the next 10 to 15 years,&quot; said GRI senior vice president David, Webb.  </p>
<p>The outlook for natural gas depended on restructuring of the electricity market opening new opportunities for gas. At the same time GRI officials said the industry could not afford to lose any share of residential or commercial demand.</p>
<p>&quot;The loss of even part of this large load would offset much of the potential gain in the industrial or power generation markets,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>Growth in power generation and industrial demand for gas is expected to keep a lid on gas prices. &quot;If prices don't remain competitive, the growth will not occur,&quot; the report said.  </p>
<p>GRI sees average gas prices in 1996 dollars increasing to $1.66 per million Btu in 2015 from $1.58 in 1995, with oil prices dipping to $17.05 from $17.64 over the same period.</p>
<p>U.S. gas production is expected to grow 44 percent to 26 Tcf by 2015 from 1995, with offshore production more than doubling to 11 Tcf.</p>
<p>&quot;Reserve additions per well in the Gulf of Mexico average almost 10 times that for the average onshore well in the 1997 projection,&quot; the report said, adding that by 2015, about 40 percent of the gas supply would depend on the availability of new technology.  </p>
<p>GRI's projections assumed gross domestic product would grow on average by 2.2 percent annually between 1995 and 2015, with inflation rising at an average 2.7 percent annually.</p>
<p>The institute, which is battling cuts in its research budget, is a research, development and commercialization organization whose members include natural gas pipeline companies, producers, distribution companies and municipal gas utilities.  </p>
<p>The 1997 baseline projections, used by GRI to help lay out its research strategy, were slightly higher than last year's outlook, largely because of a &quot;more optimistic outlook for gas supply and prices,&quot; group manager Paul Holtberg said at a news conference.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
