<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24789" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK extends gas deregulation as &quot;hard landing&quot; hits.</title>
<headline>UK extends gas deregulation as &quot;hard landing&quot; hits.</headline>
<byline>Sebastian Alison</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's fast-liberalising natural gas market takes another step forward on Sunday with the introduction of a stringent new code regulating market users.</p>
<p>Britain, which launches the second stage of its Network Code gas shipping rules at the weekend, is the first country in Europe to start deregulating its gas market. The rest of the continent is watching with interest.</p>
<p>&quot;It's incredibly high in the priority of every European utility to keep an eye on what's going on in the UK,&quot; said gas analyst Julian Kennedy at consultancy Wood Mackenzie.</p>
<p>Phase two of Britain's Network Code gas shipping rules, known as the &quot;hard landing&quot; for the tight conditions it applies, comes into force on September 1 with the possibility of stiff fines for companies which do not observe its terms.</p>
<p>But whether or not it is possible to tell if companies are honouring the terms depends on availability of accurate data about volumes of gas entering and leaving the system, and there are still many question marks about this.</p>
<p>&quot;Quality and timeliness of data are vital to the success of the hard landing,&quot; says Bob Bruce, of Eastern Natural Gas who is also the chairman of the Gas Forum Network Code Working Group. According to Bruce, data provision may not yet be sufficient to allow the code to work smoothly.</p>
<p>&quot;That fact is acknowledged by (industry regulator) Ofgas to be material to pipeline users' performance under the hard landing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Deregulation in the gas market so far means that any licensed company can deliver gas to any business using more than 2,500 therms a year. This compares with a typical household's consumption of 650 therms a year, and allows most small businesses to shop around.</p>
<p>And in one pilot region, the southwestern counties of Devon, Cornwall and Somerset, householders can already buy gas from any supplier. This scheme will be extended to cover the whole country by 1998.</p>
<p>But while there are now many competing gas suppliers, there is only one transporter: TransCo, the pipeline arm of British Gas Plc, and shortly to become a separate company as British Gas demerges.</p>
<p>And it is to regulate dealings between TransCo and shippers, or users of the National Transmission System (NTS) as the pipeline system is known, that the Network Code exists.</p>
<p>Its most important provision is that users of the National Transmission System must ensure that offtakes - gas leaving the system to customers - are balanced by inputs, or deliveries to the NTS at coastal landing points, known as beach terminals.</p>
<p>And under the hard landing this balancing must now be done daily. This is the main difference between the hard landing and the old &quot;soft landing&quot;, in force from March 1 until now, under which penalties have been applied monthly, so allowing participants ample time to correct imbalances.</p>
<p>Failure to balance will result in financial penalties. The more extreme the level of imbalance, the higher the penalty.</p>
<p>Wood Mackenzie's Kennedy said he doubted other countries would try to deregulate to the same extent as Britain, allowing liberalisation of the market right down to householders.</p>
<p>The Netherlands and Germany are taking the lead on deregulation eleswhere in Europe. The Netherlands published a White Paper discussing market liberalisation late last year, although no further progress has since been made and competition was only expected to apply to bulk deliveries.</p>
<p>And Germany's economics minister Guenter Rexrodt announced on Friday that Germany is preparing a bill to end regional monopolies for electricity and gas supplies. The bill is expected to be ready by September 25.</p>
<p>Kennedy says that competition in Germany is not expected to go further than the level of regional distribution companies, or for competition in deliveries to city gates, restricting it to bulk deliveries as in the Netherlands.</p>
<p>Gas is growing in importance in Europe's energy balance partly because of the huge availability of supply, with many new projects coming onstream in the next few years from Algeria, Russia, Norway, and Britain, and partly for environmental reasons.</p>
<p>European consumption is now around 377 billion cubic metres (bcm) a year, but availability will jump by 90 bcm by 1999.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
