<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27402" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: World gas supplies enough for 60-70 years, growing.</title>
<headline>World gas supplies enough for 60-70 years, growing.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Natural gas supplies are sufficient for current demand worldwide for between 60 and 70 years, and reserves are increasing all the time, a conference was told on Monday.</p>
<p>Kristian Hausken, senior vice president of Norway's Statoil, told a news conference at the International Energy Agency's third natural gas conference that over the last 10 years, gas reserves have risen sharply.</p>
<p>&quot;In the early 80s gas reserves stood at 50 years at then production levels. Now this has gone up to between 60 and 70 years as the industry continues to search for reserves and technology improves.&quot;</p>
<p>By comparison, oil reserves will last 40 years at current production levels, and coal supplies around 230 years, Hausken said.</p>
<p>&quot;But there are big regional differences, and gas is not always where the market is,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Reserves are concentrated in relatively remote areas such as western Siberia and the Middle East, while North America has only just over 10 years of remaining reserves. And demand in Asia and Europe is expected to grow significantly.</p>
<p>As a result, Hausken said, &quot;There will have to be a continued switch from indigenous production to export/import both for pipeline gas and liquefied natural gas (LNG).&quot;</p>
<p>At present, Hausken said, 82 percent of all gas produced is consumed in the country of production, with 13.5 percent exported by pipeline and 4.5 percent shipped abroad as LNG. So 18 percent of all gas is now traded internationally.</p>
<p>The potential shortfall in North American supplies will lead to increased imports soon.&quot;We can expect more imports from the south, especially Mexico, and in the future from Canada and perhaps even Greenland,&quot; Hausken said.</p>
<p>The conference was originally to have been held in the U.S., but the dramatic growth in the markets of Eastern Europe made Berlin a more natural choice.</p>
<p>Berlin's mayor, Eberhard Diepgen, put the city's role as a gas centre in context. The Soviet Union cut off its supply completely during the blockade of 1948, and Berlin produced gas from coal and oil.</p>
<p>It was only in the 1980s that direct gas supplies from Russia started. The city then built a huge gas holder to allow for uninterrupted deliveries in case of supply problems.</p>
<p>&quot;Now Berlin has united the two partial gas grids of the divided city,&quot; said Diepgen. &quot;We have repaired over 50,000 leaks and rehabilitated over 300 km of pipeline.&quot;</p>
<p>Berlin has emerged as a major gas player in its own right, with investment coming in from around the world and going out to developing gas markets in eastern Europe, he added.</p>
<p>Statoil's Hausken was upbeat about the future of gas. &quot;It's environmentally friendly, and this should imply that it will continue to take market share, especially in power generation. We will also see significant technological progress.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
