<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27441" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Gas as transport fuel needs incentives - Snam.</title>
<headline>Gas as transport fuel needs incentives - Snam.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Increased use of natural gas as a transport fuel depends on a much greater range of government incentives to boost its demand, a conference was told on Monday.</p>
<p>Ferdinando Russo of Italy's Snam told an International Energy Agency conference on natural gas that the development of gas for transport depended on its environmental advantages, and so technological developments already under way needed government support to prosper.</p>
<p>The market potential is gigantic, said Russo, pointing out that of 500 million vehicles in use worldwide, only just over a million are fuelled by gas.</p>
<p>Argentina leads the way, with 345,000 vehicles using 480 refuelling stations accounting for 4.6 percent market penetration. Italy has 290,000 gas-powered vehicles, but few other countries are seriously pursuing natural gas.</p>
<p>In New Zealand, 45,000 vehicles use it, in the U.S. 40,000 and in Canada, 38,000.</p>
<p>There are also indications that Russia has about 100,000 gas powered vehicles, down from a peak of around 250,000 in the whole Soviet Union immediately before its break up, said Russo, although accurate data is hard to obtain.</p>
<p>Further development is threatened by high equipment costs, heavy onboard gas storage units, reduced range in comparison with a gasoline engine, reduced power and limited refuelling options.</p>
<p>Set against this, gas is extremely clean burning. It has excellent anti-knock qualities and better cold start performance than a gasoline engine. It also offers longer engine life, safe and reliable use, and quiet performance, industry sources say.</p>
<p>Both BMW and Volvo already produce bi-fuel vehicles, Russo said.</p>
<p>Although transport fuel is a potential growth area for gas in the domestic and commercial - as opposed to heavy industrial - sectors, more growth is seen from traditional areas, he added.</p>
<p>These are space heating, the largest area, cooking and water heating, and, increasingly, space cooling.</p>
<p>Technology allowing gas-powered air conditioning is improving, said Russo, and the market is little developed.</p>
<p>While the penetration rate of air conditioning in the residential sector has reached 73 percent in Japan and 70 percent in the U.S., it is a mere nine percent in Spain and five percent in Italy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
