<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27845" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Russia's Gazprom to boost gas exports.</title>
<headline>Russia's Gazprom to boost gas exports.</headline>
<byline>Sebastian Alison</byline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russian state gas monopoly Gazprom will increase its exports of natural gas to European customers by 50 billion cubic metres (bcm) a year by 2010 as part of an ambitious expansion programme, a senior Gazprom official said on Monday.</p>
<p>A.D. Sedykh, head of the department of scientific and technical progress and ecology at Gazprom, told an International Energy Agency conference that the company had ambitious plans for the next 20 years.</p>
<p>Gazprom will produce 750 to 770 bcm of gas by 2005, and this will rise to 800 to 820 bcm by 2010, Sedykh said. This compares with output of 559.5 bcm last year.</p>
<p>Exports will also rise. Just to keep its current share of the European gas market, Gazprom sees exports needing to rise by 50 bcm by 2010. Last year sales of gas outside the former Soviet Union totalled 117.4 bcm, he said.</p>
<p>And still more gas can be produced. &quot;The level of gas production depends not on the production capacity, which already exceeds demand, but rather on the demand for gas on both domestic and foreign markets,&quot; Sedykh said.</p>
<p>To allow the extra export volumes, construction of the 4,000 km Yamal-Europe pipeline is under way, Sedykh said, stretching through Russia, Belarus and Poland to the German frontier.</p>
<p>Sedykh outlined a number of other areas in which Gazprom intends to develop.</p>
<p>The company plans to increase gas supply for transport needs, with a view to providing gas as a motor fuel for 15 to 20 percent of cars and other vehicles. A gas plant for producing high pressure polyethylene is under development in Urengoi, with a capacity of 700,000 tonnes a year.</p>
<p>A plant to produce methanol from natural gas is planned at Archangelsk, also with a capacity of 700,000 tonnes a year, and a 100,000 tonnes a year polyethylene plant is planned at Astrakhan, near the Caspian Sea.</p>
<p>Sedykh acknowledged that for the first time Gazprom now has full access to Western technology, which &quot;due to reasons associated with peculiarities of a planned economy&quot; were not previously available.</p>
<p>Gazprom plans to use new technology among other things to increase use of horizontal wells; to increase condensate recovery; to introduce energy saving technology in gas transportation; and to develop a unified gas supply network, by building new storage units and increasing the capacity of existing storage.</p>
<p>Sedykh said Gazprom was committed to development of liquefied petroleum gas (LPG), and currently supplies a fleet of 30,000 LPG-powered vehicles from 190 filling stations.</p>
<p>He said Russia's potential reserves stood at 212 trillion cubic metres (tcm), of which only 49 tcm have been explored. The main centre of gas production was set to remain in western Siberia &quot;for many years to come.&quot;</p>
<p>Gazprom produces 94 percent of Russia's gas, and transports virtually all of it. It also owns all assets of the whole spectrum of activity from drilling wells to supplying customers.</p>
<p>As well as total exports of 180 bcm a year, Gazprom also produces 7.8 million tonnes a year of of crude and natural gas liquids, refined in its own plants.</p>
<p>But its greatest asset is a pipeline network of 140,000 km of trunk lines, with a total power rating of its compressor stations of 37.5 million kilowatts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
