<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="27921" id="root" date="1996-09-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Global gas use to rise 60 pct by 2010 - IEA.</title>
<headline>Global gas use to rise 60 pct by 2010 - IEA.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Global demand for natural gas is set to grow 60 percent by the year 2010, Executive Director of the Paris-based International Energy agency (IEA) Robert Priddle said on Monday.</p>
<p>Opening the third IEA gas conference here, Priddle said that total world energy demand will increase by 50 percent over the same period.</p>
<p>&quot;Nearly all of this wil be met by fossil fuels&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Much of the technology is already in place to meet demand, he said, but work is needed to bring down costs and improve environmental performance.</p>
<p>He identified three key issues for the future of natural gas -- availability of resources, structure of markets and technology.</p>
<p>The first meant areas of production were far from those of demand. In 1995 Europe and North America accounted for 53 percent of demand but only 10 percent of reserves.</p>
<p>By contrast, the Middle East had 32 percent of reserves but only six percent of consumption. Japan has a well developed gas industry but no significant reserves.</p>
<p>The cost of shipping gas was a major barrier to developing its use, said Priddle.</p>
<p>&quot;The cost of shipping one unit of gas from the North Sea to Europe is the same as tansporting the same unit of oil twice round the world.</p>
<p>&quot;And one cubic metre of gas contains only one thousandth of the energy of the same volume of crude oil,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Market structure was important because the international nature of gas made a legal framework crucial, he said.</p>
<p>In Europe, the Energy Charter has now been signed by 49 countries and ratification is set to grow.</p>
<p>&quot;The intention is to make safeguards so investment and trade can proceed&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Liberalisation of gas industries is starting in countries with a high degree of self sufficiency, such as the U.S., Canada and Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;But even in Japan, third party access (to pipelines) is starting,&quot; Priddle said.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe is slow to catch up, but the basis for third party access exists in Sweden, Ireland, Spain. The Netherlands is preparing, and the debate has now begun in Germany&quot;.</p>
<p>In technological terms, Priddle saw the growth of Combined Gas Turbine technology for power generation as behind the growth in gas use.  But there was also scope to increase gas use as a transport fuel.</p>
<p>&quot;Ninety-nine percent of Europe's modest fleet of gas powered vehicles is now in Italy and Russia,&quot; he said. &quot;Can we expect sufficient technological progress to help increase this?&quot;</p>
<p>--Sebastian Alison, Berlin Newsroom</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
