<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29928" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Czech natural gas use to grow 75 pct by 2010.</title>
<headline>Czech natural gas use to grow 75 pct by 2010.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Natural gas consumption in the Czech Republic will increase by 16 percent this year following a similar increase in 1995, and is set to grow by 75 percent by 2010, a senior Czech gas official said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Jan Malinsky, vice President of the Czech gas and oil association and head of marketing at state company Transgas, told an industry conference that the Czech gas industry is undergoing unprecedented growth and now stands at the threshold of overall integration into the European gas industry.</p>
<p>&quot;After five years of stagnation, gas consumption surged in 1995 by 16 percent and this trend continues this year, due to the very severe 1995/1996 winter. Natural gas' share of total energy sources rose to 15.7 percent in 1995,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added that the main cause for growth was gas' increasing use as a heating fuel in the residential sector.</p>
<p>Around 54 percent of Czech households are now connected to the natural gas grid, he said. But demand is also coming from industrial growth.</p>
<p>&quot;After a few years of slump, GDP picked up again in 1994 and 1995. Industrial production grew by 9.2 percent in 1995.&quot;</p>
<p>Household demand is fuelled by persisting subsidies.</p>
<p>While prices to the industrial and commercial sectors are comparable to those in Belgium, Germany and Britain, the average price to households is &quot;more than two times lower than the European average&quot;, according to Malinsky.</p>
<p>The Czech gas industry did not take off until 1972 when transmission of Russian natural gas to western Europe across Czech territory started.</p>
<p>From then until 1989, Malinsky said, the Czech gas industry was controlled by a single state owned company, CPP.</p>
<p>This was divided between the Czech and Slovak governments in the years following, until in 1994 eight regional distribution companies were demerged from CPP and turned into shareholding companies.</p>
<p>Transgas was then set up as a state-owned company to become the exclusive gas importer into the country.</p>
<p>It is also responsible for transit transmission for foreign customers, mainly of Russian gas going to western Europe, for gas storage and for dispatching control.</p>
<p>The Czech republic has production of 0.1 bcm a year of gas, a mere one percent of demand.</p>
<p>&quot;This suggests a nearly absolute dependence on imports which, however, is no exception in the European context,&quot; Malinsky told delegates at the third International Energy Agency gas conference here.</p>
<p>&quot;We still reckon that the major proportion of natural gas on our market in the future will be made up of Russian gas, at least nine bcm a year,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But diversification of sources and supply routes would markedly enhance the security of supplies. The most promising source appears to be from the Norwegian sector of the North Sea,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Norway recently signed a preliminary supply agreement with Transgas. Deliveries are slated to begin next year, ramping up to a plateau level of 3-bcm a year in 2002.</p>
<p>&quot;In the next fourteen years, it (Czech gas demand) might go up by 75 percent,&quot; Malinsky said. &quot;To meet the demand, efforts will be continued to diversify sources and supply routes.&quot;</p>
<p>--Sebastian Alison, Berlin Newsroom</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
