<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29922" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Natgas sees environmental benefit as key to growth.</title>
<headline>Natgas sees environmental benefit as key to growth.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Demand for ever more, but ever cleaner, sources of energy is behind the phenomenal growth of natural gas use worldwide in recent years, a gas conference heard on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The International Energy Agency's (IEA) third natural gas conference in Berlin was told that the environmental benefits of natural gas are the key to its future success and growth in market share.</p>
<p>Kurt Reinicke, technical executive at BEB Erdgas und Erdol, told delegates &quot;People around the world demand energy in increasing quantities, and at the same time they demand a cleaner, healthier and safer environment. The natural gas industry does not see any conflict in meeting both objectives.&quot;</p>
<p>He pointed out that natural gas is &quot;the least polluting fossil fuel: it produces less climate-forcing gases than any other fossil fuel.</p>
<p>&quot;It leaves no residue behind: ashes or dust are not generated during combustion. And it is energy efficient. A large number of energy-efficient technologies are continuously being improved.&quot;</p>
<p>As well as environmental benefits, gas offers security of supply, Reinicke said. &quot;Of the fossil fuels, the resource base is second only to coal. Its proved reserves will last for over 60 years at current production levels.&quot;</p>
<p>Many believe that gas reserves are far bigger than suggested by current reserve-to-production data, which yield the figure of 60 years. &quot;Now we have gas like we've never had before,&quot; said Bernard Leblanc, Senior Vice President of Gaz de France.</p>
<p>&quot;Every month new finds are made. Ten years ago, to find gas was a nuisance for an oil company. Now the situation has changed.&quot;</p>
<p>And Peter Hinstrup, director of the Danish Gas Technology Centre, believes technology may make gas redundant long before 60 years are up.</p>
<p>&quot;60 years may not seem long. But look at energy technology developments over the last 60 years, and it's a very long time indeed. Before we run out of gas, we may have carbon-free technology that makes gas redundant. And with the growth of renewable sources such as wave power and solar power, we may have pollution-free energy in 60 years.&quot;</p>
<p>Gas currently accounts for around 20 percent of global energy consumption, according to the IEA, but this is growing fast.</p>
<p>In Europe, supply of 371 billion cubic metres (bcm) in 1995 is to be boosted by 90 bcm a year by the end of the century as new supplies from Russia, Norway, Algeria and Britain come onstream.</p>
<p>And gas industries are being deregulated, putting an end to some of the huge monopolies now in place. The European Commission is shortly to start discussion of a gas directive aimed at opening up the European gas market to competition, as has already started in Britain.</p>
<p>But while gas may be cleaner than alternative fossil fuels, demand growth means that ever greater volumes must be burned.</p>
<p>&quot;Society should learn to accept that the energy industry is not the problem, but society with its increasing demand for energy,&quot; said Kurt Reinicke. &quot;Too often those who are willing to meet society's hunger for energy are held responsible that this demand exists.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
