<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30473" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: EC gas directive talks seen starting soon.</title>
<headline>EC gas directive talks seen starting soon.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission is ready to begin talks on a natural gas directive after the adoption of its electricity directive in June this year, a senior industry figure said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Bernard Leblanc, senior vice president of Gaz de France told a news conference here that discussions on the gas directive, which will open up gas markets progressively across the European Union, will start shortly.</p>
<p>&quot;Discussions on the electricity directive lasted eight years but I hope it will be faster in the case of gas,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The electricity directive opens up the market gradually so that eventually users of more than nine gigaWatt hours will be able to buy from different suppliers.</p>
<p>Around 20 to 25 percent of the market will be covered by the directive, including most large industrial end users.</p>
<p>Leblanc said that Gaz de France has drawn several lessons from the electricity directive which can be applied to gas.</p>
<p>&quot;First, the electricity directive allows a differentiated approach for the various member states. In effect, it allows members several options while leading to the same level of market opening,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Second, it recognises that member states have the right to impose public service obligations in the general economic interest,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>This allows governments to undertake long term planning in such areas as security of supply and environmental protection.</p>
<p>&quot;And lastly the directive allows for progressive implementation,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>But Leblanc was keen to point out that the electricity directive should not be seen as a blueprint for natural gas, because of the fundamental differences between the two.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a basic inequality between various member states: some are blessed with considerable resources and others are not,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Countries had different interests depending on whether or not they produced gas.</p>
<p>&quot;Also, much more gas than electricity is traded across borders,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Physical exchanges of electricity are low, while some dependent gas consumers import 100 percent of their requirements. As a result, electricity has only local implications while gas has geopolitical ramifications.</p>
<p>&quot;Added to that is the fact that the EU's already high dependence on natural gas from outside the region will continue to grow&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>That dependence is now 40 percent, rising to 50 percent in 2000 and to 60 percent in 2010.</p>
<p>&quot;One must not be blinded by the temporary British gas bubble&quot;, he added.</p>
<p>Gaz de France believes the European Commission must consider several factors to allow the directive to work smoothly.</p>
<p>High among these are allowing companies to conclude long term contracts while finding a solution to the &quot;take or pay&quot; problems on existing contracts.</p>
<p>&quot;All gas companies should find lessons in the recent example provide by British Gas on take or pay. This issue must be resolved before the introduction of any institutional amendment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Leblanc, attending the third International Energy Agency gas conference here, was upbeat about the prospects for growth in the European gas market.</p>
<p>&quot;The gas resources accessible for European markets at a reasonable price are abundant. They will not actually be available, however, unless the rules of the institutional game do not threaten fundamental balances.&quot;</p>
<p>--Sebastian Alison, Berlin Newsroom</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
