<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33229" id="root" date="1996-09-04" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spain approves natural gas price hike of 1.5 pct.</title>
<headline>Spain approves natural gas price hike of 1.5 pct.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1996-09-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Spanish government approved a rise of 1.5 percent in natural gas prices from this month, a spokesman for the Ministry of Industry told Reuters.</p>
<p>From July of 1997 through the same month in 1998 the price of natural gas will decline by 0.5 percent, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;This price change will be applied provided that raw material prices remain stable,&quot; the spokesman told Reuters.  </p>
<p>Shares of 3.8 percent state-owned Gas Natural slid sharply on the bourse in response to a report on Wednesday in business daily Expansion that said the price of gas for domestic and commercial use would rise by 1.5 percent next year and would fall by 0.5 percent in 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;The hike is less than expected so profit estimates for next year will have to be revised down,&quot; said an analyst at Ibersecurities brokerage in Madrid.</p>
<p>But a spokesperson at the gas firm told Reuters that the decision on the increase in the gas tariff should not impact profits. This is because supply costs from next year will fall as a gas pipeline from Northern Africa comes onstream.</p>
<p>At 1215 GMT, shares in Gas Natural were down 1,870 pesetas at 22,090. They had fallen a maximum of 9.22 percent to 21,750.</p>
<p>Repsol, which has an around 45 percent stake in Gas Natural, was down 40 pesetas at 4,030.  </p>
<p>Gas Natural also stands to benefit from new government legislation via which companies are allowed to update the value of fixed assets on their balance sheets. This will boost cash flow, the spokesperson said.</p>
<p>Gas Natural said the fact the tariff hike is less than anticipated &quot;is a sacrifice that we all have to make but from next year we'll have cheaper costs with the Mahgreb-Europe pipeline and the effect of the (law to) update balance sheets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But analysts said the lower-than-expected price hike could well have an effect because the market had taken into account these cost reductions when assessing the firm.</p>
<p>A trader at a Madrid brokerage who requested anonymity said the stock had fallen sharply, beset in part by a lack of official information over the timing and size of the tariff rise.</p>
<p>Although the stock's fall today was &quot;exaggerated,&quot; in his opinion, the confusion may have longer term effects on the share price.</p>
<p>&quot;People will lose confidence in the stock. It will become clear that at the end of the day (the company) relies on the state.&quot;</p>
<p>--Madrid Newsroom +34 1 585 2167</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-04"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-04"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
