<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="33736" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Coastal, Westcoast seen set for gas megamerger.</title>
<headline>Coastal, Westcoast seen set for gas megamerger.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Jones</byline>
<dateline>CALGARY, Alberta 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>Houston-based Coastal Corp. and Westcoast Energy Inc. of Vancouver appeared close to announcing a merger of their natural gas marketing divisions, industry sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The merger would create North America's fourth largest marketing operation.</p>
<p>&quot;It is going ahead,&quot; said a well-placed source, who spoke on condition of anonymity. &quot;The impression that they're trying to give people is that it's being discussed, when it's being discussed with a view to completion.&quot;</p>
<p>The move would follow recent similar gas marketing mergers, including those by NGC Corp. and Chevron Corp., as well as PanEnergy Corp. and Mobil Corp.</p>
<p>Together, the combined entity of Coastal and Westcoast would manage about 6.7 billion cubic feet of gas per day. This is less only than NGC-Chevron, Enron Corp. and Mobil-PanEnergy.</p>
<p>Officials of Westcoast and Coastal declined to comment on the deal's progress.</p>
<p>&quot;It's an industry trend,&quot; said Coastal spokesman Brian Mitchell. &quot;But as far as this particular report, I can't add anything to it.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I really have to decline commenting at this stage,&quot; said Westcoast spokeswoman Patricia Bowles.</p>
<p>Westcoast, Canada's third-largest integrated pipeline and gas marketing company, operates British Columbia's gas gathering and transport systems and owns gas utilities Centra and Union Gas.</p>
<p>Westcoast's gas marketing arm, Westcoast Gas Services, provides merchant sales, trading and risk management services across North America. Its main office is in Calgary.</p>
<p>In 1995, Westcoast Gas, which moves an average of 3.2 billion cubic feet of gas a day, lost C$1 million.</p>
<p>Coastal Gas Marketing, a unit of integrated oil and gas company Coastal Corp., is the eighth largest gas marketing company in the United States, moving an average of 3.5 billion cubic feet a day. It also has a Calgary office.</p>
<p>One Canadian analyst said Westcoast, faced with intense and growing competition in gas marketing, was at a point where it had to decide to grow much larger or leave the sector.</p>
<p>&quot;(There's been) a lack of earnings capability to date, partly due to depressed gas pricing in British Columbia,&quot; said ScotiaMcleod's Sam Kanes. &quot;They should get bigger or get out and taking a smaller percentage of something bigger makes sense.&quot;</p>
<p>Carol Coale, natural gas analyst at Prudential Securities in Houston, said the trend to megamarketers had grown as companies found the need to cover the largest market area for the lowest cost.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless you have a small, focused effort, you really have to play the market share game,&quot; Coale said, adding that Coastal's marketing arm had been an underperformer.</p>
<p>&quot;To be a low-cost provider, you've got to run enough volumes through your system to make it worthwhile,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Westcoast's stock on Thursday closed down C15 cents to C$21.50 ($15.70) on the Toronto Stock Exchange. Coastal was off 37.5 cents to $39.625 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CALGARY, Alberta"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
