<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="36398" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Gas price doubts hit Gas Natural, Repsol holds up.</title>
<headline>Gas price doubts hit Gas Natural, Repsol holds up.</headline>
<byline>Elisabeth O'Leary</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in Spain's Gas Natural were down sharply again on Thursday after news of smaller gas price increases than expected in the next two years raised doubts over the company's future, analysts said.</p>
<p>At 1116 GMT, Gas Natural was down 1,380 pesetas, or 6.49 percent, to 20,200, bringing the shares' total loss in two days to 15 percent. But Repsol, which has an around 45 percent stake in Gas Natural, was up five pesetas to 4,040.</p>
<p>&quot;The problem for the stock market now is, what happens after 1998?. Up to now (Gas Natural's) profile was one of strong growth with fat margins, a company which the government favoured and a safe stock. Now that perception has changed,&quot; said an analyst at a Madrid brokerage who requested anonymity.</p>
<p>Today's fall in the gas firm's shares follows a 9.93 percent fall in the stock on Wednesday after the government said natural gas prices would rise 1.5 percent from this month through July 1997 and then decline for one year by 0.5 percent.</p>
<p>A second energy analyst said he was not surprised at the apparent change in the government's stance.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been waiting for a tougher regulatory regime for some time. We're not surprised,&quot; said Mark Flannery at BZW Securities in London.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, many analysts had been anticipating an annual rise of two to three percent in the gas tariff effective this month, followed by a one-year rise next July of one to 1.5 percent.</p>
<p>Despite the disappointment over the modest tariff rise, analysts said this factor could only account for an around five percent fall in the share.</p>
<p>The severity of the fall showed that the market had acquired a bad case of the jitters over the government's future stance toward the group, according to Juan Carlos Calvo, energy analyst at Merrill Lynch.</p>
<p>But despite Gas Natural's share woes, stock in its largest shareholder Repsol's has weathered the problems in good form.</p>
<p>Given the size of its stake, analysts calculate that theoretically Repsol shares should lose one-third of a percent of their value for every one percent decline in Gas Natural share.</p>
<p>However two factors offset this. Firstly, Repsol's share price has been consistently weak on a raft of bad news this year while Gas Natural has continued to soar.</p>
<p>Secondly, Gas Natural is not liquid enough to provide arbitrage for Repsol investors, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts are now revising down Gas Natural profits estimates for the next three years by up to seven or eight percent annually, starting in 1996.</p>
<p>--Madrid newsroom +341 585 2160</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
