<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73146" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Bad roads threaten Indian car industry - report.</title>
<headline>Bad roads threaten Indian car industry - report.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Inadequate infrastructure facilities, mainly a poor road network, could slow the growth of India's car industry, officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Lack of infrastructure, particularly roads, will affect the automobile industry,&quot; Brijmohan Lall, president of the All India Association of Automobile Manufacturers (AIAM), told a business conference.</p>
<p>The AIAM said in a report released on Monday that the poorly maintained road network was likely to put a brake on the booming domestic automobile industry.</p>
<p>India began opening its domestic car industry to foreign investors as a part of an economic liberalisation programme launched in 1991.</p>
<p>Indian car sales have risen by 25 to 27 percent in the past two years, officials said.</p>
<p>The report said India's 2.2 million km (13 million miles) of roads were inadequate to accommodate the growing numbers of vehicles.</p>
<p>&quot;With a total vehicle population of about 31 million units, the infrastructure is not adequate enough,&quot; Surface Transport Minister T.G. Venkatraman said.</p>
<p>The car makers must adopt stringent emission norms and improved technology to produce vehicles which pollute less, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;India with its vast resources of Compressed Natural Gas (CNG) and Liquid Petroleum Gas (LPG) has a capability to operate large number of vehicles on these alternate fuels,&quot; Venkatraman said, adding this would reduce pollution.</p>
<p>He said government investment in public transport had dwindled in the last five years, leading to an increase in the number of vehicles.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is making all-out efforts to improve roads,&quot; Venkatraman said.</p>
<p>He said the financing requirements of building additional roads was enormous and this would require the coming together of the government and the private sector.</p>
<p>-- Sabyasachi Mitra, New Delhi news room +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5020041">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
