<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74003" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-INTERVIEW-Australian gas set to expand.</title>
<headline>RTRS-INTERVIEW-Australian gas set to expand.</headline>
<byline>Graeme James</byline>
<dateline>SURFERS PARADISE, Australia 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's gas industry is on the verge of a massive spending spree with plans to invest more than A$14 billion over the next 10 years to bring the country's fledgling energy network onstream.</p>
<p>&quot;We spent A$1 billion in 1995/96 (June 30) on capital expenditure works. We will see capital expenditure of A$14 billion in the next 10 years to the year 2006,&quot; Australian Gas Association (AGA) chief executive Ian Woodward said in an interview on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>&quot;The amazing thing is that most of that sum will come from private sector investment,&quot; Woodward said on the final day of an AGA gas convention here.</p>
<p>Woodward said that about one third of the capital spending would be on natural gas pipelines that would fill in large gaps still left in a planned vast national network.</p>
<p>&quot;Other spending will be on LNG (liquefied natural gas) production facilities, 400 to 500 miles of local reticulation systems as well as distribution systems,&quot; he said. Funds would come from various sources including equity market raisings.  </p>
<p>&quot;I would think this would be similar to methods used by gas companies over the last ten years,&quot; Woodward said.</p>
<p>Other funds would come from a continuing privatisation programme of public gas utilities in the various Australian states, Woodward said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Victorian Government, for example, has indicated a plan to privatise the state's Gas and Fuel Corporation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The AGA said Australian consumers would see some examples of a burgeoning gas industry shortly in the form of major co-generation projects using natural gas and continuing expansion of residential users.  </p>
<p>Latest figures showed that the number of natural gas customers increased by 93,240 to 2.9 million in the year ended June 30 1996 with 13,188 km of gas transmission lines operational, approved or under construction.</p>
<p>In the next five years, the industry would also be continuing its push for gas as an energy fuel for commercial buildings, Woodward said.</p>
<p>Encouragement also came from the enviromental movement which has given its blessing to gas as a fuel of the future.  </p>
<p>&quot;Natural gas has a role as a transitional fuel in the next 50 years,&quot; Australian Conservation Foundation co-ordinator Peter Kinrade said in a convention speech.</p>
<p>&quot;It is heartening to see the gas industry taking up the challenge in its environmental code of practice,&quot; Kincade said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SURFERS PARADISE, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
