<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="76092" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Auto group, oil industry tangle over premium gas.</title>
<headline>Auto group, oil industry tangle over premium gas.</headline>
<byline>Ransdell Pierson</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>The American Automobile Association and an oil industry group locked horns Wednesday, a day after the AAA said drivers wasted $1.7 billion a year buying higher-octane gasoline.</p>
<p>&quot;Many drivers are falling for the 'octane myth' in gasoline ads and are giving $1.7 billion to the nation's oil industry needlessly,&quot; the Washington-based motorists' group said in a statement on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The AAA said consumers should realise &quot;only exotic cars, some sport utility vehicles and vehicles with high-performance engines really need premium,&quot; which costs consumers about 15 cents a gallon more than regular grade fuel.</p>
<p>The nationwide auto club contended fewer than 10 percent of cars on U.S. roads needed premium although it constituted nearly 20 percent of total gas sold.</p>
<p>The renewed attack against premium echoed a similar call by the Federal Trade Commission last week. The federal agency, seeking to warn consumers against paying extra, sued Exxon Corp. on Sept. 17 for making allegedly overblown advertising claims that premium enabled engines to run cleaner and with better mileage.</p>
<p>Exxon, the fourth major U.S. oil company called to task by the FTC, became the first not to settle before a suit was filed.</p>
<p>&quot;Contrary to popular opinion, premium gas does not provide more power, doesn't improve performance, burn more clearly, reduce engine wear or improve mileage,&quot; AAA spokesman Dave Van Sickle said Wednesday.</p>
<p>An oil industry group disputed some of AAA's claims.</p>
<p>&quot;That's dead wrong, they're giving short shrift to the facts,&quot; said Thomas Hogarty, senior research manager for the American Petroleum Institute, who defended premium for promoting low-knock combustion.</p>
<p>Hogarty conceded in a telephone interview there was little evidence premium reduced engine wear or improved mileage.</p>
<p>&quot;I won't argue with those points,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Hogarty said a recent study by the Coordinating Research Council, an oil industry group based in Atlanta, showed 19 percent of U.S. vehicles needed premium to assure smooth combustion and prevent knocking and ping noises associated with lower-octane fuels.</p>
<p>&quot;Light trucks, vans and utility vehicles are less likely to get by on regular,&quot; he said, because of built-in vehicle &quot;knock sensors&quot; that limit acceleration ability if fuel quality is below the premium standard of 92- to 93-grade octane.</p>
<p>Regular gasoline's octane level, a measure of resistance to knocking, is rated at 87-grade.</p>
<p>Hogarty also said vast numbers of old vehicles that once used anti-knock leaded fuel, now outlawed, cannot operate properly on regular unleaded gasoline.</p>
<p>&quot;They (AAA) are giving short shrift to a lot of old cars and trucks,&quot; he said, adding that many of the vintage vehicles are operated in the western United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
