<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81420" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Plans underway to market water-based fuel in Asia.</title>
<headline>Plans underway to market water-based fuel in Asia.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Plans are underway to market a breakthrough, water-based fuel for cars in Asia following its introduction in the western United States.</p>
<p>The fuel is made of 30 percent water, 67.5 percent naphtha and 2.5 percent of additives that bind water and naphtha, an oil product, an official with A-55 Ltd told a news conference on Friday.</p>
<p>A-55 can be used as a replacement for diesel in boilers and heating units, while another new fuel, A-21, can be used in cars as an alternative to both petrol and diesel.</p>
<p>The company says the new fuel is cheaper and less polluting. When used in diesel engines, emissions of harmful particles are half that of diesel fuel.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a mixing plant in Reno, Nevada and plan to open another in Sacramento, California,&quot; said inventor Rudolf Gunnerman, the president and chief executive officer of A-55 Ltd.</p>
<p>The company sells about 8,000 gallons per day of the new fuel, mainly to owners of fleets of vehicles like bus and taxi operators.</p>
<p>The company plans to market the fuel in Asia by early next year, but first must educate and inform the public and the authorties, said Alex Ling, a partner in A-55 Ltd.</p>
<p>He said the company had held talks directly with the Malaysian state-owned oil company Petronas, and through third-parties with Indonesian state-owned Pertamina.</p>
<p>Ling said the company had sent a Proton (the Malaysian national car) engine to its laboratory in the United States to test the emissions of A-55 and other fuels.</p>
<p>&quot;We will then send it to an independent laboratory for tests as well,&quot; Ling said.</p>
<p>He hoped the test results would convince the Malaysian authorties and Petronas to let it start marketing the new fuel in Malaysia.</p>
<p>Ling said the company would initially focus its Asian marketing efforts in South East Asia.</p>
<p>--Singapore Newsroom (+65-870-3093)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
