<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19885" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish mobster shot dead, wife vows revenge.</title>
<headline>Turkish mobster shot dead, wife vows revenge.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gunmen killed a leading Turkish organised crime boss in a drive-by shooting at a Bosphorus cafe early on Wednesday, police said, and his wife vowed a bloody revenge.</p>
<p>Turkish newspapers said panicked diners in the fashionable cafe in Istanbul's posh Bebek district, including a top singer and a talk show host, jumped into the water to escape the hail of bullets.</p>
<p>The Anatolian news agency said Tevfik Agansoy's henchmen shot open the doors of an Istanbul hospital to get him treated quickly, but to no avail.</p>
<p>&quot;Agansoy died of his wounds on his way to hospital,&quot; a police official told Reuters.</p>
<p>Anatolian said three other people, including an off-duty bodyguard of foreign minister Tansu Ciller, were killed after two gunmen opened fire with automatic weapons.</p>
<p>Seven people were wounded, Turkish television said, including another of Ciller's bodyguards. Newspapers said the bodyguards were friends of Agansoy.</p>
<p>Agansoy, 36, managed to shoot one of the assailants in the head, killing him, Hurriyet daily said.</p>
<p>Agansoy's wife Hulya said he was killed by a rival gang boss and vowed vengeance.</p>
<p>&quot;Look, I am not crying,&quot; she said on private ATV television as she kissed her husband's body in hospital. &quot;I shall cry only when I have avenged your blood,&quot; she told the corpse.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be much blood. There will be a massacre,&quot; Anatolian quoted her as saying.</p>
<p>Television showed pictures of Agansoy, stripped to his underpants and covered in blood, being carried off on a stretcher. Blood covered the floors of the cafe.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
