<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="39907" id="root" date="1996-09-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Search unveils East German order to shoot refugees.</title>
<headline>Search unveils East German order to shoot refugees.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1996-09-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Researchers have found the first tangible evidence that communist East Germany ordered border guards to shoot anyone trying to escape to the West, a magazine said on Sunday.</p>
<p>The newsmagazine Der Spiegel said a government-backed agency had uncovered long-sought documentation supporting the existence of an official command to shoot refugees fleeing to West Germany in the Cold War era.</p>
<p>More than 800 people were killed or maimed in the decades before the Berlin Wall fell in 1989, but former leaders from Erich Honecker down have long insisted there never was a formal order to shoot refugees from the communist east.</p>
<p>The Gauck agency sorting through mountains of security police documents left behind when East Germany collapsed found a 1973 document that makes clear guards were under orders to shoot any would-be refugee.</p>
<p>The magazine said the Gauck agency had discovered minutes from a July 1973 meeting when security police chief Erich Mielke urged that an &quot;order to shoot&quot; be temporarily lifted while a world youth organisation met in East Berlin.</p>
<p>&quot;Naturally the order to shoot will not be permanently lifted,&quot; Mielke was quoted as saying. Rather, during the time of the international meeting in Berlin the border guards should &quot;work in a way that we don't have to shoot in the first place.&quot;</p>
<p>Three lower ranking communist officials have been given jail sentences for up to seven years for a shoot-to-kill policy at the border, although until now prosecutors had never been able to find any written evidence of the shoot order.</p>
<p>A number of border guards, who argued they were only following verbal orders from superiors, have been tried but handed mostly-suspended sentences for the border killings.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
