<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="50614" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Videotape shows rap star in argument before shooting.</title>
<headline>Videotape shows rap star in argument before shooting.</headline>
<dateline>LAS VEGAS 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>A surveillance tape filmed at a heavyweight title fight shows rap music star Tupac Shakur was involved in an argument with an unknown man shortly before he was shot and critically wounded, police said Wednesday.</p>
<p>But Las Vegas police said they had &quot;no reason, at this time, to believe that the altercation has any connection to the shooting.&quot;</p>
<p>Shakur, one of the most notorious performers of hardcore &quot;Gangsta&quot; rap, remained in critical condition in the intensive care unit of a Las Vegas hospital Wednesday, a University Medical Centre spokesman said. Shakur's right lung was removed in one of two operations on Sunday.</p>
<p>A hospital source said the 25-year-old singer and actor had been on life support since the surgery. The source said that was not unusual for such a serious injury.</p>
<p>Shakur and a group of friends were driving to a nightclub after watching the Mike Tyson-Bruce Seldon world heavyweight title fight at the MGM Grand arena in Las Vegas Saturday night when a white Cadillac pulled alongside the black BMW in which Shakur was a passenger. A gunman fired a hail of bullets, hitting Shakur four times.</p>
<p>Las Vegas police said they had viewed a surveillance tape, provided by the MGM Grand, showing &quot;an altercation&quot; between Shakur, some of his associates and an unknown man before the title fight. Police spokesman Phil Roland said the argument was verbal and not physical.</p>
<p>Police said the quarrel was broken up immediately by security. Shakur and his associates left the area, they said. The unknown man involved in the dispute was interviewed by MGM security and police officers later, but declined to file a report, they said.</p>
<p>Roland said security officers talked with the man after the boxing match and it would have been impossible for him to have followed Shakur's group when they left. Police did not have the name of the man and had been unable to trace him, he said. The reason for the argument was unknown, he said.</p>
<p>Police have still not been able to interview Marion &quot;Suge&quot; Knight, who was driving the car when the attack happened, Roland said. Knight, 31, co-founder of the controversial music label Death Row Records, suffered a minor gunshot wound to the head. Investigators were again hoping to talk with Knight on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Roland said police had no suspects, no leads and no motive in the case. Police have complained that the people in Shakur's entourage who witnessed the incident have given them little information.</p>
<p>Shakur is no stranger to trouble. He has spent much of the last 2-1/2 years in court, prison or hospitals. In November 1994, he was shot five times while being robbed of $40,000 in jewels in the lobby of a Manhattan recording studio.</p>
<p>In February 1995, he was sentenced to prison for involvement in a sexual attack on a 21-year-old woman in a New York hotel room. He spent eight months behind bars until he was released pending his appeal.</p>
<p>Shakur is best known for raw lyrics laced with violence, sex and profanity. His latest album, &quot;All Eyez on Me,&quot; released this year, celebrates his own outlaw image and has sold several million copies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAS VEGAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
