<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64482" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Death Row head would give it up to get Shakur back.</title>
<headline>Death Row head would give it up to get Shakur back.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Marion &quot;Suge&quot; Knight, the record executive in whose car &quot;gangsta&quot; rapper Tupac Shakur was fatally shot this month, said he would give up his lifestyle to bring Shakur back, a newspaper said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;I would give up Death Row, I would give up this lifestyle, I would give up a life to bring him back. ... Me and Tupac was joined at the hip,&quot; the head of Death Row Records told the Los Angeles Times in his first published interview since the fatal shooting.</p>
<p>Knight suffered minor gunshot wounds in the Sept. 7 shooting, which occurred as he and Shakur were driving in Knight's BMW to his new nightclub in Las Vegas after watching the Mike Tyson-Bruce Seldon heavyweight boxing title fight.</p>
<p>The former football player who built Death Row into a multimillion dollar company denied that he was uncooperative with police, saying he delayed talking to them because he had to recover from his own injuries, the newspaper reported.</p>
<p>A Cadillac pulled alongside as the BMW stopped at a red light and a gunman inside fired at least nine bullets, four hitting Shakur. Knight, 31, was driving the BMW and suffered a minor wound to the head.</p>
<p>Shakur died Friday after several operations, including the removal of his right lung, and was cremated the next day. Police said they have few concrete leads in the investigation.</p>
<p>Knight refused to speak about the details of the shooting or speculate on reasons for it but said he had not stopped mourning since Shakur's death. Theories include that Shakur took a bullet that was meant for Knight, who has said in the past that there were contracts out on his life.</p>
<p>Knight told the newspaper he is planning a memorial service in the next few weeks to celebrate the life of the rapper and plans to promote an upcoming record by Shakur.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
