<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75435" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Bloody Israeli-Palestinian clashes in West Bank.</title>
<headline>Bloody Israeli-Palestinian clashes in West Bank.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot dead at least one Palestinian stone-thrower, wounded more than 200 and exchanged fire with Yasser Arafat's police on Wednesday in the bloodiest clashes in the West Bank since PLO rule began two years ago.</p>
<p>The fighting erupted as part of widespread protests in the West Bank and Gaza against Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's decison to open a tunnel in Jerusalem near Islam's third holiest shrine.</p>
<p>The clashes outside the PLO-ruled enclave of Ramallah were reminiscent of the 1987-1993 Palestinian uprising or intifada against Israel -- only now there are nearly 30,000 armed Palestinian police in self-rule areas.</p>
<p>Israeli troops fired live ammunition and rubber bullets when they came under a hail of stones and bottles at the crossing to the Ramallah enclave, north of Jerusalem, witnesses said.</p>
<p>One angry Palestinian policeman grabbed a rifle and started shooting back at the Israelis, according to five witnesses questioned at the scene. Others from Palestinian President Arafat's Force 17 guard joined in, sparking the most serious gunfight between Israeli and Palestinian forces since Arafat returned to Gaza in July 1994.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers later entered the self-rule area for the first time to try to stop the fire, witnesses said.</p>
<p>At sundown, after more than five hours of clashes, two truckloads of Palestinian police arrived and tried to prevent protesters from attacking the Israeli post.</p>
<p>Ramallah hospital doctors said one youth was shot dead in the head. Up to 200 Palestinians were wounded, six from live ammunition, the rest from rubber bullets, beatings and teargas inhalation.</p>
<p>Israeli authorities contacted Arafat in Gaza in an attempt to halt the protests, Israeli officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is escalation from the Israeli government against our people who are protesting against the breaching of the agreement and especially the tunnel under our holy, sacred places in Jerusalem,&quot; Arafat told reporters in Gaza.</p>
<p>&quot;The most important thing that we cannot accept is the Judaization of Jerusalem. East Jerusalem is our capital and this has been occupied since 1967,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, on a European tour, defended his decision on Tuesday to open a second entrance to a tunnel beside the Dome of the Rock and al-Aqsa mosque complex, saying it made an important archaeological site more accessible to tourists.</p>
<p>But as Netanyahu arrived in Paris for talks with President Jacques Chirac, French Foreign Ministry spokesman Yves Doutriaux accused Israel of fuelling tension.</p>
<p>&quot;The opening of a tunnel by the Israelis under the (Temple Mount) mosques esplanade and the Arab city of Jerusalem is an old project that had been frozen for 10 years. This initiative adds a new and regrettable factor of tension,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The underground tunnel, with its sensitivities for the whole Moslem world, provided a perfect vehicle for the Palestinian leadership to mobilise popular sentiment against Netanyahu's delay in implementing self-rule.</p>
<p>&quot;This government is trying to undermine the very foundations of the peace process,&quot; said Palestinian cabinet minister Hanan Ashrawi as she tried to push through police lines to reach al-Aqsa from Damascus Gate in Jerusalem's walled Old City.</p>
<p>Ashrawi eventually got through but phalanxes of riot police prevented slogan-chanting youths from accompanying her.</p>
<p>Arafat cancelled a meeting on Thursday of the Israeli- Palestinian steering committee overseeing implementation of the Oslo accord.</p>
<p>In Cairo, the Arab League said it would meet on Thursday at the request of the Palestinians to discuss the tunnel.</p>
<p>Palestinians charge that Israel is trying to turn Jerusalem into a wholly Jewish city and undermine Moslem and Christian holy places.</p>
<p>They say Israel allows Jews to build in the city but restricts Arabs from building. They also say most Palestinians are barred from entering Jerusalem -- the political, cultural and religious centre of Palestinian life -- by closures of the West Bank and Gaza.</p>
<p>Israeli experts denied charges the tunnel threatened to damage al-Aqsa's structure.</p>
<p>&quot;I know clearly and with certainty that we are not touching the Temple Mount whatsoever -- only around the Temple Mount. We aren't touching on any Arab property and not Temple Mount,&quot; Israeli Professor Yaacov Glick told Israel Radio.</p>
<p>The tunnel runs alongside the Wailing Wall, the Herodian retaining wall of the Second Jewish Temple, on whose ruins first churches were built, then mosques after the Arab conquest of Jerusalem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
