<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="81462" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: More deaths in Israeli-Palestinian clashes.</title>
<headline>More deaths in Israeli-Palestinian clashes.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Seven Palestinians, two Israeli paramilitary policemen and an Israeli soldier were killed in a third day of violence in the West Bank, Gaza Strip and Jerusalem on Friday.</p>
<p>On Jerusalem's Temple Mount, site of al-Aqsa mosque, Israeli security forces shot dead three Palestinians during a stone-throwing protest, Arab hospital officials said.</p>
<p>In the West Bank, four Palestinians and two Israeli paramilitary policemen were shot dead in separate clashes as violence continued to rage, hospital officials and witnesses said. A senior Israeli soldier was killed in the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Moslem Friday prayers and Palestinian protest marches were the backdrop for the latest bloodshed.</p>
<p>On the Temple Mount, Islam's third holiest shrine, several hundred Palestinians threw stones, injuring five Israeli policemen. Israeli security forces responded with gunfire, killing the three Palestinians and wounded more than 50, the hospital officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was massive stone-throwing at our forces...there was no choice but to finish dealing with the demonstrators. The truth is we didn't make any use of live ammunition. Rubber bullets were used and maybe one tear gas grenade,&quot; Israeli police commissioner Assaf Hefetz told Israel Radio.</p>
<p>In the West Bank town of Tulkarm, two Israeli paramilitary policemen and a Palestinian were killed in clashes, Israel Radio and Arab hospital officials said. Fifteen Arabs were hurt and Israel's chief artillery officer was wounded.</p>
<p>Brigadier General Dan Harel told reporters in hospital that he was shot while sitting in his jeep by Palestinians who rioted in the town.</p>
<p>Just outside Jericho, also in the West Bank, three Palestinians were shot dead by Israeli gunfire and 12 Arabs and two Israeli soldiers were wounded when demonstrators threw stones at troops, hospital officials and Israeli security sources said.</p>
<p>In clashes in the town of Rafah, on Gaza's border with Egypt, an Israeli colonel was killed and two soldiers were wounded.</p>
<p>Israeli attack helicopters fired into Rafah after clashes with Palestinian policemen and protesters, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Palestinians had earlier knocked down a border fence between Rafah and Egypt and attacked the position with bullets and firebombs.</p>
<p>Security sources in Cairo said an Egyptian police lieutenant patrolling the North Sinai area on the Egyptian side of the Rafah border was killed when he was hit by fire from the attack helicopter sent to quell clashes.</p>
<p>Some Palestinian policemen and civilians who had been at the position fled to Egypt when the helicopters began their attack in the late afternoon.</p>
<p>Also in Gaza, two Palestinians who were shot by Israeli forces on Thursday died of their wounds on Friday, hospital sources said.</p>
<p>Arabs threw rocks at an Israeli checkpoint near the West Bank town of Ramallah, drawing Israeli gunfire. Witnesses said many of the protesters were wounded, but no exact number was available.</p>
<p>Violence also erupted in Bethlehem, where 29 Arabs were taken to hospital suffering either from gunshot wounds or tear gas inhalation.</p>
<p>In Qalqilya, also in the West Bank, 10 Palestinians were shot and wounded, witnesses said. Five Arabs suffered gunshot wounds in the Hebron area.</p>
<p>Since Wednesday, 67 people -- 53 Palestinians and 14 Israelis -- have been killed in violence touched off by Israel's opening of a tunnel near Moslem holy sites in Jerusalem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
