<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82908" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel blames PLO, sides try to arrange summit.</title>
<headline>Israel blames PLO, sides try to arrange summit.</headline>
<byline>Howard Goller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel blamed the Palestinian Authority on Friday for two days of gun battles in which more than 50 people died, while the two sides sought a summit to try to safeguard five years of Middle East peacemaking.</p>
<p>&quot;The government of Israel is demanding of the Palestinian Authority to cease the incitement and to restrain the violent activity in its territory against Israeli civilians and Israeli army soldiers,&quot; Israel's security cabinet said in a statement issued after seven hours of emergency talks.</p>
<p>A senior Israeli official said Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu urgently wanted a meeting with Yasser Arafat to stop two days of bloodshed triggered by his decision to open an archaeological tunnel near an Islamic shrine in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>But PLO officials said Palestinian President Arafat would have little success in quelling the violence unless assured that Netanyahu would commit at the meeting to implementing the peace deals of the government he ousted in May.</p>
<p>In the statement, Israel called on the Palestinian Authority to renew peace talks &quot;without preconditions&quot; and accused it of breaking a clause of an interim Israeli-PLO peace deal calling for the &quot;prevention of hostile acts&quot; from both sides.</p>
<p>&quot;The fire on the part of the Palestinian police officers and the incitement to violence represents a severe violation of the interim agreement and their continuation endangers the continuation of the peace process,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak tried to arrange a three-way meeting in Cairo and Netanyahu spoke with him twice by telephone from the security cabinet meeting in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called for a halt to the fighting and a resumption of talks. U.S. diplomats in Israel were working intensively behind the scenes to arrange an Arafat-Netanyahu meeting.</p>
<p>Facing international condemnation and having sent in tanks and helicopters to quell the violence which, apart from the deaths, wounded more than 1,000, mainly Palestinians, Netanyahu cut short a European tour to deal with the emergency.</p>
<p>It was the first time Israel had used tanks in the West Bank since the territory's capture in 1967, Israel Radio said.</p>
<p>Israeli troops braced for renewed violence on Friday when Palestinians planned to bury their dead and Moslems to attend Friday prayers. Israeli Arab leaders called a general strike in solidarity with Palestinians of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>Arafat's health ministry said 39 Palestinians died on Thursday, raising to 44 the number killed in two days of gunfights unprecedented in the two years since he returned to run self-rule areas under peace deals with Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;What happened is a real massacre against the Palestinian people,&quot; Arafat told reporters during a hospital visit in Gaza.</p>
<p>The Israeli army said 11 of its soldiers were killed by gunfire on Thursday, six of them during a siege of the domed tomb of the biblical Joseph in the heart of Palestinian-ruled Nablus in the West Bank.</p>
<p>Israelis voiced outrage in radio programmes that Palestinian police would turn on them with weapons provided under peace deals with Israel.</p>
<p>Washington, Israel's closest ally, asked Netanyahu to close down the tourist tunnel, but the Israeli leader seemed opposed, telling Secretary of States Warren Christopher in a phone call that it would reward violence, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, 46, had angered Arabs and Palestinians by opposing the policy of swapping occupied land for peace which had been the basis of five years of U.S.-brokered peace talks.</p>
<p>Israeli helicopters fired at gunmen in apartment blocks in Ramallah, north of Jerusalem, and armoured personnel carriers tried to rescue Israelis trapped in Joseph's Tomb. Fighting was strongest in those areas and around Jewish settlements in Gaza.</p>
<p>Israel denied its tunnel opening was an assault on Moslem sites, but the move unleashed pent-up Palestinian frustration with the self-rule agreement which Netanyahu has held up.</p>
<p>Western diplomats said in private the move was the biggest political miscalculation of Netanyahu's 100-day-long term.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
