<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="85997" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli officers fault Israelis for Gaza clashes.</title>
<headline>Israeli officers fault Israelis for Gaza clashes.</headline>
<byline>Colleen Siegel</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli commanders in the Gaza Strip were quoted on Monday as saying indiscriminate shooting by Jewish settlers and Israeli soldiers ignited the bloodiest day of clashes in the strip last week.</p>
<p>The report in Israel's Haaretz daily came as Palestinians accused Jewish settlers of shooting at Arabs in the West Bank last week and of harassing Palestinians this week.</p>
<p>&quot;We are worried that provocations by settlers might re-ignite violence. They have provoked people during the clashes and now that the situation is calming, they could stir it up again,&quot; a senior Palestinian security official told Reuters.</p>
<p>Fifty-five Palestinians and 14 Israelis were killed in several days of fierce clashes and gun battles in the West Bank and Gaza Strip spurred by the opening of a second entrance to a tourist tunnel in Jerusalem opposed by Palestinians.</p>
<p>The bloodiest day of clashes was last Thursday when 42 Palestinians and 11 Israelis were killed. The battles that day began near the Kfar Darom Jewish settlement in Gaza.</p>
<p>Haaretz said during a tour of the Gaza settlements on Sunday Israeli Infrastructure Minister Ariel Sharon was told by army commanders that shooting by settlers and Israeli soldiers had set events spinning out of control.</p>
<p>The commander of the Kfar Darom sector, identified only as Lieutenant Colonel Avi, told Sharon:</p>
<p>&quot;An assembly began and stone throwing and there were a demonstration and attempts to disperse it by Assaf (the Israeli officer in charge) and also by the Palestinian police.</p>
<p>&quot;The demonstrators got too close to the (settlement's) fence and a number of shots were fired in the air. That pretty much set the sector on fire.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked who fired the shots, he said: &quot;Both the settlers and our forces...Indiscriminate shooting was what caused this whole situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Haaretz quoted division commander Brigadier General Yitzhak Eitan as then adding: &quot;This place is what in fact set the whole strip on fire in the morning.&quot;</p>
<p>The Israeli army said it was checking the report.</p>
<p>Shawki Harb, head of Ramallah hospital in the West Bank Palestinian enclave of the same name, told Reuters that on Thursday and Friday he treated Arabs wounded by settlers.</p>
<p>Palestinian witnesses said that on Sunday they saw settlers beating Arabs at Qalandia in the West Bank. They said settlers were periodically blocking the road to Nablus, stopping cars and beating the Palestinian occupants.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu left Israel for Washington on Monday to attend a summit called by President Bill Clinton to end the violence.</p>
<p>Egyptian and Palestinian Presidents Hosni Mubarak and Yasser Arafat asked Clinton to postpone the summit set to begin on Tuesday until they could be assured it would produce results.</p>
<p>Israel's opening of the tunnel near Moslem holy sites in Jerusalem, whose final status is a matter of hot dispute between Israelis and Arabs, combined with festering Palestinian frustration over Netanyahu's policies to ignite the gun battles.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has vowed not to close the tunnel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
