<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="12890" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British TV seeks to learn from Dunblane massacre.</title>
<headline>British TV seeks to learn from Dunblane massacre.</headline>
<byline>Keith Weir</byline>
<dateline>EDINBURGH 1996-08-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>A community leader from the Scottish town of Dunblane, where a gunman massacred 16 children and their teacher last March, urged news media on Sunday against trampling local feelings underfoot when covering such a story.</p>
<p>&quot;You say that you were restrained, well I would hate to see it when you unleash your full action,&quot; Pat Greenhill told a forum of broadcast industry leaders at the Edinburgh International Television Festival.</p>
<p>&quot;There were individual instances of horrendous behaviour from some press and television,&quot; said Greenhill, who acted as a spokeswoman for the community in the aftermath of the killings.</p>
<p>The quiet town of Dunblane became a focus of world media attention give months ago when grudge-bearing loner Thomas Hamilton went berserk with guns at an entire class assembled in a school gymnasium.</p>
<p>Local people were at first anxious to help the hordes of reporters but their mood gradually changed and they made clear they wanted to be left to grieve alone.</p>
<p>News organisations heeded the pleas and withdrew after five days of intensive coverage, leaving the families to bury their dead without the intrusion of the television camera.</p>
<p>Greenhill said she had been forced to unplug her telephone in the middle of the night to gain some respite from reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;It was hard at times not to feel you were nothing more than a commodity to fill a 20-second slot,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>But Greenhill added that British television had in general got its coverage right and praised the decision to pull out before the funerals.</p>
<p>Britain's Broadcasting Standards Council has criticised Independent Television News (ITN) for showing pictures of grieving relatives of the five and six-year-olds who died.</p>
<p>But ITN defended the decision.</p>
<p>&quot;Those were harrowing and heart-rending pictures,&quot; said Nigel Dacre, editor of ITN News on the commercial ITV network.</p>
<p>&quot;But we can't create a make-believe world in which people don't cry.&quot;</p>
<p>ITN Editor-in-Chief Richard Tait criticised some foreign television crews who he said had arrived late in Dunblane and tried to get local people to restage interviews they had already given to other networks.</p>
<p>&quot;That is intrusive, unacceptable and bad TV,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added that American colleagues had told him that broadcasters in the U.S. would have set up cameras outside the homes of the parents of the victims, something that did not happen in Dunblane.</p>
<p>Two members of the public attending the session in Edinburgh, an hour's drive south of Dunblane, had differing views on the coverage.</p>
<p>&quot;With hindsight, it was quite restrained and it did bring to mind the horrors caused by lax gun laws,&quot; said one woman.</p>
<p>But another woman said she had been so upset that she had turned off the television and stopped listening to the radio.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't need to see those images, thank you very much. I have enough compassion and humanity to imagine what happened.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EDINBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
