<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14567" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton stokes train trip with anti-crime initiative.</title>
<headline>Clinton stokes train trip with anti-crime initiative.</headline>
<byline>Gene Gibbons</byline>
<dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Monday launched a Democratic Convention-linked barrage of policy initiatives by calling for a ban on the sale of handguns to people convicted of domestic violence.</p>
<p>Clinton unveiled the anti-crime proposal, which was designed to widen the gender gap which gives him an edge over Republican Bob Dole among women voters, as he started the second leg of 559-mile train trip to Chicago, where party activists were gathered to renominate him.</p>
<p>Speaking at the Columbus Police Academy, with lines of police as his backdrop, Clinton said public safety should not be a partisan issue but &quot;an American issue.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Under the current law, thousands of people who are wife- beaters or child abusers ... can still buy handguns with potentially deadly consequences,&quot; Clinton said. &quot;I believe strongly in the right of Americans to own guns. I have used them as a hunter with great joy.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;But make no mistake: those who threaten the safety of others do not deserve our trust,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A White House statement said there were 88,500 incidents of domestic violence in 1994 where a firearm was present. Over a 10-year period ending that year, it said 65 law enforcement officers were killed when responding to family quarrels.</p>
<p>Many spousal abusers are not now affected by a ban on the sale of firearms to convicted felons because many domestic violence cases are treated as misdemeanors.</p>
<p>Clinton's proposal would expand the Brady Bill, which requires a five-day waiting period for handgun purchases to run background checks and which bans felons from buying guns.</p>
<p>Clinton also called for banning cop-killer bullets, saying every law enforcement group backs it and Congress should too. &quot;If a bullet can slice through a bulletproof vest like a hot knife through butter, it should be against the law,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton, on an old-fashioned whistlestop train tour through the Midwest with his daughter Chelsea, 16, while his wife Hillary conducted a separate schedule in her hometown of Chicago, intended to grab headlines with a new proposal every day of his trip. Tuesday's will concern education; Wednesday's, the environment.</p>
<p>His focus on crime was designed to tie into the opening session of the convention, which featured a speech by Sarah Brady, wife of former White House spokesman James Brady, whose wounding inspired the gun law.</p>
<p>Brady is wheelchair-bound because of the gunshot wounds he suffered when John Hinckley Jr. tried to kill then-President Ronald Reagan in 1981.</p>
<p>Clinton, campaigning through five states with 64 of the 270 electoral votes needed to win the presidency on his way to Chicago, is on the 559-mile trip to energise grassroots support for his re-election bid.</p>
<p>In a USA Today/CNN poll released on Monday, Clinton held a 12 percentage point lead over Dole among registered voters, beating the Republican 50-38 with independent Ross Perot winning only 7 percent.</p>
<p>Clinton boarded his &quot;21st Century Express&quot; for the four-day whistlestop in Huntington, West Virginia, on Sunday and rolled through parts of Kentucky before reaching Ohio. His train will also travel through Michigan and Indiana.</p>
<p>As he has at every previous stop, Clinton slammed the tax cut proposal at the heart of Dole's campaign. &quot;We cannot afford to blow a hole in the deficit again,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton was heckled at the start of his speech by a small group of demonstrators, but he silenced them by saying they did not want the American people to know of his record.</p>
<p>If the public learns the truth, Clinton said, his opponents &quot;won't have a chance.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLUMBUS, Ohio"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
