<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15065" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Brady Law stopped 100,000 from buying guns - report.</title>
<headline>Brady Law stopped 100,000 from buying guns - report.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Brady Law, which imposes a five-day waiting period for buying handguns so background checks can be conducted, has kept guns away from more than 100,000 criminals and other banned purchasers, according to a study released Monday by the law's chief proponent.</p>
<p>The study was released hours before President Clinton was to propose extending the law to bar handgun sales to anyone convicted of domestic violence against women.</p>
<p>According to the survey by the Centre to Prevent Handgun Violence, the Brady law stopped 72,325 felons and more than 30,000 others from buying a handgun since it took effect February 28, 1994.</p>
<p>The law is named for James Brady, the White House spokesman wounded in the March 1981 assassination attempt against former President Ronald Reagan. The Centre to Prevent Handgun Violence is chaired by Brady's wife, Sarah.</p>
<p>Beside convicted felons, the law is aimed at preventing handgun purchases by people adjudicated mentally defective or subject to a restraining order.</p>
<p>Clinton was to unveil his proposal, the latest in a series designed to protray him as tough on crime and to appeal to women voters, during a four-day whistlestop train tour through West Virginia, Kentucky, Ohio, Michigan and Indiana.</p>
<p>The Dole-Kemp campaign issued a statement saying Bob Dole supported an initiative to prevent domestic abusers from buying any type of gun and criticised the administration's record on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;Dealing with America's epidemic of domestic violence will take tough laws and tough prosecutors, not more empty rhetoric,&quot; said deputy press secretary Christina Martin.</p>
<p>The president arrives in Chicago Wednesday for the Democratic convention, where he is to be named his party's nominee for re-election on November 5 in a race against Dole.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
