<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="26301" id="root" date="1996-09-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.African leaders to consider return of hanging.</title>
<headline>S.African leaders to consider return of hanging.</headline>
<byline>Anton Ferreira</byline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1996-09-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's ruling African National Congress is to consider reinstating the death penalty in view of a wave of violent crime that is engulfing the country, Justice Minister Dullah Omar said on Sunday.</p>
<p>Omar, summing up after a two-day meeting of ANC leaders on crime, told delegates:</p>
<p>&quot;The view of the summit is that the ANC, as the leading liberation force and democratic force in our country, representing the will of the people, should not be afraid to reassess its position with regard to the death penalty.</p>
<p>&quot;The summit has taken the position that the national executive committee (NEC) should as a matter of urgency review the whole question of the death penalty and if it is necessary the whole policy position of the ANC should be reviewed.&quot;</p>
<p>No one has been executed in South Africa since the then president F.W. de Klerk imposed a moratorium on hangings as part of his political reforms early in 1990.</p>
<p>The death penalty is still on the statute books but the constitutional court has ruled that it cannot be carried out in terms of the country's new democratic constitution.</p>
<p>The ANC, which won the country's first all-race elections in April 1994, has until now opposed capital punishment. But grass-roots pressure for it to be reimposed has gathered pace in recent months as violent crime rages unabated with police apparently powerless to bring it under control.</p>
<p>The constitution can be amended by a two-thirds majority vote in parliament.</p>
<p>Addressing the weekend conference, Omar said action had to be taken to address the socio-economic causes of crime but legislation also had to be tightened.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to send out a clear signal from the ANC that we cannot allow criminality to prevail in our society. We want to ensure our women, our girls, can live in safety,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The death penalty is an issue of concern to communities throughout our country. We are saying that therefore it has to be discussed.&quot;</p>
<p>The conference brought together influential ANC committees involved in studying issues such as policing, crime, defence, prisons and intelligence on a national and provincial level.</p>
<p>President Nelson Mandela was quoted in a newspaper interview on Sunday as saying crime was out of control in some parts of the country.</p>
<p>&quot;People have cause to be worried and we appreciate that,&quot; he said. &quot;When people decide to take the law into their own hands, then the social fabric is breaking down.&quot;</p>
<p>Last month a militant Moslem group launched a campaign against gang leaders in Cape Town, shooting and burning to death a notorious drug dealer in a public lynching.</p>
<p>Last week an executive of the German car maker BMW, Bernd Pischetsrieder, said South Africa's level of violent crime was a disincentive to investors.</p>
<p>The head of another German company in South Africa was shot dead by car hijackers in Johannesburg last month. Days later hijackers killed the father of Doc Khumalo, a member of the national soccer squad.</p>
<p>The president of the constitutional court, Arthur Chaskalson, was robbed at knife point in his home last month.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
