<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54608" id="root" date="1996-09-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: South Korea strengthens police use of firearms.</title>
<headline>South Korea strengthens police use of firearms.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1996-09-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The South Korean government plans to ease regulations on police use of firearms as part of a crackdown on growing violent crimes, the domestic Yonhap news agency said on Sunday.</p>
<p>The revision to the law governing police operations would also allow riot police to strengthen crackdowns on violent student demonstrations, Yonhap said.</p>
<p>&quot;Existing equipment such as plastic shields are almost useless in battling attacks with steel pipes and molotov cocktails,&quot; Yonhap quoted a senior party official as saying.</p>
<p>Traditionally, police have been restricted from using fire arms because civilian arms ownership has been totally banned in South Korea with the exception of hunting guns.</p>
<p>&quot;We consider introducing multi-purpose equipment, for example, specially-designed armoured vehicles, and replacing plastic shields with transparent ones.&quot;</p>
<p>The move follows a wave of violent anti-government demonstrations in which both civilians and police have been injured.</p>
<p>Last month, a riot policeman died from head injuries when police stormed a Seoul university campus to end an occupation by students demanding reunification with communist North Korea.</p>
<p>Hundreds of police officers and students were also injured in the seven-day showdown on the Yonsei University campus in western Seoul.</p>
<p>Shocked by the worst campus violence since he took office in 1993, President Kim Young-sam has accused radical students of waging urban guerrilla warfare and vowed to punish violent activists.</p>
<p>On Sunday, state KBS television said prosecutors would seek homicide charges against about 10 students arrested in the Yonsei demonstration in relation to the policeman's death.</p>
<p>Prosecution officials could not be immediately reached for comment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
