<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56579" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Astronomers say Major tricked over Dunblane star.</title>
<headline>Astronomers say Major tricked over Dunblane star.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Prime Minister John Major has named a star in memory of the 16 children gunned down with their teacher in the Dunblane school massacre.</p>
<p>But astronomers said on Monday that Major's bid to commemorate the infants, killed in Scotland in March by crazed gunman Thomas Hamilton, was worthless and he had been tricked.</p>
<p>&quot;The prime minister should have been advised not to have anything to do with this huge commercial con. It beggars belief he was not warned that it has no astronomical significance,&quot; said John Mason, former president of the British Astronomical Association.</p>
<p>A number of organisations advertise in Britain offering people the chance to name stars after loved ones. They pay a sum and receive a certificate.</p>
<p>&quot;Sometimes the star names are sold three or four times over to unsuspecting buyers. I know Dunblane was a terrible tragedy, but this is no way to commemorate it,&quot;</p>
<p>Officials at Major's office said the prime minister had taken a personal decision to name a star on the suggestion of a member of the public.</p>
<p>&quot;It was definitely something he wanted to see happen because he was so moved by the plight of the people of Dunblane.&quot;</p>
<p>A spokesman for Major told reporters: &quot;The intent is to find yet another way of marking the appalling tragedy of Dunblane and to take a further step to ensure that the memory of those children is never lost.&quot;</p>
<p>Astronomers said that although many of the brighter stars in the sky have names handed down from antiquity, the recognised designations of stars are in the form of letters or numbers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
