<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="73397" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Violent crime rises in England and Wales.</title>
<headline>Violent crime rises in England and Wales.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Crime rose in England and Wales for the first time in two years, the government reported on Tuesday, with the biggest increase in violent crimes like assault and rape.</p>
<p>The Home Office (interior ministry) reported overall recorded crimes had risen 0.4 percent in the year to June.</p>
<p>&quot;This compares to the 12 months to June 1995 which saw a fall of five per cent and the 12 months to June 1994 in which recorded crime fell by 5.5 per cent,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>The rise was certain to embarrass the Conservative government of Prime Minister John Major, ahead of his party's annual conference next month. Crime has been a big issue in British politics and is likely to figure highly as a general election, due by next May, approaches.</p>
<p>The number of violent crimes had risen 10 percent, with assaults, rapes and muggings all on the increase.</p>
<p>But police said violent crimes are still rare in Britain, making up only six percent of all crimes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
