<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74790" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK retailers launch scheme to combat violent crime.</title>
<headline>UK retailers launch scheme to combat violent crime.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>British retailers on Wednesday launched a campaign to help stores combat robbery and violence, which cost the industry at least 1.5 billion pounds ($2.35 billion) last year.</p>
<p>The crime prevention effort, backed by the government, aims to train shop owners and their staff to try and prevent retail theft and cope with robbery and violence.</p>
<p>Last year, there were more than 15,000 robberies at retail outlets, up 17 percent on the year before, with losses more than doubling to 29 million pounds from 12 million, according to statistics from the British Retail Consortium.</p>
<p>There were 11,540 violent incidents reported and 1,154 staff injured as a result.</p>
<p>Jerry Walton, managing director of Whitbread Plc's off-licence chain Thresher and chairman of Retail Action Group, said the statistics did not tell the whole story. &quot;The real victims are the innocent people involved in the offences who are threatened with violence, shot, stabbed or clubbed.&quot;</p>
<p>He said off-licences and small chemist shops were particularly vulnerable. Thresher recorded 1,600 serious incidents in its 1,600 stores last year, although not one per shop, Walton told a news conference.</p>
<p>He said big retailing firms had the capacity to train staff and support those affected by crime but staff in small shops were much more isolated.</p>
<p>&quot;Independent retailers work long hours, frequently in difficult trading areas and suffer particular problems because they also live over or near the shop,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Home Affairs minister Timothy Kirkhope, giving his support to the training effort, said the risk to small retailers of being a victim of an attack was five times higher per employee.</p>
<p>The training package, which includes two training videos -- Stop Violence and Counter Violence -- is sponsored by the BRC, leading retailers and National Lottery company Camelot LOTT.CN. The films show how to deter thieves and how to diffuse potentially violent situations.</p>
<p>David Boot of retail consultancy Compass Vision, which produced the videos, said the increase in part time work meant staff were less experienced in dealing with aggression, or &quot;store rage&quot; as it has been dubbed in the newspapers. ($1=.6392 Pound)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
