<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74917" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa's Mandela refuses review on death penalty.</title>
<headline>S.Africa's Mandela refuses review on death penalty.</headline>
<dateline>PRETORIA 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Nelson Mandela said on Wednesday he would not consider reinstating the death penalty despite a poll that showed 93 percent of South Africans wanted hangings to combat increasing violent crime.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be no review by this government. We have outlawed the capital sentence,&quot; Mandela told a news briefing.</p>
<p>Rapidly escalating crime, from car hijackings to commercial fraud, is a main obstacle cited by the business community to economic growth and by South Africans leaving the country.</p>
<p>A poll published this week by The Star daily showed only seven percent of its readers, of all ethnic groups, opposed a return of state hangings. Of those, many wanted life imprisonment without remission for murderers.</p>
<p>The majority wanted a state of emergency introduced and said a suspension of some civil rights was justifiable to counter the nearly two million serious crimes reported last year, including 18,983 murders and 66,838 robberies.</p>
<p>But Mandela said the death penalty went against fundamental human rights and an outdated answer to crime: &quot;Our task is to go to the grassroots, to modernise them and indicate the strategies that should be adopted if we are going to bring down the level of crime.&quot;</p>
<p>Pledging his faith in anti-crime measures begun during his two years in office, Mandela said a campaign to root out corruption in the police force had led to the arrest of 708 officers between July 1994 and June this year.</p>
<p>&quot;So, the tide against crime is gathering momentum. We believe that in due course we will be able to bring down the high levels of crime,&quot; the president said.</p>
<p>The crime wave prompted Justice Minister Dullah Omar to announce recently that the ruling African National Congress (ANC) would reassess its opposition to the death penalty.</p>
<p>But Mandela, jailed for 27 years for his opposition to apartheid before becoming South Africa's first democratic president, has always made clear that state hangings are repugnant to the human rights culture he wants to uphold.</p>
<p>No one has been executed in South Africa since former president F.W. de Klerk ordered a moratorium in 1990 as part of political reforms. In June 1995 the death penalty was ruled invalid by the Constitutional Court.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRETORIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
