<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="15776" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Web sweepstakes for college fund account.</title>
<headline>Web sweepstakes for college fund account.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-08-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>A no-load mutual fund firm has launched a sweepstakes on the World Wide Web where parents can take a chance on winning a fund account to help pay their children's college costs.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to show parents that investing even as little as $100 a month, if they start early enough, can help then pay for their child's education,&quot; said Stanley Egener, president of fund firm Neuberger &amp; Berman.</p>
<p>The &quot;College Starter Sweepstakes&quot; at the Web site will run through Nov. 30 and give parents a shot at winning a no-load mutal fund account valued at $1,200.</p>
<p>To enter, the parent must fill out a college planning worksheet and an on-line entry form. The firm will deposit $100 a month for 12 months into a custodial account in the name of the child of the winner. The parent can pick the fund of his or her choice.</p>
<p>Three winners will be chosen at random in December, the company said. The Web site's address is http://www.nbfunds.com.    The contest was announced in conjunction with the release of the results of a study the firm commissioned that showed parents are saving very little for their children's college costs.</p>
<p>Of 1,000 parents surveyed with children under 13 years old in May, more than one-third could not even guess what it would cost to send their children to college. Of those who tried to guess, two-thirds underestimated the cost and half of those were off by 50 percent or more, the company said.</p>
<p>The survey showed that parents who have started a savings plan for college costs are only saving about half or less then they will need for college bills.</p>
<p>And those bills will be staggering for some people.</p>
<p>By the time the class of 2010 enters college, the estimated cost for tuition, room, board and other expenses for a full four years will be $87,000 for a public school and $185,000 for a private school, based on data from the College Board Annual Survey of Colleges.</p>
<p>Parents who haven't started saving will need to invest $360 a month per child for a public school and $767 a month for a private college, according the college planning worksheet available at the fund's Web site.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
