<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="17498" id="root" date="1996-08-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson lawyer asks ban on broad range of evidence.</title>
<headline>Simpson lawyer asks ban on broad range of evidence.</headline>
<byline>Dan Whitcomb</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-08-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson's attorneys filed a battery of motions Monday asking the judge in his civil wrongful deaths lawsuit to bar evidence ranging from spousal abuse to the former football hero's financial worth.</p>
<p>Simpson, found not guilty by a criminal jury last October of the murders of his former wife, Nicole Brown Simpson, and her friend Ronald Goldman in June 1994, is being sued for damages by the families of the victims, who allege he was responsible for their deaths.</p>
<p>Among the two-foot stack of motions filed by Monday's deadline was one by the family of Nicole Brown to bar any mention of stories they sold about the criminal proceedings to tabloid newspapers.</p>
<p>Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki is set to rule on the motions from all parties when the trial gets under way Sept. 17.</p>
<p>Jury selection is expected to take at least a month, after which testimony will begin with Simpson expected to take the witness stand in his own defence at some point. He did not testify in the criminal trial.</p>
<p>The motions filed on behalf of Simpson by his lead attorney, Robert Baker, sought to prevent the jury from hearing:</p>
<p>-- All evidence of domestic discord, including Simpson's plea of no contest to spousal abuse during their marriage stemming from a police emergency call made by Nicole Brown.</p>
<p>-- Any characterisation of Nicole Brown as a battered wife.</p>
<p>-- Any evidence of drug use or marital infidelity by Simpson.</p>
<p>-- Any evidence of Simpson's financial worth.</p>
<p>-- Any opinions from witnesses of Simpson's guilt or innocence.</p>
<p>-- Any statements made by Nicole Brown to friends or family expressing fear of Simpson.</p>
<p>Simpson also asked that the jury be shown his mansion in the upscale Brentwood area of Los Angeles as well as the murder scene outside Nicole Brown's luxury townhouse two miles away.</p>
<p>In his motions, Baker stressed, &quot;The defence in this case is simply that Mr. Simpson did not kill the victims of this double homicide.&quot; Any evidence of prior physical confrontations between the couple would be prejudicial to Simpson's case, he added.</p>
<p>The Brown family, in motions filed by their attorney, John Kelly, also asked Fujisaki to ban any reference to &quot;generosity and benevolence&quot; and financial support to the Browns by Simpson during the time of his relationship with Nicole Brown.</p>
<p>They also asked that the jury not hear any reference to the Nicole Brown Simpson Charitable Foundation, set up by Denise Brown in the wake of her younger sister's murder to aid battered women.</p>
<p>Motions filed by the Goldman family were expected to be released Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
