<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="24340" id="root" date="1996-08-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. court rules killer better parent than lesbian.</title>
<headline>U.S. court rules killer better parent than lesbian.</headline>
<dateline>TALLAHASSEE, Fla 1996-08-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Florida court on Friday ruled that a convicted murderer was a better potential parent for his 12-year-old daughter than her lesbian mother.</p>
<p>The Florida First District Court of Appeals upheld a trial court ruling in September 1995 that removed Cassie Ward from the home of her mother, Mary Ward, and her lesbian partner and placing her in the home of John Ward, her father, who was convicted 22 years ago of murdering his first wife.</p>
<p>Mary Ward had appealed the ruling saying Pensacola trial judge Joseph Tarbuck had removed her daughter solely because of her lesbian relationship. But John Ward countered that Cassie had exhibited inappropriate behaviour including poor hygiene, bad table manners and a preference for men's cologne, which warranted the change in custody.</p>
<p>Mary Ward had gained custody of Cassie in 1992. Her ex-husband, who is now married to his fourth wife, sought custody after she sued for increased child support.</p>
<p>The appeals court on Friday said the trial judge must be given extreme leeway in rendering decisions and that Tarbuck had weighed all the evidence, not just Mary Ward's sexual orientation, in making his decision.</p>
<p>&quot;Absent a showing of an abuse of discretion by the trial court, this court is not at liberty to disturb the modification of custody,&quot; it said in its opinion.</p>
<p>Mary Ward's attorney, Charlene Carres, said her client planned an appeal to the Florida Supreme Court.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLAHASSEE, Fla"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
