<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29314" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albanian jailed for trying to rape 7-year-old.</title>
<headline>Albanian jailed for trying to rape 7-year-old.</headline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Albanian court sentenced a man to 12 years in jail for the attempted rape of a seven-year-old girl, a local newspaper said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The court in the port town of Durres, 45 km (30 miles) west of Tirana, found the 19-year-old, identified only as D.H., guilty of trying to sexually abuse the child.</p>
<p>The man, who confessed to the attempted rape, said he would not appeal, the daily Koha Jone said.</p>
<p>D.H. was alleged to have lured the girl into his home and to have tried to take advantage of her, the paper said.</p>
<p>&quot;But she screamed so loudly that he was frightened and released her,&quot; the daily said. &quot;He tried to hide but police managed to take him into custody after several days.&quot;</p>
<p>Albanian authorities last week arrested and charged a British man for alleged sexual abuse of two young boys. If found guilty, he could face up to five years in jail.</p>
<p>The British embassy in Tirana said the man was still in custody while investigations continued.</p>
<p>Koha Jone said police had arrested another man several days ago on suspicion of raping a 14-year-old girl.</p>
<p>The age of consent for heterosexual and homosexual sex in Albania is 14.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
