<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="29729" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson judge warns lawyers over frivolous motions.</title>
<headline>Simpson judge warns lawyers over frivolous motions.</headline>
<byline>Michael Miller</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>The judge in charge of O.J. Simpson's civil trial warned lawyers in the case on Tuesday not to file frivolous or publicity-seeking motions, telling them, &quot;Don't waste my time.&quot;</p>
<p>Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki also said he was not going to allow attorneys, &quot;to garbage up this trial with extraneous witnesses.&quot;</p>
<p>Simpson, a former football hero, was found not guilty of the June 1994 murders of his ex-wife, Nicole Brown Simpson, and her friend, Ronald Goldman, who were knifed to death outside Nicole Brown's luxury townhouse.</p>
<p>The families of the victims are suing him for their wrongful deaths, seeking financial damages to make up for the loss of their loved ones.</p>
<p>During a status conference with lawyers from both sides Fujisaki, who has a reputation as a no-nonsense, blunt speaking jurist, said to the lawyers, &quot;If you are just trying to generate interest in this case I would suggest that counsel on all sides refrain from that type of activity.&quot;</p>
<p>And if the lawyers were just &quot;throwing dust in the air and see who blinks,&quot; with their motions, Fujisaki said, &quot;I would suggest don't do it, don't waste my time.&quot;</p>
<p>The judge also put his firm stamp on the proceedings, telling Simpson's lawyers, &quot;I am not going to allow you to garbage up this trial with a bunch of extraneous witnesses. I am not going to allow you to parade witnesses who come from the planet Mars.&quot;</p>
<p>Fujisaki's comments on witnesses followed an accusation by Daniel Petrocelli, appearing for the Goldman family, that Simpson's defence team, headed by Los Angeles attorney Robert Baker, had added 20 unexpected witnesses to the list after both sides had agreed on who should testify in the case.</p>
<p>The judge, noting that some attorneys were not present in court, reminded the lawyers, &quot;If you are going to participate in this case, you had better be here.&quot;</p>
<p>Fujisaki is known for his insistence that attorneys be on time, have their witnesses prepared and be ready to go ahead with their cases.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
