<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="34684" id="root" date="1996-09-05" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: German denies molesting teenage Filipino boys.</title>
<headline>German denies molesting teenage Filipino boys.</headline>
<dateline>MALOLOS, Philippines 1996-09-05</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German engineer on Thursday denied sexually molesting two teenaged Filipino boys in the latest prosecution aimed at stamping out child abuse in the Philippines.</p>
<p>&quot;Not guilty,&quot; Konrad Heinrich Jecht, 63, of Munich said after a clerk read out charges against him in a court in the town of Malolos in Bulacan province, just north of Manila.</p>
<p>Jecht faces three counts of child abuse for his alleged fondling of the private parts of two boys aged 16 and 15.</p>
<p>Court documents said Jecht committed the acts twice in August on the 16-year-old and once in the same month on the younger boy.</p>
<p>None of the alleged victims was present in court.</p>
<p>The 16-year-old said in a sworn statement that Jecht offered him 150 pesos ($5.75) to go with him to Jecht's room in Bulacan and the German had just undressed him when police arrived.</p>
<p>Philippine courts earlier convicted an Australian and a Briton of sexually molesting Filipino children and sentenced them to 17 years in jail each, part of a crackdown to eradicate the country's image as a haven for paedophiles.</p>
<p>The judge who sent Briton Steven Roy Mitchell to jail last month for having sex with two brothers aged eight and four said the verdict should warn foreigners that &quot;this country can no longer be made their playground for illegal activities, like paedophilia and child abuse&quot;.</p>
<p>Jecht is in police custody. His trial opens later this month.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-05"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-05"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MALOLOS, Philippines"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
