<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46566" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson civil trial expected to last four months.</title>
<headline>Simpson civil trial expected to last four months.</headline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif. 1996-09-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The civil trial of O.J. Simpson will begin on schedule next Tuesday and was expected to last a minimum of four months, the ex-football star's lawyer said in court on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But Simpson will not be present on the opening day since he must be in another courtroom to hear the outcome of the legal battle for custody of his children, his attorney Robert Baker told the trial judge.</p>
<p>Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki, presiding over the wrongful death civil trial, met with lawyers from both sides for a status hearing on Wednesday and asked if they were ready to proceed.</p>
<p>Confirming it will start on Sept. 17, Fujisaki asked Baker how long he expected the trial to last. Baker replied at least four months and told the judge Simpson must be in a court in suburban Orange County next Tuesday to hear the ruling in his efforts to retain custody of his two young children.</p>
<p>Sydney, 10, and Justin, 8, have lived with their grandparents Juditha and Louis Brown since Simpson was arrested in June 1994 and charged with murdering his ex-wife, Nicole Brown Simpson, and her friend, Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>Simpson was acquitted of the murders last October but now faces the unlawful death civil suit brought against him by the families of the victims.</p>
<p>Fujisaki has barred television cameras from covering the trial and has issued a sweeping gag order preventing lawyers and witnesses from commenting on the proceedings publicly.</p>
<p>The first day of the trial was expected to consist of discussions about legal motions and the jury selection process was expected to begin on Sept. 18. Fujisaki set another hearing this Friday to discuss evidence issues with lawyers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
