<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="49766" id="root" date="1996-09-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson may face tougher battle in civil trial.</title>
<headline>Simpson may face tougher battle in civil trial.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson will sit at the defence table surrounded by some of America's best legal minds. His accusers will call him a wife beater and a murderer. A jury of 12 will decide his fate.</p>
<p>In many ways, the drama about to unfold in a crowded Santa Monica courtroom may seem strikingly familiar but no one should expect a rerun of last year's sensational trial.</p>
<p>The script, the setting and even the cast of characters have been changed for Simpson's civil trial, which gets under way on Tuesday nearly a year after the former football star was cleared of criminal charges in the 1994 murders of his ex-wife and her friend.</p>
<p>Inside the courtroom, cameras and microphones have been banned, blacking out the proceedings to millions of TV viewers who followed every twist and turn of Simpson's first trial. Outside, a gag order muzzling all trial participants means attorneys will not be battling with sound bites or family members tearfully proclaiming Simpson's guilt or innocence.</p>
<p>This time, Simpson's money -- not his freedom -- will be on the line as he defends himself against wrongful death lawsuits brought by the victims' families. While he cannot be punished with jail time, he could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages if the jury finds him responsible for the murders of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>But Goldman's father, Fred Goldman, has repeatedly maintained his lawsuit is not about cash but about assigning blame for two brutal killings.</p>
<p>Simpson, who has steadfastly maintained his innocence, opted not to take the witness stand at his criminal trial, but this time he will be forced to testify. &quot;He could win or lose depending on his testimony,&quot; said Robert Pugsley, a professor at Southwestern University School of Law in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>The victims' families lack the resources of the district attorney's office, which spent millions unsuccessfully prosecuting Simpson. But they have a major advantage --  rules of civil procedure that make it easier to prove &quot;liability.&quot;</p>
<p>The plaintiffs will prevail if they can convince jurors there is a 50.1 percent probability -- a &quot;preponderance of the evidence&quot; -- that Simpson committed the murders. It is a far cry from the burden faced by criminal prosecutors, who had to prove guilt &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt.&quot;</p>
<p>And the verdict need not be unanimous -- just nine of 12 jurors are required for a judgment for or against Simpson.</p>
<p>Another factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in affluent Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Polls show an overwhelming majority of whites believe Simpson got away with murder, while most blacks support the verdict that freed one of America's top black celebrities.</p>
<p>Jury selection gets under way on Wednesday, beginning a painstaking process of picking 12 regular jurors and eight alternates. Given the extraordinary publicity surrounding the criminal trial, said Loyola Law School professor Laurie Levenson, &quot;It's going to be almost impossible to find people who haven't made up their minds already.&quot;</p>
<p>Taking aim against Simpson will be a battery of nine attorneys representing the Goldman and Brown families.</p>
<p>Prosecutors were accused of botching the criminal case. Now the families hope to right those wrongs with evidence about the famous slow-speed freeway chase and Simpson's history of domestic violence.</p>
<p>Flashy defence attorney Johnnie Cochran, who led Simpson's &quot;Dream Team&quot; in the criminal trial, has stepped aside in favour of Robert Baker, a veteran civil lawyer with strong credentials in wrongful death suits.</p>
<p>Baker, who has assembled a team of five lawyers, wants to introduce many of the same theories of police racism and conspiracy that helped Simpson beat the criminal charges.</p>
<p>Presiding over the trial is Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki, a no-nonsense jurist who banned cameras to prevent a repeat of what he called the &quot;circus atmosphere&quot; of the criminal trial.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
