<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="51780" id="root" date="1996-09-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: TENNIS-CUSTODY ORDER LIFTED ON STEFFI GRAF'S FATHER.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-CUSTODY ORDER LIFTED ON STEFFI GRAF'S FATHER.</headline>
<byline>Michael Able</byline>
<dateline>STUTTGART, Germany 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German court on Friday lifted a custody order on tennis star Steffi Graf's father Peter, currently on trial for tax evasion, but he remained in jail for the time being, Peter Graf's lawyer said.</p>
<p>Kurt Himmelsbach said prosecutors in the town of Mannheim had appealed against the city court's decision, and a high court in Karlsruhe would have to make a final ruling. This decision was unlikely to come on Friday, he said.</p>
<p>Peter Graf, 58, has been in jail in the southwestern town of Mannheim since August 1995.</p>
<p>He is accused, together with family tax advisor Joachim Eckardt, of evading 19 million marks ($12.5 million) of taxes on his daughter's income between 1989 and 1993, and could face up to 10 years in jail if convicted.</p>
<p>At the trial, which began last week, Graf said politicians and tax authorities had led him to believe they approved of his methods of minimising tax on his millionaire daughter's earnings.</p>
<p>Eckardt's lawyers told the court the world number one tennis player, who won the latest of her 21 Grand Slam titles at the U.S. Open in New York last week, had been informed of the details of her father's tax schemes.</p>
<p>She has denied this in interviews, saying she left her tax affairs in her father's hands from the very outset of her career and paid little attention to what she was earning.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Steffi Graf is still formally under investigation in the affair.</p>
<p>She told Friday's edition of the mass-circulation daily Bild that prosecutors were waiting for the outcome of the trial against her father to decide whether to drop the investigation against her in return for a fine.</p>
<p>Himmelsbach said the Mannheim court had also ruled Eckardt should be released from custody. This is usually done if the court decides there is no danger that the accused will flee or falsify evidence.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STUTTGART, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
