<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56519" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: STEFFI GRAF'S FATHER MUST WAIT FOR RELEASE RULING.</title>
<headline>STEFFI GRAF'S FATHER MUST WAIT FOR RELEASE RULING.</headline>
<dateline>STUTTGART, Germany</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tennis star Steffi Graf's father will have to wait several days to see if a court will free him on bail during his current trial for tax-evasion, a court spokesman said Monday.</p>
<p>The court trying Peter Graf in the city of Mannheim ruled Friday that he should be released on $1.98 million bail but prosecutors appealed to a higher court in Karlsruhe.</p>
<p>&quot;There will certainly be no decision in the next two or three days,&quot; the spokesman said, adding that the court needed time to look over the case documents.</p>
<p>Graf and family tax adviser Joachim Eckardt could face a jail sentence of up to 10 years if convicted of evading taxes of around $12.5 million on the multimillionaire player's earnings between 1989 and 1993.</p>
<p>The men who have been in investigative custody about a year went on trial 10 days ago. The court can free them if it decides there is no danger of their fleeing or trying to falsify evidence.</p>
<p>Graf says politicians and fiscal authorities gave him the impression they approved of his financial methods in cutting taxes. His daughter, who is still under investigation, has paid the tax debt in full.</p>
<p>Eckardt, for whom the Mannheim court set bail of 300,000 marks, must wait like Graf to see if the higher court will agree to release him from custody.</p>
<p>Steffi Graf, the world number one tennis player, won the latest of her 21 Grand Slam titles at the U.S. Open in New York earlier this month as the trial was beginning.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STUTTGART, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
