<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="56735" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson trial to begin without TV, without Simpson.</title>
<headline>Simpson trial to begin without TV, without Simpson.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson's civil trial, the sequel to one of the most sensational murder cases of all time, gets under way on Tuesday with cameras banned, the &quot;Dream Team&quot; replaced and the former football star absent from court.</p>
<p>Nearly a year after being cleared of criminal charges in the killings of his ex-wife and her friend, Simpson now faces trial in a wrongful death civil case brought against him by the victims' families.</p>
<p>The question is the same: Did he stab Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman to death on June 12, 1994? But the ground rules have changed, the setting is new and even the cast of characters isn't what it used to be.</p>
<p>There will be no cameras or microphones allowed in the Santa Monica courtroom, so the proceedings will be blacked out to millions of TV viewers who followed every twist and turn of Simpson's first trial.</p>
<p>There will be no celebrity lawyers holding forth outside court to put their spin on trial developments. Superior Court Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki has imposed a sweeping &quot;gag order&quot; to muzzle all participants in the case.</p>
<p>And when the trial officially opens on Tuesday in the seaside enclave of Santa Monica, Simpson himself won't be present, his lawyers say. He has been ordered to an Orange County courtroom, 40 miles (65 km) away, where he is fighting his former in-laws for custody of the two young children he had with his slain ex-wife.</p>
<p>If the custody hearing continues into Wednesday -- the day Fujisaki intends to begin screening the first 225 prospective jurors -- Simpson will have to decide where he's needed most.</p>
<p>In the civil trial, Simpson's money -- not his freedom -- will be on the line. While he cannot be punished with jail time, he could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages if the jury finds him &quot;liable&quot; for the murders.</p>
<p>After a final pre-trial hearing on Monday, the trial begins on Tuesday with legal arguments on requests by both sides to exclude certain key pieces of evidence and lines of testimony.</p>
<p>The families' lawyers want to prevent Simpson's side from floating conspiracy theories about racist cops planting evidence and crime-scene experts contaminating blood samples -- a defence strategy that struck a chord with jurors in the criminal trial.</p>
<p>For its part, the defence team has asked the judge to bar the plaintiffs' attorneys from bringing up Simpson's history of domestic violence against Nicole Brown.</p>
<p>&quot;The judge's rulings will determine whether one side gets a major tactical advantage,&quot; said Robert Pugsley, a professor at the Southwestern University School of Law in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Fujisaki, known for his no-nonsense approach, has already banned TV coverage to prevent a repeat of what he called the &quot;circus atmosphere&quot; of the last trial.</p>
<p>As a result, &quot;Camp O.J.&quot; -- the media compound that sprung up outside the downtown courthouse for Simpson's criminal trial -- has been scaled down. TV networks have set up a smaller encampment of trailers -- dubbed &quot;Camp O.J. By the Sea&quot; -- in the parking lot of the Rand Corp. think tank.</p>
<p>Simpson, who has steadfastly maintained his innocence, opted not to take the witness stand at his criminal trial, but this time he will be forced to testify.</p>
<p>The flamboyant &quot;Dream Team&quot; that defended him against murder charges -- including lead attorney Johnnie Cochran, celebrity lawyer Robert Shapiro, courtroom legend F. Lee Bailey and Harvard law professor Alan Dershowitz -- has been dismantled.</p>
<p>In its place is a team of veteran civil lawyers led by Los Angeles attorney Robert Baker, a master of wrongful death suits known for being tight-lipped with the press. And they are expected to face a challenge in some ways more daunting than the &quot;Dream Team&quot; confronted.</p>
<p>Under the rules of civil procedure, the plaintiffs will prevail if they can convince jurors there is a 50.1 percent probability -- a &quot;preponderance of the evidence&quot; -- that Simpson committed the murders. It is a far cry from the heavier burden faced by criminal prosecutors, who had to prove guilt &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt.&quot;</p>
<p>And the verdict need not be unanimous -- just nine of 12 jurors are required for a judgment for or against Simpson.</p>
<p>Another factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Polls show an overwhelming majority of whites believe Simpson got away with murder, while most blacks support the verdict that freed one of America's top black celebrities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
