<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58428" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Judge in Simpson trial deals setbacks to defense.</title>
<headline>Judge in Simpson trial deals setbacks to defense.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson's civil trial officially got under way on Tuesday with a judge imposing strict limits on the defence team's plan to depict the former football star as the victim of a conspiracy led by a racist policeman.</p>
<p>In a barrage of rapid-fire rulings, Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki dealt Simpson's attorneys a series of setbacks in their efforts to replay in civil court the same controversial theories that led to his acquittal in the murders of his ex-wife and her friend.</p>
<p>Nearly a year later, the case was back in court, but with two glaring absences -- Simpson himself and the TV cameras that made his criminal trial an international media event.</p>
<p>Simpson, who has struggled in vain to repair his battered image, faces a wrongful-death lawsuit brought by the victims' families that accuses him of being responsible -- and financially liable -- for the June 12, 1994, murders of Nicole Brown Simpson and her friend Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>As expected, the Hall of Fame running back was a no-show on opening day. Due to a conflict in court calendars, he had to be 40 miles (65 km) away in an Orange County courtroom, where he is fighting his former in-laws for custody of the two young children he had with his slain ex-wife.</p>
<p>Even with Simpson missing, dozens of camera crews descended on the seaside enclave of Santa Monica, but it was a far cry from the carnival atmosphere that surrounded Simpson's first trial. One sign of calmer times: a scaled-down media encampment, dubbed &quot;Camp O.J. By the Sea.&quot;</p>
<p>Only a handful of publicity seekers were on hand outside the courthouse. One lone protester held a sign that read &quot;O.J. is a murderer.&quot;</p>
<p>Jury selection was set to begin on Wednesday. Attorneys have estimated that trial testimony will last about four months -- less than half the time it took in the first trial.</p>
<p>Simpson's civil trial began with more than three dozen rulings by Fujisaki, who has made clear he does not plan to play ringmaster to another courtroom circus like the criminal trial presided over by Judge Lance Ito.</p>
<p>Most of Tuesday's decisions went in favour of the families, but Fujisaki also gave Simpson several victories, including allowing videotaped testimony by forensics expert Henry Lee, a star witness in the criminal trial.</p>
<p>Fujisaki barred Simpson's lawyers from using their opening arguments to accuse former police detective Mark Fuhrman, a key investigator, of being a racist. During the criminal trial, the defence alleged Fuhrman hated blacks and planted a bloody glove at the black celebrity's estate to frame him.</p>
<p>In another setback for the defence, the judge rejected a defence motion to exclude evidence of Simpson's history of domestic violence against his ex-wife. &quot;This type of evidence is admissible to prove motive, opportunity and intent,&quot; Fujisaki said.</p>
<p>Fujisaki also ruled out a generalized attack on the department's evidence-handling procedures and said the defence could only raise allegations of planted evidence if it could provide solid proof to back their theory.</p>
<p>And he barred Simpson's lawyers from claiming the murders were linked to Nicole Brown Simpson's friend Faye Resnick or Colombian drug lords unless they can provide firm evidence.</p>
<p>Saying he wants to avoid the &quot;spectacle&quot; of the last trial, Fujisaki rejected a defence request to take jurors on a field trip to the crime scene in upscale Brentwood.</p>
<p>Inside the second-floor courtroom, cameras and microphones have been banned, blacking out the proceedings to millions of TV viewers who followed every twist and turn of Simpson's first trial. Outside court, the judge has imposed a &quot;gag order&quot; that will keep attorneys from battling one another with sound bites.</p>
<p>Simpson never took the witness stand during the last trial but he will be forced to testify in civil court. He cannot be punished with jail time, but he could be forced to pay millions in damages if found &quot;liable&quot; for the murders.</p>
<p>Unlike the criminal trial, which required &quot;proof beyond a reasonable doubt,&quot; the plaintiffs in the civil trial will prevail if they can prove there is a 50.1 percent probability - - a &quot;preponderance of the evidence&quot; -- that Simpson committed the murders. Only nine of the 12 jurors' votes are required for a judgment for or against Simpson.</p>
<p>Another factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
