<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58504" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson case filled with tales of murder, conspiracy.</title>
<headline>Simpson case filled with tales of murder, conspiracy.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a chronology of events in the O.J. Simpson double-murder case:</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>1994</p>
<p>June 13 - The bodies of Simpson's ex-wife Nicole Brown Simpson and her friend Ronald Goldman are found outside her Brentwood townhouse. Simpson returns home after an overnight flight to Chicago, is questioned by police and then released.</p>
<p>June 17 - Simpson is arrested after a nationally televised slow-speed chase along Los Angeles freeways.</p>
<p>June 20 - Simpson pleads not guilty.</p>
<p>June 30 - Simpson's preliminary hearing begins.</p>
<p>July 8 - Judge orders Simpson to stand trial.</p>
<p>July 20 - Simpson offers $500,000 reward for information leading to the &quot;real killer or killers.&quot; Ron Goldman's mother, Sharon Rufo, files wrongful death lawsuit against Simpson.</p>
<p>July 22 - Simpson pleads &quot;absolutely, 100 percent not guilty&quot; at his arraignment. Case assigned to Judge Lance Ito.</p>
<p>Sept. 9 - Los Angeles district attorney's office says it will not seek death penalty against Simpson.</p>
<p>Sept. 26 - Jury selection begins.</p>
<p>Nov. 3 - Jury of 12 sworn-in.</p>
<p>Dec. 8 - Twelve alternate jurors sworn-in.</p>
<p>1995</p>
<p>Jan. 11 - Jury sequestered.</p>
<p>Jan. 24 - Prosecutor Marcia Clark begins opening statement.</p>
<p>Jan. 25 - Cochran begins defence opening statement.</p>
<p>Jan. 31 - Testimony begins.</p>
<p>Feb. 3 - Denise Brown takes the witness stand to testify about Simpson's alleged abuse of her sister, Nicole Simpson.</p>
<p>Feb. 12 - Jury tours crime scene and Simpson's mansion.</p>
<p>Mar. 9 - Detective Mark Fuhrman takes the witness stand to testify about finding both bloody gloves.</p>
<p>May 5 - Ron Goldman's father, Fred, files wrongful death lawsuit against Simpson.</p>
<p>May 12 - Nicole's father, Louis Brown, files a wrongful death lawsuit against Simpson for Nicole's estate.</p>
<p>June 15 - Simpson tries on bloody gloves in court and pronounces them &quot;too small.&quot;</p>
<p>July 6 - Prosecution rests case.</p>
<p>July 10 - Defence begins its case.</p>
<p>Aug. 29 - Portions of taped interviews with Fuhrman played in court in which he is heard uttering racial slurs.</p>
<p>Sept. 6 - Taking the witness stand with jury absent, Fuhrman asserts constitutional right against self-incrimination and refuses to answer questions.</p>
<p>Sept. 22 - Simpson proclaims his innocence in a surprise courtroom statement; both sides rest; Ito instructs jury.</p>
<p>Sept. 25 - Prosecution's Clark begins closing statement.</p>
<p>Sept. 27 - Prosecution concludes first phase of closing argument. Defence begins closing statement.</p>
<p>Sept. 28 - Defence wraps up closing argument.</p>
<p>Sept. 29 - Prosecution completes final phase of closing argument. Case is handed over to jury.</p>
<p>Oct. 2 - Jury reaches verdict after less than three hours of deliberation. Ito says verdict to be read next day.</p>
<p>Oct. 3 - Simpson is acquitted and set free.</p>
<p>1996</p>
<p>Jan. 22 - Lawyers for plaintiffs begin taking Simpson's sworn deposition.</p>
<p>Jan. 25 - In first full post-trial TV interview, Simpson tells a Black Entertainment Television reporter that he is innocent.</p>
<p>July 17 - Los Angeles Superior Court Judge Alan Haber, who presided over all pre-trial issues, is removed from case at request of Simpson's attorneys.</p>
<p>July 23 - Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki assigned to preside over civil trial.</p>
<p>Aug. 13 - Fujisaki imposes sweeping gag order on trial participants.</p>
<p>Aug. 23 - Fujisaki bans all electronic media and still cameras from the courtroom.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
