<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58582" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Judge in Simpson civil case deals setbacks to defense.</title>
<headline>Judge in Simpson civil case deals setbacks to defense.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson's civil trial got under way on Tuesday with a judge imposing severe restrictions on his legal team's plan to claim he was framed for murder in a conspiracy led by a racist rogue cop.</p>
<p>In a barrage of rulings, Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki dealt Simpson's attorneys a series of setbacks in their efforts to replay in civil court the same controversial theories that led to his acquittal in the murders of his ex-wife and her friend.</p>
<p>Nearly a year later, the sensational case was back in court with two glaring absences -- the former football star himself and the TV cameras that made his criminal trial an international media event.</p>
<p>Simpson, who has struggled in vain to repair his battered image, faces a wrongful-death lawsuit brought by the victims' families that accuses him of being responsible -- and financially liable -- for the June 12, 1994, murders of Nicole Brown Simpson and her friend Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>As expected, the Hall of Fame running back was a no-show on opening day. Due to a conflict in court calendars, he had to be 40 miles (65 km) away in an Orange County courtroom, where he is fighting his former in-laws for custody of the two young children he had with his slain ex-wife.</p>
<p>Simpson's civil trial began with a series of rapid-fire rulings by the judge, who has made clear he does not plan to play ringmaster to another courtroom circus like the criminal trial presided over by Judge Lance Ito.</p>
<p>Fujisaki barred Simpson's lawyers from using their opening arguments before the jury to accuse former Los Angeles police detective Mark Fuhrman, a key investigator in the criminal case, of being a racist. During the criminal trial, the defence alleged that Fuhrman hated blacks and planted a bloody glove at the black celebrity's estate to frame him.</p>
<p>The judge also raised doubts about whether he would allow any mention of Fuhrman's alleged racism in trial testimony. Fuhrman, who now lives in Idaho, was not expected to testify.</p>
<p>Taking aim at another key defence strategy, Fujisaki ruled out a generalized attack like the one mounted during the criminal trial on the police department's evidence-handling techniques.</p>
<p>He also barred the defence from citing any other possible killers without first showing they have specific evidence to back their claims. That would likely prevent Simpson's lawyers from floating theories that the murders were linked to Colombian drug dealers.</p>
<p>Fujisaki also issued several key rulings in favour of Simpson, including allowing his defence to present allegations of contamination of evidence at the Los Angeles police department's crime laboratory.</p>
<p>Inside the wood-panel second-floor courtroom, cameras and microphones have been banned, blacking out the proceedings to millions of TV viewers who followed every twist and turn of Simpson's first trial. Outside court, the judge has imposed a sweeping &quot;gag order&quot; that will keep attorneys from battling one another with sound bites.</p>
<p>As a result, the media frenzy that surrounded Simpson's first trial has largely subsided -- at least for now. One sign of calmer times: a scaled-down media encampment, dubbed &quot;Camp O.J. By the Sea,&quot; under construction outside the courthouse.</p>
<p>Simpson attorney Robert Baker had asked the judge to delay questioning potential jurors until his client can return to court on Friday, but Fujisaki plans to go ahead with the first phase of jury selection beginning on Wednesday. Testimony is expected to last about four months -- less than half the time it took in the criminal trial.</p>
<p>Simpson never took the witness stand during the last trial but he will be forced to testify in civil court. He cannot be punished with jail time but he could be forced to pay millions in damages if found &quot;liable&quot; for the murders.</p>
<p>Unlike the criminal trial, which required &quot;proof beyond a reasonable doubt,&quot; the plaintiffs in the civil trial will prevail if they can prove there is a 50.1 percent probability -- a &quot;preponderance of the evidence&quot; -- that Simpson committed the murders. And only nine of the 12 jurors' votes are required for a judgment for or against Simpson.</p>
<p>Another factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Polls show an overwhelming majority of whites believe Simpson got away with murder, while most blacks support the verdict that freed one of America's top black celebrities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
