<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="58651" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson II - the major players in the civil trial.</title>
<headline>Simpson II - the major players in the civil trial.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following were the major players in the wrongful death lawsuit brought against O.J. Simpson by the families of murder victims Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>THE DEFENDANT</p>
<p>-- O.J. Simpson, a former star running back in the National Football League who glided into careers as a sportscaster, actor and advertising pitchman. He was acquitted last Oct. 3 in the murders of his ex-wife and her friend.</p>
<p>Since the end of his year-long criminal trial, Simpson has maintained his innocence in a series of TV interviews and in his own mail-order video while contending that he was framed by the Los Angeles Police Department.</p>
<p>Despite his efforts to repair his tarnished image, polls showed that most whites believed he got away with murder while most blacks support the verdict that freed one of the nation's top black celebrities.</p>
<p>THE JUDGE</p>
<p>-- Los Angeles Superior Court Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki, a 16-year veteran of the bench who was assigned to handle the Simpson case after defence attorneys removed Judge Alan Haber.</p>
<p>Fujisaki put the parties on notice that he would not tolerate a &quot;circus atmosphere&quot; in the civil case; one of his first acts as trial judge was to impose a strict gag order on trial participants. He followed that ruling with a complete ban on cameras and tape recorders from the courtroom.</p>
<p>THE PLAINTIFFS</p>
<p>-- Sharon Rufo, Goldman's mother, who divorced Goldman's father, Fred Goldman, in 1974. Fred Goldman was awarded custody of Ron and his sister, Kim; Rufo apparently had limited contact with Ron in the intervening 14 years leading up to his murder.</p>
<p>Rufo was the first plaintiff to sue Simpson, filing her complaint about five weeks after the murders. A resident of St. Louis, she was rarely spotted at the criminal trial and is expected to attend the civil trial only sporadically.</p>
<p>-- Fred Goldman and Kim Goldman, Ron's father and sister, respectively, who in May 1995 filed suit against Simpson in a separate action from Rufo's. Both attended the criminal trial almost daily and were outspoken in their belief that Simpson committed the murders.</p>
<p>-- The estate of Nicole Brown, in a lawsuit filed in May 1995 by her father, Louis Brown, acting as executor. Though Brown Simpson's family members -- including her father, her mother Juditha and sisters Denise, Dominique and Tania -- could be called to testify in the case, they were not named as plaintiffs.</p>
<p>Simpson's two children with his wife, Sydney, 10, and Justin, 8, were the subject of a custody battle between Simpson and the Brown family.</p>
<p>THE LAWYERS</p>
<p>-- Simpson was represented by a battery of at least five lawyers, led by veteran Santa Monica civil attorney Robert Baker, his son, Phillip, and associate Melissa Bluestein.</p>
<p>Robert Blasier, a Sacramento-based lawyer who specialises in DNA evidence and played a role in Simpson's criminal defence, signed on for the civil trial. Courtroom legend F. Lee Bailey, a key member of Simpson's &quot;Dream Team,&quot; also discussed joining the team.</p>
<p>In contrast to the headline-grabbing style of lead criminal lawyer Johnnie Cochran and his &quot;dream team,&quot; the defence attorneys in the civil case largely shunned media attention.</p>
<p>But in pre-trial hearings the defence attorneys suggested they would stress some of the same themes jurors heard in the criminal trial, including a contention that police failed to investigate other possible suspects.</p>
<p>-- The Goldmans were represented by Los Angeles lawyer Daniel Petrocelli and several associates, including Edward Medvene and Peter Gelblum.</p>
<p>Petrocelli, a New Jersey native who finished first in his class in law school, took the lead in many pre-trial issues and in depositions, earning praise from other plaintiffs' attorneys for his thorough, methodical style.</p>
<p>-- The estate of Nicole Brown was represented by New York attorney John Quinlan Kelly and Los Angeles lawyer Natasha Roit. Kelly, with his square-jawed, camera-friendly good looks and deep voice, appeared during the criminal trial on FOX-TV in New York as an expert legal commentator.</p>
<p>-- Rufo was represented by Los Angeles lawyer Michael Brewer, a Los Angeles attorney who graduated from law school in 1985 and specialised in civil litigation for his firm, Hornberger and Criswell.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
