<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="59340" id="root" date="1996-09-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: O.J. Simpson II ready to open in Santa Monica court.</title>
<headline>O.J. Simpson II ready to open in Santa Monica court.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson's civil trial is set to begin on Tuesday, but with two glaring absences - the celebrity defendant himself and the TV cameras that made the American football star's criminal trial an international media event.</p>
<p>Nearly one year after he was acquitted of murdering his ex-wife and a friend, the Simpson case is back in court, this time as a wrongful death civil lawsuit filed by the families of the victims.</p>
<p>But unlike the criminal trial in which he did not testify, Simpson will be forced this time to take the stand to tell what he was doing the night of June 12, 1994, when Nicole Brown and Ronald Goldman were slashed to death.</p>
<p>On the eve of the civil trial, the judge surprised defence attorneys by ordering them to disclose all facts supporting their claims that police tainted evidence and tried to frame Simpson for murder.</p>
<p>No-nonsense Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki told Simpson's attorneys their written answers to questions about their conspiracy theories were &quot;as good as a non-response.&quot; He gave the defence until Sept. 25 to provide the plaintiffs with better information or he would bar their conspiracy theories.</p>
<p>Allegations about a wide-ranging police frameup formed the foundation of the defence strategy that led to Simpson's acquittal last October on double-murder charges.</p>
<p>When the civil trial opens on Tuesday in nearby Santa Monica, Simpson himself will be absent. He has been ordered to a suburban Orange County courtroom where he is fighting his former in-laws for custody of the two young children he had with his slain ex-wife.</p>
<p>Simpson's attorney Robert Baker asked the judge to delay questioning potential jurors until his client can return to court on Friday, but Fujisaki plans to go ahead with the first phase of jury selection on Wednesday.</p>
<p>In contrast to the criminal trial, which Judge Lance Ito allowed to be televised, Fujisaki has barred cameras from his courtroom.</p>
<p>As a result, the proceedings will be blacked out to millions of TV viewers who followed every twist and turn of Simpson's first trial. Neither will there be celebrity lawyers holding forth outside the court to put their spin on trial developments, since Fujisaki has imposed a sweeping &quot;gag order&quot; to muzzle all participants.</p>
<p>Testimony is expected to last about four months -- less than half the duration of the first trial. Simpson cannot be punished with jail time, but he could be forced to pay millions in damages if found &quot;liable&quot; for the murders.</p>
<p>The trial will begin with arguments on motions to exclude key evidence and testimony. The families want to keep Simpson from floating theories about racist police planting evidence and crime-scene experts contaminating blood samples -- a strategy that struck a chord with jurors in the criminal trial.</p>
<p>For its part, the defence team has asked the judge to bar any mention of Simpson's history of domestic violence against Nicole Brown.</p>
<p>In civil suits, a jury does not have to prove guilt &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt.&quot; It is enough for the jury to decide that a &quot;preponderance of the evidence&quot; shows Simpson committed the murders.</p>
<p>And the verdict need not be unanimous -- just nine of 12 jurors are required for a judgment for or against Simpson.</p>
<p>Another factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
