<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62293" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson case turns to new challenge - jury selection.</title>
<headline>Simpson case turns to new challenge - jury selection.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Now that the O.J. Simpson civil trial is under way, the judge and attorneys face a daunting challenge -- finding 12 jurors who haven't already made up their minds.</p>
<p>Simpson's murder trial was by far the most highly publicised courtroom drama in U.S. history, and his acquittal last October in the killings of his ex-wife and her friend divided Americans sharply along racial lines.</p>
<p>With the former football star now facing wrongful-death lawsuits brought by the victims' families, it's hard to find anyone who hasn't already formed a strong opinion about the case.</p>
<p>Either he got away with murder, as the plaintiffs contend, or he is an innocent man being unjustly persecuted, as his supporters argue.</p>
<p>&quot;If any prospective jurors tells the judge they don't have an opinion about Simpson's guilt or innocence, he shouldn't believe them,&quot; said Erwin Chemerinsky, a law professor at the University of Southern California.</p>
<p>Legal scholars agree it will be impossible to find jurors who know nothing about the case. Simpson's yearlong criminal trial was broadcast gavel to gavel on national television.</p>
<p>The media frenzy inspired by the first trial has largely subsided, thanks mostly to the judge's decision to pull the plug on TV coverage.</p>
<p>But given the enormous publicity generated by the criminal case, the best hope, experts say, is to pick jurors who can set aside their opinions and decide the civil suit based on the evidence presented in court.</p>
<p>The trial began on Tuesday. Now comes the painstaking process, beginning on Wednesday, of selecting 12 jurors -- plus eight alternatives -- to decide whether Simpson is responsible for the murders of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>Simpson was expected to miss the first phase -- the weeding-out of those who can't serve because of personal or financial hardship -- because he has to be in an Orange County courtroom fighting his former in-laws for custody of his two young children.</p>
<p>But his attorneys say he will be back on Friday when Superior Court Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki begins questioning prospective jurors to see if they have been tainted by publicity. It took three months to seat a jury in the criminal trial, but Fujisaki has made clear he intends to push the case along, and legal analysts expect testimony by mid-October.</p>
<p>A factor likely to weigh against Simpson is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, all but ensuring the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted him last Oct. 3 in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Polls have consistently shown that an overhelming majority of whites think Simpson committed the murders, while most blacks believe in his innocence.</p>
<p>Fujisaki has no plans to sequester the jury, meaning that unlike the panel in Simpson's criminal trial, they will be allowed to go home each day after court.</p>
<p>It was to shield potential jurors from prejudicial publicity that Fujisaki imposed a &quot;gag order&quot; on trial participants, keeping attorneys from holding forth for the cameras outside court as they did during the criminal trial.</p>
<p>But that may change. An appeals court, responding to objections raised by various news organisations, ruled late on Tuesday that Fujisaki may have overstepped his authority by muzzling witnesses and limiting expressions of opinion about trial proceedings.</p>
<p>The three-judge panel stayed those sections of the gag order, pending further review.</p>
<p>Simpson's trial opened with a flurry of rulings that placed strict limits on the defence team's strategy of depicting their client as the victim of an evidence-planting conspiracy led by a racist detective.</p>
<p>Simpson faces no threat of jail time but could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages if he loses the case.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
