<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64476" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: O.J. Simpson absent for civil trial jury selection.</title>
<headline>O.J. Simpson absent for civil trial jury selection.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson, temporarily thwarted in a legal battle with his slain ex-wife's parents for custody of his two children, was again absent from the courtroom on Thursday as jury selection continued in his wrongful-death civil trial.</p>
<p>He had been expected to show up since the custody hearing in Orange County, some 40 miles (65 km) south of Los Angeles, that he attended the last two days was adjourned on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Lawyers in the child custody case were barred from commenting on the case in which Simpson is trying to regain custody of Sydney, 10, and Justin, 8, the children he had with Nicole Brown Simpson.</p>
<p>But the Orange County Register newspaper reported the hearing to determine whether the ex-football star gets temporary custody was adjourned at the request of the Brown family pending a Nov. 4 trial to consider permanent custody.</p>
<p>Simpson, a football Hall of Famer who became a TV celebrity and bit-part movie actor, was acquitted on Oct. 3 of murdering his ex-wife and her friend Ronald Goldman, who were found slashed to death on June 12, 1994.</p>
<p>The families of the victims filed a wrongful-death civil suit against him alleging he is responsible for the deaths. If they win, he might have to pay millions of dollars in damages.</p>
<p>On the third day of the civil trial, Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki resumed questioning potential jurors who for financial or personal reasons said they were unable to serve on the case, which is expected to last four months.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, he was unsympathetic to excuses from people who cited medical emergencies or a reluctance to serve in such a high-profile case, but he excused some people who said their employers were unwilling to pay for their time in court.</p>
<p>Of a total of 169 possible jurors who reported to the Santa Monica Superior Court on Wednesday, 85 went on to the pool from which the final twelve and eight alternates will be chosen. Court officials said the other 84 were either excused or sent back to serve on other trials.</p>
<p>Once the final pool is established, Fujisaki and lawyers for both sides will begin questioning them about personal attitudes and opinions in an attempt by each side to seat a jury it believes will be able to render a fair judgment.</p>
<p>Among questions they must answer are whether they believe a person has the right to pursue a civil action against a defendant acquitted in criminal court of the same conduct, whether they believe the case is an &quot;unfair attack upon an African-American&quot; and if they think Simpson is a victim of racial discrimination.</p>
<p>The questions, suggested by Daniel Petrocelli, the attorney for Goldman's father Fred, were approved by Fujisaki and will be included on the general questionnaire potential jurors must fill out.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
