<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65289" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Judge imposes &quot;gag order&quot; in Simpson custody fight.</title>
<headline>Judge imposes &quot;gag order&quot; in Simpson custody fight.</headline>
<byline>Andrea Orr</byline>
<dateline>ORANGE, Calif 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>A judge Wednesday imposed a &quot;gag order&quot; in a battle between O.J. Simpson and his former in-laws for custody of his two children as one attorney said the court proceedings were over for now.</p>
<p>Lawyers for both sides were tight-lipped about what, if any, resolution had been reached in the case in which Simpson is trying to regain full custody of the children he had with his slain ex-wife.</p>
<p>&quot;For now, the matter is concluded,&quot; said Saul Gelbart, attorney for Nicole Brown Simpson's parents, Louis and Juditha Brown, who have had temporary guardianship of Sydney, 10, and Justin, 8, since just after their mother's murder in 1994.</p>
<p>After a series of closed-door hearings at an Orange County family court, Gelbart told reporters no further sessions were scheduled for the rest of this week or next. But he declined to say whether a settlement had been reached in the case.</p>
<p>Simpson, who was acquitted last October of murdering his ex-wife and her friend, was a no-show for the first two days of his civil trial in Santa Monica while attending the custody hearings 40 miles (65 km) away in Orange County.</p>
<p>Gelbart's comments and the decision by family court Commissioner Thomas Schulte to muzzle all participants in the case raised speculation that Simpson and the Browns had reached some kind of temporary agreement.</p>
<p>The Orange County Register newspaper reported Wednesday that the purpose of the confidential hearing was to decide whether to grant preliminary custody to Simpson pending a full trial.</p>
<p>Simpson turned the children over to the Browns in June 1994 after he was arrested on murder charges. They have had weekend visits with him since his acquittal, but he now wants them back while the Browns want to keep them.</p>
<p>Simpson contends that since he is the biological father, he should get sole custody. He is reportedly concerned that living with the Browns, who are white, the children are not learning enough about their black heritage.</p>
<p>Schulte's gag order showed that &quot;the privacy of the children is paramount in the court's mind,&quot; Gelbart said.</p>
<p>Time magazine reported in its latest edition that Schulte believes the Simpson household is not the best place for the children and he has told both sides he would consider placing Sydney and Justin with a third party, even in a foster home, if a compromise was not reached.</p>
<p>But Gelbart said putting the children in foster care was &quot;not an option.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ORANGE, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
