<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67144" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson makes first appearance at civil trial.</title>
<headline>Simpson makes first appearance at civil trial.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greeted by jeering protesters, O.J. Simpson walked into court on Friday for his first encounter with prospective jurors who may end up deciding whether he was responsible for the murders of his ex-wife and her friend.</p>
<p>After being a no-show for the first three days of his civil trial, Simpson arrived at the Santa Monica courthouse where he was confronted outside by about 30 sign-waving demonstrators shouting &quot;You're a murderer!&quot; and &quot;You can't hide!&quot;</p>
<p>Inside the courtroom, the former football star -- looking relaxed and confident -- took his place beside his attorneys to hear questioning aimed at weeding out members of the jury pool tainted by the massive publicity surrounding the sensational case.</p>
<p>A middle-aged black man was the first to be questioned, and he told attorneys he believed police had engaged in a &quot;coverup&quot; in their investigation of the June 1994 murders of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman.</p>
<p>But he maintained that despite his opinions, he could still serve as a fair and impartial juror if chosen to sit on the panel.</p>
<p>Simpson was acquitted last October of criminal charges, but he now faces a wrongful-death civil suit brought by the victims' families. The former football star faces no threat of jail time, but could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages if he loses the case.</p>
<p>The prospective jurors being questioned on Friday were among the 169 who survived a first round of &quot;hardship&quot; interrogation to determine whether they were unable to serve because of personal or financial problems.</p>
<p>The judge took a hard line, refusing to excuse many of the people who claimed that physical ailments or family duties made it hard for them to serve during a long trial.</p>
<p>The next phase -- known as &quot;publicity voir dire&quot; -- was considered crucial. Simpson's murder trial was by far the most highly publicised courtroom drama in U.S. history, and his acquittal divided Americans largely along racial lines.</p>
<p>The first trial was broadcast gavel to gavel on national television, making it all but impossible to find jurors who know nothing about the case.</p>
<p>The best hope, legal experts say, is to pick jurors who can set aside their knowledge and opinions and decide the civil suit based solely on the evidence presented in court.</p>
<p>But the difficulty of that task became clear when the first man was questioned about how he was affected by his exposure to the media frenzy that has surrounded the Simpson saga.</p>
<p>The man said he occasionally followed the first trial on television, read about the case in newspapers and magazines and discussed it with friends and family members.</p>
<p>From that, he said he had reached the conclusion that police had conducted a &quot;bad investigation.&quot; &quot;I believe somebody made a mistake and it was a coverup,&quot; he said under questioning by Daniel Petrocelli, attorney for the Goldman family.</p>
<p>During the criminal trial, Simpson's defence team argued that police bungled the murder investigation and tried to frame him in a broad conspiracy led by a racist detective.</p>
<p>Simpson missed the first phase of his civil trial because he had to be in an Orange County courtroom 40 miles (65 km) away to fight for custody of the two young children he had with his slain ex-wife. The closed-door custody battle was put on hold on Wednesday.</p>
<p>When Simpson arrived at the courthouse on Friday, he was met by jeering protesters held behind police barricades chanting, &quot;O.J., O.J., you can't hide. We charge you with homicide.&quot; Several Simpson supporters tried to shout them down.</p>
<p>Simpson stared at the demonstrators from inside a black sports utility vehicle before dashing through a side entrance to the courthouse. Clad in a dark blue suit, he sat just behind his attorneys in court and took copious notes.</p>
<p>The judge and attorneys are trying to pick 12 regular jurors -- plus eight alternates. Jury selection is expected to take up to two weeks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
