<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="67717" id="root" date="1996-09-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson absent as civil trial jurors questioned.</title>
<headline>Simpson absent as civil trial jurors questioned.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>O.J. Simpson, temporarily thwarted in a legal battle with his slain ex-wife's parents for custody of his two children, was a no-show in court on Thursday as jury selection continued in his wrongful-death civil trial.</p>
<p>Meanwhile Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki enacted orders complying with an appeals court ruling that modified his original gag-order against witnesses and attorneys commenting on the case.</p>
<p>He also agreed to let the press have an audio feed of trial proceedings -- although TV cameras are still barred -- and he allowed sketch artists to do their work inside his courtroom, as the appeals court had ruled.</p>
<p>However, Fujisaki, who is intent on reducing the &quot;circus atmosphere&quot; that surrounded Simpson's criminal trial last year, reserved the right to pull the plug on the audio feed if reporters record or broadcast it.</p>
<p>Simpson had been expected to show up on Thursday since the custody hearing in suburban Orange County, which he attended the last two days, some 40 miles (65 km) south of Los Angeles, was abruptly adjourned on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Lawyers in the child custody case were prohibited from commenting on the case in which Simpson is trying to regain custody of Sydney, 10, and Justin, 8, the children he had with his ex-wife Nicole Brown.</p>
<p>However the Orange County Register newspaper reported that the hearing to determine whether the ex-football star gets temporary custody was adjourned on the request of the Brown family, pending a Nov. 4 trial to consider permanent custody.</p>
<p>Simpson, a Hall of Fame running back who went on to become a TV celebrity and bit-part movie actor, was acquitted Oct. 3 of murdering Nicole Brown and her friend Ronald Goldman, found slashed to death on June 12, 1994.</p>
<p>The families of the victims filed a wrongful-death civil lawsuit against him alleging he is responsible for the deaths. If the plaintiffs prevail, Simpson might have to pay millions of dollars in damages.</p>
<p>On the third day of the civil trial, Fujisaki resumed questioning potential jurors, who for financial or personal reasons said they are unable to serve on the case which is expected to last four months.</p>
<p>The no-nonsense Japanese-American jurist was unsympathetic to all but the most pressing of excuses. Of the 43 people he questioned on Thursday, only 15 were excused. In all, 146 prospective jurors reported to the Santa Monica Municipal Court on Thursday -- 75 were kept in the Simpson pool and 71 were either excused or returned to the pool for other trials.</p>
<p>Fujisaki released one pregnant woman and another who was going on honeymoon in January -- as long as she came back to court to show him her tickets to Hawaii.</p>
<p>One woman said she had broken her tooth and her dog might escape through a broken gate, but Fujisaki was unsympathetic. And to a postal worker he said: &quot;If they give you a hard time, have them call me.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
