<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="68812" id="root" date="1996-09-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson gets mixed reviews from potential jurors.</title>
<headline>Simpson gets mixed reviews from potential jurors.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif. 1996-09-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>In their first face-to-face encounter with O.J. Simpson, some prospective jurors in his civil trial said Friday he was probably a murderer, while others saw him as the victim of a conspiracy.</p>
<p>Simpson, a no-show for the first three days of the proceedings, was confronted outside the Santa Monica courthouse by about 30 jeering protesters who chanted: &quot;O. J., O. J., you can't hide. We charge you with homicide.&quot;</p>
<p>Inside the courtroom, Simpson showed little expression as potential jurors were questioned to determine whether they had been prejudiced by the massive publicity surrounding the sensational case.</p>
<p>Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki dismissed a number of panellists who expressed strong bias while keeping more than a half-dozen others, including a black man who said he believed there was a police coverup and several white women who said Simpson probably murdered his former wife and her friend.</p>
<p>The former football star was acquitted Oct. 3 of criminal charges in the killings of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman, but he now faces a wrongful-death civil case brought by the victims' families.</p>
<p>The 19 potential jurors questioned Friday were largely divided along racial lines, with whites tending to believe Simpson committed the murders and blacks more convinced of his innocence.</p>
<p>Simpson's lead defence attorney Robert Baker accused the families' lawyers of singling out blacks for removal from the jury pool, but Fujisaki dismissed the complaint without comment.</p>
<p>Not even the victims' families were spared. A black woman in her 60s looked straight at Fred Goldman, the father of murder victim Ronald, and accused him of being &quot;greedy&quot; in his quest for monetary damages. Goldman glared back from across the courtoom.</p>
<p>But most panellists also insisted they could set aside their opinions and serve as impartial jurors. &quot;In my mind the score is zero-to-zero,&quot; said a black man who was kept in the jury pool.</p>
<p>Fujisaki, a no-nonsense jurist who has made clear he has no plans to play ringmaster to another courtroom circus like Simpson's criminal trial, scolded attorneys for proceeding at a &quot;snail's pace.&quot; And he ordered them to speed up the process of picking 12 regular jurors and eight alternates.</p>
<p>Jury selection is expected to take up to three weeks, followed by testimony lasting at least four months.</p>
<p>A middle-aged black man was the first to be questioned, telling attorneys he thought police had engaged in a &quot;coverup&quot; in their investigation of the June 1994 murders.  He was allowed to stay on the panel.</p>
<p>A white woman in her 60s dismissed the conspiracy theories that have been floated by Simpson's defence, saying she was &quot;90 percent certain&quot; of his guilt. She was dismissed.</p>
<p>The prospective jurors being grilled Friday were among the 169 who survived a first round of &quot;hardship&quot; questioning to determine whether personal or financial problems would prevent them from serving.</p>
<p>But the latest phase -- known as &quot;publicity voir dire&quot; -- is considered even more crucial.</p>
<p>The first trial -- the most highly publicised courtroom drama in U.S. history -- was broadcast gavel to gavel on national television, making it all but impossible to find jurors who know nothing about the case. The best hope, legal experts say, is to pick jurors who can set aside their opinions.</p>
<p>Legal analysts believe both sides will be anything but colourblind in choosing a jury. Polls have shown that an overwhelming majority of whites believe Simpson got away with murder, while blacks mostly support the not-guilty verdict.</p>
<p>A factor that weighs against the black celebrity is that the case is being tried in upscale Santa Monica, increasing the likelihood that the jury will be whiter and wealthier than the mostly black panel that acquitted Simpson in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>A black man in his 40s told attorneys Simpson was probably framed for the murders and accused police of mishandling blood evidence. Fujisaki ruled that the panellist &quot;has already formed opinion&quot; and dismissed him.</p>
<p>A white woman in her 20s said she thought Simpson was probably guilty and accused him of &quot;bad taste&quot; for selling a home-made video about the case. She stayed on the panel.</p>
<p>Simpson missed the first phase of his civil trial because he had to be in an Orange County courtroom to fight for custody of the two young children he had with his slain former wife. The custody battle was put on hold Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
