<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="75624" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Simpson case lawyers clash over black jurors.</title>
<headline>Simpson case lawyers clash over black jurors.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, California 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers in the O.J. Simpson civil trial clashed in court Wednesday as Simpson's attorney accused his opponents of singling out black potential jurors for questioning about bias they might bring to the trial.</p>
<p>Simpson, who has been sued for monetary damages by the families of the two people he was acquitted in criminal court of murdering, was absent from the civil courtroom as questioning of prospective panellists continued.</p>
<p>Of 14 people interviewed by lawyers Wednesday morning, only five were black and three of them were among the eight people excused from the pool from which 12 jurors and eight alternates will eventually be chosen.</p>
<p>Daniel Petrocelli, lawyer for murder victim Ronald Goldman's father Fred, objected to one young black woman, saying she had &quot;undisclosed bias&quot; she had not revealed in a preliminary questionnaire.</p>
<p>&quot;This witness did not tell the truth,&quot; he told Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki after the woman admitted under questioning that she had &quot;yelled&quot; last Oct. 3 when she ehard Simpson was found not guilty of murder by a mostly black jury.</p>
<p>She also said she believed that police had planted evidence and that white detective Mark Fuhrman, a key prosecution witness, was a racist. Simpson's attorney Robert Baker appealed to Fujisaki to seat the woman.</p>
<p>&quot;A couple of things before we brand this witness a liar,&quot; Baker said. &quot;For Mr Petrocelli to say what he said is outrageous. This is about the tenth black juror in a row the plaintiffs have challenged.&quot;</p>
<p>But Fujisaki, who has a reputation as a no-nonsense jurist, would have none of it and admonished Baker to &quot;just cut it out and sit down.&quot; He excused the woman, saying:&quot;The court finds the juror has evidence of bias.&quot;</p>
<p>The racial makeup of the jury could be crucial in the wrongful death civil trial in which Simpson could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages if found responsible for the deaths of his ex-wife Nicole Brown and her friend Goldman, who were slashed to death on the night of June 12, 1994.</p>
<p>In contrast to last year's criminal trial held in downtown Los Angeles with its ethnically mixed population, the civil trial is taking place in the seaside town of Santa Monica, where people are more affluent and predominantly white.</p>
<p>National polls have consistently shown that Americans are roughly divided along racial lines on the criminal trial outcome, with a majority of whites thinking Simpson got away with murder and blacks supporting the verdict.</p>
<p>During questioning Wednesday, another black woman was told she was not required on the jury after she said her husband had taken her to visit the crime scene a couple of times and had purchased Simpson's video in which he explained his side of events the night of the murders.</p>
<p>The woman also said she believed Nicole Brown was involved in illegal drugs, that police tampered with evidence, that the coroner's report had been &quot;shabby&quot; and that she was happy when Simpson was found not guilty.</p>
<p>During the criminal trial, the former football star and bit-part actor's attorneys contended their client had been framed by racists in the Los Angeles Police Department.</p>
<p>Baker noted the woman had vowed to put aside her beliefs to consider the civil trial fairly, but Fujisaki excused her, saying: &quot;The response of the juror shows strong bias.&quot;</p>
<p>An older black man who said he believed Simpson was &quot;definitely not guilty&quot; was also kicked off the jury pool.</p>
<p>Baker did not object to several white potential jurors who said that although they felt Simpson might have been guilty, they could put that aside and view the civil case objectively.</p>
<p>But one elderly white woman was excused after she said: &quot;If my husband had half of what he (Simpson) had to put up with, he would have killed me long ago.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked to explain, she said &quot;her (Brown's) infidelity.&quot;</p>
<p>In another development, Simpson's legal team filed a motion asking the plaintiffs to hand over Nicole Brown's financial records.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, California"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
