<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="82229" id="root" date="1996-09-27" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: O.J. Simpson trial jury selection inches along.</title>
<headline>O.J. Simpson trial jury selection inches along.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jury selection in O.J. Simpson's wrongful-death civil trial moved at a snail's pace Thursday, with lengthy questioning by lawyers trying even the judge's patience.</p>
<p>In five-and-a-half hours Thursday, only 16 potential jurors were questioned, of which 10 were accepted into the pool from which 12 jurors and eight alternates will be selected.</p>
<p>So far, in four days of questioning potential jurors about their attitudes, only 39 have been selected for the pool -- 20 whites, 15 blacks and four from other ethnic groups.</p>
<p>The panel will hear the civil case brought by the families of Simpson's ex-wife Nicole Brown and a friend Ronald Goldman, who were murdered on June 12, 1994. Simpson was acquitted of the murders last October.</p>
<p>Judge Hiroshi Fujisaki, who at one point appeared to be leaning back in his seat on the bench with his eyes closed, was clearly annoyed by some of the pedantic questioning by attorneys.</p>
<p>At one point, the no-nonsense jurist who this week complained of the &quot;snail's pace&quot; of the proceedings and has banned TV cameras and barred a sketch artist from his courtroom, admonished Brown family lawyer John Kelly, who repeatedly asked one black juror if he had an opinion about ex-detective Mark Fuhrman.</p>
<p>When the man repeatedly replied &quot;no&quot;, Fujisaki snapped at Kelly: &quot;He's already given you the answer, now move on or sit down.&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Fujisaki had shown his patience was wearing thin with one of Simpson's lawyers, Daniel Leonard.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't want to get short with you, but I will get short with you if you keep wandering around,&quot; the stern Japanese- American judge told the lawyer during questioning of another potential juror.</p>
<p>Simpson, an ex-football star and movie actor, was absent for a second day from the courtroom and aides were reported as saying it was because of his frustration with the media coverage of his legal battle against the Brown family for custody of the two children he had with his ex-wife Nicole.</p>
<p>The jury selection process is expected to last at least another week, according to Judge Fujisaki, who told one potential juror he could probably attend a job interview on Oct. 4 since the panel would probably not be seated before then.</p>
<p>In the so-called &quot;publicity voir-dire&quot; phase of the selection process, potential jurors are being asked about their knowledge and opinions of the Simpson criminal trial and whether they feel they can put aside their prejudices or biases, to fairly consider the civil case. They were questioned specifically on their answers to a questionnaire that included such questions as whether they thought Simpson was a victim of racial discrimination or a police conspiracy.</p>
<p>During Thursday's morning session, Simpson's lead attorney Robert Baker once again complained that the lawyers for the plaintiffs were singling out black jurors for more detailed questioning.</p>
<p>&quot;Your honour, this is the 15th challenge of African-American jurors,&quot; he told the judge after another black candidate was challenged by Goldman attorney Daniel Petrocelli.</p>
<p>Petrocelli shot back that the race issue had nothing to do with it and Judge Fujisaki excused the potential juror &quot;for cause&quot;, commenting &quot;This juror questioning reinforced his racial bias.&quot;</p>
<p>The racial makeup of the jury could be crucial since unlike the predominantly black jury that acquitted Simpson in the criminal trial in downtown Los Angeles, the civil trial is being held in predominiantly white Santa Monica.</p>
<p>Also, in a civil trial, a jury may reach a verdict on a 9-3 majority and may find on the basis of &quot;a preponderance of evidence&quot; as opposed to the more stringent guidelines of &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt&quot; used in criminal cases.</p>
<p>If he is found responsible for the deaths of Nicole Brown and Goldman, Simpson could be forced to pay millions of dollars in damages.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-27"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-27"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA MONICA, Calif"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
