<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="54844" id="root" date="1996-09-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INTERVIEW-Sangstat trial results due soon.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW-Sangstat trial results due soon.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1996-09-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>SangStat Medical Corp expects to release in October Phase III clinical trial results of its Thymoglobulin treatment for organ transplant rejection, chairman Philippe Pouletty said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are now in the process of validating the data,&quot; Pouletty said. &quot;We will apply for (U.S. Food and Drug Administration) approval probably by the year end.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that, while the application will not get an expedited review, &quot;the FDA has a history of being active and efficient with drugs for transplantation&quot; and has cleared some recent candidates in well under a year.  </p>
<p>&quot;Thymoglobulin is subject to FDA approval by the end of 1997. It has the potential to take SangStat to profitability,&quot; said Pouletty, explaining the drug has fewer side effects than similar treatments already on the market.</p>
<p>Pouletty said Thymoglobulin's annual sales in Canada, where it already is used on a compassionate basis but not approved for general use or supported by any marketing, are $1 million. He estimated that market is roughly five percent of the size of the U.S. market. The company is also drafting an application for its Cylosporine drug on a claim of bioequivalence with other drugs already on the market.  </p>
<p>Cyclosporine is an immunosuppresive drug designed to minimize the threat graft rejection in organ transplants.</p>
<p>Pouletty also said SangStat hopes to file in the first quarter of 1997 for approval of Azathioprine, another transplant drug currently in Phase II trials.</p>
<p>As part of its strategy to compete with other transplant drugs on the market, SangStat is focusing on service and marketing, partly through its new Transplant Pharmacy, to address long term needs of transplant recipients.</p>
<p>&quot;The Transplant Pharmacy fills a gap in the continuum of care for these patients,&quot; Pouletty said, explaining that transplant patients have to take drugs for the rest of their lives to prevent rejection of the new organ. A major function of the Transplant Pharmacy is to provide easy access to SangStat's brand of drugs through mail deliveries.</p>
<p>--Andrea Orr 213 380-2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
