<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="60471" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Baxter sees stable margins.</title>
<headline>Baxter sees stable margins.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Baxter International Inc, which is spinning off its Allegiance Corp health care products unit, said on Wednesday that it expects to maintain operating profit margins in the 16 to 17 percent range.</p>
<p>Competition and tight pricing will likely keep the margins in check in 1997 and beyond, chief financial officer Harry Kraemer said in an interview following a news conference.</p>
<p>But if growth opportunities in the company's four core businesses pan out, the margins could expand, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're pretty confident we will definitely maintain our operating margins in the 16-to-17 percent range,&quot; Kraemer said. Kraemer reiterated earlier statements that Baxter expects sales growth going forward at around 10 percent and earnings per share growth in the low teens.</p>
<p>In 1997, Baxter's sales growth will be over 20 percent due to the company's acquisition this year of Immuno International AG, he said.</p>
<p>Baxter's continuing renal, biotechnology, cardiovascular and intravenous operations had 1995 sales of $5.0 billion, a 13 percent rise over 1994.</p>
<p>Among growth prospects highlighted by Baxter executives were endovascular grafts, expected to enter clinical trials in the U.S. in mid-1997 and a blood substitute product, entering late-stage trials later this year.</p>
<p>The company is also expecting to begin trials in 1997 or 1998 transplanting pig hearts or kidneys into humans.</p>
<p>On Monday, Baxter said its shareholders will receive one share of health care products unit Allegiance Corp for each five shares of Baxter stock under a spinoff unveiled by the company last year.</p>
<p>-- R. Jacobsen, 212-859-1733</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
