<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="62586" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - Sept 18.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - Sept 18.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>-- BARINGS COLLAPSE CAUSED BY SINGLE TRADER</p>
<p>An in-depth investigation by journalists from the Financial Times has concluded that the collapse of merchant bank Barings was caused almost entirely by the trader Nick Leeson. The results of the investigation are to be published in a book, and show that some other traders had suspicions about Leeson's methods, but that he acted alone.</p>
<p>-- WARNING OVER NEW STYLE PENSIONS</p>
<p>A report from the leading pensions body the Association of Consulting Actuaries has warned that a new type of pension - the portable 'money purchase' schemes - could leave millions of employees with serious pension difficulties. The new schemes are expected to cover one million British employees over the next ten years, but, says the report, because they are linked to share price movements members could end up receiving only 20 or 30 percent of their final salaries compared with 40 percent for traditional company pensions.</p>
<p>-- P&amp;O CHIEF PRESSES FOR CUTS IN CHANNEL FERRY SERVICES</p>
<p>P&amp;O chairman Lord Sterling has hinted that cross-Channel ferry services could be reduced after he commented that overcapacity in the industry needs to be quickly resolved. P&amp;O, which took control of North Sea Ferries this week by acquiring Royal Nedlloyd's 50 percent stake for 25.25 million stg, has seen profits from its ferry operations fall from 24.8 million stg to 500,000 stg in the first half of this year.</p>
<p>-- INTERNET SECURITY FEARS AFTER HACKER ATTACKS</p>
<p>Fresh concerns about the security and reliability of the World Wide Web have been raised by a series of hacker attacks which have left commercial sites disabled and inaccessible. The attacks have even affected information technology companies and Internet access providers, and raise doubts as to the safety of planned banking and transaction services on the Internet.</p>
<p>-- LAST DITCH BID TO HALT THE SALE OF SCOTRAIL</p>
<p>Strathclyde Passenger Transport Executive (SPTE) has appealed to transport secretary Sir George Young to intervene before the sale of the ScotRail franchise this week. SPTE has claimed that any attempt by the franchising director Roger Salmon to invite bids would be illegal since local councillors in the area have not agreed on minimum timetable levels. The SPTE claims that without these the potential bidders will not have all the information they need.</p>
<p>-- MIDLANDS GROUP WINS 17 MILLION STG DEAL FROM BMW</p>
<p>German automotive group BMW has awarded its largest single contract with a UK manufacturer after signing a 17 million stg deal with midlands-based Automotive Products to supply speed- sensitive flywheels for BMW's new family of four and six-cylinder engines. BMW once ran an advertising campaign based on the smoothness of its engines, and Automotive claims that its innovative new flywheel will further reduce vibration from a car's engine and gearbox.</p>
<p>-- TESCO RISES AND LIFTS MARKET SHARE</p>
<p>Supermarket chain Tesco has reported a 12 percent rise in first-half pre-tax profits, to 326 million stg. The results consolidate Tesco's position as the UK's number one supermarket, and the group also reported a rise in market share from 13 to 14 percent. The results were about 20 million stg below expectations due to a petrol price war.</p>
<p>-- BIOTECH GROUP WORKS ON PIG CLONE</p>
<p>Scottish biotechnology company PPL Therapeutics says it hopes to announce soon a collaboration with a British academic group on animal-to-human transplants (xenographs). PPL, which has also genetically engineered sheep to produce medicines in their milk, hopes to clone pigs with organs compatible with humans to offer new technology to prevent human recipients from rejecting pig hearts, kidneys and even lungs.</p>
<p>-- BA TO OUTLINE 1.0 BILLION STG SAVINGS</p>
<p>British Airways is expected Wednesday to announce management plans for one billion stg of savings over the next three years. However, company chairman Robert Ayling is not expected to give details of job losses or business disposals, despite recent speculation. The company has rejected claims that 10,000 jobs will be lost, and Ayling has said recently that he hopes any staff reductions will be on a voluntary basis.</p>
<p>For a full range of news monitoring services, phone BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
