<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="64967" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Neurex pain drug filing seen end of 1997.</title>
<headline>Neurex pain drug filing seen end of 1997.</headline>
<dateline>MENLO PARK, Calif. 1996-09-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Neurex Corp said Thursday it plans to file a new drug application with the Food and Drug Administration for it SNX-111 pain drug by the end of 1997.</p>
<p>The company said it modified its clinical trial strategy for the drug to include a submission for the treatment of cancer pain as well as neuropathic pain.</p>
<p>Previous plans called for a submission for cancer pain treatment only in 1997.  </p>
<p>It said it modified its plan because patient recruitment in the cancer pain study has continued to be &quot;challenging&quot;, and as a result this study would not be completed until 1997 instead of the end of 1996 as previously announced.</p>
<p>Also, the neuropathic pain study has recently been initiated.</p>
<p>With a target of 20 active centers and patient accrual already underway, this study should be completed in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore, these two studies should form the basis of an NDA filing by the end of 1997,&quot; the company said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Cancer patients tend to be closely monitored by their oncologists and this has inhibited referral to our investigator sites, which combined with the need for close monitoring in the SNX-111 study, has inhibited progress,&quot; Paul Goddard, chairman and chief executive of Neurex, said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;By contrast, patients in the non-malignant study seem to be much more readily identifiable and we foresee access to a large pool of patients who have been under treatment at our investigator sites for many years,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>In response to this situation, the company has designed additional studies that will allow patient recruitment at or near the site they are being treated for their underlying disease and overcome resistance to patient referral by specialists.</p>
<p>Neurex said it expects these studies to be initiated soon, widening the clinical trial centers working on SNX-111 and providing further support for a filing with the FDA for chronic severe pain treatment with SNX-111.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MENLO PARK, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
