<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74652" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. stocks end slightly up as techs, bonds surge.</title>
<headline>U.S. stocks end slightly up as techs, bonds surge.</headline>
<byline>Betty Wong</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. stocks ended modestly higher, bolstered by a rally in bonds and high-technology issues, as traders repriced stocks a day after the Fed surprised some by leaving interest rates unchanged.</p>
<p>&quot;Technology is doing well and bonds are doing very well. But there's still some caution. People are not rushing head-long into the market,&quot; said Hildegard Zagorski, a market analyst at Prudential Securities.</p>
<p>The Dow rose three to about 5877 after Tuesday gyrating to a 21-point loss on news of no change in U.S. monetary policy.  </p>
<p>Winners beat losers 6-5 on very heavy NYSE volume of about 448 million shares.</p>
<p>The tech-studded Nasdaq Composite surged nine to about 1225. Technology buying was stoked by 3Com Corp's unexpectedly strong first-quarter earnings report. Shares in the computer networking company rallied eight to 64-5/8.</p>
<p>The long bond climbed 22/32 to yield 6.93 percent, decisively below the key seven percent level, after strong demand for Treasury's $18.25 billion auction of two-year notes.</p>
<p>Hugh Johnson, chief investment officer at First Albany, said the market's focus was &quot;earnings, earnings, earnings.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;Defensive industry groups are performing better than economically sensitive, aside from technology. On the plus side we have banks, food stocks and household products -- those whose earnings tend to do well if the economy slows. On the negative side, autos and retailers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Citicorp edged up 1/8 to 89-7/8, Sara Lee added 7/8 to 34-3/4, GM lost 7/8 to 47-1/2 and Sears fell 1/4 to 45-1/2.</p>
<p>&quot;Compare the performance of 3Com or Cisco with Apple South and Checkpoint Systems,&quot; Johnson said.</p>
<p>Apple South slumped 7-7/8 to 13 and Checkpoint tumbled nine to 27-3/8 after they warned of earnings shortfalls.  </p>
<p>&quot;There is a deep concern that earnings are going to slow and you need to pick the stocks of companies that will continue to post good earnings,&quot; Johnson added.</p>
<p>Among other stocks, Loral Space rose 2-1/2 to 15-3/4 after agreeing to buy AT&amp;T's SkyNet Satellite Services for $712.5 million in cash, in a deal that would create the world's largest satellite-based businesses. AT&amp;T rose 1/4 to 51-3/4 after Tuesday's 5-5/8-point drubbing on an earnings warning.</p>
<p>Apria Healthcare lost 3-3/8 to 17-3/8 after forecasting it would report third-quarter net income that would fall short of Wall Street expectations.  </p>
<p>Several initial public offerings drew buying interest. Snyder Communications, which provides outsourced marketing services, surged 3-5/8 to 20-5/8.</p>
<p>American Residential Services, a provider of heating, ventilation and air conditioning systems service, rose three to 18 and Coffee People lost 3/4 to 8-1/4. Among others making Wall Street debuts, LCC International, which provides radio frequency engineering and network design services for the wireless telecommunications industry, climbed four to 20.</p>
<p>Amway Asia Pacific rose 4-1/8 to 33-7/8. Merrill Lynch named Amway its Focus One stock of the week.  </p>
<p>TCSI Corp, a maker of communications software mainly for telephone companies, lost 5-1/4 to 15-1/2 on market talk the company would not meet third-quarter earnings expectations. Company officials were not available for comment.</p>
<p>Biotechs rallied from a summer slump after some positive industry news. Protein Design jumped 9-7/8 to 26 after it and Roche Holding said their Zenepax drug was successful for preventing kidney transplant rejection in a late-stage trial.</p>
<p>Genetics Institute rose 1-1/4 to 65-7/8 after signing Chiron and Genentech as partners for a protein discovery program.  </p>
<p>Biotech group bellwether Amgen rose 1-1/2 to 63-3/8.</p>
<p>Among stronger technology stocks, IBM added 2-3/8 to 126-1/2, Micron rose 1-1/8 to 32-1/2, Cisco Systems was up 2-11/16 to 63-3/16 and Intel added 3/4 to 97-1/4.</p>
<p>The Nasdaq Composite rose 9.39 to 1224.66.</p>
<p>The S&amp;P 500 index rose 0.22 to 685.83.</p>
<p>(Figures official as of 1645 EDT/2045 GMT)</p>
<p>-- Wall Street desk, 212 859 1721</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
