<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="86304" id="root" date="1996-09-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Contrarian analyst McDougall pushes Roche.</title>
<headline>Contrarian analyst McDougall pushes Roche.</headline>
<byline>Peter Nielsen</byline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1996-09-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Industry analyst Peter McDougall, known for his strong and often contrarian views, will shortly issue a research note that is hot on Roche Holding AG, the Swiss pharma giant that celebrates its centenary on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Although McDougall has moved to Deutsche Morgan Grenfell from Barclays de Zoete Wedd, he continues to have controversial opinions and believes that Roche's growth potential outstrips that of Novartis, the company that will arise from the merger of Ciba-Geigy AG and Sandoz AG.</p>
<p>&quot;While we are happily buyers of Novartis over the short-term, we feel that further upside looks limited in comparison with the Roche story,&quot; McDougall told Reuters.</p>
<p>Plans to create Novartis, the world's second largest pharma company, have stolen the spotlight from Roche, hitherto the undisputed star of the Swiss pharmaceuticals industry.</p>
<p>&quot;But mergers don't create better drug companies, only bigger ones,&quot; McDougall said, going against the general bullish opinions that have accompanied Novartis.</p>
<p>The combination of a slowdown in Roche's growth rate and cost cutting potential of 1.8 billion Swiss francs ($1.4 billion) from merging Sandoz and Ciba shifted market sentiment to Novartis.</p>
<p>The result is that shares in Ciba and Sandoz have soared 40.4 percent and 29.5 percent respectively since the merger was announced on March 7.</p>
<p>But Roche's non-voting equity securities, or genuesscheine, have slipped 2.3 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;But anyone who castigates Roche for growing costs to launch new products while recommending Novartis on the back on enhanced cost cutting simply misses the point,&quot; McDougall said.</p>
<p>The point, according to McDougall, is that Roche has some 23 drugs in late phase III with 11 new chemical entities, a position that is better than any other pharma stock.</p>
<p>Now that the shares of Novartis and Roche are priced roughly the same -- both are trading at prospective price/earnings (P/E) ratios of 17-18 -- it is time to compare the contents of research pipelines as a guide to future growth, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Roche just looks fantastically cheap at these levels,&quot; McDougall said, adding that Roche is the most undervalued stock in the pharma sector.</p>
<p>McDougall said the gains in Ciba and Sandoz shares mean that the benefits from cost cutting are now discounted in the price.</p>
<p>Admitting that Roche is in a weak earnings phase, McDougall eyes a rebound and estimates compound growth in Roche's earnings per share (EPS) of 18.5 percent over the next five years.</p>
<p>This year McDougall estimates a 17.7 percent rise in Roche's EPS and a 17.2 percent rise in 1997, before it picks up to 19.4 percent in 1998 and 21.5 percent in 1999.</p>
<p>Asked how McDougall's growth estimates tally with Roche's own forecast, a spokesman for the Basle-based group declined to give precise forecasts, but said growth should improve after 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;The effect of huge investments in R&amp;D over the past few years, which have resulted in a promising product pipeline -- as well as investments in Genentech and PCR technology -- should after 1997 become visible on the market and result in accelerated growth over next five years,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Roche had compound profit growth of 27 percent over the last 10 years, but this slowed to an annual 15.7 percent in 1994 and 17.8 percent in 1995.</p>
<p>Over the last few years Roche has poured in excess of two billion francs annually into research and development, or more than 15 percent of group sales.</p>
<p>McDougall also forecasts compound growth for Novartis of 18 percent over five years, but argues that the quality of the earnings are very different.</p>
<p>While Roche's growth by 1998 will be fuelled by demand for new products, McDougall said cost-cutting will still account for a large part of the growth in Novartis' earnings.</p>
<p>-- Zurich Editorial +41 1 631 7340 ($ = 1.256 Swiss Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
