<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="13147" id="root" date="1996-08-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - Aug 26.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - Aug 26.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Schools, Vocational Education and Training Minister David Kemp said the Federal Government will be asking schools to take on greater responsibility for the job prospects of their graduates, and their activities may even be extended to become employment placement enterprises. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Industry Commission has offered the automotive industry more influence over the agenda of the Commission's review of the industry's assistance arrangements after 2000 and has said the main subject for the review to look at would be productivity. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The ACTU is planning to launch a major campaign against superannuation changes announced in last week's Federal Budget, arguing the changes will allow employers to stop any payments to low-paid workers and undermine a universal superannuation system. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Opposition Leader Kim Beazley has claimed the new Charter of Budget Honesty will force the Opposition to delay detailed election promises until the second week of the next election campaign, and while he indicated his party's support for the government's new charter, he claimed it would &quot;massively&quot; constrain debate. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Former Defence Minister and National Party Leader Ian Sinclair, has, in his role as chair of the joint parliamentary foreign affairs and defence committee, advised Prime Minister John Howard to meet Tibetan spiritual leader the Dalai Lama in defiance of warnings by the Chinese Government. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Controversy continued over the weekend after Brisbane's Courier Mail newspaper published an eight page spread alleging one of Australia's foremost historians, Manning Clark, was awarded the Order of Lenin, the Soviet Union's highest decoration. Clark's fmily admits he was awarded a medal in Moscow in 1970 after delivering a lecture on Captain Cook, but denies it was the Order of Lenin. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>A study conducted for the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation has found that three in four Australians support a formal reconciliation agreement with legal backing that acknowledges that aborigines lived here before European settlement. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>New South Wales National Party leader Ian Armstrong last night made an embarrassing backdown from his threat to split from the Coalition after five hours of crisis talks. New South Wales Opposition Leader Peter Collins has confirmed the Liberals would run a candidate against the Nationals in Port Macquarie, a safe National party seat. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>Commander Peter Sinclair, the captain of Australia's first commissioned Collins class submarine, is pushing for it to be fitted with Tomahawk cruise missiles. Concerns are held that this could see a regional race for such long-range attack weapons. Sinclair also admitted the submarines will be used for extensive intelligence gathering and communications intercepting operations. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The allegations by Brisbane's Courier Mail newspaper that Australian historian Manning Clark was a spy looked shaky last night, as Clark's cousin, former New South Wales Supreme Court judge Bob Hope called them baseless and disgusting.  The Courier Mail caimed Clark was &quot;indeed a communist&quot; and an &quot;agent of influence&quot; for the Soviet Union during the cold war days. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Despite a backdown by the New South Wales National Party to allow the Liberal Party to contest the Port Macquarie by-election, the future of the New South Wales Coalition remained in limbo overnight.  Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>New South Wales health and agricultural authorities are investigating claims that meats and meat products may be spreading a drug-resistant germ associated with one found in livestock fed the antibiotic avoparcin from livestock to humans, after the diagnois of four Australian patients with the bug. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard has questioned Australia's aboriginal leaders, wondering if they fully represent indigenous views. He believes they have failed to cooperate with the Coalition Government, and his comments will increase pressure on the relationhip between the Government and the Aboriginal community. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Fitzroy players, officials and supporters attended their own funeral at the Melbourne Cricket Ground yesterday as the 100-year-old Australian Rules team played its last game in Melbourne. More than 48,000 people witnessed the final game, which saw the clb thrashed by Richmond by 151 points. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Legislation to be tabled in the Victorian Parliament over the next few months will see the Law Institute of Victoria, the regulatory body for the State's legal profession, abolished, and the powers of a replacement body to be severely curtailed. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Under a Victorian Government review of redundant and unclear legislation, the 1959 Hire Purchase Act faces the axe, much to the disappointment of farmers, small business and consumer groups.  According to the Victorian Farmers' Federation, farmers would suffer without the cheap alternative to an overdraft, which incurs no establishment fee and no stamp duty. Page 3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
