<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="14377" id="root" date="1996-08-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Aug 27.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Aug 27.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>The Federal Government has been forced to reconsider a controversial Budget cost-saving measure to charge entry fees for nursing homes in a bid to stem adverse public reaction, especially from the growing numbers of the aged vote. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Government agencies will be given access to cheaper telecommunications services under an unusual plan from the Commonwealth to become a Telstra &quot;reseller&quot;. The resale plan forms part of a broader policy which will see all Government agencies sign telecommunications agreements with Telstra. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Treasurer Peter Costello has signalled that reform of corporate governance is a government priority. Costello says it is critical to international competitiveness that business adopt internationally acceptable standards, and improve corporate accontability. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Maintenance workers from ACI Packaging's glass plant at Spotswood, Victoria, will offer their employer a peace-plan to settle a seven week-old industrial dispute over retrenchments. The Australian Manufacturing Workers Union said the decision was reached unanimously over the weekend. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>According to the latest Newspoll, voters have given the Costello Budget a positive reaction with 50 per cent of voters believing it to be good for the country. Support for the Coalition has also increased three per cent, up from 47 to 50, despite the view of one in three voters that they will be worse off as a result of the Budget. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>A submission to Foreign Affairs Minister Alexander Downer from his department has recommended that nominees for departmental senior positions sign a declaration claiming they know of no &quot;personal or professional&quot; factors that could count against them being appointed. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The New South Wales National Party has declared its intention to introduce its own legislation into Parliament in a move which threatens the delicate relationship repaired with the Liberals just this week. State National Party leader Ian Armstrong has warned the National Party will not see it necessary to obtain Liberal Party approval to introduce any new Bills. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Microbiologists and immunologists have warned contaminated livestock may be the source of an outbreak of a deadly antibiotic-resistant bacteria which has killed two people and infected four in the eastern States. However the claims are not conclusive and speculation remains that Vancomycin-resistant enterococcus (VRE) could originate in a patient's bowel. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>Universities in New South Wales claim they will be forced to slash more than 6,700 student places over the next two years following the Federal Government's decision to cut funding to higher education by nearly five per cent. The cuts will fall in the post-graduate study area as the Government has been told it, cannot change the number of undergraduate places. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The internationally renowned Australian Council on AIDS - the Federal Government's main advisory body on HIV/AIDS - is to be axed by the Department of Human Services and Health and re-established as a body set up to advise on HIV, sexually transmitted disases and hepatitis C. The move has been defended as a push to recognise HIV/AIDS as part of the mainstream health system. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Federal Government's promise to provide more jobs for young people has been threatened by Democrats youth affairs spokeswoman Senator Natasha Stott Despoja, who is opposing the proposed &quot;youth wage&quot; as a part of the Coalition's Workplace Relations Bill which allows reduced rates of pay for young workers and apprentices. Page 2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>New South Wales Premier Bob Carr has called for a meeting between rugby league administrators and the government following the death of two players in separate incidents during junior league games on the weekend. Carr said he would seek changes from officals to work harder to ensure safety in the game. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>The AFL is in upheaval after a day of somewhat unlikely developments that saw the possible collapse of the Melbourne-Hawthorn merger through the emergence of two benefactors, including mining magnate Joseph Gutnick, and the shock resignation of the leagues chief investigator, Martin Armad. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to an Age poll, most voters believe the Howard Government's first Budget is fair, and while most admit it contains broken promises, few were ready to punish the Government so early. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Father Frank Brennan, one of the key players in the push for Aboriginal reconciliation, has accused Prime Minister John Howard of racism, because of scepticism on behalf of Howard in regard to whether present Aboriginal leaders and ATSIC representatives fully represented indigenous views. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victorian Government MPs are poised to push strongly for tougher sentencing with one MP even raising the issue of chemical castration of child-sex offenders. A cross section of MPs interviewed by the Age believed a push from the Attorney-General will meet little resistance. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
