<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="19285" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>Australia: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Aug 29.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News -Aug 29.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Addressing a meeting of Asia Pacific Energy Ministers in his first major speech on APEC in Sydney last night, Prime Minister John Howard proposed the adoption of free trade in primary energy products by 2000 and called for greater coordination in the market-opening plans to be embraced by the forum's 18 economies. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Deputy Opposition Leader and Shadow Treasurer, Gareth Evans, has urged the Federal Government to put reducing unemployment ahead of cutting the deficit and accused the Coalition of ignoring A$17.2 billion of promises over four years following last week's budget. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian Private Hospitals Association has rejected the proposed application of competition reform in the health sector, claiming the Trade Practices Act protects the market dominance of health insurance funds at the expense of small private hospitas. In a submission to a Senate Committee, the  </p>
<p>APHA said small hospital groups should be allowed to negotiate contracts with major health insurance funds collectively. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Bureau of Statistics figures released as a part of Australia's quarterly international investment position reveal net foreign equity investment in Australia mounted to a record A$94.6 billion and net foreign debt climbed to A$187.8 billion during the June quarter. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard has warned private health funds against undermining the Government's health rebates after five of the biggest funds increased premiums by up to 10 per cent. Howard is determined the full tax rebate benefit of last week's Budget will flow through to health fund members. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Tougher means testing signals the Federal Government's intention to slash payments to 170,000 unemployed job seekers as a result of the Budgetary spending clampdown. As the Government aims to make unemployed people more self-reliant, credit schemes to assit pensioners and unemployed people will also be  </p>
<p>abolished. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Three New South Wales Police officers were yesterday given permission to sue the State Government for negligence after a shootout with dangerous criminals five years ago. Counsel for the officers argued to the Supreme Court the men had been forced to confront heavily armed robbers despite a plan devised by specialist police to protect them. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Federal Government has conceded the '&quot;appalling&quot; conditions some Aborigines live in will not be solved before the Sydney 2000 Olympics. The admission was made as a Queensland Government Minister warned Australia would face international condemnation over the treatment of indigenous people. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>The health insurance rebate announced in the Federal Budget is likely to be off-set by a jump in fee rises by the major insurers. At least nine funds were given Federal Government approval to lift fees by up to 17.5 per cent weeks before the  </p>
<p>rebate scheme aimed at cutting the cost of health insurance was revealed. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian Bureau of Statistics has released figures revealing the level of foreign ownership in Australia surged by A$18 billion last year, confirming speculation that Australia is holding a fire sale of assets to finance the current account deficit.The increase was three times the A$6 billion rise in net foreign debt last financial year. 1995-96 figures show Australia owes A$437 billion to the rest of the world. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The New South Wales Government has issued a health warning after a freak outbreak of meningococcal disease, a potentially lethal condition which can develop into meningitis and septicaemia. Health authorities believe the source is a Penrith nightclub whee seven of the 10 people infected are believed to have contracted the disease. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to new research by the Environment Protection Authority, The Hawkesbury-Nepean River system is experiencing a massive build-up of a toxic dinoflagellate, an exotic micro-organism thought to have been introduced from ship's  </p>
<p>reach the multi-million-dollar target. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Bureau of Air Safety reports show that since 1990 four commercial airliners, including at least two fully laden 747 passenger jets, have been redirected from Essendon Airport by air traffic control after mistaking the airport for Melbourne's Tullamarine Arport. According to Federal member for Wills, Kelvin Thomson, Essendon is not equipped to handle emergencies involving large airliners and if there was an accident, nearby housing would be at risk. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>ballast water.  The increasing level of Alexandrium dinoflagellate could contaminate filter-feeding marine animals such as commercial species of oysters and mussels and lead to public health bans. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>Estimates by Melbourne Major Events reveal that the 2006 Commonwealth Games would cost Melbourne up to A$146 million, plus an extra A$50 million to upgrade sports facilities. The Victorian State capital would rely on corporate sponsorship, ticket sales, merchandising and &quot;coin and stamps projects&quot; to  </p>
<p>Justice Department criminal records and allowed to monitor phone calls from prisons, according to a State Government paper. Page A3.</p>
<p>The Federal Government is now expected to pay possibly two-thirds of the States' and Territories' costs for the national gun buy-back scheme, after Attorney-General Daryl Williams was forced to revise his original offer to pay 50 per cent following opposiion from Police Ministers. Page A3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Privacy Commissioner Kevin O'Connor has criticised the planned move by Victoria's private prison operators to hire their own intelligence officers to collect information on prisoners, staff, visitors and anyone of interest to the prison system.  The intelligence officers would be given access to  </p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
