<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="20350" id="root" date="1996-08-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia says can't help all Aborigines by Olympics.</title>
<headline>Australia says can't help all Aborigines by Olympics.</headline>
<byline>Mark Bendeich</byline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1996-08-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia said on Wednesday it could not fully remedy appalling living conditions of Aborigines before the Sydney 2000 Olympics, when the nation's record on indigenous affairs was expected to come under world scrutiny.</p>
<p>Aboriginal Affairs Minister John Herron made the admission after a fellow conservative political leader said the nation risked embarrassment over &quot;worse than Third World&quot; conditions in some remote communities.</p>
<p>Queensland state's housing minister, Ray Connor, who recently toured outback aboriginal and island communities in the state's north, said people at one remote community drew water from septic reservoirs.</p>
<p>&quot;It's just impossible to explain how bad the situation is,&quot; said Connor, who belongs to the rural-based National party, a partner in Prime Minister John Howard's government which came to power in March.</p>
<p>&quot;Once you see a family of six trying to live in 12 sq metres (130 sq ft)...it's just impossible to imagine this happening in a place like Australia,&quot; Connor told state radio.</p>
<p>Herron said in response to Connor's remarks that the government was not proud of conditions at some aboriginal communities but said remedying all of them would take time.</p>
<p>Asked if this could be done before the Olympics, he said: &quot;It couldn't possibly be.&quot; But he added: &quot;Things are being done in relation to water and power and sewerage and roads, housing, rubbish (collection).&quot;</p>
<p>Some aboriginal leaders have warned of street protests at the Olympics to highlight Aborigines' concern that the new government is risking efforts to improve white-black relations.</p>
<p>Connor visited 10 communities during last week's tour of the Cape York peninsula, including island settlements in the Torres Strait, which separates north Australia from Papua New Guinea.</p>
<p>The island communities are among the most poorly housed, and nearly a fifth of houses there need to be replaced, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;In a very short period of time we are going to have the...world watching us very, very closely,&quot; Connor said.</p>
<p>He agreed the situation in Queensland could embarrass Australia in the media glare surrounding the Sydney Olympics.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a lot less than four years to get this right,&quot; Connor said.</p>
<p>Connor said the funds needed to address the problem were beyond the state's resources. He estimated A$300 million (US$236 million) over the three years would only &quot;scratch the surface&quot;.</p>
<p>He appealed for Canberra to help find and fund a solution.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to deal with it at the most senior level,&quot; he said, suggesting a top-level political task force be formed.</p>
<p>Connor denied the problem would be exacerbated by spending cuts to the administration costs of aboriginal programmes in the 1996/97 (July/June) national budget, announced on August 20.</p>
<p>The cuts sparked a violent protest by Aborigines in the capital last week. There are about 300,000 Aborigines in Australia's 18 million population.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.7880)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
