<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="21511" id="root" date="1996-08-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News-Aug 30.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News-Aug 30.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard yesterday revoked the Federal Health Department's authority to approve health insurance premium rises, following a public outcry over recent increases. Future premium increases must be approved by Health Minister Michael Wooldridge, in conjunction with the Prime Minister and Treasurer Peter Costello. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Following his conviction on four company fraud charges relating to the French Impressionist painting La Promenade, businessman Alan Bond has launched an appeal in the West Australian Supreme Court. Sentenced to three years jail, Bond will apply for release from Perth's Casurina Prison on bail conditions. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Backbencher Kevin Andrews has secured the support of Opposition Whip Leo McLeay as his seconder for the private member's bill challenging the Northern Territory's euthanasia legislation. Prime Minister John Howard and Opposition Leader Kim Beazley have also expressed their support for the bill, but backbenchers Anthony Albanese and Chris Gallus are seeking help to uphold the controversial law. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>In a letter to the New South Wales Farmers Federation, Federal Communications Minister Richard Alston suggested analog mobile technology could be retained for use in rural areas despite the decision to phase out the analog service by the end of the decade to make way for digital to become the sole mobile phone technology. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>After admitting Health Minister Michael Wooldridge had not been consulted over recent increases in health insurance premiums, Prime Minister John Howard yesterday shifted responsibility for premiums from the Health Department to the Health Minister, but the Prime Minister and the Treasurer will have to be consulted before any decisions are made. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Amidst concerns over threats to the safety of Federal Ministers by extremist groups in the gun control debate and more frequent high-level visits to Australia by Asian politicians, this year's Budget allowed for a 32 per cent funding increase for the cental agency charged with handling all VIP protection, the Protective Security Coordination Centre.  Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Federal Government is set to cut more than 230,000 places from employment and training programmes - a decline of almost 35 per cent - despite receiving pre-Budget advice from the Employment Department that a &quot;potential for unemployment to rise&quot; would make selling the budget cuts difficult. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Addressing a national conference of community legal centres in Melbourne, Aboriginal and Social Justice Commissioner Mick Dodson attacked the Howard Government's approach to Aboriginal affairs, claiming the Coalition had created a culture of &quot;disrespect, resentment and vilification&quot; towards indigenous people. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>With at least 11 major health funds receiving Federal Government approval to lift their fees by up to 30 per cent, Prime Minister John Howard yesterday accepted personal responsibility for any future price increases in health insurance premiums. However, Howard refused to rule out further price increases before his proposed private health fund rebates come into effect next July. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>New South Wales' peak parent body has attacked a pay deal that gives public school teachers a 16 per cent salary increase between now and mid-1999, with some senior teachers receiving A$50,000 a year. The New South Wales Parents and Citizens Association claims further school funding cuts will be implemented to pay the rise, which will end up costing taxpayers A$465 million. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The NRMA board decided yesterday to publish the notice of a special meeting to be held on October 30 without the &quot;Yes&quot; case of 250 disgruntled members, but including the &quot;No&quot; case of six directors. The meeting will decide motions calling for the dismissal of the six directors. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The son of William Fox, on the run after allegedly shooting his estranged wife Patricia, has urged anyone helping his father to turn him over to the police. Peter Fox escaped the house where his mother was killed and two other people were left with gunshot wounds. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>Although he will personally assess future applications for private health insurance premium increases, Prime Minister John Howard yesterday refused to rule out further premium rises, which may be required by law to save some health funds' financial reserves falling below the minimum level. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Deputy Prime Minister Tim Fischer has attracted criticism from human rights groups for his attack on American actor Richard Gere and his support for China's Tibet policies. Touring China on a trade visit, Fischer said Gere, a close associate of the Dalai Lama, was not entirely right on the complexities and dimensions of the issue and China was not totally wrong. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>After gathering in Melbourne city yesterday to protest against higher tertiary fees and tougher Austudy rises, about 200 demonstrators stormed the foyer of BHP Petroleum's offices. One student was arrested after smashing a window and a fight broke out when protesters tried to stop television crews filming the demonstration. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to Royal Dental Hospital director Dr Deborah Cole, A$15 million worth of Federal funding cuts may force the closure of the hospital and jeopardise Victoria's rural dental services. The Dental Hospital is set to lose all its Federal funding and ther public dental services face a 60 per cent cut. Page A3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-08-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-08-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
