<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="30653" id="root" date="1996-09-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>PNG'S PRIME MINISTER WARNS AUSTRALIAN FOREIGN MINISTER</p>
<p>Papua New Guinea's (PNG) Prime Minister has criticised Australian Foreign Minister Alexander Downer, saying the Minister is ill-informed about the Bougainville crisis.</p>
<p>Speaking after talks with Prime Minister John Howard at the South Pacific Forum in the Marshall Islands, Sir Julius Chan threatened to wrap Mr Downer across the knuckles.</p>
<p>Mr Downer has warned PNG that military aid could be withdrawn if Australian helicopters are used for a military offensive on Bouganville.</p>
<p>But Sir Julius says the use of the helicopters has been taken out of context.</p>
<p>He said Australia was entitled to impose conditions and it was PNG's choice whether to accept those conditions.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>VICTORIAN GAMBLING SURVEY</p>
<p>A new survey shows that most Victorians want the minimum gambling age raised to 21, and automatic teller machines removed from gaming venues.</p>
<p>But the Casino and Gaming Authority Survey also has revealed public support for the economic benefits of gambling.</p>
<p>Results of a state-wide telephone survey, released today, show about two-thirds of respondents believe the introduction of poker machines has created jobs, and helped government revenues. However, more than half those surveyed want more done for problem gambling.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BEAZLEY ACCUSES WOOLDRIDGE OF DOWNER DEFENCE</p>
<p>The Federal Opposition says Health Minister Michael Wooldridge chose to ignore correspondence from a health insurance company that it was about to lift its rates.</p>
<p>A newspaper report this morning says National Mutual Health Insurance wrote to Dr Wooldridge in July, out of courtesy, advising him it was about to lift its premiums.</p>
<p>Opposition Leader Kim Beazley has accused Doctor Wooldridge of taking the Downer Defence of - &quot;yes the correspondence came in but we didn't show it to the Minister&quot;.</p>
<p>Mr Beazley says it's the Minister's responsibility to know what the health funds are doing.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ALLERGIES COST DAYS OFF</p>
<p>Australians of all ages took more than 433,000 sick days last year due to allergies.</p>
<p>The Institute of Immunology and Allergy Reserach has launched Wattle Week, a campaign to educate Australians about the proper diagnosis and treatment of allergies, to try to reduce this statistic.</p>
<p>Leading allergist Dr Connie Katelaris of Sydney's Westmead Hospital says the message is simple: visit your doctor for correct diagnosis and advice on the most effective allergy treatment.</p>
<p>One in three Australians suffer from allergies, with symptoms ranging from sneezing, running nose and watery eyes, to conjunctivitis and asthma triggered by irritants such as pollen.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HOLSWORTHY AIRPORT WILL MEAN RISE IN LEAD</p>
<p>A lobby group has warned that Sydneysiders face a big jump in airborne lead levels if the Federal Government chooses Holsworthy Army Base as the site for the second international airport.</p>
<p>Spokesman for the Western Sydney Community Alliance, Roy Carter, says the site has been used as a gunnery range for naval guns, small arms and artillery weapons by the army and for carpet bombing by aircraft.</p>
<p>Mr Carter says there's an estimated 250-million ounces of lead on the site with a good percentage deteriorating into lead-oxide.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ALZHEIMERS ASSOCIATION SAYS CARERS NEED BREAKS</p>
<p>The Alzheimers Association says the Federal Government is starting to address the need for &quot;time out&quot; for people caring for sufferers of the disease.</p>
<p>The Association says about 135,000 Australians suffer from moderate to severe Alzheimers, with projections of 240,000 cases by the year 2010, due to an ageing population.</p>
<p>At an Alzheimers forum in Adelaide, the Association's Helena Kyriazopolous, says home care for sufferers is far more cost effective.</p>
<p>But Ms Kyriazopolous says carers need some time off for themselves to make the caring a little bit easier to cope with.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HIGH COURT CHALLENGE TO NT SEAT</p>
<p>A High Court challenge by defeated former member, Warren Snowdon, to the result in the Northern Territory (NT) seat at the Federal election, has heard that votes should be counted the same way in every state.</p>
<p>There's one Federal electorate for the NT and 25 electorates for the Territory Parliament.</p>
<p>The court heard 1,500 votes weren't counted where people had moved between Territory electorates without changing their enrollment.</p>
<p>Mr Snowdon's lawyer says the votes would have been counted in other States.</p>
<p>However John Reeves QC, for the successful candidate Nick Dondas, argues it was the voters responsibility to ensure they were enrolled at the correct address.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ANOTHER RALLY PERSON ARRESTED</p>
<p>Another person has been arrested over the violent demonstration at Parliament House in Canberra the day before the Federal Budget.</p>
<p>An Australian Federal Police team investigating the rally has arrested a 26 year old man from Yass, north of Canberra.</p>
<p>The man has been charged with four counts of assault police and four counts of assault whilst participating in a public assembly.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
