<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="46194" id="root" date="1996-09-11" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Midday Update.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Midday Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>HOWARD WELCOMES NUKE TREATY SUPPORT</p>
<p>Prime Minister, John Howard, says Australia welcomes the adoption of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty by the United Nations.</p>
<p>He says the CTBT is a vital step towards the goal of the elimination of nuclear weapons.</p>
<p>He has urged all nations to join Australia in signing and ratifying the treaty.</p>
<p>Mr Howard says Australians can be proud of the role Australia's played in achieving the outcome.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BY-ELECTION DATE TO BE DETERMINED</p>
<p>House of Representatives Speaker, Bob Halverson, will announce a date for the western Sydney by-election after consulting with the electoral commission and the leaders of the two main parties.</p>
<p>The court of disputed returns this morning ordered a by-election in the seat of Lindsay on the grounds that the winning Coalition candidate was ineligible to stand.</p>
<p>Jackie Kelly was ruled ineligible on the grounds that she was a New Zealand citizen at the time of the election.</p>
<p>Ms Kelly won Lindsay in March with a margin of one-point-six per cent from former Labor minister, Ross Free,</p>
<p>Both will recontest the seat.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BEAZLEY: ALP UNDERDOGS IN BY-ELECTION</p>
<p>Opposition leader, Kim Beazley, says the Lindsay by-election will be the first chance for Australian voters to make a statement about the Federal Government's performance so far.</p>
<p>The court of disputed returns this morning ordered a re-run of the election in the western Sydney seat after it ruled the winning Coalition candidate ineligible.</p>
<p>The court found Jackie Kelly ineligible because she was a New Zealand citizen at the time of the election.</p>
<p>Mr Beazley says ALP candidate and former minister Ross Free will come into the by-election as the underdog.</p>
<p>He says there's been no indication that voter intentions have changed since the federal election.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>INDEPENDENT MP'S MAIDEN SPEECH CONDEMNED</p>
<p>The Federation of Ethnic Communities Councils says Queensland Independent MP Pauline Hanson is out of touch with reality.</p>
<p>This follow Ms Hanson's maiden speech to Federal Parliament last night where she called for a review of immigration policy and the abolition of multiculturalism.</p>
<p>Ms Hanson told Parliament that a truly multicultural country could never be strong or united.</p>
<p>Chairman of the Federation of Ethnic Communities Councils, Vic Rebikoff, has condemned the speech as racist and ignorant.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CATHOLIC CHURCH WEIGHS INTO ABORTION CASE</p>
<p>The Catholic Church has told the High Court it must hear argument about the legality of abortion.</p>
<p>The church is seeking a chance to put its arguments in a case currently being heard in Canberra between Super Clinics Australia and a female patient.</p>
<p>The patient is claiming damages because she says doctors failed to diagnose her pregnancy until the fifth month when it was too late for termination.</p>
<p>Counsel for the church has told the judges that the defence of necessity used to allow abortions is unclear and the court should take the opportunity to hear legal argument.</p>
<p>The church claims any win for the woman will have wide ranging ramification for all health care providers.</p>
<p>The woman is opposing the application, the hearing is continuing.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>N.T. MAY THREATEN GOVT'S SENATE POSITION</p>
<p>A Northern Territory politician says the Government's position in the Senate will be weakened if a bill overriding the Territory's voluntary euthanasia law is passed.</p>
<p>Country Liberal Party member Eric Poole says success of the bill would force Territory Senator Grant Tambling onto the cross benches in protest against the assault on Territory rights.</p>
<p>The bill to prevent any Australian Territory making a law to allow voluntary euthanasia was introduced by a Liberal backbencher this week.</p>
<p>But Mr Poole says any advantage gained by the Government from the defection of Labor Senator Mal Colston to the crossbenches could be lost if the bill is passed.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>WORRIES FOR REMOTE TELSTRA CUSTOMERS</p>
<p>Doubt has been cast on the ability of a partially privatised Telstra to meet its commitments to regional and remote Australians.</p>
<p>The Consumer Telecommunications Network says the Federal Government's proposed protections for such customers under its partial Telstra sell-off plans will be hard to enforce.</p>
<p>The network's Helen Campbell says in order to complain, Telstra customers would have to go to the ombudsman to obtain a certificate of complaint, then go to the Federal Court to get it enforced.</p>
<p>Ms Campbell says this would make it difficult for remote customers to get redress if service guarantees aren't met.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MEDIBANK DENIES FEE RISE INTENTION</p>
<p>Health insurer, Medibank Private, says it hasn't applied to the Federal Government to increase its premiums.</p>
<p>It has been reported that Medibank wants to increase its premiums by more than 10 per cent, or 190 dollars a year for families, and 97 dollars for singles.</p>
<p>But Medibank General Manager, Ken MacDougall, says the insurer is in the process of reviewing its costs and bottom line, but no recommendations have yet been put to the board.</p>
<p>Mr MacDougall says any proposed fee changes have to be passed by the board, before a formal application can be made.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CENTURY ZINC: ABORIGINES SUBMIT PLAN</p>
<p>ATSIC Deputy Chairman, Ray Robinson, says the Century Zinc mine dispute in Queensland's north west could be settled for much less than the 60 million dollars the company's offering Aborigines.</p>
<p>Mr Robinson says Aboriginal groups have forwarded an alternative proposal worth 20 million dollars to the state government.</p>
<p>It involves signing over the ownership of five cattle properties from Century Zinc to Aboriginal groups, and the acquisition of properties along the proposed pipeline to Karumba.</p>
<p>Under the plan, these properties would be designated National Parks.</p>
<p>Mr Robinson says the state government and Century Zinc should agree to accept the offer in order to get the billion dollar mine off the ground.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-11"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-11"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
