<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="53830" id="root" date="1996-09-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Olympics-Sydney launches 2000 Olympic logo.</title>
<headline>Olympics-Sydney launches 2000 Olympic logo.</headline>
<byline>Robert Galvin</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1996-09-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sydney launched the logo for the 2000 Olympics on national television on Saturday as Games organisers predicted an A$1.0 billion (US$800 million) merchandising bonanza over the next four years.</p>
<p>The logo, featuring at its centre three Aboriginal boomerang shapes joined together in a stylised image of an athlete, was unveiled to a television audience as part of a Sydney harbourside ceremony attended by Prime Minister John Howard. The Sydney Organising Comittee for the Olympic Games (SOCOG) has predicted it will earn A$100 million in copyright fees and royalties from domestic and international merchandising.</p>
<p>Products bearing the new logo will be available for sale from January 1, 1997. Major sponsors will also be able to use the logo from that date, the official start of the four-year Sydney Olympiad.</p>
<p>&quot;The logo is part of a very substantial marketing programme which will deliver about A$1.0 billion in turnover. About A$100 million will go to SOCOG,&quot; SOCOG marketing director John Moore said.</p>
<p>The design also features a stylised outline of the Sydney Opera House, the central feature of the logo used by the city in its bid for the Games. Its principal colours are blue, red and yellow to represent the ocean and Australia's arid interior.</p>
<p>&quot;We wanted the logo to bring in our culture, our country and our background,&quot; SOCOG chief executive Mal Hemmerling said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was also very important to us that the athlete should have centre place and that the athlete should be moving forward towards the new millenium,&quot; Hemmerling said.</p>
<p>A steel sculpture of the logo design has been erected next to the water at Darling Harbour in the city.</p>
<p>The use of the boomerang symbol, a curved throwing stick which Aborigines traditionally used for hunting, was welcomed by Aboriginal leaders, who are campaigning for land rights and social equality.</p>
<p>Aborigines, numbering 300,000 among Australia's 18 million population, are the nation's most disadvantaged group. Their life expectancy is 17 to 20 years less than white Australians, and have higher rates of unemployment and health problems.</p>
<p>Some Aboriginal leaders have threatened to disrupt the 2000 Games as a way of protesting against their people's plight.</p>
<p>SOCOG has estimated it will spend A$1.87 billion on running the Games. The New South Wales state government, as underwriter, is committed to spend A$1.9 billion on infrastructure.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$.80)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
