<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="61262" id="root" date="1996-09-18" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News-Sept 19.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News-Sept 19.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard will face a difficult task today when he meets Japanese business groups to stress the federal government's commitment to micro-economic reform, following growing Japanese business concern about Australia's worsening industrial relations, particularly, a recent series of strikes in the Australian coal, waterfront and motor industries. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The federal Parliamentary Joint Committee on the National Crime Authority has indicated it will probably wait until the Attorney-General's Department has conducted a review of &quot;the role of the NCA in the Elliott case&quot; before it launches any formal inquiry into the NCA's Elders IXL investigation. Page 2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>In a bid designed to avert moves by employers to enforce &quot;bans clauses&quot;, the Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union has lifted all strikes and bans for 10 days as negotiations continue with employers on its claim for increases of around A$30 a week in workers' travel allowances. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The National Farmers Federation and the Minerals Council of Australia have given their support to the federal government's action plan proposal to review the five percent general tariff by 2000, but Metal Trades Industry Association director Leigh Purnel has warned that removing the general tariff without proportionate responses from other APEC economies would be inappropriate. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Concerned that the U.S. presidential election has prevented the leading APEC nation from offering an adequate free-trade &quot;action agenda&quot;, Prime Minister John Howard and Japanese Prime Minister Hashimoto will tomorrow discuss how to persuade the United States to a stronger commitment to free trade at November's Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation summit. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Aboriginal Affairs Minister John Herron is seeking legal advice to consider an appeal against yesterday's decision by the Federal Court that he did not have the power to appoint a special auditor with the authority to veto ATSIC's funding arrangements to indigenous organisations. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>In a report to Federal Parliament, Commonwealth Ombudsman Philippa Smith has called for more powers for the Ombudsman to cover problems created by fovernment departments contracting out services to the private sector. Smith warned that people could be denied recourse to appeals against the federal government because of the practice. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Military Board of Inquiry into the Black Hawk helicopter crash in northern Queensland which claimed the lives of 18 Australian servicemen has heard that the diagram used to brief the air crew on the counter-terrorist exercise did not accurately depict the target site. Other problems identified were log book anomalies, an apparent lack of risk analysis, a lack of inter-aircraft coordination and limitation of night vision glasses. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>A military board of inquiry into the mid-air collision between two army Blackhawk helicopters near Townsville last year has heard damning evidence about problems with the preparation for the counter-terrorist exercise. The inquiry heard that briefing diagrams issued to the flyers before they took off misrepresented mountaintop targets and the order in which the six aircraft were to fly. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>With many parents believing single-sex schools benefit their daughters academically and socially, New South Wales Education Minister John Aquilina has ordered a departmental review of enrolment policies to measure the growing demand for new single-sex schols. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Appearing on a charge of being an accessory to murder, 23-year-old Sean Cushman was granted bail yesterday after the Waverley Local Court heard that Cushman had watched his friend Aaron Martin engage in a fight with British tourist Brian Hagland and then left the scene with Martin after both he and Hagland came into contact with the side of a bus. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Federal Court has checked Aboriginal Affairs Minister John Herron's attempt to appoint a &quot;special auditor&quot; to approve grants or loans and block funds distributed by the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission by yesterday ruling that the minister was acting beyond his powers in making the appointment. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>Gold production is set to return to Bendigo after a 42-year lay-off. Bendigo Mining Gis accelerating development of its gold interests in Victoria's Bendigo region by seeking permission to develop a combined open-pit and underground mining operation. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victorian Ombudsman Liza Newby has attacked the state government for putting the health system under strain and compromising the independence of her office. Newby's resignation was announced by the government earlier this week. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Northern Territory Attorney-General Denis Burke has informed the federal government that legal opinions suggest the federal private member's bill seeking to overturn the territory's euthanasia laws could interfere with other territory laws, such as abortion and the switching off of life-support machines. Page A3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Health Department told a Senate estimates committee yesterday that the department had commissioned a report on the physiological effects of the drug ecstasy and was discussing with the National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre the feasibility of running an information-based campaign to educate young people on the effects of the drug. Page A3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-18"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-18"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
