<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="65604" id="root" date="1996-09-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>INFORMATION WITHHELD IN NATIONAL INTEREST</p>
<p>The Chairman of a public inquiry into a helicopter accident which killed 18 soldiers has withheld key information from the media in the interest of national security.</p>
<p>Fifteen Special Air Service soldiers and three airmen died when two Blackhawk helicopters crashed during anti-terrorism training exercises near Townsville in June.</p>
<p>Information regarding the formation in which the helicopters were flying prior to the accident was kept from the public by inquiry's Chairman, Brigadier O'Sullivan.</p>
<p>Brigadier O'Sullivan conceeded that the evidence was vital to the investigation, but said the lives of those still employed in the Service must be protected.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MINISTER ON HEALTH FUND RISES</p>
<p>Federal Health Minister, Michael Wooldridge, has told parliament he's sought assurances from health funds they won't raise premiums in other areas to compensate for new products.</p>
<p>Dr Wooldridge says he won't allow health insurance funds to raise premiums for families if the increases are a result of lowering premiums in other areas.</p>
<p>The Minister has said he will allow funds to offer products with lower premiums tailored to childless couples and single parents.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>AIR DEAL COULD LEAD TO LOWER AIR FARES</p>
<p>The travelling public and consumers are set to benefit from the announcement today of a single aviation market between Australia and New Zealand.</p>
<p>Trans-Tasman airfares are forecast to fall when Australian and New Zealand airlines gain unrestricted rights from November. The deal allows airlines unlimited access to domestic routes in each country, and gives them unrestricted rights to operate trans-tasman services.</p>
<p>The single market was set to take effect in November 1994, but the then Transport Minister Laurie Brereton pulled out of the agreement.</p>
<p>Mr Brereton's successor, John Sharp, says the single market will generate greater competition.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HIV VILIFICATION CASE</p>
<p>In the first case to use New South Wales HIV sexual vilification laws, a gay man has been awarded 50-thousand dollars compensation for prolonged abuse.</p>
<p>The Equal Opportunity Tribunal ordered Elizabeth and Dobrivoje Marinkovic to pay 25-thousand dollars each to the complainant, for subjecting him to years of harassment.</p>
<p>Ruth Hennessy from the anti-discrimination board says it sends a clear signal to people that certain behaviour is unacceptable.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>DODSON SAYS CHANGES WILL DESTROY BALANCE</p>
<p>Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Social Justice Commissioner, Mick Dodson, says the Federal Government's proposed changes to the Native Title Act reduce the property rights of indigenous people.</p>
<p>The Government wants to reduce indigenous negotiation rights on mining exploration, and allow pastoral leases to be renewed or extended indefinitely without the approval of native title holders.</p>
<p>Mr Dodson says the proposals the native title act rests on a vital balance of interests between indigenous and non-indigenous Australians.</p>
<p>He says by destroying that balance, the government will drive Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples away from the Act and into the courts.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>COSTELLO ANNOUNCES PRICES SURVEILLANCE REFORMS</p>
<p>Federal Treasurer Peter Costello says reforms to prices surveillance activity will remove red tape and allow businesses to focus on their real purpose -- doing business.</p>
<p>Mr Costello says in future prices surveillance activity will only be applied to markets where there isn't enough competition.</p>
<p>The price declarations for beer and cigarette manufacturers have been rescinded.</p>
<p>However the companies involved have entered into agreements with the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission to keep price rises below the general inflation rate for the next year. Mr Costello says Government is still considering a recommendation to revoke the declarations for petrol, however he's written to motoring organisations encouraging them to work with the Commission to monitor petrol prices in country areas.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>DAME BERYL CONCERNED ABOUT MEDICARE ABORTIONS</p>
<p>One of the Liberal Party's most prominent members, Dame Beryl Beaurepaire, says one man holding the government to ransom over funding to abortions is democracy gone wrong.</p>
<p>Dame Beryl -- who was an integral player in obtaining the Medicare rebate for abortions -- says publicly funded abortions are at risk of being traded away for secure Senate votes on the part-sale of Telstra.</p>
<p>She's told a meeting of women's political groups in Canberra she's concerned Tasmanian Independent Senator, Brian Harradine's proposal to abolish the rebate is being seriously considered.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>NEW TURTLE SPECIES</p>
<p>In northern Australia, two new species of turtle have been discovered, close to the Katherine Gorge in Nitmiluk National Park.</p>
<p>The creatures were discovered by a team of scientific divers three weeks ago in a billabong close to a popular tourist spot.</p>
<p>Doctor Rod Kennett from the North Australia Research Unit says the turtles are a distinct, new species.</p>
<p>The two species are the long neck turtle, which has a much larger and flatter head, and the short neck turtle, which has a much larger plate inside its mouth for crushing food.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
