<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="69236" id="root" date="1996-09-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - Sept 23.</title>
<headline>RTRS-PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - Sept 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>An Alectus Personnel survey of office support temporary and contract workers has found that more men are &quot;temping&quot;, with 22 percent of temporary and contract workers men. The results are due in part to the changing role of secretaries and the increasing use of computers and they challenge the traditional stereotype of this type of work being an exclusively female domain.  Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard told the Liberal Party's Queensland State Council in Brisbane yesterday the Coalition could be credited with removing censorship restrictions on &quot;certain issues&quot; from Australian public debate, however Aboriginal Social Justice Commissioner Mick Dodson said the Federal Government was pandering to &quot;prejudice, bigotry and hatred&quot;.  Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>In an effort to put greater security in people's lives while avoiding the tight &quot;accord&quot; of the Hawke-Keating years, the Federal Opposition is likely to embrace a loose agreement with the unions. Opposition Leader Kim Beazley highlighted this theme in his weekend Ben Chifley &quot;Light on the Hill&quot; lecture at Bathurst. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Cabinet is expected tomorrow to consider a plan to dump a public inquiry into the media cross-ownership rules, in favour of a Green Paper, as the Government has had problems finding an appropriate chair for the inquiry - an idea that is understood to be supported by Prime Minister John Howard and Federal Treasurer Peter Costello. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>World scientists are excited, but not necessarily convinced by revelations of Australian rock carvings and stone artefacts found in sandstone outcrops on a Dreaming track at Jinmium in the Northern Territory, that may date back 176,000 years and indicate the Australian continent has been inhabited for much longer than the 60,000-odd years thought previously. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Following Independent MP Pauline Hanson's controversial speech on Aboriginal welfare, multiculturalism and immigration, Prime Minister John Howard appealed yesterday for Australians to embrace tolerance in using a &quot;new found&quot; freedom to speak out on sensitive topics such as race relations. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The New South Wales Cabinet will today consider the State Government's forestry protection package, which proposes thousands of hectares of State forest used by the timber industry be made into national parks this year - including parks in Eden, on the State's south coast, and on the mid and far-north coasts. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victoria's chief examiner in Latin and head of classics at Melbourne Grammar, Peter Mountford, warned yesterday a decision by the University of Melbourne to stop teaching advanced level ancient Greek and Latin threatened the survival of Latin in Victorian schools and went against an emerging international trend. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>Amid threats of political recriminations from the timber industry, conservationists and the unions, the New South Wales Government put the finishing touches to its forest and wilderness policies announcing plans to declare four new national parks, expand the South-East forest and convert large areas of bushland into new wilderness areas. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to Real Estate Institute of Australia figures and a new Westpac study, Sydney home prices barely kept pace with inflation over the past year, rising just 2.3 per cent in the year to July, and it is easier to afford a home at the moment than at any time in the past decade. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to Australian and overseas research presented this month to the Fertility Society of Australia annual meeting, sperm donors, particularly family men are more willing to forgo their anonymity than is commonly assumed. The research suggests many dnors would be prepared to have future contact with the children they helped to create. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Despite strong opposition from the Australian Medical Association, which has warned of a mass rally, Federal Health Minister Michael Wooldridge said yesterday the Government's plan to limit the number of new doctors was non-negotiable. A Government spokesoman said the Coalition had to limit the number of Medicare provider numbers issued to medical graduates to correct an over-supply of doctors in metropolitan areas. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>As an internal memo revealed the Royal Melbourne Hospital is considering plans to close its community rehabilitation service and cut inpatient rehabilitation beds from 48 to 34, the Victorian Opposition said the Royal Melbourne would post a A$15 million dficit for 1995-96 and slash 100 jobs over the next year. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victorian racing officials are hoping this year's spring racing carnival can build on last year's record earnings of A$145 million, but the industry must compete with an explosion in the popularity of electronic gaming and the increasing threat posed by the Melbourne casino. Page A1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>In a veiled reference to comments by controversial independent MP Pauline Hanson, Prime Minister John Howard told the Queensland Liberal Party State Council that Australians enjoyed far greater free speech under the Coalition than under the former Labor Gvernment, but said this freedom should be used with greater tolerance and sensitivity. Page A2.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>An assessment by the Victorian Office of Training and Further Education estimates that because of Federal Budget cuts, labor-market programs at Victorian TAFE institutes will be cut by A$60 million to A$80 million and Victoria could also lose A$9 million in capital works funding and A$6 million in projects. Page A3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
