<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74036" id="root" date="1996-09-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FEATURE - Aboriginal artist highlights his people's plight.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Aboriginal artist highlights his people's plight.</headline>
<byline>Terry Friel</byline>
<dateline>DARWIN, Australia 1996-09-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eymard Tungatalum's inspirations are simple things: the ancient dreamtime tales of his gentle Tiwi people; the suffering of Australia's aborigines; returning to the lush green of his native Bathurst Island.</p>
<p>After years of fighting &quot;the grog&quot;, or alcohol, the softly-spoken woodcarver, poet and singer in Australia's frontier Top End is focusing his time, talent and money on helping his people combat drug and alcohol abuse.</p>
<p>Living in a small room in a Salvation Army hostel and rebuilding his life through his art, the short, dark-skinned 41-year-old has spent the past six years studying to be a drug and alcohol counsellor.</p>
<p>He graduated recently and is about to start work at a clinic in Darwin, tropical capital of Australia's Northern Territory.</p>
<p>But his real dream is to build up his experience and return to tropical Bathurst Island, 100 km (60 miles) north of Darwin, and work with his Tiwi tribe to fight the grog.</p>
<p>&quot;We got a big drinking problem on the island,&quot; Eymard says, sipping his milky tea in the shade of the hostel.</p>
<p>&quot;Grog is the biggest problem on the island,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;They need somebody like me -- I want to help my people.&quot;</p>
<p>Australia's 260,000 aborigines are one of the poorest and most disadvantaged groups among this wealthy country's 18 million people, with a life expectancy 10 to 15 years less than other Australians.</p>
<p>Alcoholism and petrol-sniffing are common, and growing, problems among some aboriginal communities, especially in poorer, isolated areas of the remote Northern Territory.</p>
<p>A study earlier this year found aboriginal men in some Territory communities were drinking more than 60 cans of beer a week -- three times the recommended limit for responsible consumption and more than twice the level medical authorities say is harmful.</p>
<p>The study, by the Menzies School of Health Research, warned alcohol abuse was tearing apart traditional aboriginal society.</p>
<p>&quot;Apart from long-term effects on health, vehicle accidents result from it, sometimes deaths, and certainly violence against property and people,&quot; the study said.</p>
<p>&quot;Money is diverted from food to beer, energies are diverted from ceremonies to beer. And energies are consumed -- principally by women -- in maintaining a social fabric that alcohol threatens to tear down daily.&quot;</p>
<p>It's a problem that has not only threatened Eymard and his people, but their very culture as well.</p>
<p>Along with his new qualifications in health care, Eymard is using his art and his experience to help his fellow Tiwi.</p>
<p>&quot;I used to drink a lot. The grog got into me, into my life,&quot; says Eymard.</p>
<p>&quot;Now I'm trying to give the message to my people, and I can do that through my music, through my poems, my art.&quot;</p>
<p>Instead of seeking solace in the grog, Eymard, from generations of woodcarvers, now finds expression in his songs, his poem and his carving -- which features at one of Darwin's most exclusive galleries.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel at peace,&quot; he explains. &quot;I don't know how I do these things, it comes from inside, in my heart.&quot;</p>
<p>The stories and dreamings of his people figure heavily in his work, especially his carvings, but Eymard's art also reflects the world around him, including the tragic side of aboriginal life more than 200 years after European settlers first arrived.</p>
<p>Eymard is recording a music album in his native Tiwi tongue, featuring songs about life for his people in the modern world, as well as in the past.</p>
<p>One track, &quot;Tragedy Song&quot; tells of the recent death in custody of one of Eymard's cousins, who can't be named for several more months because of aboriginal tradition.</p>
<p>Another, &quot;Too many lives have gone&quot;, sings of the death of native people around the world.</p>
<p>Eymard, always looking for a challenge, hopes to produce his own video for the album, due for release later this year.</p>
<p>&quot;Maybe they'll use a song at the 2000 Sydney Olympics,&quot; he says with a smile.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DARWIN, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
