<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="74846" id="root" date="1996-09-25" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Olympics - IOC says Sydney must solve transport problem.</title>
<headline>Olympics - IOC says Sydney must solve transport problem.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1996-09-25</dateline>
<text>
<p>Olympic inspectors said on Wednesday that transport would be a major challenge for the organisers of the Sydney Games, but they were confident that the city could avoid the kind of problems seen in Atlanta.</p>
<p>After a three-day visit to the 2000 Olympic host city, members of the International Olympic Committee Coordination Commission said they were satisified with preparations so far and pleased to see the state government closely involved with the Games.</p>
<p>Commission chairman Jacques Rogge listed various problems, however, including transport, accomodation, and even the possibility that indigenous Aborigines or other ethnic minorities could try to &quot;take the Games hostage&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not a honeymoon, but the problems we've analysed can all be overcome,&quot; Rogge told a news conference.</p>
<p>The total number of spectators is expected to be much lower than in Atlanta, where stories abounded of untrained, out-of-town bus drivers getting lost and athletes having to hijack buses to get to venues.</p>
<p>But hundreds of thousands of people will travel every day to the western suburb of Homebush, where most of the Olympic venues, including a new 110,000-seat Olympic stadium, are being built.</p>
<p>On the busiest day of the Games, the second Saturday, up to half a million people are expected to use either buses, ferries or a new train link to Homebush.</p>
<p>Rogge welcomed Sydney's decision to move the Olympic velodrome away from Homebush to cut back on crowds and said some events would have to be rescheduled to reduce peak-hour traffic.</p>
<p>Aborigines and other ethnic minorities have threatened to use street protests during the Games to draw attention to their poor living conditions.</p>
<p>Australia's 300,000 Aborigines have a life expectancy that is as much as 20 years lower than that of white Australians.</p>
<p>Rogge said groups always tried to exploit the Olympics for publicity but Sydney Games organisers had &quot;no responsibility for Australia's long-term problems&quot;.</p>
<p>Sydney Games organisers also announced that Spaniard Manolo Romero had been appointed chief executive of its host broadcasting operation, which will provide the bulk of worldwide television coverage of the Games.</p>
<p>Romero headed the host broadcasting operations at the Los Angeles Olympics of 1984, at Barcelona in 1992 and in Atlanta this year. He has also handled two soccer World Cups.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-25"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-25"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
