<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="78447" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia torn by outback euthanasia death.</title>
<headline>Australia torn by outback euthanasia death.</headline>
<dateline>DARWIN, Australia 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Australian cancer patient who said he lived on a &quot;roller-coaster of pain&quot; has committed the world's first legally-assisted suicide, sparking a fiery national debate on the issue of mercy killing.</p>
<p>Bob Dent, a 66-year-old former carpenter from this northern outback city, died from a computer-delivered lethal injection last Sunday after persuading doctors he had nothing to live for.</p>
<p>He shared a last meal and drink with doctor Philip Nitschke and told him that what he was doing was an &quot;act of love&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;If I were to keep a pet animal in the same condition I am in, I would be prosecuted,&quot; Dent wrote in an open letter to Australian members of parliament on the eve of his death.</p>
<p>&quot;For months I have been on a roller-coaster of pain made worse by the unwanted side effects of the drugs.&quot;</p>
<p>Australian church leaders, who want the Northern Territory voluntary euthanasia law quashed, were outraged.</p>
<p>Sydney's Roman Catholic archbishop Edward Clancy said he was &quot;deeply ashamed that Australia should be the only country in the world to legalise the killing of an innocent person.</p>
<p>&quot;Respect, reverence for human life is a cornerstone of our civilisation,&quot; Clancy said. &quot;When that goes, our society begins to unravel.&quot;</p>
<p>Dent's death marked the first time that the Northern Territory's euthanasia law had been successfully used since it came into operation on July 1.</p>
<p>It saw battlelines drawn up on Thursday for a fresh fight over mercy killing. Government backbencher Kevin Andrews, who has launched a private action in federal parliament to have the state's law quashed, said euthanasia was now a national issue.</p>
<p>It also polarised opinion in Australia, with one state politician describing it as &quot;beautiful&quot; and church leaders expressing their shame.</p>
<p>Victoria state premier Jeff Kennett, a supporter of voluntary euthanasia, said moves to have the law quashed were immoral.</p>
<p>&quot;For people to be able to die with grace and dignity at their choosing as opposed to suffering is just beautiful,&quot; Kennett told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Life is about choice; death should be about choice and politicians ought to butt out.&quot;</p>
<p>Nitschke told reporters up to five more people from around Australia had sought to use the legislation and that another death could occur within weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;There is little doubt that the events surrounding this first use of the act will make it that much easier for the next terminally ill person,&quot; Nitschke said.</p>
<p>The doctor, dubbed Australia's &quot;Doctor Death&quot; after American euthanasia campaigner Jack Kevorkian, said the atmosphere in Dent's Darwin home had at first been tense.</p>
<p>But he said Dent had reassured him as he died, telling him that what he was doing was &quot;an act of love&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The patient was expressing a sense of gratitude. He was as happy as someone could be under the circumstances,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dent wrote that he he had been an active, outgoing person and that &quot;being unable to live a normal life causes much mental and psychological pain, which can never be relieved by medication&quot;.</p>
<p>The deputy prime minister in Australia's conservative government, Tim Fischer, repeated warnings the territory law was a move towards &quot;a culture of death&quot;.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard, Labor opposition leader Kim Beazley, other prominent community leaders and Australia's indigenous Aborigines have all condemned the law.</p>
<p>Previous political and legal challenges against the law in the Northern Territory have failed, although a coalition of doctors, church and Aboriginal leaders have petitioned the Australian High Court to declare the law unconstitutional.</p>
<p>Dent in his letter urged parliament to allow people to choose to die when Andrews' bill is voted on later this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The church and state should be kept separate,&quot; he wrote. &quot;What right has anyone because of their own religious faith, to which I don't subscribe, to demand that I behave according to their rules and endure unnecessary intractable pain.</p>
<p>&quot;If you disagree with voluntary euthanasia, then don't use it, but please don't deny the right to me to use it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DARWIN, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
