<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79951" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>REACTION TO EUTHANASIA DEATH</p>
<p>A monstrous step and a landmark are among polarised reactions to the world's first termination of life under voluntary euthanasia law, with the death of a man under Northern Territory legislation.</p>
<p>Darwin doctor Philip Nitschke ended the 66 year old cancer suffer's life last Sunday with a lethal injection he had requested.</p>
<p>Doctor Nitschke has read a letter from the man asking what right anyone has to demand he live by their rules just because of their religious faith.</p>
<p>And Victorian Premier, Jeff Kennett, says giving people the right to die with grace and dignity is beautiful.</p>
<p>But Deputy Prime Minister Tim Fischer says there's enough culture of death in the world without taking what he calls this monstrous step to euthanasia.</p>
<p>Federal Liberal MP, Kevin Andrews' bill to overturn the Northern Territory law is expected to be debated next month.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ABORIGINE HOME OWNERSHIP RATE LOWER THAN AVERAGE - SURVEY</p>
<p>A bureau of Statistics survey of aboriginal housing has found that most indigenous households rent their homes, with the home ownership rate much lower than for non-aborigines.</p>
<p>Released today, the survey shows an estimated 20 percent of private dwellings were described as not meeting the needs of indigenous households.</p>
<p>That compares with three percent for non aboriginal households.</p>
<p>The most common complaints of indigenous tenants were that properties were in need of repairs, and had a shortage of bedrooms and living space.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SYDNEY MIGRATION AGENCY FACES INVESTIGATION</p>
<p>The Federal police are expected to investigate a Sydney migration agency which demanded huge fees from migrants to help arrange permanent residency.</p>
<p>Nineteen Hong Kong and Chinese migrants have won a Federal Court action allowing them to recover the 20,000 dollars or so they each paid to North-West Immigration Services.</p>
<p>Justice Graham Hill found the company often didn't do anything to assist the migrants get permanent residency.</p>
<p>The Public Interest Advocacy Centre says it will prepare a brief for the Federal police so they can take action against the company and its principal employee Leslie William Alexander.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>INQUIRY HEARS OF NEAR CLASH AFTER CRASH</p>
<p>A military inquiry in Perth has heard how two Blackhawk helicopters flew within metres of each other moments after two other aircraft collided and crashed to the ground.</p>
<p>The inquiry is hearing evidence from eye witnesses to the high risk counter-terrorists exercise in Townsville in June in which 18 servicemen were killed.</p>
<p>A soldier who was in one of two sniper helicopters told the inquiry another Black Hawk passed directly below his aircraft which was in a hover.</p>
<p>He said he didn't believe it came dangerously close, but he was concerned about the distance between the two.</p>
<p>He said directly after this, his helicopter landed to help to evacuate the injured from the wreckage of the two crashed aircraft.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BATTLE OVER HANCOCK FORTUNE CONTINUES</p>
<p>The family battle for control of the riches of the late mining magnate Lang Hancock is being argued in the Supreme Court in Perth today.</p>
<p>Mr Hancock's widow, Rose Porteous, has gone to Court to try to wrest some control of the Hancock companies from the late magnate's daughter Gina Reinhart.</p>
<p>In Court today, Mrs Reinhart's lawyers sought to have her step mother's claim struck out, describing parts of it as fundamentally flawed, embarrassing and vague.</p>
<p>Neither of the Hancock women are in Court today. However, Mrs Porteous' husband is monitoring proceedings.</p>
<p>The case is continuing.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TITANIC SURVIVOR'S FUNERAL</p>
<p>There's been a funeral service for the last Adelaide survivor of the Titanic disaster.</p>
<p>96-year-old Thomas Bell, who died last Friday, was a cabin boy aboard the liner, when it sank on its maiden voyage in 1912. Mr Bell's funeral service has been held at Saint Albans Anglican Church at Largs Bay.</p>
<p>A representative of the Titanic and Steamship Historical Society says that Mr Bell had supported the recent salvage work on the wreck of the Titanic.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ABC METROS TO LOSE PRESENTERS</p>
<p>ABC metropolitan radio stations will lose at least one of their morning presenters as part of a shake-up prompted by Federal Government funding cuts.</p>
<p>From next year, the two shows that now run between 8-30 and Midday on metropolitan stations will become one program and the early afternoon program will be transformed into a statewide broadcast.</p>
<p>The final on-air line-ups have yet to be finalised, with ABC Management saying no committments have been made to any of the presenters affected by the changes.</p>
<p>Metropolitan and regional stations will lose around 63 jobs nationwide as a result of the restructure.</p>
<p>The ABC's Board has also decided to either axe or merge a number of Radio National programs, including religious, arts, education and science shows.</p>
<p>ABC Managers have told a Senate committee in Canberra a total of 900 positions were likely to be cut over the next two financial years because of the funding shortfall...that's just under 20 per-cent of the Corporation's current workforce.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
