<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="79988" id="root" date="1996-09-26" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia shocked by mercy killing first.</title>
<headline>Australia shocked by mercy killing first.</headline>
<dateline>DARWIN, Australia 1996-09-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>An elderly cancer patient has become the first person to take his life under Australia's unique voluntary euthanasia law, the doctor who assisted his suicide said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The man, named by local media as Bob Dent, died by a computer-delivered lethal injection in this northern outback city on Sunday after persuading doctors that his case was hopeless and he knew what he was doing.</p>
<p>In an emotional open letter written on the eve of his death, Dent said painkilling drugs given for his prostate cancer made him suicidal.</p>
<p>&quot;If I were to keep a pet animal in the same condition I am in, I would be prosecuted,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>News of Dent's death outraged political and religious leaders, many of whom are campaigning to have the law quashed in either the federal parliament or High Court.</p>
<p>&quot;I was, and still am, deeply ashamed that Australia should be the only country in the world to legalise the killing of an innocent person,&quot; Roman Catholic archbishop Edward Clancy told a news conference outside the city's St Mary's Cathedral.</p>
<p>&quot;Respect, reverence for human life is a cornerstone of our civilisation,&quot; Clancy added. &quot;When that goes, our society begins to unravel.&quot;</p>
<p>Darwin doctor Philip Nitschke told Reuters he had helped his dying patient administer a lethal injection on Sunday. It was the first time that the Northern Territory's euthanasia law had been successfully used since it came into operation on July 1.</p>
<p>Dent wrote that &quot;drugs given to enhance the pain-relieving effects of the morphine have caused me to feel suicidal to the point that I would have blown my head off if I had had a gun.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always been an active, outgoing person, and being unable to live a normal life causes much mental and psychological pain, which can never be relieved by medication.&quot;</p>
<p>Nitschke told reporters the atmosphere at Dent's Darwin home, where the euthanasia was carried out, had at first been tense and disquieting.</p>
<p>But Dent had reassured him and told him it was an act of love. &quot;The patient was expressing a sense of gratitude. He was as happy as someone could be under the circumstances,&quot; Nitschke said.</p>
<p>The deputy prime minister in Australia's conservative government, Tim Fischer, repeated warnings the territory law was a move towards &quot;a culture of death&quot;.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard, Labor opposition leader Kim Beazley and other prominent community leaders have also condemned the territory law.</p>
<p>The law has also been condemned by Australia's indigenous Aborigines.</p>
<p>Since it came into operation, the law has been hit by a series of political and legal challenges which had until this month deterred doctors from approving patients' deaths.</p>
<p>Government backbencher Kevin Andrews, backed by Howard, has launched a private action in parliament that would see the national parliament use its constitutional powers to quash the territory law.</p>
<p>But Dent, in his letter, urged parliament to allow people to choose to die when the bill is voted on later this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The church and state should be kept separate,&quot; he wrote. &quot;What right has anyone because of their own religious faith, to which I don't subscribe, to demand that I behave according to their rules and endure unnecessary intractable pain.</p>
<p>&quot;If you disagree with voluntary euthanasia, then don't use it, but please don't deny the right to me to use it.&quot;</p>
<p>Andrews told reporters he was protecting the community and warned the law could be abused.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not just an issue that affects one individual, or even that individual and his or her families, it's a matter which effects the entire community.... the way in which we see things such as death and care and what hope we give people,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Andrews' challenge is the latest in a series of legal and political attacks on the territory law.</p>
<p>Challenges in the territory parliament and the territory's Supreme Court have failed.</p>
<p>The law faces a separate threat in Australia's highest court, the High Court, where an anti-euthanasia coalition of doctors, church and Aboriginal leaders is seeking to have it declared unconstitutional.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-09-26"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-09-26"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DARWIN, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
